<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Supreme Test of Religion</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1949,  pp. 12-18</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I wish I might say something to the missionaries of the Church that would be helpful in their
work in teaching the gospel. In a broad sense, we are all missionaries who hold the priesthood
of God. We are ever ready to give the message of eternal life because of the truth, beauty,
and goodness of the divine teachings of the Savior. Out of our faith, we find everything that
is holy and pure and of good report. I was thinking this morning of the
Sabbath day after the arrival of the pioneers in this valley. July 24, 1847. Divine services
were held, and the people were seated in a circle out in the sagebrush, and nearby were the
waters of a lovely stream. Gratitude to God was expressed in song and prayer, and the words
of Isaiah were read by Apostle Orson Pratt, who gave the sermon:
</p><p>
How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of him that bringeth good tidings,
that publisheth peace; that bringeth good tidings of good; that publisheth salvation;
that saith unto Zion, Thy God rejoiceth!
</p><p>
Thy watchmen shall lift up the voice; with the voice together shall they sing: for
they shall see eye to eye, when the Lord shall bring again Zion
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/52/7-8#7">Isa. 52:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
TRUTHS OF GOD
</p><p>
The Saints had sung their sacred hymns during their long journey. They had endured their
trials, and the more they suffered, the deeper was their gratitude to God. The missionaries go
forth to speak of these things, because the history of this people is in many respects the most
majestic and sublime of any people that ever lived. There is a sacred foundation to their
teachings. The Latter-day Saints believe and know honestly that Adam came to earth sent of
God from heaven. He held the priesthood of God and became the first teacher of the gospel to
his descendants. The divine ideals as taught by the Father of us all were held sacred, and from
that time to the days of the Messiah upon the earth, the truths of God were planted in the
hearts of his children. Maurice Maeterlinck in his book, The Great Secret, says that what we
read in the oldest archives of wisdom gives us only a faint idea of the sublime doctrines of
the ancient teachers. The older the texts, the more pure, the more awe-inspiring are the
doctrines they reveal. They may be merely an echo of sublimer doctrines. We come down to
the age of the prophets. Says a noted historian:
</p><p>
How fitting it is that Malachi should seal up the book of the Old Testament
prophecy by such a clear statement of the coming of the Lord, the Messenger of
the Covenant (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/1#1">Mal. 3:1</a>),
the Son of righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/25/2#2">3 Ne. 25:2</a>),
and thus give the last prediction of him,
with whom the evangelists begin their gospel history.
</p><p>
Hugo Munsterberg of Harvard University wrote, in his Psychology and Life, something of the
past glory of the sacred records:
</p><p>
There is a truth, a beauty, a morality, which is independent of psychological
conditions. Every straightforward man, to whom the duties of his real life are no
sounding brass, speaks with a sound voice to the psychologist: "There are more
things in heaven and earth than are dreamt of in your philosophy."
</p><p>
GOSPEL RE-ESTABLISHED
</p><p>
We have the age in which the Prophet Joseph Smith lived. He was undoubtedly the greatest
character in history since the days of the Savior of the world. He re-established the divine
principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ in the day in which we live. We first see him in the
woods on the frontier of America praying as a child might pray and the Lord appearing to
him, using the words of the Psalmist,
</p><p>
. . . grace is poured into thy lips, therefore, God hath blessed thee forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/45/2#2">Ps. 45:2</a>).
</p><p>
With the Father was Jesus the Savior. Joseph heard the voice of God and the divine words:
"This is My Beloved Son!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
A new day was at hand. From that moment he was heart and mind
to the word of the Lord.
</p><p>
He learned that day that the divisions of Christendom are its most conspicuous reproach and
the chief cause of its inefficiency. They present a moral affront to the enterprise inaugurated
by Jesus Christ and constitute the outstanding limitation of its progress. Christianity is
weakened by its divisions in facing the problems of today, among which are class hatreds,
race antagonisms, blindness to social justice, the lure of vicious literature, crime-instigating
narcotics, and the spread of military spirit in the world.
</p><p>
PRINCIPLE OF REVELATION
</p><p>
The supreme test of religion is revelation. No religion can be persuasive unless it relies on the
principle of revelation. The living Church of Jesus Christ must be revelatory. Christianity in
its pure sense is the religion of redeemed personality. While all true men reveal God, the
completest carrier of revelation can be no other than a chosen personality.
</p><p>
By the power of the Holy Priesthood which Joseph Smith received from heaven, he
established our true relationship to God. Out of this grows the salvation of man&mdash;his true
immortal life. The nations all bear witness to the need of a light that is not of man. We can
give our word to the world that the forces which are to make the world the world it ought to
be are now within it. My fellow missionaries: We are to study more deeply and constantly the
divine truths of the gospel of Jesus Christ. We must know the history of the Church of which
we are members. We must understand the meaning of the priesthood of God which has been
given to us. We must know the divine teachings of the Holy Bible, the Book of Mormon, The
Doctrine and Covenants, and The Pearl of Great Price. How beautifully do they teach the
words of Shakespeare:
</p><p>
What a piece of work is a man! how noble in reason! how infinite in faculty!
in form and moving how express and admirable! in action how like an angel! in
apprehension how like a God! (Shakespeare, <i>Hamlet</i>, Act II, Sc. 2.)
</p><p>
FAITH IN REVEALED WORD
</p><p>
Think of what your message can become as you go forth to teach. But it is going to require
of you some sort of planning toward an end. Your minds must become more sensitive to the
revealed truths of God as never before. Your faith in your work must deepen from day to day.
Let me call to your minds the words of the first two verses of the first chapter of the Book of
Mormon:
</p><p>
I, Nephi, having been born of goodly parents, therefore I was taught somewhat in
all the learning of my father: and having seen many afflictions in the course of my
days, nevertheless, having been highly favored of the Lord in all my days; yea,
having had a great knowledge of the goodness and the mysteries of God, therefore
I make a record of my proceedings in my days.
</p><p>
Yea, I make a record in the language of my father, which consists of the learning
of the Jews and the language of the Egyptians
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/1/1-2#1">1 Ne. 1:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
What a noble tribute to education these words are. Lehi had become an educated man in his
day, and his son pays him loving tribute. So you must study the words of Holy Writ every
hour of the day and remember the admonition of the first teacher to the American Indians,
called by some the apostle John Eliot:
</p><p>
Work, with faith in Jesus Christ can accomplish anything.
</p><p>
"WORDS OF WISDOM"
</p><p>
What a directive purpose the Prophet Joseph Smith gives us in the words as found in the 88th
Section of the Doctrine and Covenants:
</p><p>
. . . seek ye diligently and teach one another words of wisdom; yea, seek ye out
of the best books words of wisdom; seek learning, even by study and also by faith.
</p><p>
Organize yourselves; prepare every needful thing; and establish a house, even a
house of prayer, a house of fasting, a house of faith, a house of learning, a house
of glory, a house of order, a house of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118-119#118">D&amp;C 88:118-119</a>).
</p><p>
From the beginning of the history of the Church, Joseph Smith organized schools of learning.
He became a student and a member of the Latin, Greek, and Hebrew classes established in the
Kirtland Temple. He established the University of the City of Nauvoo, encouraged the
building of the Seventies' Hall of Science. In volume five of the <i>Times and Seasons</i> is found
this brief, but noble statement:
</p><p>
Among the improvements going forward in this city, none merit higher
praise, than the Seventies' Library. The concern has been commenced on a footing
and scale, broad enough to embrace the arts and sciences, everywhere: so that the
Seventies while traveling over the face of the globe, as the Lord's "Regular
Soldiers," can gather all the curious things, both natural and artificial, with all the
knowledge, inventions, and wonderful specimens of genius that have been gracing
the world for almost six thousand years. (p. 762; January 1, 1845.)
</p><p>
REFINEMENT AND CULTURE
</p><p>
The early history of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints was one of refinement
and culture. The people became lovers of good literature. Even when they were camping on
the frozen ground of Iowa as they began their exodus to the far West, they read their sacred
books and before the campfires they knelt in prayer. We are told that in one of the camps was
a copy of Mlle. Cottin's beautiful story, entitled "Elizabeth." It was so sought after that some
read the book by the light of the moon. They were sustained by day and by night by
</p><p>
. . . keeping up the songs of Zion, and passing along Doxologies from front to rear
when the breath froze on their eyelashes.
</p><p>
Jane Bicknell Young, the wife of Joseph Young, sang to her children the "Song of the Silent
Land":
</p><p>
Into the Silent Land!<br />
Who shall lead us thither?<br />
Clouds in the evening sky more darkly gather<br />
And shattered wrecks lie thicker on the strand.<br />
Who leads us with a gentle hand<br />
Thither, oh, thither,<br />
Into the Silent Land.
</p><p>
They trained themselves to read and to think, but they had no set regulations for their studies.
They embraced only guiding principles. They knew nothing of set rules and methods which
would have limited their imaginations and initiative, which are so important in the successful
presentation of great truths. One of the first things that President Brigham Young did after the
advent of the pioneers to Utah was to issue an epistle&mdash;and this in 1847&mdash;which reads as
follows:
</p><p>
It is very desirable that all the Saints should improve every opportunity of
securing at least a copy of every valuable treatise on education&mdash;every book, map,
chart, or diagram that may contain interesting, useful, and attractive matter, to gain
the attention of children, and cause them to love to learn to read; and also every
historical, mathematical, philosophical, geographical, geological, astronomical,
scientific, practical, and all other variety of useful and interesting writings, maps,
etc., to present to the general church recorder, when they shall arrive at their
destination, from which important and interesting matter may be gleaned to
compile the most valuable works on every science and subject, for the benefit of
the rising generation. We have a printing press, and any one who can take
good printing or writing paper to the valley will be
blessing themselves and the Church. We also want all kinds of mathematical
instruments, together with all rare specimens of natural curiosities and works of
art that can be gathered.
</p><p>
FIRST LIBRARY
</p><p>
In 1851 the first extensive library was brought by ox teams to this state. It had been
purchased in New York City by Dr. John M. Bernhisel and was a wonderful collection of
books. There were the works of Shakespeare, Milton, Bacon, Homer, Juvenal, Lucretius,
Virgil, Euripides, Sophocles, Plato, Montaigne, Tacitus, Spenser, Herodotus, Goldsmith, and
many others of the great masters of the world's best literature. The library received copies of
the New York <i>Herald</i>, New York <i>Evening Post</i>, the Philadelphia <i>Saturday Courier</i>, and the
<i>North American Review</i>. Of the scientific works there were Newton's <i>Principia</i>, Herschel's
<i>Outlines of Astronomy</i>, and Von Humboldt's <i>Cosmos</i>. The treatises on philosophy included
the works of John Stuart Mill, Martin Luther, John Wesley, and Emanuel Swedenborg.
</p><p>
Time will not permit my going into the cultural aspects of the early days of the Church, The
Latter-day Saints were a cultured people from the first, and they indicated this in their lives.
The inventory of the educational resources of Utah have been what Dr. Samuel T. Dutton, of
Columbia University, has pointed out. These resources are: First, homes, churches, schools,
and libraries; second, newspapers, magazines, museums, drama, industry, and government;
third, those intellectual and ethical aptitudes of the people which make it possible for them to
be quickened and influenced in the right direction.
</p><p>
ACHIEVEMENTS OF PIONEERS
</p><p>
The pioneers were always striving to understand the arts and sciences, for they sensed keenly
the power of all truth. They knew the human constants&mdash;hunger and labor, seedtime and
harvest, love and faith&mdash;which entered into their lives from the very first. They built this
Tabernacle in which we are worshiping today. They continued establishing schools and
colleges and established a theatre in the wilderness which in time became recognized by the
artists of the London stage as well as the famous dramatists of America. Mr. M. B. Leavitt
has written in his <i>Fifty Years of the American Stage</i>:
</p><p>
Sweeping as the statement may seem, I do not believe that the theater has ever
rested on a higher plane, both as to its purpose and its offerings, than at Salt Lake
City, the Capital of Mormondom.
</p><p>
Utah today has become a great state. Ellsworth Huntington has recently written in his book,
entitled <i>Civilization and Climate</i>:
</p><p>
The proud position of Utah is presumably the result of Mormonism. The
leaders of that faith have had the wisdom to insist on a thorough system of
schools, and have obliged the children to attend them. The "Gentiles" have in
self-defense been forced to do equally well, and the result has been admirable.
Whatever one may think of Mormonism as a religious belief, it must be credited
with having accomplished a remarkable work in spreading a moderate degree of
education almost universally among the people of Utah.
</p><p>
Count Hermann Keyserling, the noted German philosopher and historian, came to Salt Lake
City a few years ago and afterwards wrote in his <i>Travel Diary of a Philosopher</i> these words:
</p><p>
The Mormons have achieved a civilization hardly attained by any other people. In
barely half a century they have changed a salt-desert into a garden. They are
moreover admirable citizens, law-abiding, honest, and progressive.
</p><p>
MISSIONARIES TO TEACH WORLD
</p><p>
You missionaries of Jesus Christ, our Savior, are taught the divine precepts of the religion of
the Master, and you go forth in all the world to teach. Out of the faith of your fathers you
take to peoples all that is holy and pure and of good report. Your zeal and self-devotion shall
be increased. Your heavenly aspirations, your human sympathies, your endless deeds of
charity will bring you the hearts of the people. You need never hesitate, for you have entered
upon your many duties and responsibilities, your trials and discouragements "with the zeal of
Peter and the gentleness of John." Well may you read the words of the Prophet Joseph Smith
as he wrote in the Articles of Faith:
</p><p>
We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good
to all men; indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We
believe all things, we hope all things, we have endured many things, and hope to
be able to endure all things. If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report
or praiseworthy, we seek after these things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p>
</div>
</div>
