<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1944, pp. 79-84</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I sincerely trust, my brethren, that I might enjoy the spirit of the Lord for the moment or two
that I stand before you. It is now six years since the present Presiding Bishopric was sustained
in its present position. I should like to say that this period of our lives has been a period of
inspiration because of the fact that we have had the privilege of being so closely associated
with the living prophets of God, these men who receive the mind and will of our Heavenly
Father to guide and direct the destiny of this great Church. I am deeply grateful for the
association that I have with you, for the privilege of visiting your stakes and wards and
observing the high degree of loyalty and devotion to the cause of the Lord Jesus Christ
manifested by you.
</p><p>
GRATEFUL FOR LABORS AMONG YOUTH
</p><p>
The Presiding Bishopric is most grateful for the high privilege we enjoy in laboring with the
youth of Zion. Of our several responsibilities and duties, we are agreed that the most
important is our participation with you in directing and guiding the destiny of the Aaronic
Priesthood of the Church. I want to say to you that laboring with boys and young
men, securing their confidence and trust, is the sweetest experience that can
come into the life of any man. When one speaks of boys, the memory of the Boy of Nazareth
always comes to mind, particularly that period of His life when He was twelve years of age.
It was the custom of the Jewish people, when a boy attained the age of twelve, to make him a
member of his home community. At this age, a boy was expected to have selected his life's
vocation. He was given higher assignments in the study of the law, and, if he qualified, he
was recognized by the religious leader, the priest, as a son of the law. The Jewish boy at the
age of twelve was extended the privilege of attending the Feast of the Passover, which was
held in Jerusalem. Christ at the age of twelve accompanied His father and mother to attend
this great Jewish celebration, which lasted for a week. Thereafter, His parents, Joseph and
Mary, started their homeward journey, and at the end of the first day of travel, they
discovered Jesus was not with them. They immediately retraced their steps to the city, and,
after searching diligently, they found Jesus in the temple, discussing with the scribes and wise
men the problems of the day, propounding and answering questions to the amazement of these
men of learning. Mary reproached her son in the following words: "Son, why hast thou thus
dealt with us? behold, thy father and I have sought thee sorrowing. And He said unto them,
How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/48-49#48">Luke 2:48-49</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus Christ, at the age of twelve, was aware of His great mission in the world, and in this
day, twenty centuries since the Boy of Nazareth lived, it is most inspiring to know that young
men at the age of twelve are given definite Priesthood responsibilities. The Boy of Nazareth
received His training and assignments under the old Mosaic law. The young servants of God
today receive their assignments and Priesthood training under the law of the divine direction
of Jesus Christ, who has set in motion the great training program for the young men of the
Church. The Priesthood extended to young men is the Aaronic Priesthood, after the order of
Aaron, the heritage of which belongs to the descendants of Aaron and Levi; but until such
time as these descendants claim their Priesthood inheritance of necessity the work is being
carried on by the heirs of Ephraim and Manasseh, whose heritage is the Melchizedek
Priesthood. However, the Aaronic Priesthood for these young men becomes a great school of
preparation for the higher order of the Priesthood, the Melchizedek Priesthood.
</p><p>
THE AARONIC PRIESTHOOD AND ITS FUNCTIONS
</p><p>
The Lord, in making known to the Prophet Joseph the powers and the rights of the
Priesthood, indicated in the 107th section of the Doctrine and Covenants: "Why it is called the
lesser Priesthood is because it is an appendage to the greater, or the Melchizedek Priesthood,
and has power in administering outward ordinances"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/14#14">D&amp;C 107:14</a>). This statement of the
Lord to the Prophet Joseph has provoked some thinking on my part, particularly as the
Priesthood is related to Latter-day Saint homes. If every Latter-day Saint
home were in order as it should be, the head of that home would be one holding the
Melchizedek Priesthood, the Priesthood after the order of the Son of God, and all the sons in
that home of the age of twelve and over would hold the Aaronic Priesthood, an appendage to
the higher Priesthood.
</p><p>
It occurs to me that after all, a son is an appendage to his father. He is a part of his father,
and how glorious it is to contemplate the relationship of father and son in connection with the
holy Priesthood of the Lord Jesus Christ. As the Aaronic Priesthood is an appendage to the
Melchizedek Priesthood, the son is an appendage to his father, and hence they become one in
the work of the Boy of Nazareth.
</p><p>
One of the evidences of the divine origin of the Priesthood is in its organization. Standing at
the head of the Aaronic Priesthood in every ward as the presidency are three high priests,
constituting the bishopric of the ward. The young men of the Church come in contact with
and immediately under the direction of these common judges in Israel, these men who are
endowed with inspiration from on high to guide and direct the destiny of these young servants
of the Lord Jesus Christ. The bishop, according to divine revelation, stands at the head of the
priests' quorum, the Lord making it known to Joseph Smith: "Also the duty of the president
over the Priesthood of Aaron is to preside over forty-eight priests, and sit in council with
them, to teach them the duties of their office, as is given in the covenants&mdash;This president is to
be a bishop; for this is one of the duties of this Priesthood"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/87-88#87">D&amp;C 107:87-88</a>). This is as
it should be, for as a boy passes from adolescence to young manhood, the Lord's servant, the
bishop, becomes his counselor, becomes the president of the priests' quorum to which he
belongs, preparing him to function in the office of a priest as did John the Baptist of old, and
eventually so qualifying him that he may receive the Melchizedek Priesthood.
</p><p>
As with a bishop, so with his first and second counselors. These men constitute a part of the
presidency of the Aaronic Priesthood of a ward. Therefore, the first counselor should be
intensely interested in the welfare of teachers or deacons and the same applies to the second
counselor, affording a training for the twelve-year-old and the fifteen-year-old boy which will
qualify them to receive higher offices in the Aaronic Priesthood.
</p><p>
DUTIES OF BISHOP IN RELATION TO THE AARONIC PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
The bishopric of the ward participates in all of the steps which mark a young man's spiritual
progress. First, in fast meeting, under the direction of the bishopric, the infant boy is
presented to the Lord to receive a father's blessing and a name. Second, the bishopric directs
his baptism, and in fast meeting assembled, directs his confirmation. Third, the Priesthood is
conferred upon him under the hands of the bishopric, as Aaron conferred it upon Joseph
Smith and Oliver Cowdery. Fourth, the bishopric recommends him for advancement to the
Melchizedek Priesthood. Fifth, the bishopric recommends him to the First
Presidency for missionary service. Sixth, the bishop of the ward issues a certificate of
worthiness in evidence of clean, sweet living, which permits the young man to enter the house
of the Lord to receive his endowments and be sealed to Iris life's mate for time and eternity.
</p><p>
As we contemplate the relationship established by the divine Priesthood of the Lord Jesus
Christ between young men and the bishopric of the Church, it should be a great source of
inspiration and motivation, not only to youth but to parents and the men who preside over the
Aaronic Priesthood, parents and members of bishoprics cooperating together to
the end that these young men may become more than the Jewish boy at twelve, a son of the
law, but instead well-trained, devoted, faithful servants of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
No young man can render service in the Aaronic Priesthood sincerely without feeling the
influence of the Boy of Nazareth. For example, the deacon who participates in the
administration of the sacrament must think of the fact that Jesus Christ was the first to pass
the sacrament to the congregation. It should have a beautiful and sacred influence upon the
mind and heart of every deacon.
</p><p>
The ordained teacher, whose right and duty it is, as the Lord indicates in the 20th section of
the Doctrine &amp; Covenants, verse 53, "to watch over the Church always, and be with and
strengthen them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>),
is afforded a magnificent opportunity in connection with their Melchizedek
Priesthood companions in watching over the flock and particularly in training young men in
the great art of teaching the divine laws of the gospel. He learns to express himself freely, and
in preparing a message for the people, he unconsciously converts himself to the great truths of
the restored Gospel. Again this duty of teaching the people follows the example of the Boy of
Nazareth, for he was the Great Teacher.
</p><p>
The office of a priest is one of the most inspirational offices of the entire Priesthood because
of the duties involved. To kneel at the sacrament table and utter the revealed blessings on the
bread and water as Christ repeated them before His assembled apostles should inspire a young
man to the most high and noble motives and impress upon him the necessity of living a
sweet, clean life. The privilege of performing the ordinance of baptism is one which must
impress upon the young priest the reality of the Priesthood and the authority that it carries, for
no young man could utter the revealed baptismal prayer without feeling that he has indeed
been commissioned of Jesus Christ. With uplifted hand, he declares to the candidate and to
the world, "Having been commissioned of Jesus Christ, I baptize you in the name of the
Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. Amen"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/73#73">D&amp;C 20:73</a>). The utterance of the prayer gives him
the assurance, the testimony, that his authority is valid, that the visitation of John the Baptist
was a reality, and that the priesthood he holds was handed down from John the Baptist
through Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
OPPORTUNITY FOR SERVICE
</p><p>
The Aaronic Priesthood affords the privilege of service, and with that service
there comes a fundamental training in Priesthood work to the end that some day these young
servants of the Lord will receive their Priesthood inheritance, namely the Melchizedek
Priesthood, which Priesthood is after the order of the Son of God. In the minds of the
Presiding Bishopric, there is no question but what this sacred privilege of Priesthood service
will inculcate into the hearts of these youthful servants a testimony of the restored Gospel,
and they will become thoroughly familiar with the fundamental principles of the plan of life
and salvation. They are taught to be clean in body and mind by observing God's law of health
and to observe the law of dependability, for an assignment to pass the sacrament, to teach the
people, to bless the sacrament, or to baptize someone is equivalent to keeping an appointment
with Jesus Christ. The lesson of rendering service unto others exemplifies the second part of
the first great commandment, "Love thy neighbor as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>). The payment of tithing is a
manifestation of their desire to return to the Lord His portion for the building up and
sustaining of His kingdom here upon the earth. Participation in the welfare program affords a
training and experience that will qualify them fully for the carrying on of this most important
work when they obtain a place in the Melchizedek Priesthood.
</p><p>
TESTIMONY OF A YOUNG MAN
</p><p>
A great deal is said about the problem of juvenile delinquency, but how often do we consider
that in our hands rests the solutions and the implements whereby the youth of Israel can be so
trained that they will accept the declaration of the Boy of Nazareth, "Wist ye not that I must
be about my Father's business?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
Any young man trained properly and fully in the Aaronic
Priesthood will so live that his parents will never be plagued with any kind of problem in
juvenile delinquency. An illustration of what Priesthood training will do for a young man
supported by excellent parents came to my attention in a recent conference wherein a young
man was invited to speak. He said:
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, in two days I will be eighteen years of age, and you know what that
means to me. I expect to be inducted into the armed services of my country. To many this
seems a hard thing for one as young as I, but it is easy, for there burns in my heart a
testimony of the divinity of this great work, and because of that testimony, my heart is filled
to overflowing with gratitude for the many blessings the Lord has so generously bestowed
upon me. I'm grateful for my beloved parents, grateful for the Priesthood I bear, and grateful
for the knowledge that should my life be taken in battle, I shall return to Him who gave me
life. I'm grateful for the opportunity of mortality, and the spirit of testimony which whispers
to me that I shall again have my father and mother and that the privilege of serving the Lord
on the other side shall be made available to me.
</p><p>
The attitude of this young man, his testimony, his cleanliness, his implicit faith are all the
results of a splendid home and his loyal devoted service in the cause of the Boy of Nazareth.
</p><p>
ADULTS HOLDING AARONIC PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
Bishops preside over young men from twelve to twenty-one years of age, but there is another
great army of 36,880 men over the age of twenty-one in the wards and stakes of the Church,
still holding the Aaronic Priesthood. It is needless to point out to you that they, too, are your
responsibility and mine, and these souls are precious in the sight of the Good Shepherd. There
devolves upon us the responsibility to so motivate them and inspire them to the end that they
will qualify and make themselves worthy to receive the Melchizedek Priesthood and all of its
attendant blessings. 
</p><p>
The future of the Church depends upon the youth of today. Their leadership will be no more
effective nor efficient than that for which you and I qualify and train them.
</p><p>
May we inspire every boy and young man who comes under our direction to so live the
gospel and feel the importance of the priesthood that the young sisters, the companions of
these boys and young men, will also be influenced to live righteously. Then, at some future
date, because of their virtuous lives, these young men and women will enjoy the blessings of
the Priesthood together with their life's companions. May the Lord bless us to the end that
our efforts in behalf of these young servants of the Boy of Nazareth may bring into fruition
his statement, "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?" which I humbly pray
will be the blessing not only of the Aaronic Priesthood but of the Melchizedek Priesthood and
every mother and every daughter in Israel. 
</p>
</div>
</div>
