<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">And the Gospel Must First Be Published</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Victor L. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Victor L. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 34-37</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
In recent days, it has been my privilege to walk on the shores of the Sea of Galilee where
Jesus, speaking to two fishermen, Simon and Andrew, said: "Come ye after me, and I will
make you to become fishers of men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/1/17#17">Mark 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
As I stood on the Mount of Olives, looking toward Jerusalem, I recalled that on this same
mount, the Master instructed Peter, James, John, and Andrew as to the future of the world,
even as to his second coming (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/6-7#6">Matt. 24:6-7</a>). He told them of wars and rumors of wars, of terrible 
calamities that would befall nations, kingdoms, and peoples before the Son of Man would
come in clouds of great power and glory (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/30#30">Matt. 24:30</a>).
</p><p>
Another statement Mark attributes to the Savior on this same occasion took
on new meaning for me.  He said: "And the gospel must first be published among all
nations" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/13/10#10">Mark 13:10</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Assignment to increase communication of gospel to the world</b>
</p><p>
Approximately two years ago, the First Presidency of the Church directed the Presiding
Bishopric to establish a translation, publishing, and distribution organization, with the charge
that Spanish-speaking members of the Church in Mexico, Central America, and South
America were to receive the literature and materials of the Church in their own language and
that they were to receive them at the same time they were received by the members of the
Church in the center stakes.
</p><p>
<b>Translating increases</b>
</p><p>
Shortly thereafter, Portuguese and the languages of western Europe&mdash;Finnish, Swedish,
Norwegian, Danish, Dutch, German, French, and Italian&mdash;were included. And now in recent
days, Samoan, Tahitian, and Tongan have been added.
</p><p>
Bishop Vandenberg asked that I represent the Presiding Bishopric in carrying out this
assignment. During these past two years, many faith-promoting and inspiring events have
taken place. May I share some with you.
</p><p>
In approaching such an assignment, one first begins by developing an organization. This
involves people. It is my conviction that the Lord has touched the hearts and the lives of men
and women in many lands who&mdash;have been preparing for such a work, and then he has led
us to them.
</p><p>
As Brother J. Thomas Fyans, the director of the overall organization, and I have traveled over
the world, carrying out our assignment, we have marveled at what has taken place.
</p><p>
We traveled to one distant land, not having an idea as to the course of action that would be
necessary. Within two or three hours after meeting with the mission presidents involved, our
course of action was as clear as though we had spent weeks of analysis. We were able to
appoint a manager and initiate the work within a matter of hours after our arrival.
</p><p>
One of the mission presidents said, "We are ready for a stake in our mission, but it cannot be
accomplished in our mission until your program is in operation." The program is in operation.
The first stake in South America was organized under the direction of Elders Spencer W.
Kimball and Franklin D. Richards, May 1, 1966, in Sao Paulo, Brazil.
</p><p>
Within the last few weeks, a similar experience has taken place in another area of the world.
Several weeks ago, as we traveled to New Zealand to meet with the mission presidents of the
South Pacific, we had no idea as to the means for the solution to the literature problems of
the Church in the non-English languages of the South Sea islands. After meeting only a few
hours with Elder Thomas S. Monson, Elder Paul H. Dunn, and the mission presidents, again
the course was clear. Now we have a manager in this area and a building has been leased.
The preparatory work to translate the Church literature into Samoan, Tongan and Tahitian is
moving forward at full speed. Of course, all of this is under the direction of the First
Presidency and those members of the Twelve responsible for these areas of the world.
</p><p>
As we have met with the translation personnel in the various countries, I have marveled at
their unusual talents translating is a very exacting work, requiring considerable training and
much concentration. Just because someone is familiar with a particular language does not
mean he can translate into that language. Each translation applicant is given a thorough test,
which he must pass before he can begin to work with us. Many who would like to do this
work cannot because they are not sufficiently well trained. There are many words and terms
in English that cannot be translated directly into other languages. The translator must have the
ability to transfer the author's meaning from one language and culture to another with an
absolute minimum of distortion. This is most difficult. It is even difficult sometimes
to be sure one understands the author's intent in English. Take, for instance,
the translator who received a Relief Society lesson for translation. In the lesson was a recipe
calling for "Chicken of the Sea." Every Relief Society sister knows that "Chicken of the Sea"
is a brand of tuna fish&mdash;that is, every sister in the United States. The translator checked her
encyclopedia and other reference books. She checked the library and university. Finally, in
desperation, she translated "Chicken of the Sea" as "hen of the ocean."
</p><p>
Here is what one of our wonderful Danish translators has to say about translating work in the
Church: 
</p><p>
"I should like to tell you just a fraction of what you ought to know when asked to translate
MIA books. You have to be a dancing master, beauty specialist, choir director, and you have
to know something about sports and athletics. You should be a chemist or a druggist. You
should be an educated musician. You ought to know something about baking, cooking,
gardening, arranging of flowers; something about singing, acting, first aid, and puppet shows.
</p><p>
"You have to know as much as possible of Church organizations and of how the different
auxiliaries are organized and how they work. In some cases, you will have to call the ministry
of education, the airport, the fire service a domestic science college, the Olympic games
committee, and the inspector of business. You have to know about weights and measures and
of the different expressions used by lawyers, and so forth.
</p><p>
"You must know the scriptures, and it is good if you know Shakespeare's works almost by
heart, because you will often find quotations or citations without any references. You must be
able to know where to find a quotation, if it belongs to the Bible, the Book of Mormon,
Doctrine and Covenants or Pearl of Great Price, and also if it is written by Matthew, John, or
Paul."
</p><p>
Another of our translators received the songbook <i>The Children Sing</i> to be translated into
German. Music is most difficult to translate, and <i>The Children Sing</i> is no exception. In this
case, however, the translator could not write fast enough to keep up with the flow of words as
they came to her.
</p><p>
There was no doubt in her mind as to the source of her inspiration.
</p><p>
One example of devotion was manifest in the life of a lovely sister who recently passed away.
She had just completed translating the book <i>Jesus the Christ</i> into Swedish, her native tongue.
Her manuscript was typewritten. This does not seem unusual until we are made aware of the
fact that she was almost totally paralyzed and was so crippled that she pressed one key at a
time with a rubber-pointed stick. You can imagine the thousands of times this stick held in
her gnarled hand had to be depressed on a typewriter key to record the teachings of this book
in her native language.
</p><p>
There are many other stories, some humorous, some serious, all examples of devotion and
faith.
</p><p>
It might be well to indicate in general the materials to be translated. Of course, the
standard works have been translated into many languages. They will be done in others as the
First Presidency directs. Other approved books will be translated. Material to appear in the
July monthly unified magazine is being worked on today.
</p><p>
The programs that have been
correlated for the English-speaking Saints, such as home teaching, family home evening,
Melchizedek Priesthood, Aaronic Priesthood, and the Relief Society lessons, will be available
in the Latin American and European languages on September 1, 1967, which is the date they
will also be introduced in the English language.
</p><p>
Once these materials have been translated, they must be printed and distributed to the officers,
teachers, and members of the Church. Six printing and distribution centers have been
established to accomplish this phase of the work.
</p><p>
In Copenhagen, Denmark, we are now prepared to serve Finland, Sweden, Norway, and
Denmark. In Liege, Belgium, service is being provided for all French- and Dutch-speaking
members of the Church. Frankfurt, Germany, is providing service to the
German and Italian members; Sao Paulo, Brazil, to the Portuguese: Mexico City, to the
Spanish. Auckland, New Zealand, will soon be in operation, providing services to Samoa,
Tonga, and Tahiti.
</p><p>
In each case, we are convinced that special men, with particular training  abilities, have been
called. Time after time, I have heard such comments as this: "Now, we finally know why we
moved here," or, "I know my training over the years has been to prepare to accomplish this
work." These and many other comments have come have come from our associates. Most of
them have been members of the Church for less than five years.
</p><p>
<b>Aided by correlation</b>
</p><p>
All of this work is being accomplished under the direction of the First Presidency and the
Council of the Twelve. It is possible today because of the great correlation program that is in
the Church. I think it would be almost impossible without correlation.
</p><p>
Our associates, both at home and abroad, are motivated by the desire to be anxiously engaged
in this great cause as we contemplate the 90th section of the Doctrine and Covenants, 11th
verse, we realize the Lord is speaking of our day. He says: "For it shall come to pass in that
day, that every man shall hear the fulness of the gospel in his own tongue, and in his own
language" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/11#11">D&amp;C 90:11</a>).
</p><p>
We feel this work is a literal fulfillment of prophecy. We are deeply grateful for the great
privilege of being a small part in making it possible for many thousands to hear the fullness
of the gospel in their own language. If I interpret the scriptures correctly, all of this is to the
end "that his kingdom may go forth upon the earth, that the inhabitants thereof may receive it
and be prepared for the days to come, in the which the Son of Man shall come down in
heaven, clothed in the brightness of his glory, to meet the kingdom of God which is set up on
the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/65/5#5">D&amp;C 65:5</a>).
</p><p>
It is my witness, my brothers and sisters, that God lives, that Jesus Christ will come again,
and that there is much to be done before he comes. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
