<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Changing World for the Barry Begays</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 65-72</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters: I desire today to emphasize our responsibility to the children of
Father Lehi. In preface may I present this human drama composed of several acts and a
number of scenes.
</p><p>
<b>Actors and Setting</b>
</p><p>
The time: yesterday, today, and tomorrow. The place: the world. The performers: flesh and
blood and spirit people, awakening from the centuries' long sleep of their ancestors.
</p><p>
There he is running like the wind, barefoot, hatless, long hair in flight, in worn overalls and
ragged shirt, his face brown, not only by the Arizona sun and wind, but from his parents,
themselves brown-skinned. Barry and his little brother and sisters are a lively group, playing
around the rock, pole, and dirt hogan. As we approach they scamper to cover in the hogan.
Timidly in the doorway he peeks out as we approach. The Begays, sitting on the dirt floor,
are eating their meal.
</p><p>
There is a leg of mutton. There is fry bread. There are no spoons nor forks. There is no milk;
they have no cow. There is no salad, they have no garden. Their fare is scant.
</p><p>
Barry is seven. His little brother has no clothes on his little brown body. The little sisters have
long, full skirts like their mother's, some silver coins sewed to their blouses.
</p><p>
The mother wears a worn, purple, velveteen skirt, reaching nearly to her ankles and a waist of
greenish hue. Out here styles change slowly if at all. Her shoes are high-laced ones, her hair
in a bob at the back tied with white wool yam. The father is thin and tall. He wears his
curled-up hat even while he eats. They are not demonstrative, but it is evident that pride and
affection are in these humble quarters.
</p><p>
<b>Mother, Home and Daily Life</b>
</p><p>
A few days pass. It is bright and summery. Barry Begay is herding the few sheep. There is
little fat on their bones, for this pasture is overgrazed and is dry and dusty. The scraggly dog
also shows malnutrition. But as he barks and bites hind legs, the woolly animals heed
direction. The little boy has a man's responsibility, for there are coyotes and other predatory
animals also starving in this barren valley, and the sheep are precious. The lamb furnishes
meat for the table; the pelt covers the cold ground in their hogan, being at once rug, chair,
bed, cover. The fleece is sold at the trading post or saved to cord and spin and weave into
rugs to exchange for flour and cloth and food.
</p><p>
Under the shade of the lone cedar tree, Mother Begay, an expert in her field, sits on the
ground and laboriously works into an intricate design the yams she has dyed in brilliant
colors.
</p><p>
Two years have passed. Nine-year old Barry may now go to the new government school only
three miles away. How they want education for their children! Little Susie can now herd the
sheep and drive away the predatory thieves. John Begay hitches up the hungry-looking horses
to the light spring wagon; and they all drive to the school near the trading post, the mother
and the children sitting on the floor, the father driving. For Barry it will be a long walk, and
at times the wind will be merciless, the sun will beat down like a blowtorch, and the snow
will be wet and freezing; but loving parents, ambitious to give their children what they never
had, and a starry-eyed little boy are determined to make the effort.
</p><p>
<b>Begays Are Baptized</b>
</p><p>
A year has passed eventfully. It is a summer day, and the wind in whirling cones picks up
trash and tumbleweeds and dances across the valley. Two fair and well-groomed young men
are walking toward the hogan. Father Begay is fixing his wagon, and Mother Begay sits under
the gnarled, weathered cedar, weaving her blanket.
</p><p>
"<i>Yatehee</i>," they say in greeting as they wipe the sweat from their brows and introduce
themselves as missionaries for The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The Begays
have heard about the elders whom they called <i>gamalii</i>. They become interested as they listen.
From the briefcase comes a little black book, and in spite of the Navajo-English language
barrier, John and Mary Begay seemed to understand that the book was a history of their "old
people" back for ages. It seemed that the spirit which accompanied the strange mixture of
words and signs was like a "familiar spirit" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/4#4">Isa. 29:4</a>).
Curiosity, genuine interest, and the pleasing
personalities of the teenage ministers brought about many hours of learning, and then one day
it happened. The Begay family members were baptized in the little pond some distance away,
and when they had returned to the hogan, the young men laid their hands on their heads and
conferred upon each the Holy Ghost. The Begays were members of the far-away Salt Lake
City church, in which they now had confidence and a warm feeling of belonging. The
missionaries returned frequently and taught them. Sundays, the family drove the wagon to the
little branch many miles away to meet with the other Indians who were also joining the
Church.
</p><p>
<b>Indian Seminary</b>
</p><p>
Time moves on. The Mormon elders have moved a trailer house near the school, and Barry
attends the seminary they are teaching. It is crowded, but the elders tell the little red men
stories about their forebears and teach them honesty and kindness and goodness and of the
big, wide world "out there" where Indian children may have all that non-Indian children have.
The little Indians have found real friends in the young elders as they learn English, ethics, and
doctrine not taught in the secular school.
</p><p>
<b>Placement Program</b>
</p><p>
Barry is ten years old now, husky, laughing, running, and joking. He is summer-herding the
sheep. The missionaries have announced a fantastic program. Barry may go to faraway Utah
and live in a good home, attend a superior school, and be given advantages not afforded on
the reservation. "Unthinkable," his parents feel at first, to send their little boy so far away for
so long a time, but the Littlehorse family had spent one season in the beet fields up there and
glowingly told of that promised land of prosperity and opportunity. Convinced it was for
Barry's good, they agreed.
</p><p>
When the time came, all the family went in the wagon to the point of assembly, a day's
journey away, and, with few tears but pounding hearts, placed their loved boy on the big bus
with about thirty other little Indian boys and girls. They stoically stood like statues until the
bus disappeared over the distant horizon. The hogan was a little empty without Barry, but
opportunity would come to him. The chaperones on the bus were pleasant and tender, the bus
driver was kindly, and their faith in their new Mormon brothers and sisters sustained them.
</p><p>
A few days later the Begays relived at the trading post a fat letter from the Smiths, the foster
family here Barry had become a loved member, telling the intriguing story of how the bus
had been met by interested case workers, former missionaries who fed the Indian people, how
he had been shingled by a kindly volunteer barber, bathed and shampooed by other friendly
volunteer men, and then had been examined by dentists and doctors and interested and
concerned nurses, all of whom freely gave their time without compensation. The letter told
then of a loving family driving to their comfortable home far away&mdash;how he had
immediately found real companionship in a white brother his own age. The letter told of
Barry's timidity and silence at first and then his blossoming out when he felt the warmth in
his new home and family. And there was a picture of Barry. He is in new overalls and shirt
and seemed happy.
</p><p>
<b>Family Life</b>
</p><p>
Barry has been home for two summers and eagerly returned to Utah each August. The Begay
family themselves are on the big bus headed northward. They locate the Smith family home,
and what a joy to these good parents as they find Barry sharing a pleasant room with Sammy.
They visit the school, and Barry and Sammy come meet them&mdash;white and brown, arms about
each other. What an exultant moment! Embraces, tears, affection, pride. Barry is clean and
neat, his eyes sparkling. It is evident he is well accepted here. The teacher comes to meet
them, and there is warmth and friendliness.
</p><p>
The Begays attend the Sunday services with the foster family. They are little fearful of all
these sophisticated folks but are soon at ease, and many me to greet them. In the Sunday
school there are two or three hundred people, all Mormons like themselves. Two young
people give extemporaneous talks, one a little white girl and the other their own Barry. He
stands up speaks up in good English, and their pride knows no bounds. The Sacrament is
administered, and, with nine other boys about the same size, Barry, a deacon, carries the plate
with the broken bread, then the tray with the little paper cups of water blessed by two larger
boys, one of them also an Indian.
</p><p>
What a new world the Begays have now entered! What a world of opportunity for their
firstborn. They will try to get their little girls also in the program. They return home at peace,
knowing their son is in good hands.
</p><p>
<b>Service In the Church</b>
</p><p>
The summers are delightful for Barry. He is back with the sheep&mdash;back in the hogan, where
there are now beds and a table and chairs. He is helping the Begay family to get into the
regular habit of family prayers on their knees, which was so foreign to them, but they are
learning the "Lord's way." They are speaking better English now that Barry teaches them.
This carefree summer is a happy one for all the family. Out in the wind and the weather, he
runs and yells and plays. On Sundays the Begays drive to the distant branch, and Barry helps
with the Sacrament and speaks in the meeting, telling about his experiences in the northern
land.
</p><p>
The summer is over, and Barry is as eager to go as he was to return home. Again the family
is at the gathering point, and three instead of one climb out of the Begay wagon and board
the big bus for the north. The two sisters have mixed feelings of awe and wonder and fear
and eagerness. With near empty arms and hearts, the Begay parents return with their smaller
ones to the hogan. Their personal sacrifices for their children are calculated ones.
</p><p>
Arriving in Utah, there are happy renewals of friendships. His white brother is overjoyed at
the reunion. Barry is now a teacher in the priesthood, and, with a white adult brother, he visits
five families and teaches them the gospel. Barry and Sammy are enrolled in seminary where
they learn the gospel and to pray and speak and socialize. Barry is in MIA, the youth
organization, and takes part in the dramatic skits, sings in the music groups, and is prominent
in athletics. Young Begay for two years wears a Scout uniform purchased with money his
generous foster family made possible for him to earn. He will go to Provo with hundreds of
other Explorers, white, brown, and yellow. Now he is a priest. He may baptize with authority,
bless the Sacrament emblems; in fact, no privilege of any boy is denied this fast-growing,
young brave.
</p><p>
<b>Graduation</b>
</p><p>
Eventful, full years have passed. It is graduation night, and Barry and his friend-brother are in
cap and gown and in the line to receive high school diplomas. His foster family are as proud
of Barry as of their own son. Barry has been president of his class, presiding over white and
red. He was swift and strong and accurate on the ward basketball team. He has participated in
every activity of the school, Church, and community.
</p><p>
At home this summer, he finds his parents have been prospering. Their faithful lives have
brought them a degree of prosperity. No money do they spend on tobacco or liquor. All goes
into their progressive living. Barry is surprised to find this time a two-room, frame house out
in front of the hogan. There are curtains at the windows and rugs on the lumber floors and a
cupboard with dishes and pots and pans. The gospel and the church associations are working
miracles with the Begay family. When on Sunday he is called on to speak by the Indian
president of the branch, he stands tall and straight and there is firmness in his voice as he
says: "I am proud I am a Mormon. I am grateful for all the kindness of the people of the
Church. I am proud I am an Indian. I am proud of my people. I intend to train to serve them,
I shall attend Brigham Young University, and then I desire to fulfill a mission for the
Church."
</p><p>
<b>Missionaries, Red and White</b>
</p><p>
Another year is history. Two young nineteen-year-olds, one red and one white, are driving a
car on the Indian reservation. They approach a cluster of hogans and spend the day among the
families. The white companion sits quietly, adding a thought now and then; but the Indian
elder&mdash;for he now holds the highest priesthood known to man&mdash;can speak two languages
fluently. He knows these people's thinking processes, their idioms and expressions, their
reactions. He is educated and inspires confidence. Coffee is thrown away, and milk
substituted. No more liquor for these good people&mdash;that money will go into fixing up the
home. A baptismal service is being conducted at the river, and twenty men, women, and
children are brought into the fold of Christ's Church. The two missionaries take turns in
baptizing and confirming. A little branch is soon organized; and Elder Begay is its first
president, soon to be replaced by the older Indian converts as they are trained.
</p><p>
<b>Teaching Navajo</b>
</p><p>
We enter a new chapel on the reservation and hear a chatter which is unintelligible. Why such
a noise on this weekday morning? We open the door and see about ten young missionaries in
a semicircle and Barry, the expert, as instructor. He is drilling them in Navajo so that they
may better reach the understanding of the Indians on the reservation. He gives them a word.
In unison they repeat it over and over. He corrects their pronunciation. He gives them a
sentence, and they respond individually and as a group hundreds of times. A couple of intense
hours and they take a breather, then are at it again. Their sounds must be near perfect. From
Monday to Saturday they drill, then return to proselyting for three weeks using that which
they have learned, and they note that the Navajos listen more intently now. Another week of
drilling, then three weeks putting to use that which they have learned. Oh, how the Indians
drink in the gospel message as it comes flowing clearly and distinctly from Elder Begay and
his companions. The baptisms increase, and the branches grow.
</p><p>
<b>To College</b>
</p><p>
Two years have flown by as by magic. Elder Begay says farewell to his fellow missionaries,
stops a few days at the Begay home to ruffle his hair, put on his old overalls, run with the
dog, tend the sheep, and to tell his loved folks more about the glorious message he has
learned&mdash;and of the beautiful, talented Indian girl he met at the university, and of her concurrent
mission in the Northern Indian Mission, and of his growing romantic interest in her. As he
returns to college the wise and generous tribe gives him a scholarship, making his further
education a certainty. There is pride and heartache, loneliness and joy as the Begays wave at
the northbound bus heading for Provo [Utah].
</p><p>
<b>At the Temple</b>
</p><p>
Time flies on wings of lightning. We are now in a beautiful temple dedicated in "holiness to
the Lord." The room is large, modest, exquisite. The tan rug helps keep a sacred quietness. In
the center is the altar tastefully upholstered. Many people are here in white, for they, with
Barry and the returned lady missionary Gladys, also have previously secured their holy
endowments in the temple. The many witnesses are both Indian and non-Indian.
</p><p>
Four parents are here, exultant: the foster parents, the Smiths, so kind and gracious and
generous, and there, miracle of miracles, are John and Mary Begay. The years and the
associations have made some changes. They are older now. His long bobbed hair of years ago
is short. He has been wearing a suit; his shoes have been shined and his clothes pressed.
There he sits, tall and dark and handsome in his white temple clothes&mdash;robes appearing to be
even whiter in contrast with his ruddy, happy, smiling face. And there sits Mary. Though she
still loves her beads and turquoise, her silver and her velveteen, she now modernizes and
styles her hair and dresses. And there she sits smiling, wondering, expectant, and happy
beyond expression. Today she is to be sealed for all eternity to this stalwart husband with
whom she has shared joy and pain, hardship and privilege, wind and weather, and she will be
his loved wife for endless ages. How glad she was that the Mormon elders found her long ago
weaving under that gnarled cedar! These new gospel truths are even more beautiful now.
</p><p>
And here we are in the house of the Lord, and with the eternal priceless keys of the
priesthood, I am performing these holy ordinances. What a beautiful couple they are as tall,
stalwart, intelligent Barry and his bright-eyed sweetheart Gladys stand admiring each other,
then kneel and are sealed for all eternity! She wipes a tear, and his eyes are glistening. These
and the tears from others around the room are not white tears or red tears for tears are not
white tears or red tears, for tears are colorless, but impressive tears as they roll down both
brown faces and white.
</p><p>
And now John and Mary come to the altar. Ah! What joy! What satisfaction! What
accomplishment! A long looked for and awaited privilege is finally here. They kneel at the
altar. The faces, which were near expressionless that first time we saw them, are now
beaming. There is a new light in those eyes. In their white temple clothing, they look
heavenly. And through the impressive priesthood ceremony, Mary becomes the wife of John
for all eternity. These tears are quiet, happy tears. There are, you know, tears of ecstasy and
joy, and these were of that holy kind.
</p><p>
Now John and Mary and Barry and his brother and sisters, all in white, become a tightly sealed
eternal family. The guests are embracing them, and happy faces respond to kindly congratulations.
</p><p>
<b>Degrees</b>
</p><p>
The today is gone, tomorrow dawns. More years pass on. We are on the university campus.
The organ is playing a staccato march. A long double line of people in dark gowns, some
adorned with bright colors and all with tasseled caps, march from the gathering field to the
auditorium. The main body of the house is occupied by the graduates, the sidelines by
relatives and friends. I peer about for certain faces. Ah yes, they are there on the sixth row,
and the Begay parents are beaming. By them is Gladys with two little ones by her side and a
baby in her arms. The marching lines are punctuated with darker faces. Yes, there is an Indian
graduate, and there, and there, and there. How rewarding! And there is Barry. How handsome
he is, and poised! Our pride is boundless. And now the president of the university is awarding
the doctor's degrees. When the name "Barry Begay" is spoken, my heart jumps. Barry Begay
with a doctor's degree! Our Barry Begay with a PhD! <i>Our</i> Barry Begay! All our efforts, our
disappointments, our worries, our battles with contending forces, all our waiting and striving
and praying! Our dreams are coming true! John, Mary, and Gladys modestly wait their turn to
express pride and affection to their Dr. Barry Begay.
</p><p>
<b>Tribal Leadership</b>
</p><p>
The scene changes to the Hole in the Rock at the Red Haystacks Cliffs at Window Rock.
Several years have passed. We enter the little "Pentagon" in little "Washington," and at his
desk in a most vital position is tribal councilman Barry Begay, tall and handsome and
wielding a powerful influence among his people. Because of him and his fellow workers, the
Indians now ride in better cars on safer highways to better homes. There are lights and water
and telephones and radio and TV. Their sick and afflicted are treated in modern,
well-equipped hospitals, and Indian nurses attend the patients for whom Indian doctors
prescribe and on whom they operate. Tribal funds derived from gas, oil, coal, and timber
guarantee every Indian child schooling through college. The former powwows are now
fairs&mdash;dignified, colorful, impressive, national attractions. The Indians are experts on the farm, on
the grazing lands, in the silversmith shop. Indian teachers train the little ones; Indian lawyers
look after legal matters. Trained Indians are prominent in office, industry, business,
government, and on college faculties. There are Indian governors, senators, and impressive
and influential laymen.
</p><p>
<b>Church Leadership</b>
</p><p>
The scene changes and years pass. It is the Sabbath, and stake conference is in session. The
great congregation is mostly Indian. The one-hundred voice choir is a dark-skinned folk,
though they are now much lighter. They have long been delightsome. It is 10 am. General
Authorities from Salt Lake City are on the stand. The high council and the bishoprics, largely
Indian, sit on the stand of the newly completed stake and ward building. Here is dignity and
impressiveness. Three thousand eyes and an equal number of ears are focused on the
impressive man who rises to the pulpit and opens the stake conference. It is President Barry
Begay, former bishop, called Doctor Begay at the little "Pentagon," who preaches such a
profound sermon to his people. His children are all being well trained. His son Barry, Jr., is
on a mission in Bolivia.
</p><p>
It is President Begay, Doctor Begay, Brother Begay, Elder Begay who administers to the sick
in the hospital, preaches funeral sermons, assists people with their marital, moral, financial
problems. It is <i>our</i> Barry Begay, a little boy who is now a big man.
</p><p>
<b>Finale</b>
</p><p>
Barry Begay is typical. There are thousands of Barrys. They are of many tribes from New
York to San Diego, and from Alaska to Florida, and from the isles of the sea. They are of
numerous tribes and of many languages and dialects. They are coming from Cardston and
Bemidji, from Blackfoot and Hopi-land, from South America and Mexico. They are coming
to training in schools and church, growing in wisdom and coming into their own, learning the
best of the white man's culture and retaining the best of their own.
</p><p>
The Lord chose to call them Lamanites. They are fulfilling prophecies. They are a chosen
people with rich blood in their veins. They are casting off the fetters of superstition, fear,
ignorance, and prejudice and are clothing themselves with knowledge, good works, and
righteousness. And this Church is elated to have an important part in bringing about this
transformation. The prophet echoed the promise of the Father of us all when he wrote: 
</p><p>
"And blessed are they who shall seek to bring forth my Zion at that day, for they shall have
the gift and the power of the Holy Ghost, and if they endure unto the end they shall be lifted
up at the last day . . . how beautiful upon the mountains shall they be"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/37#37">1 Ne. 13:37</a>).
</p><p>
Yesterday they were deprived, weakening, vanishing; today thousands are benefiting in the
Indian seminaries, in regular seminaries and institutes as they become involved in the
placement program and church work within the stakes and missions. Numerous are receiving
secular as well as spiritual training in Mexico, South America, and Hawaii and the isles of the
sea. Many are now in college and large numbers in full-time mission service. Tens of
thousands are now eligible for superior training and service through church organizations in
all the Americas and in the Pacific. Lamanite-Nephite leaders are now standing forth to direct
and inspire their people. <i>The day of the Lamanite is come</i>, and tomorrow will be even better.
</p><p>
<b>Waif from the Streets</b>
</p><p>
May I conclude with this experience of my friend and brother, Boyd K. Packer, as he returned
from Peru. It was in a branch Sacrament meeting. The chapel was filled, the opening
exercises finished, and the Sacrament in preparation. A little Lamanite ragamuffin entered
from the street. His two shirts would scarcely make one, so ragged they were and torn and
worn. It was unlikely that those shirts had ever been off that little body since they were
donned. Calloused and chapped were the little feet which brought him in the open door, up
the aisle, and to the Sacrament table. There was dark and dirty testimony of deprivation, want,
unsatisfied hungers&mdash;spiritual as well as physical. Almost unobserved he shyly came to the
Sacrament table and with a seeming spiritual hunger, leaned against the table and lovingly
rubbed his unwashed face against the cool, smooth, white linen.
</p><p>
A woman on a front seat, seemingly outraged by the intrusion, caught his eye and with
motion and frown sent the little ragamuffin scampering down the aisle out into this world, the
street.
</p><p>
A little later, seemingly compelled by some inner urge, he overcame his timidity and came
stealthily, cautiously down the aisle again, fearful, ready to escape if necessary, but impelled
as though directed by inaudible voices with "a familiar spirit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/4#4">Isa. 29:4</a>) and as though memories long
faded were reviving, as though some intangible force were crowding him on to seek
something for which he yearned but could not identify.
</p><p>
<b>Safe Harbor</b>
</p><p>
From his seat on the stand, Elder Packer caught his eye, beckoned to him, and stretched out
big, welcoming arms. A moment's hesitation and the little ragamuffin was nestled
comfortably on his lap, in his arms, the tousled head against a great warm heart&mdash;a heart
sympathetic to waifs, and especially to little Lamanite ones. It seemed the little one had found
a safe harbor from a stormy sea, so contented he was. The cruel, bewildering, frustrating
world was outside. Peace, security, acceptance enveloped him.
</p><p>
Later Elder Packer sat in my office and, in tender terms and with a subdued voice, rehearsed
this incident to me. As he sat forward on his chair, his eyes glistening, a noticeable emotion in
his voice, he said, "As this little one relaxed in my arms, it seemed it was not a single little
Lamanite I held. It was a nation, indeed a multitude of nations of deprived, hungering souls,
wanting something deep and warm they could not explain&mdash;a humble people yearning to
revive memories all but faded out&mdash;of ancestors standing wide-eyed, openmouthed, expectant
and excited, looking up and seeing a holy, glorified Being descend from celestial areas, and
hearing a voice say: 'Behold, I am Jesus Christ, the Son of God. I created the heavens and the
earth, and all things that in them are . . . and in me hath the Father glorified his name . . .
</p><p>
"'I am the light and the life of the world. I am Alpha and Omega, the beginning and the end'"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/15,18#15">3 Ne. 9:15,18</a>).
</p><p>
This day of the Lamanite brings opportunity. Millions farm the steep hillsides of Andean
ranges and market their produce with llamas and horses and burros. They must have the
emancipating gospel. Millions serve in menial labor, eke out bare subsistence from soil and
toil. They must hear the compelling truths of the gospel. Millions are tied to reservations,
deprived, untrained, and less than they could be. They must have the enlightening gospel. It
will break their fetters, stir their ambition, increase their vision and open new worlds of
opportunity to them. Their captivity will be at an end&mdash;captivity from misconceptions,
illiteracy, superstition, fear. "The clouds of error disappear before the rays of truth divine."
(Parley P. Pratt, <i>Hymns</i> 269.)
</p><p>
And Nephi's vision is realized: 
</p><p>
". . . I beheld that the church of the Lamb, who were the saints of God, were also upon all
the face of the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/14/12#12">1 Ne. 14:12</a>).
</p><p>
The brighter day has dawned. The scattering has been accomplished; the gathering is in
process. May the Lord bless us all as we become nursing fathers and mothers (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/49/23#23">Isa. 49:23</a> and
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/21/23#23">1 Ne. 21:23</a>)
unto our Lamanite brethren and hasten the fulfillment of the great promises
made to them, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
