<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marvin O. Ashton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marvin O. Ashton, <i>Conference Report</i>, pp. 45-46</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Clark's concern in the short time left and the number of us yet to be heard from,
reminds us we must be brief. A minister in his efforts to impress his good people with the
miraculous in nature observed in his talk this particular Sunday that in every blade of grass
there was a sermon. The following Saturday one of the boys of the parish found the minister
cutting his lawn. In greeting his spiritual adviser the boy exclaimed, "Reverend, I am sure
glad to see you cutting your sermons short." I shall make you happy in making my sermon
short.
</p><p>
Will you please have your thinking machinery shift gears into the realm of temporal affairs?
The temporal problems are the responsibilities of the Presiding Bishopric, and to be frank
with you we don't blush in reminding you of them from time to time. In quoting Joseph
Smith, I was interested in what Brother Marion Romney had to say about the temporal and
the spiritual things of the Church. The Prophet observed that the man who could make an
intelligent demarcation would be a very wise man. Brethren, in living our religion, we just
can't get away from the temporal things. They "smack us in the eye," so to speak, everywhere
we go, and if we hope to have our thinking on terra firma, we've got to meet fairly and
squarely our stewardship. We brethren assembled here tonight are the directors of this great
Church corporation, of course, keeping in mind that the bishops working with us are
influenced and guided, if you please, by our attitude and instructions. Some people are so
constituted that even common sense must be reinforced with chapter and verse. For their
benefit, here we go: "And even the bishop, who is a judge, and his counselors, if they are not
faithful in their stewardship shall be condemned, and others shall be planted in their stead"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/40#40">D&amp;C 64:40</a>).
</p><p>
Please keep in mind that you have fifteen hundred buildings in this Church. If you put an
average value of twenty thousand dollars on each, the minimum value of Church property is
at least thirty million dollars. I dare say your cost of replacement would be nearer one
hundred million dollars. Now don't forget this depreciation business. Still using the minimum
figure: one percent depreciation is three hundred thousand dollars per year; two percent or the
figure used by the government in the most substantial construction will be six hundred
thousand dollars per year. If you depreciate those buildings five percent, as the neglect some
buildings get will indicate, (and that isn't fiction) your depreciation per year would be one
million five hundred thousand dollars.
</p><p>
I ask you who is the "watch dog" of the treasury? Is he only that fellow who writes out the
checks? Is he only the one who watches the gates of the Church vaults? In a big sense the
"watch dogs" are those who are the custodians of our Church buildings. Don't forget it. "A
stitch in time saves nine." "Trifles make perfection, but perfection is no trifle."
</p><p>
I brought over with me today a board panel with some evidences of mistakes wired thereon.
Like other sins, here are displayed evidences of sins of omission and sins of commission.
Don't forget, one spark will burn up a million dollars of the hardest earned money in the
world. When you take a fuse plug and insert a penny therein, or twist the brass so it laps over
the contact in the center, that is a sin of commission. Yes, only a little thing, but the spark
may send smoke to the skies of our people's hard earned savings. Our people take the skin off
their hands in the sacrifices they make, and plain carelessness burns up in a minute the results
of such sacrifices. That fuse plug is so constructed as to make for you a night watchman to
guard your property when you are asleep. He makes your absence from home safe from fire.
Yet in some of these sins of commission you take a six shooter, as it were, and pick him off.
Yes, you kill the guard that protects your home. We have asked you to install at a cost of
twenty-one dollars a low water cutoff in your boiler. Some of you won't. We ask you to test
the water in your boilers to save corroding, but you won't. Right while we talk, the good
people of a little ward who can't dig down any more will have to raise nine hundred dollars
to replace a boiler because some one blundered in a detail we are talking about &mdash; a little sin
of commission. In this boiler was inserted a leadlike substance as a plug which, when
subjected to extra heat, would melt and automatically shut off the furnace. What did he do?
He plugged the hole with a hickory stick &mdash; a sin of commission here. In some chapels we
have found the controls and safety appliances wired down, and maybe two hundred little
children on the floor just over this danger of explosion, they and their devoted teachers in
oblivion of the "dynamite" they are hovering over. If you want to get some faith-promoting
stories, just follow us around to some of the Church buildings and see how the Lord has His
arm around us. Keeping in mind our carelessness, if the Lord didn't have His arms around us,
we'd have a hundred fires a year.
</p><p>
We are still talking about the temporal things. The lives of' our people are at stake. I don't
care whether you place the Church property at thirty million dollars or one hundred million
dollars, we are reminded in a big way that we are the watch dogs of the treasury. A custodian
is either too lazy or he doesn't know how to clean the ashes out of his stoker, and a
sacrificing handful of people have to dig down in their pockets for three hundred dollars for a
new stoker.
</p><p>
Another ward has to meet a bill of six hundred dollars for a new boiler because the custodian
failed to go to the expense of ten cents worth of labor and five cents for a postage stamp in
the examination of the water in his boiler.
</p><p>
A keeper of a ward's property won't clean out the old rags from the basement and thirty
thousand dollars honest-to-goodness toil and sacrifice goes up in smoke.
</p><p>
The skies of the most beautiful hamlet in our country are darkened by the smoke of a fifty
thousand dollar beautiful edifice and contents because the bishop would not take counsel as to
how easily fires are started by defective wiring.
</p><p>
It is like the Irishman who cut off one of his fingers in the rip saw and was showing his
friends how he did it. While demonstrating, he had to exclaim, "Gee, there goes another one."
Yes, brethren, while we are talking, there goes another meetinghouse up in smoke.
</p><p>
Now you stake presidents, we have asked you to appoint a member of your high council to be
the point of contact between our office and the wards of your stake. If you haven't done so,
please appoint him now and give as his name and address.
</p><p>
I do want to say this before I sit down: We compliment most of you men on the way you are
teaming with us. There are some of you who don't. We don't know why; when we visit your
places, we just don't understand; we can't understand it. As Bishop Richards said today,
climate doesn't determine what your stake is going to be. It is initiative. We keep crying and
crying to have some of these things taken care of, and they are not.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us in our responsibilities, I ask in the name of Jesus Christ, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
