<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Mission Calls and Selective Service</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Gordon B. Hinckley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Gordon B. Hinckley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 99-103</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I suppose, brethren, that not in a long while have we had a communication which has brought
greater disappointment than did the First Presidency's letter of September 22nd, placing
restrictions on the number of young men who may be recommended for missions. No one
feels more concerned than I over the thought that possibly some of our young men who have
counted on and dreamed of missions may not be able to go, at least in the immediate future.
</p><p>
<b>Draft Officials Cooperative</b>
</p><p>
I want to say that what has been done has been done voluntarily. For the past fifteen years I
have worked with draft officials in matters affecting our missionary program. From the
national director on down through state directors and local board members, I have found them
to be reasonable, fair, and disposed to be cooperative when they understand our program.
Only two weeks ago General [Lewis B.] Hershey was in Salt Lake City and met President
McKay and said in the course of that interview that it had been a pleasure to work with this
Church over the years in this difficult matter, and particularly so in comparison with some
other organizations with whom he had had to deal. We have come a long way since the days
of the Korean War, when we had such serious misunderstandings. At that time under the
inspired direction of President McKay and under the wise counseling of President Stephen L
Richards, his first counselor, we set about to establish a legal and legislative history so that
we might know where we stood should there develop such a situation as we are faced with
today.
</p><p>
<b>Rights of the Church: The Obligations of Citizens</b>
</p><p>
The repeated findings of the presidential appeal boards and the testimony of national Selective
Service officials before both the Senate and House Armed Services Committees leave no
doubt concerning the right of the Church to select, ordain, and send on missions such young
men as we feel to call under our established procedures, and the eligibility of these young
men for ministerial classifications. On the other hand, we recognize that the Selective Service
System has an obligation under the law to meet certain requirements and quotas and that
every young man in the United States who is a citizen, or who is in the United States as an
alien under certain circumstances, has a military obligation imposed by the law. I should like
to add parenthetically that the local draft boards did not write the law, that we did not write
the law, and that our young men did not write the law. Congress wrote the law, and if you
have complaints to make concerning the law, don't blame the draft board; more appropriately,
you might write your congressman.
</p><p>
We have an obligation to uphold and sustain the law
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/12#12">A of F 1:12</a>), as President Tanner made clear this
morning. Local draft boards are made up of local citizens who perform without remuneration
what at times must be for many of them an unpleasant duty. They deserve understanding
rather than recrimination. They do not establish policies and regulations of their own. These
are determined by national headquarters. I want to emphasize that we are not the enemy of
Selective Service and that Selective Service is not our enemy.
</p><p>
Now as you know, draft calls have increased from about 8,000 in April to 34,600 for
November. To meet these calls, national Selective Service headquarters, through state offices,
imposes quotas on local boards. The boards must meet their quotas. If one young man cannot
go for one reason or another, then some other Young man must go in his place. We should
bear this fact in mind.
</p><p>
I have wanted to set forth these general principles as a preamble to what I wish to say briefly
about our specific problem.
</p><p>
About 45 percent of our entire full-time missionary force comes from stakes within the area
of Utah. It will be readily apparent to all that any appreciable increase in the number of
young men sent on missions at a time when draft calls have been increased more than 400
percent could quickly result in serious tensions within local communities. These matters are
likely to become emotional issues without regard to the facts. Parenthetically, I should like to
mention one or two facts.
</p><p>
<b>Deferment for Missionary Service, and School</b>
</p><p>
Our figures indicate that for comparable periods we have sent only 4 percent more young men
on missions during 1965 than we sent during 1964. The natural growth of the Church would
account for that increase. Actually, with all of the emphasis placed on getting more young
men on missions that has been given in stake conferences, antedating by many months the
increased draft calls, we might reasonably have expected a larger increase. I have said this
only to set the record straight, that except for possibly an occasional instance there has been
no apparent abuse on the part of bishops and stake presidents and no apparent effort on the
part of young men to go on missions to escape the draft, as some may have inferred. Why
should there be? Under present regulations a young man may continue in school and qualify
for deferment. But because tensions were beginning to build in some communities, as more
and more young men were ordered for induction while other young men were going on
missions, Utah Selective Service officials came to us and requested our cooperation in setting
up a program to provide some restraint and control on the number of young men sent on
missions, and thus make it possible for local boards to anticipate the number of young men in
whose behalf the Church might request ministerial classifications. This program was designed
to permit approximately the same number to go this year as went last. We thought their
request to be reasonable and in the best interests of the Church, the Selective Service System,
and the young men themselves. The letter of September 22nd was the result.
</p><p>
We recognize that there has been some serious disappointment. We have been assured that if
it becomes apparent that the program as announced places too tight a restriction and results in
injustices, the entire matter will be discussed, and if feasible, adjustments will be made.
</p><p>
Numerous questions have been raised by church officers from other states where the problem
is not so acute. We have felt that the program should be the same throughout the nation.
There is wisdom in consistency and uniformity, and the more nearly we stay with uniform
procedures, the stronger our position in dealing with problems. We ask, therefore, that until
we have had opportunity to observe the effects of the announced program over a period of
months, that you follow it and not attempt negotiation with local officials in your particular
cities or states. We shall keep close to the matter and shall be available for consultation with
you at any time.
</p><p>
<b>The Plan of the Church for Cooperation with Selective Service</b>
</p><p>
Now very quickly, by way of amplifying and clarifying some points in the letter: The
effective periods set up are periods of six months, one missionary per ward each six months,
the dates being October 1st to March 31st inclusive, and April 1st to September 30th. The
governing date will be the date of the letter of call, and if there be any local board members
from the state of Utah who are listening to this tonight, I hope that they will not indulge in
any speculative discussion on this matter until they have talked with the state Selective
Service director or the deputy state director, with whom we have spent many hours in
meetings.
</p><p>
Ward and branch quotas will be transferable within the area of the stake under the direction of
the stake president, but will not be transferable at this time between the various stakes. No
young man who has actually received notice of induction should be recommended for a
mission. However, notice to report for preinduction physical examination should not be
regarded as a notice for induction. It will not be unusual to find a young man who even
though he has been called for a mission is ordered to report for preinduction physical
examination. He must take that examination; and if there are any conflicting dates involved, I
think that if you get in touch with us we can iron out those problems. We do not suggest that
you go to boards and hasten examinations with the thought that some young men may be
declared IV-F and may be able to go without being counted against the quotas.
</p><p>
<b>Classifications not Under Quotas</b>
</p><p>
Men in the following classifications will not be counted against the quotas. I would like to
take just a moment to explain these classifications: 
</p><p>
I-D are men with reserve classifications most of whom have served under the so-called six
months' program. Their status may be subject to adjustment, depending on what happens
concerning the reserves, and you should not consider that as a fixed situation governing the
future.
</p><p>
I-Y are men given temporary deferments because of physical handicaps.
</p><p>
IV-A are for the most part men who have served two or more years on active duty.
</p><p>
IV-F are men who are disqualified for physical or mental reasons. I want to say that many
men who have IV-F classifications can still be effective missionaries.
</p><p>
V-A are men 26 years of age or over and have no current military obligation.
</p><p>
<b>Members of student Wards; Church Builders</b>
</p><p>
Young men sent from student wards will be counted against the quotas of their home wards,
although there may be some converts to the Church who have a student ward as a home ward.
</p><p>
Church builders who are out of their own wards and Indian students under the placement
program will be considered as are students. No young man should be recommended for a
mission more than thirty days in advance of his nineteenth birthday, and all recommendations
concerning missionaries should give in detail the draft classification called for on the
recommendation form, and also the name of the ward and the stake whose quota will be used
by that particular individual.
</p><p>
<b>Measures for maintaining missionary work</b>
</p><p>
Now, brethren, we can do several things to keep the work going without a serious reduction
in results: 
</p><p>
1. We can strengthen our stake missions, which, in terms of hours spent, are far more fruitful
in converts than are our full-time missions in terms of hours spent.
</p><p>
2. We can resolve that each one of us will be a missionary as President McKay has requested
from this pulpit.
</p><p>
3. Bishops can and should appraise the older couples in their wards who might be eligible for
missionary service and who can give needed service under some circumstances.
</p><p>
<b>Plans and Saving for Missionary Service</b>
</p><p>
Several bishops have been in during the last few days and have said that our young men have
been saving money for years to go on missions. What shall they do? I say keep saving and
praying. I think that every priesthood holder in the Church ought to pray for peace, and I
have the faith that the Lord will hear and heed those prayers.
</p><p>
We know that wars will come upon the earth. The word of prophecy is clear on that. But
somehow I feel satisfied that God will hear our prayers and that most of those young men
who want to go on missions will have the opportunity to go on missions. Some who may not
have the opportunity may help others to go. Some years ago a letter came to the office of the
First Presidency reading substantially as follows: 
</p><p>
"Dear Brethren: 
</p><p>
"All my life I have dreamed of going on a mission. I saved my money to that end. Then
during the Korean War I was wounded, and I now carry a metal plate in my head. Because of
that you and my doctors have said that I should not go on a regular mission. I work hard all
day shoveling sand in a brick and tile factory. From my small wages I have been able to add
to my savings account. I have now withdrawn my savings and am sending you herewith a
cashier's check for $1,500. Since I cannot go, please use it to help some worthy boy who can.
I will share my savings with him and hope that he will share with me his joy as he labors in
the ministry of the Lord."
</p><p>
I hope that each young man who has been saving will go on saving and praying and preparing
for that day when every boy who desires to go may go, and that in the meantime we shall
have the faith to accept this program and live with it, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
