<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Preserve Our Heritage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1949, pp. 61-65</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I trust and pray that while I speak I may be guided by the Holy
Spirit of God, that some of my words at least may touch the hearts of some of those who
listen.
</p><p>
It is good to meet in these great conferences. Thousands of us are of one mind, of one faith,
of one purpose. It is always good to bear witness to the reality of the restoration of the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ. I bear that witness for myself that this is indeed the work of God,
that we are not following a mistaken path, but that we are walking in the light of truth, and
that more than one hundred years of existence of this Church of the restoration have
demonstrated the truth, the integrity, and the reality of the work begun under divine direction
by the Prophet Joseph.
</p><p>
A GREAT HERITAGE
</p><p>
We have a great heritage, we Latter-day Saints, a heritage of doctrine, of practice, of
tradition. I know of none like it. Just as these conferences coming every six months stand out
as unique in the history of the world, so that which we have inherited from those who have
gone before us is equally unique and distinctive. It is our duty to respect this heritage, to
honor it, and to use it. Things that are not used are dead. They are of little or no value to
human kind. It is only by use that knowledge and all the possessions of mankind blossom into
life and become of real value.
</p><p>
If this were a testimony meeting, there are thousands here who would bear witness to their
knowledge of the truth of this work. A testimony is a living thing. Like all living things it
must be fed and nourished and cared for if it is really to be of service and value in human life
and in carrying out the purposes of the Lord. So the heritage, that which has been given us,
must be used to become effective in the building of God's kingdom.
</p><p>
We have noble traditions handed down from the past. My mind has been concerned for some
time with one of these traditions. Some may say that this tradition is not spiritual, therefore
not part of the gospel, but the Lord himself has said to some of his servants in early days that
before him all things are spiritual
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/34#34">D&amp;C 29:34</a>),
provided, as I understand it, they are used in the building of God's kingdom.
</p><p>
A LAND-LOVING PEOPLE
</p><p>
We Latter-day Saints are a land-loving people. We believe in the land. We are a land-using
people. Most of us are farmers, directly or indirectly. Some few years ago&mdash;not many years
ago&mdash;in a census then taken, approximately sixty-five percent, at least, of our people were
engaged in agriculture, in tilling the soil, or in making use of the things that grow upon the
mountains, in the valleys and on the deserts. That has given us strength. I hope that we as a
people will not depart from that tradition. Those who own the land and use it in the end will
determine the future of mankind. It will not come from those who work in the factories or
who live in crowded cities; from those whose feet are planted upon the land will come the
great determining factors in shaping human destiny. It has been so in the past. It will be so in
the future. We Latter-day Saints must ever remember the sanctity and the holiness of the land
given us by the Father. There is safety in the land.
</p><p>
NEW INDUSTRIAL ERA
</p><p>
Most of us live in the western part of the United States. In all these western states, in Utah,
the mother of them all, a new era is opening, an industrial era. Nature has laid down in these
western territories large quantities of raw materials, many, most of them perhaps, of a
non-metallic character. These deposits will be used more and more in the future. There will
be a reaching out to supply the needs of mankind by the use of these raw materials, of which
great deposits have been laid down by nature throughout the centuries. I am afraid a good
many of us will be tempted to say, "I'll join the industrial procession. I will forget the land."
This industrial era is welcomed. There's no question about that; but as it arises, we must keep
our minds steadily upon the old established tradition that we are a land-loving and land-using
people. We must remember that industry itself thrives best in the midst of an agricultural
community. Witness the social troubles of today in our own land. Analyze them, and you
soon discover that if we had built, as the Saints a century ago wanted us to build, we would
have escaped many of the troubles, chiefly by giving heed to the call of the land.
</p><p>
STRENGTH FROM SOIL
</p><p>
When Joseph Smith laid out his ideal city many years ago, he planned it so that while the
farms would all be around the city, every homestead would have a kitchen garden in the rear
of the house and a flower garden in front. There was tremendous wisdom in that. Men, no
matter what their work may be, or what their daily callings may require of them, if steadily
and vigorously they touch the soil, be it ever so lightly or ever so small an acreage, perhaps a
back yard, will receive from that contact spiritual strength. There is something in the
soil and mother earth that gives strength to all who make things grow
on the land.
</p><p>
One great man in our history, Henry Ford, sensing this thing, undertook some years ago to
make arrangements by which all the employees of one of his factories might be provided with
homes surrounded by a little acreage, on which the owners might toil or play throughout the
year, and thereby take away the monotony that follows work in a factory. The plan has only
partially been carried out as yet, but thinking men are looking in that direction for social
safety.
</p><p>
Some years ago, at the time of the first great war, we undertook in Salt Lake City, in
common with other cities, to raise all the foodstuff we could on vacant lots and in the back
yards of the city. We were not successful in converting all of them to small farms, but quite a
number were so converted. When the season was over and we took an inventory of what we
had done, we found that six hundred thousand dollars worth of food had been raised in the
back yards and vacant lots of Salt Lake City. That was a real contribution to our war needs in
those days.
</p><p>
RECLAMATION OF LAND
</p><p>
Our young people often say, "There is no more land, none for us." To my office come quite
regularly men, usually young men, who want to know where to go to find new land. There is
much land still available in the west. We can make more if we want to, for nearly all of these
western states lie under irrigation. I trust you of Utah will not feel embarrassed when I tell
you that the water now used in the state of Utah could be made to serve twice the area now
being served. We have it in our own power, with the canals and reservoirs and conditions that
exist today, to double the area of cultivated land in this state alone. The same holds true in
nearly all the western states. Moreover, it is a pity that the hundreds of pioneer irrigation
projects in this and neighboring states, built by the pioneers in their poverty, with their small
means and poor tools, remain unfinished. In the state of Utah alone we have hundreds of
pioneer irrigation projects waiting for modern pioneers to finish them with modern appliances,
modern means. That is the challenge of the pioneer spirit to young and old. We are fixing our
eyes too much upon the great projects. They will come, but meanwhile the little projects
scattered all over this western country should be our first obligation as individuals, as
communities. The states and federal government will and must take care of the larger ones.
</p><p>
FERTILITY OF SOIL
</p><p>
I have noticed also, to my sorrow throughout a rather long life now, that the fertility of our
soils seems to be diminishing. Our crop yields are not what they were some years ago, using
the same kind of methods as we used then. There seems to be a diminution. That is
not the way we should preserve our heritage. When the pioneers came
into the west, they found great areas of land made fertile by centuries of sunshine, wind, and
rain, frost, and summer heat. Plant food lay upon the top of the soil, so to speak. We have
used it, but have not paid back what we have taken from the land. In spiritual and in temporal
matters the law of paying for what man gets is ever uppermost.
</p><p>
You farmers who are here, you children of farmers, you understand what I mean. The soil is
a willing servant. It yields to the farmer if the farmer treats it right. Forty-nine or fifty years
ago this last June I visited the great Rothhamsted Agricultural Experiment Station, the mother
of the hundreds of experiment stations in the world. The head of the station kindly spent a
day with me. He took me to a rolling hill, rather two hills with a valley between, and showed
me about ten strips of the same crop, originally, then in full blossom. One was red, another
blue, and still another yellow, each one bearing a different color. As we stood admiring the
scene in the beautiful English June sunshine, he said, "All that has come because we have
asked the soil to do certain things in a certain way, and the soil has responded. That which we
started with has disappeared under the influence of our culture." Nearby, was another field
where wheat had been grown continuously for fifty years. The soil still tried its best to do its
duty, but there was only a small yield. In a nearby field, properly handled, the wheat stood
high, comparable with the best.
</p><p>
Man has control over the earth. The Lord has given us mastery
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26,28#26">Gen. 1:26,28</a>). We are not servants upon the
face of the earth. We should use that mastery to preserve our heritage. This theme may not be
directly spiritual, but it is important to help us in our spiritual lives, perhaps as important as
anything that we give our attention to as a people.
</p><p>
GUIDING PRINCIPLES
</p><p>
I rejoice at the testimonies borne here today and yesterday. I have enjoyed them very much. I
have been thrilled by them. I could see running through the talks the age-old principles that
have made us what we are today, a great people, new witnesses of Christ. I saw in the talks
the foundation stones of this work here mentioned one after the other by those who spoke
yesterday. Faith has always been the most important cornerstone of our lives in the gospel of
Jesus Christ. It is basic to know that God lives, that the story of Joseph Smith is true, that the
Lord loves us, and has a great destiny for us. Every speaker touched upon that. Another
foundation stone is that we must seek intelligence, education, learning, knowledge. I was
thrilled by the quotation made by President [Levi Edgar] Young yesterday, showing how the
early hard-handed farmers of middle age or beyond gathered after the day's toil to study
Latin, Greek, and subjects of the mind. We must not forsake the tradition of education. Our
fathers set up also the doctrine of industry. There is no place for idleness. The idler, the
deliberate idler, has no real place in the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/75/29#29">D&amp;C 75:29</a>). All these
principles have been bound together by another foundation stone, helping one another, which
we call in modern language "cooperation." We cannot be individual members of the Church
sufficient unto ourselves. The very fact of membership in the Church and our testimonies
compel us to think of our neighbor as we go through life. With these guiding principles: faith,
education, industry, and cooperation, with our feet firmly on the land, we are safe. Disaster
cannot overtake us.
</p><p>
Now these principles and others were mentioned yesterday. They are always mentioned. There
is nothing new in the age-old gospel taught by the Lord to Father Adam when the story of
man upon this earth began.
</p><p>
I am grateful to be a member of this Church, to be one with you. I trust I am one with you. I
am grateful for the blessings that flow to those who are faithful in this great work. May we
all be faithful and worthy of the blessings we need and desire, I pray in the name of the Lord
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
