<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 130-131</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren: The 113th Annual Conference of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is
now drawing to a close.
</p><p>
TEACHINGS OF THE CONFERENCE
</p><p>
In this Conference you men who hold responsible positions as Stake, Ward, and Quorum
officers have represented the entire membership of the Church. During these six sessions the
General Authorities of the Church have set forth impressively and dearly the paramount need
that the Gospel of Jesus Christ permeate the hearts of men, and that the Spirit thereof direct
the nations of the world. The standards and ideals of the Church have been set forth most
sincerely and impressively. Earnest appeals have been made to all members, and particularly
to the young men and women, that they subscribe their lives in conformity with the standards
and ideals of righteousness. Impressively the Authorities have urged you men to be real
guides, leaders and exemplars to the membership of the Church and to all men.
</p><p>
Now in conclusion, brethren, I repeat the words of the Lord to the Priesthood of His Church:
"Wherefore now let every man learn his duty, and to act in the office in which he is
appointed in all diligence. He that is slothful and will not learn his duty shall not be worthy to
stand, and he that shows himself not approved, shall not be counted worthy to stand"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100#99">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>).
</p><p>
BLESSINGS INVOKED
</p><p>
God bless you, brethren. God bless the membership of the Church throughout the world. May
His peace be with our brethren and sisters over in the war-torn countries; be with them in the
islands of the sea, and our brethren who are there presiding, that the Spirit of the Almighty
might be with them under all conditions to comfort them and guide them.
</p><p>
God bless our boys who are at the front, fighting for freedom, offering their lives that this
world may again have peace. May the Lord's comforting influence be with the parents whose
boys have already made the supreme sacrifice. May these parents and loved ones know that
no bomb can end the life of one who thus offers himself; it may silence his heart beats, but
he lives because man is immortal. May our soldier boys so live that no matter what comes to
them, they may have in their hearts the eternal truth that "he that liveth and believeth in
Christ shall never die"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/26#26">John 11:26</a>).
</p><p>
SYLVESTER Q. CANNON ABSENT BECAUSE OF ILLNESS
</p><p>
You have noticed that one of the Twelve has been absent from this Conference. Elder
Sylvester Q. Cannon has, on account of illness, been unable to meet with us. We pray that the
comforting influence of the Holy Spirit will be with him, with Sister Cannon, and with other
loved ones who are now administering to Elder Cannon's needs.
</p><p>
God help us all so to live that we may be truly worthy of the trust that God has placed in us,
I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
