<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...as Pertaining to Our Salvation"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 25-26</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters: I assure you I need your faith and prayers in my behalf.  If there is
anyone who needs the help of the Lord, I do.  I can heartily endorse all that has been said at
this conference, and I have faith that I can endorse everything that will be said in this
conference.  I like Brother Mark Petersen's comment of a postscript to what has been said,
and I would like to add my thought as another postscript.
</p><p>
In the very beginning, God placed Adam on the earth, and he gave him dominion over the
fish and the fowl and the cattle and over all the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26#26">Gen. 1:26</a>).
Now this would seem like a pretty
exalted position for some people today, but even though he had dominion over all the earth,
God said, "It is not good that the man should be alone"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>)
and he gave unto him the
woman Eve to be a companion and helpmeet.  Then God gave unto them the first great
commandment to multiply and replenish the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
</p><p>
We are not told how long they lived in the Garden of Eden before they partook of the fruit of
the tree of the knowledge of good and evil and were cast out of the garden to start their
mortal existence.  The point I want to make clear is that God himself established the first
family unit.  It is not an institution developed by man which can be outgrown and cast aside
in the course of human progress.  All that is nearest and dearest in our lives is associated with
our families.  Love has its center here, and where love is, there we find happiness also. 
Truly, it is not good for man to be alone.  The Lord in his wisdom has provided a way for
man to be happy on this earth, and to carry that joy on through all eternity. The greatest joy
and happiness comes through the family unit.  It has been so through all mortality, so why
will it not be so in the next life?  This family unit is so important that the Lord has made it
known to us that all the families of the earth must be sealed together. By the time of the end
of the millennium all of Adam's posterity who accept the gospel must be sealed together as
one family by the power of the priesthood, which is the power to seal earth and it shall be
sealed in heaven, and to bind on earth, and it shall bound in heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/46#46">D&amp;C 132:46</a>).
</p><p>
Every person who comes to the earth must have an opportunity to receive all the blessings of
these sealings if he will accept, sometime before the end of the millennium.  There could not
be a just God if it were otherwise.  These sealing blessings are obtained, first, through the
ordinance of baptism into the Church of Jesus Christ.  Then the wife is to be sealed to the
husband for time and for all eternity, and those children who are born outside of this wedlock
must be sealed to their parents that they may receive the blessings as though they were born
under the new and everlasting covenant.
</p><p>
Those who have died without this law may have the privilege of receiving these blessings by
proxy.  That is where our responsibility comes in.  We must first teach the gospel to the
living, and then for those of our families who died without the law we must gather their
records that this great and important work can he done for them.
</p><p>
Quoting the Prophet Joseph Smith in Section 128 of the Doctrine and Covenants on this
subject: 
</p><p>
And now, my dearly beloved brethren and sisters, let me assure you that these are principles
in relation to the dead and the living that cannot be lightly passed over, as pertaining to our
salvation.  For their salvation is necessary and essential to our salvation, as Paul says
concerning the father&mdash;that they without us cannot be made perfect&mdash;neither can we without
our dead be made perfect.
</p><p>
And now, in relation to the baptism for the dead, I will give you another quotation of Paul, 1
Corinthians, 15:29: <i>Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise</i>
<i>not at all?  Why are they then baptized for the dead?</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/29#29">1 Cor. 15:29</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
And again, in connection with this quotation I will give you a quotation from one of the
prophets, who had his eye fixed on the restoration of the priesthood, the glories to he revealed
in the last days, and in an especial manner this most glorious of all subjects
belonging to the everlasting gospel, namely, the baptism for the dead; for Malachi says, last
chapter, verses 5th and 6th: <i>Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of</i>
<i>the great and dreadful day of the Lord: And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the</i>
<i>children, and the heart of the children to their fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6#5">Mal. 4:5-6</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
. . . the earth will be smitten with a curse unless there is a welding link of some kind or other
between the fathers and the children, upon some subject or other&mdash;and behold what is that
subject? It is the baptism for the dead.  For we without them cannot be made perfect; neither
can they without us be made perfect (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/15-18#15">D&amp;C 128:15-18</a>).
</p><p>
This does not refer to just the few of us who are members of the Church today&mdash;a handful of
his children&mdash;but this work must be done for all of our ancestors before we can be sure of
our salvation.  It is a tremendous task!  At the rate we are baptizing for the dead in our
temples today, plus the baptisms of the living, it is estimated that it would take over four
thousand years to baptize the two billion four hundred million who are now living on the
earth, without counting the dead.  Are there as many righteous dead as there are people living
today?  If so, how is this work going to be accomplished? It is a task which must be done. 
All of God's children who will accept the gospel must become welded into one great family. 
For this purpose he has seen fit to send choice spirits to various parts of the earth.  These
choice spirits accept the gospel when it is brought to them.  Then from that nucleus, others of
their families and friends accept the gospel.  They come to the temples of the Lord and
perform their own sealings and then the work for their dead ancestors.
</p><p>
Converts have three sealing steps they must be present for in the temple: Those who are
married must have the wife sealed to the husband, then their children sealed to them, then
those parents are to be sealed to their parents.  Those who are born under the covenant have
these choice blessings automatically.
</p><p>
Do we appreciate those blessings? Many converts would willingly spend the rest of their lives
in whatever effort is necessary to obtain the opportunity of being sealed to their parents and
consider it well worth the effort.
</p><p>
Then we need to gather all the records of our ancestors that we possibly can.  I do not mean
just a halfhearted attempt. Seek diligently, constantly, and prayerfully.  Do not wait for a
convenient time&mdash;it will never come. Do not put it off until old age when we not able to do
anything else. We never know what tomorrow will bring, and we must see that the work is
done, completing the sealing of each family group.  There is no one who can escape the
responsibility of this work. We will not be excused because we thought an aunt or some other
relative was doing the work.
</p><p>
One young lady, a genealogist, was asked the question, "What if you find an undesirable
character in your family tree, such as a pirate or convict or the like?"  She answered "My
responsibility does not concern how he lived but just that he lived and died.  After all, I owe
my existence to him, and my only way of paying that debt is to do the baptism and sealing
work for him.  It will be up to him to accept it."
</p><p>
This is a responsibility for each of us.  Not one of us can be made perfect without this work. 
I doubt if the Lord will accept the excuse that we are so busy working in the auxiliary
organizations that we cannot spend a part of our time in genealogy.  Any part of this we do
not do which we should do must be done by someone else, for it must be done.  If we shirk
our responsibilities, how can we expect to receive the blessings?
</p><p>
To those scattered around the world, may I say a word of encouragement? Be of good cheer,
be diligent, trust in the Lord, and he will help you.  You were probably placed where you are
to do a special work in gathering records or to fulfil a special missionary assignment.  If you
will let him, the Lord will give you success in your work and much happiness in so doing.
</p><p>
May his blessing be upon all those who are diligent in this work, that we may prepare the
way for his coming, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
