<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Significance of Patriarchal Blessings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1944, pp. 109-113</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Inasmuch as this is a priesthood meeting, and inasmuch as at our last semi-annual conference
I spoke at the priesthood meeting, this was the one session at which I expected to be
comfortable. I have learned another lesson in jumping at conclusions.
</p><p>
Since this is a priesthood meeting, if I may have the assistance of my Father in heaven, I
should like to attempt, at least, to make a few observations that may answer some queries you
have, and I feel safe in assuming that some of these queries are common, because of the
frequency with which they have been put to me.
</p><p>
THE NECESSITY FOR WITNESSES
</p><p>
Oliver Cowdery occupied a unique position in the Church. He was called to be a special
witness, and that is according to law
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/9#9">D&amp;C 18:9</a>).
The Lord has said time and again that his word is to be
established in the mouths of two or three witnesses
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/13/1#1">2 Cor. 13:1</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/28#28">D&amp;C 6:28</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/3#3">D&amp;C 128:3</a>). It is significant that the Prophet Joseph
Smith did not receive the priesthood by himself, but he, together with Oliver Cowdery,
received the priesthood, and it was Oliver Cowdery's calling to bear witness to these things.
</p><p>
The Savior himself, according to the law, required a witness, and his Father in person, bore
witness to the divinity of his Son. Together they appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith. You
will find ample Biblical support for the necessity of witnesses.
</p><p>
Oliver Cowdery did not remain faithful, and his position was given to Hyrum Smith.
</p><p>
And again, verily I say unto you, let my servant William be appointed, ordained, and
anointed, as a counselor unto my servant Joseph, in the room of my servant Hyrum, that my
servant Hyrum may take the office of Priesthood and Patriarch, which was appointed unto
him by his father, by blessing and also by right; That from henceforth he shall hold the keys
of the patriarchal blessings upon the heads of all my people. That whoever he blesses shall be
blessed, and whoever he curses shall be cursed; that whatsoever he shall bind on earth shall be
bound in heaven; and whatsoever he shall loose on earth shall be loosed in heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/91-93#91">D&amp;C 124:91-93</a>).
</p><p>
Hyrum Smith was called to be the patriarch to the Church, but he was also called to take
Oliver Cowdery's place as special witness to the Prophet.
</p><p>
. . . From this time forth I appoint unto him that he shall be a prophet, and a seer, and a
revelator unto my church, as well as my servant Joseph; That he may act in concert also with
my servant Joseph; and that he shall receive counsel from my servant Joseph, who shall show
unto him the keys whereby he may ask and receive, and be crowned with the same blessing,
and glory, and honor, and priesthood, and gifts of the priesthood, that once were put upon
him that was my servant Oliver Cowdery; That my servant Hyrum may bear record of the
things which I shall show unto him, that his name may be had in honorable remembrance
from generation to generation, forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/94-96#94">D&amp;C 124:94-96</a>).
</p><p>
That calling was over and beyond his office of patriarch. He was a special witness to his
brother, and was shown the keys of presidency. Now this situation has been unique in the
history of the Church. Since that time that has not been necessary. There are thousands of
persons who now are witnesses of the divinity of the Prophet Joseph Smith, so that the office
that Hyrum Smith held was more than the office which subsequent patriarchs have held.
</p><p>
SPECIFIC DUTIES OF PATRIARCHS
</p><p>
Patriarchal blessings are sacred things. It is significant to me that in the revelation, the great
revelation on priesthood, the word "patriarch" itself is not used. I have pondered that
considerably.
</p><p>
It is the duty of the Twelve, in all large branches of the church, to ordain evangelical
ministers, as they shall be designated unto them by revelation. The order of this priesthood
was confirmed, to be handed down from father to son, and rightly belongs to the literal
descendants of the chosen seed, to whom the promises were made
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/39-40#39">D&amp;C 107:39-40</a>).
</p><p>
Then the order of this priesthood, beginning with Adam, is chronicled in the 107th section of
the Doctrine and Covenants (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/41-53#41">D&amp;C 107:41-53</a>).
</p><p>
Now we know that these men were patriarchs. I am not sure that I know precisely why the
words "evangelical ministers" were used, rather than the word "patriarchs." It seems, however,
significant to me that the term here used suggests very definitely the spiritual nature of the
patriarchal office. It is not an administrative office, it is not an executive office, it is a
spiritual office.
</p><p>
The old patriarchs, of course, lived under a patriarchal system of government. The head of the
family was, actually the head of their government, and that continued for a good many
generations. We no longer live under a patriarchal form of government. Our civil government
is greatly different. The Prophet Joseph Smith, in a meeting with the Twelve, explains
specifically that "evangelical ministers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>) means "patriarchs."
</p><p>
If I remember correctly, he gave these instructions on the 27th of June, 1839. I may be
wrong. One of the duties of a patriarch in these days is to declare the lineage of the persons
receiving blessings. I am of the opinion that that means much more than simply a declaration
of fact. Some persons who have received patriarchal blessings and who have not had their
lineage declared have shown a good deal of concern, wondering about it.
</p><p>
I must confess, for myself, I have never been able quite to understand why we should be so
much concerned about merely not knowing. Certainly this declaration of lineage is a more
important thing than simply giving an individual a psychological satisfaction as to his
heritage.
</p><p>
A RESPONSIBILITY IN LINEAGE
</p><p>
I believe that a declaration of lineage, by the authority of the priesthood is also a declaration
of, and an assignment to, a responsibility. When one has his lineage declared, he is given a
responsibility to fulfill, according to that heritage.
</p><p>
On the very day that the Prophet explained that evangelical ministers meant patriarchs, he also
explained some of the functions of the Comforter. He explained the difference between the
two comforters, and he explained that one of the functions of the Holy Ghost is to purge the
Gentiles of their Gentile blood. Now we know that today heritages are mixed. Pure racial
strains&mdash;certainly in the Occident&mdash;are almost impossible to discover. Bloods are mixed but a
Gentile, born of full Gentile lineage, being converted to the gospel, accepting the gospel, and
receiving the Holy Ghost, through his faithfulness, according to the Prophet's words&mdash;and
these are not my words&mdash;according to according to the Prophet's words, will have his Gentile
blood completely purged, and he will become literally of the blood of Israel.
</p><p>
I think that fact is something for patriarchs prayerfully to ponder.
</p><p>
A FATHER'S BLESSING
</p><p>
The question has arisen a number of times recently whether or not fathers are entitled to give
their children patriarchal blessings. The answer is yes and no. After all, if you are going to
deal technically merely in the meanings of words, a patriarchal blessing means a father's
blessing. A patriarch is literally a paternal ruler. That is what the word means, and any father
in the Church who holds the higher priesthood, may, in the authority of that priesthood give
unto his child a blessing, and that is a patriarchal blessing, in that it is a father's blessing.
</p><p>
But according to the ruling of the Church, that blessing is not to be recorded as having come
from an ordained patriarch, because it does not come from an ordained patriarch. The
business of declaring lineage and giving patriarchal blessings, these blessings given by one
who is ordained a patriarch; that is the privilege of the ordained patriarch. Such blessings are
recorded and kept in the Church historian's library.
</p><p>
MORE THAN ONE PATRIARCHAL BLESSING
</p><p>
There are some who would like to have more than one patriarchal blessing. In the early days
of the Church many people received many patriarchal blessings, or at least blessings by
patriarchs. The First Presidency and Council of the Twelve have advised that one person
receive one patriarchal blessing. Now, that is not one of the laws of the Medes and Persians.
There are and have been a few cases that have come to my attention where persons have
received patriarchal blessings when they were very young, and where they have felt that the
blessings have been mostly fulfilled, and they would like another patriarchal blessing.
</p><p>
The advice of the First Presidency and the Council of the Twelve is to the effect that under
normal circumstances one person should receive one patriarchal blessing. I think that wherever
there is to be an exception, the recommendation for that exception should be made very, very
carefully, and bishops and stake presidents should exercise care in that regard. If the bishop
and the stake president concerned, after careful and very thorough consideration, feel that
conditions warrant it, they may issue a signed recommendation to their patriarch to give an
additional patriarchal blessing to the person recommended. In such rare cases, where the
lineage has already been declared, there is no need, of course, for repetition.
</p><p>
A PATRIARCHAL BLESSING FOR INDIVIDUAL COMFORT
</p><p>
A patriarchal blessing is a very personal thing. Sometimes zealous teachers in auxiliary
organizations develop enthusiasm in classes for patriarchal blessings, and there have been
cases where whole classes have gone to receive their patriarchal blessings at one time. This
brethren, would better be avoided. It is commendable, on the part of teachers of children, to
talk about patriarchal blessings, to explain the importance of them and their value, but the
individual himself, if he wants it, should first obtain his proper recommendation, and then
make his own appointment with the patriarch, and having received that blessing he should
hold it sacred. It is not a thing to be published; it is not for everybody to see; it is for his
comfort, for his strengthening. It is his blessing.
</p><p>
Every one of you who has had a patriarchal blessing probably has a testimony about it, and
almost daily one of the great joys comes to me&mdash;as it does to every patriarch&mdash;and also one
also one of the terrifying things about the position, is the testimonies of persons who have
received patriarchal blessings.
</p><p>
BLESSING UPON HIS SON
</p><p>
Let us teach our children the value of them, let us teach them what they are, let us instill into
them a desire to get them.
</p><p>
I think one of the biggest thrills that I have had was a few weeks ago. One day on my
appointment sheet I read merely "appointment." There was no name. I asked my secretary
who that was, and she mumbled something rather inarticulately. At the appointed hour, my
little nine-year-old boy came into my office, beaming all over. On his own initiative he had
gone to his bishop and the president of the stake and he brought me his recommendation to
have his daddy give him a patriarchal blessing.
</p><p>
I acknowledge my weakness; many times a day I am aware of my utter dependence upon our
Father in heaven. I ask you, my brethren for your sustaining prayers. I bespeak for every
patriarch in the Church the prayers of our brethren.
</p><p>
God give us vision in these times when nations are being sacrificed upon the altar of
righteousness. Give us the power to see and the strength to do, I pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
