<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Ye Shall Not Fear"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 85-86</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
At our April conference in 1960, I called attention to the need we had for missionaries, that
we would like at least to double the force that we then had. At that time twenty-five percent
of our young men eligible were going on missions&mdash;6,000 of them. I come to you tonight
with my heart filled with gratitude to express to you the deep appreciation of the brethren of
the fact that tonight we are on the verge of having those 12,000 missionaries in the mission
fields throughout the world. We are realizing approximately fifty percent of our potential
rather than twenty-five percent, and just as we needed more missionaries in April of 1960, we
need more tonight. We had fifty missions at that time, we now have seventy, either in
existence or in immediate contemplation, and all of these missions are calling for young men
and young women and couples to go out and to preach the gospel to the peoples of the world
who are waiting for our message.
</p><p>
Recently I found in a book of the seventeenth century, written by a Sir Walter Moyle, who
may or may not be one of my progenitors&mdash;I think in light of this great program that Brother
Lee and the brethren have presented tonight, and in light of the fact that the work of the
ministry becomes more and more intense day by day, and if we fulfil our callings, we shall of
necessity be more and more diligent, that what Mr. Moyle said has a present-day application,
in spite of its antiquity.
</p><p>
He writes: "I think our success and salvation depend largely on how well we can eliminate
idle moments from our lives and dedicate ourselves to hard work, which is
impossible without effort and concentration."
</p><p>
I have had the feeling for a long time that we are unduly influenced by fear. I think for the
most part the priesthood of the Church believe themselves to be courageous. I am sure that we
have not entirely overcome fear. I am very much impressed with the statements that Elder
John A. Widtsoe of the Council of the Twelve made at an annual general conference in April
1942: 
</p><p>
"Fear which 'shall come upon every man' (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/33#33">D&amp;C 63:33</a>),
is the natural consequence of a sense of weakness,
also of sin. Fear is a chief weapon of Satan in making mankind unhappy. He who fears loses
strength for the combat of life, for the fight against evil. Therefore, the power of evil ever
seeks to engender fear in human hearts. In this day of sorrow, fear walks with humanity. It
directs, measurably, the course of every battle. It remains as a gnawing poison in the heart of
victors as of the vanquished.
</p><p>
"As leaders in Israel, we must seek to dispel fear from among our people. A timid, fearing
people cannot do their work well. The Latter-day Saints have a divinely assigned world
mission so great that they cannot afford to dissipate their strength in fear. The Lord has
repeatedly warned his people against fear. Many a blessing is withheld because of our fears.
He has expressly declared that men cannot stop his work on earth, therefore, they who are
engaged in the Lord's latter-day cause, and who fear, really trust man more than God, and
thereby are robbed of their power to serve.
</p><p>
"The key to the conquest of fear has been given through the Prophet Joseph Smith," Brother
Widtsoe continues. "'If ye are prepared ye shall not fear'"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/30#30">D&amp;C 38:30</a>).
That is a message
from the Doctrine and Covenants, and Brother Widtsoe says in conclusion, "That divine
message needs repeating today in every stake and ward. Are we prepared to surrender to
God's commandments? . . . If we can honestly answer yes, we can bid fear depart. And the
degree of fear in our hearts may well be measured by our preparation by righteous living,
such as should characterize Latter-day Saints."
</p><p>
God bless us to eliminate fear and to meet every challenge which the priesthood of God
places upon us, I pray humbly, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
