<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Responsibilities to the Lamanites</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 54-58</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
First I should like Elder [Adam S.] Bennion to know that it doesn't take a prophetic statement
for one to suffer.  I have been suffering since yesterday morning when it was anticipated that
I should speak.
</p><p>
I desire to preface what I have to say today by recognizing and paying honor to our beloved
President, David O. McKay, who has rounded out fifty years of devoted service as one of the
General Authorities of the Church.  I want you to know that it is a great privilege and
blessing to be associated with him in the General Councils of the Church.  We love him as
you love him.  It is our privilege to feel the strength of his spirit, the power of his
personality, the strength of his character, and the inspiration of his soul as we associate daily
with him in the affairs of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
President McKay is the epitome of saintliness, for he incorporated into his life the great truths
of the gospel of our Lord.  We all know that the gospel has a great refining influence in the
lives of those who accept it and who obey it.  It is a great blessing in our Council, after a
matter has been taken care of, to hear President McKay say: "The will of the Lord has been
done." My brethren and sisters, President McKay has given a long, faithful, and devoted
service to this Church and its people.  Truly he represents everything the Church teaches, and
it couldn't fall to an individual to have a greater privilege than to sit at his feet and to learn
of him.  There is not anything too unimportant for him to give his personal attention and
consideration.  The Lord loves him and is sustaining him by his holy power.  He represents
what we look for in a prophet of the Living God. I hope we will all pay him honor on this
important day in his life.
</p><p>
Now, my brothers and sisters, today I should like to represent another voice speaking in
behalf of the Lamanite people and the Church's responsibility to them, with the hope we shall
all be encouraged more fully to support and carry the Lamanite banner until these people of
chosen lineage realize every privilege and blessing promised to them by revelation and
prophecy.
</p><p>
While there are many scriptural statements in the Book of Mormon that support with
unquestioned evidence a return to them of the true gospel of our Lord and
the restoration of promised blessings as members of the house of Israel, I shall refer to three
only: 
</p><p>
In 1 Nephi, 15th chapter, we are informed by Nephi that in the latter days and many generations
after the Messiah shall be manifested in body unto the children of men, then shall the fulness
of the gospel of the Messiah come unto the Gentiles, and from the Gentiles unto the remnant
of father Lehi's posterity, who are the American Indian and his blood relations in the isles of
the Pacific.
</p><p>
"And at that day shall the remnant of our seed know," continues Nephi, "that they are of the
house of Israel, and that they are the covenant people of the Lord; and then shall they know
and come to the knowledge of their forefathers, and also to the knowledge of the gospel of
their Redeemer, which was ministered unto their fathers by him; wherefore, they shall come
to the knowledge of their Redeemer and the very points of his doctrine, that they may know
how to come unto him and be saved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/14#14">1 Ne. 15:14</a>).
</p><p>
Now, my brothers and sisters, as I speak of the Indians, I have in mind all elements of this
branch of the house of Israel.
</p><p>
When the Savior visited the Nephites on this continent following his resurrection on the
Eastern Hemisphere, he informed them that the establishment of his Church among the
Gentiles in this land of freedom, the coming forth of the Book of Mormon and its teachings to
their descendants, was the sign by which they were to recognize his work among the children
of men. Then he affirms: 
</p><p>
And when these things come to pass that thy seed shall begin to know these things&mdash;it
shall be a sign unto them, that they may know that the work of the Father hath already
commenced unto the fulfilling of the covenant which he hath made unto people who
are of the house of Israel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/21/7#7">3 Ne. 21:7</a>).
</p><p>
Mormon, a great prophet toward the close of the Nephite history, speaks of the loathsome
state to which the Indian should fall, beyond the description of that which ever had been
among the Nephites or the Lamanites, and then declares that after the scattering of his people
by the Gentiles and after they have suffered much affliction and tribulation, then the Lord will
remember the covenant which he made unto Abraham and to all the house of Israel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/5/15-21#15">Morm. 5:15-21</a>).
</p><p>
When the Lord brought forth the record of the Book of Mormon to Joseph Smith in this
dispensation, he committed to his Church with that important record the responsibility of
taking to the Indian and Lamanite people the knowledge of their forefathers and the fulness of
the gospel, which record also includes the Lord's promises to them as a branch of the house
of Israel.
</p><p>
In the Doctrine and Covenants, section 3, the Lord, after reproving the Prophet Joseph Smith
for the loss of certain manuscripts relating to the first part of the Book of Mormon, declared: 
</p><p>
Nevertheless, my work shall go forth, for inasmuch as the knowledge of a Savior has
come unto the world, through the testimony of the Jews, even so shall the knowledge
of a Savior come unto my people&mdash;
</p><p>
. . . through the testimony of their fathers&mdash;<br />
And this testimony shall come to the knowledge of the Lamanites, and the Lemuelites,
and the Ishmaelites, who dwindled in unbelief because of the iniquity of their fathers,
whom the Lord has suffered to destroy their brethren the Nephites, because of their
iniquities and their abominations.<br />
And for this very purpose are these plates preserved, which contain these record&mdash;that
the promises of the Lord might be fulfilled, which he made to his people;<br />
And that the Lamanites might come to the knowledge of their fathers, and that they
might know the promises of the Lord, and that they may believe the gospel and rely
upon the merits of Jesus Christ, and be glorified through faith in his name, and that
through their repentance they might be saved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/3/16-20#16">D&amp;C 3:16-20</a>).
</p><p>
Very shortly after this revelation was given, the Lord gave another revelation that instructed
the Prophet to open the work among the Lamanites, as we learn in reading section 28 of the
Doctrine and Covenants, wherein Oliver Cowdery was called as the first missionary to the
Indians from the newly restored Church. The assignment reads: 
</p><p>
And now, behold, I say unto you that you shall go unto the Lamanites and preach
my gospel unto them; and inasmuch as they receive thy teachings
thou shalt cause my church to be established among them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/28/8#8">D&amp;C 28:8</a>).
</p><p>
Three others were later appointed by revelation to accompany Oliver Cowdery on this first
mission to the Indian people.
</p><p>
[President Brigham Young gave much prayerful thought and attention to promoting the gospel
among the Indians and in establishing friendly relations between them and the Saints.]
</p><p>
President John Taylor was greatly concerned about an active Lamanite program, for he
declared: 
</p><p>
The work of the Lord among the Lamanites must not be postponed, if we desire to
retain the approval of God.  Thus far we have been content simply to baptize them and
let them run wild again, but this must continue no longer; the same devoted effort, the
same care in instructing, the same organization of priesthood must be introduced and
maintained among the house of Lehi as amongst those of Israel gathered from Gentile
nations.  As yet, God has been doing all, and we comparatively nothing.  He has led
many of them to us, and they have been baptized, and now we must instruct them
further and organize them into churches with proper presidencies, attach them to our
stakes, organizations, etc.  In one word, treat them exactly in these respects, as we
would and do treat our white brethren (<i>The Gospel Kingdom</i>, p. 247).
</p><p>
President Wilford Woodruff stated: 
</p><p>
I am satisfied that, although we have done a little for the Lamanites, we have got to
do a great deal more (<i>The Discourses of Wilford Woodruff</i>, p. 296).
</p><p>
President George Albert Smith, in re-inaugurating work among the Indians during his
administration, strongly emphasized the importance of the Church mission to the Indians in
these simple yet dynamic words: 
</p><p>
"The day is here for the gospel to go to the Lamanites, and we must never fail them again.
</p><p>
This was later reaffirmed by President David O. McKay when he emphatically declared: "God
would hold us accountable if we failed."
</p><p>
These statements make unmistakably clear what our duty is to the Indian people.  Now, my
brothers and sisters, we should not deny to them longer their full rights and opportunities for
blessings.  We must a ways remember, we only have the authentic record which furnishes the
true origin of the American Indians, their history and God's work and gospel teachings among
them. Great are the promises of the Lord unto the Indians, which spiritual blessings this
people alone hold the keys, rights, and powers to grant and bestow upon them.
</p><p>
In a sense I do not feel sorry for the Indian people because they are children of promise,
belonging as they do to the house of Israel and are the posterity of Abraham, the father of the
faithful, through whose lineage the Lord promised that all nations of the earth are to be
blessed; therefore, they are a chosen race and people unto God, possessing a divine and royal
heritage. However, I do feel sorry about the lack of privileges, denial of citizenship rights,
and insufficient opportunities for schooling and culture which continue to shroud them in
darkness and despair. There are too many of them in our modern day, living under most
primitive conditions and circumstances which destroy faith, initiative, ambition, and
confidence.  That it required hundreds of years for the Indians to reach their low state of
degeneracy does not allow the Church or the nation unlimited time to return them to the high
civilization and spiritual activation they once enjoyed nor the opportunities and blessings of
our present enlightened era of scientific knowledge, productive achievement and culture.
</p><p>
Our apparent insufficient interest and somewhat unsatisfactory follow-up of the Prophet
Joseph Smith's taking the Book of Mormon and the gospel to the Indian as well as partial
failure to heed the counsel of all presidents of the Church in relation to this program, is an
indictment against us and represents a challenge and an obligation we cannot afford longer to
ignore.
</p><p>
It is unfortunate that we have permitted others to indoctrinate them to different ways of life
than that of their fathers as recorded in the Book of Mormon.  Our efforts over the years have
not been sustained, but intermittent, and each stoppage of activity causes us
to lose ground and permits others to become more firmly entrenched, creating a serious
proselyting problem which could in large measure have been avoided.  The Indians
themselves have chided the missionaries about such conditions and occurrences.
</p><p>
Without question in my mind, we must fulfil completely the Church duty to the Indian and
thus lay suitable plans to prevent any future departure from a chosen course of intense
missionary activity among them.  We truly cannot afford to neglect them again. If called to an
accounting by the Lord, could we vindicate the apparent indifference towards them?  The
Lord has counseled that we are not to be commanded in all things and he that doeth not
anything until he is commanded and receiveth a commandment with doubtful heart and
keepeth it with slothfulness, the same is damned (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/26#26">D&amp;C 58:26</a>). The revelations make
clear the Church path of duty.  What additional direction is needed to awaken us to the
importance of this God-given task?
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, the Indian cause and program is not a dead issue in the Church today
but continues a constant challenge and duty.  We must regain through devoted service to the
Indian God's approval and blessing upon this most important assignment.
</p><p>
In my judgment, to be successful the Indian program must become a full Church effort that
involves every person and organization.  We should also encourage government bodies to
study more thoroughly Indian problems, give them increasing local autonomy and furnish the
type and quality of leadership and help to elevate the Indian to his rightful place of ultimate
full citizenship with opportunity to enjoy every educational and work advantage that will
make him independent and self-sustaining.  Because the first inhabitants and rightful citizens
of our great country are in a minority group does not justify indifference to their cause, nor
should they be ignored by the strong political parties of our nation.  The government, having
subjugated and taken possession of their lands and made them wards of the government,
places upon this nation and people a debt and obligation that should be fully and honestly met
to permit them in proper time to enjoy full rights and benefits of citizenship with economic
and social privileges and proper home life in the society of American peoples.
</p><p>
Perhaps too thoughtlessly we consider the Book of Mormon as belonging to us exclusively,
overlooking the source of its divine preparation, also the descendants of the people to whom
the record was originally given.  We hold it in sacred trust for the American Indian as well as
for our own use.  The Book of Mormon record has for the American Indian a familiar voice
speaking as it does from the dust, of their ancestors.
</p><p>
We must rely on stake and full-time mission leadership and missionaries, priesthood quorums,
also the Church auxiliaries, to carry forward this important work.  I cannot promise you that it
will be an easy task.  It will be full of discouragements and will require years to attain
reasonable progress, but when accomplished, think of the marvelous blessings and
satisfactions we as a people can experience for bringing a backward branch of the house of
Israel to a knowledge of truth and of their God.  The problems and handicaps that now exist
in working among the Indians cause an assignment to be distasteful to some, and because the
results often are disappointing and quite unproductive, tend to frighten many away who are
considered for missionary service among them.  Perhaps they are fearful of what they might
find and revolt against the idea of working and associating with these people who live under
such humble circumstances and for the most part are without modern facilities that we accept
as a part of our daily living.  The Lord taught that to eat with unwashed hands did not defile
a man, but those things which proceed out of the mouth and come forth from the heart, they
defile the man (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/18-20#18">Matt. 15:18-20</a>).
</p><p>
We should take seriously these words of Jacob, the brother of Nephi: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, a commandment I give unto you, which is the word of God, that ye revile
no more against them because of the darkness of their skins
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/3/9#9">Jacob 3:9</a>).
</p><p>
Why do we as a people hesitate, my brothers and sisters, to pursue fully the work God has
assigned us to do by revelation?  How can the Indians be encouraged to a full life of
opportunity, joy, and happiness without our help? As we meditate this challenge, we should
remember the example of the Christ who humbly and washed the feet of his disciples to teach
them the lesson of humility in his service.
</p><p>
Calling to mind the vision and lesson given to the Apostle Peter, who at first resisted taking
the gospel to the Gentiles, "We cannot call that common or unclean which God has cleansed"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/15#15">Acts 10:15</a>).
Does not that same counsel apply to us today, now that the time has arrived
for the Indian to receive the fulness of the gospel of our Lord? I am firmly convinced the
Lord in his own way is preparing the Indian people to receive the message of the restored
gospel, but we must willingly cooperate with him in this program according to the important
assignment given to the Church.
</p><p>
Now we should resolve, my brothers and sisters, to never give up in this program regardless
of disappointments and discouragements, but fulfil in a pleasing way to the Lord our duty to
the Indian people with patience, love, and kindness.  Also, we must faithfully keep all
promises made to them, and by real sustained interest and never failing them again build
confidence through our efforts to serve and thus create a desire within them for the gospel and
kingdom of our Lord.
</p><p>
I do not want you to get the idea from this talk that the Church does not have an Indian
program and is not making some progress in this field of service, because we are, but we
must step up our efforts, increase effectiveness of the work, and accomplish much more than
we are now doing to fully bless these people and to please the Lord, our God.
</p><p>
I recognize and express appreciation to those of our brothers and sisters who have given and
are giving such faithful and devoted service to the peoples of Lamanite origin.  I pray that the
choice blessings of our Heavenly Father will be upon this branch of the house of Israel, that
our efforts among them will never diminish but will continue to increase in order that they
may enjoy the bless God has promised to them, which I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
