<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"In Mine Own Way"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 150-155</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Thus saith the Lord:
</p><p>
And it is my purpose to provide for my saints, for all things are mine. But it must needs be
done in mine own way. . . Thus saith the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/15-16#15">D&amp;C 104:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
Two years ago today I began my official work in this capacity. They have been two years of
great joy and happiness for me. It has been my privilege to go throughout the Church and to
have that incomparable opportunity of entering the homes and lives of the people.
</p><p>
"IN MINE OWN WAY"
</p><p>
In these two years I have seen a great drama played before my eyes. The title of the drama is:
"In Mine Own Way." The stage is the earth; the scenery consists of the mountains and plains,
the streams and oceans, the forests and deserts; its actors are the people, the sons and
daughters of God.
</p><p>
A TYPICAL "HOME NIGHT"
</p><p>
The curtain rises on the first act, showing a world of night life with its theaters, banquets, and
night clubs. Throngs of people have left homes and firesides seeking diversion in commercial
amusement and riotous living, but off in one corner of this huge stage I see a modest home in
which a family is assembled. It is a family of five. They are having a typical Latter-day Saint
home evening. Little Grace is taking her turn tonight. She has arranged the program and is
conducting. All of the family sing the song "Love At Home." The father tells a story from the
Bible; then little Jimmy, just starting out with his violin, plays a simple little tune. Little
Grace sings: "Jesus Wants Me for a Sunbeam." And then the little three-year-old, unable to do
anything else, turns somersaults to entertain the group. Some games are played and the mother
serves the refreshments, which tonight happens to be popcorn. I see them now at the close of
a perfect home evening, kneeling all together in prayer as they retire. And I seem to hear the
voice of God saying:
</p><p>
And parents . . . shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
</p><p>
BLESSINGS THROUGH FAITHFULNESS
</p><p>
The scene is changed. The setting this time is a world of selfishness, of overspending, of debt,
of grasping humans accumulating the things of the world. There is one spot on this huge stage
that arrests my attention. I see a young family, the father of which is still in his twenties. The
lovely home is bright and resounds with children's voices and beyond the walls of its
loveliness, I see prosperous mercantile establishments owned by him. His conference visitor is
talking to him, commending him for his faithfulness in the payment of his tithing which he
has paid on his prosperity. And then I hear this young, devout Latter-day Saint say: "I deserve
no commendation. I am doing only my duty and my privilege. When I came home from my
mission, wholly without funds or program, I knelt and asked for the blessings of the Lord,
and I promised him that I would give him not only the tenth of my increase, but all that I
possessed and accumulated would be his for his work and at the call of his servants, the
Authorities of his Church."
</p><p>
As that scene closes I reflect again upon the title of the drama, "But it must needs be done in
mine own way."
</p><p>
MISSIONARY WORK GOING FORWARD
</p><p>
The curtain is parted again and I see a discordant world, full of hate and envy, insincerity and
frustration. Some are seeking righteousness but great numbers are satisfied to "eat, drink, and
be merry" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/7#7">2 Ne. 28:7</a>)
and let the world go merrily on in its sin. Then at one side of the great stage, I see
the membership of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in all its activities,
including its missionary work. I see, going forth from the wards, great numbers of messengers
of peace, giving the gospel to a world freely. An old couple, arranging their affairs, are
gathering together the funds which they have earned and saved from their poultry farm
throughout a period of years. They are leaving their home for the mission field. In another
part of the stage is a group of missionaries coming into the rooms of the General Authorities
to be set apart for their missions. In one room is a father with his young daughter. He is a
patriarch and though many are his years, light is his heart. And after the girl has been set
apart, her proud father whispers to the General Authority as they go out of the room, "Maybe
you would be interested to know that this is my eleventh missionary to go into the mission
field. It isn't a sacrifice," he quickly adds, "Every one of those missionaries has brought a
blessing to our home. And I have three more children yet to go." The gospel preached in the
Lord's own way without price or compensation! And I seem to hear the Lord's comment:
</p><p>
. . . freely ye have received, freely give
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/8#8">Matt. 10:8</a>).
As my Father hath sent me even so send I you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/21#21">John 20:21</a>).
</p><p>
A STRONG CONTRAST
</p><p>
Another curtain. The scene this time is of the workers of the world, cursing in their labor;
youth who use irreverently the name of Deity in their games and sports, and socialites
indulging in vulgar and obscene stories in their parties. In contrast is presented a group of
fourteen men on the Weber River. They are stake authorities spending a night and a day in
the canyon. They are hiking, pitching horseshoes, playing volley ball, "swapping" stories
through the afternoon, and in the evening they gather together to eat, and then to spend hours
exchanging experiences and in solemn worship around the fireplace. As the men retire one of
the number whispers to a companion, "Do you realize that through this long day and evening
fourteen prominent men were together but never once was the name of Deity used improperly,
nor a single story related that had even a shady background?" And as that scene closes I find
myself thinking: "What a sweet and abundant life a Latter-day Saint may have," and I
remember the words of Paul:
</p><p>
Unto the pure all things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing
pure (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/titus/1/15#15">Titus 1:15</a>).
</p><p>
HELP IN TIME OF NEED
</p><p>
Another scene: I see a world of people confused with social problems, "each for himself and
the devil take the hindmost." There is evidence of riches and poverty, luxury and want; and
then within this world of selfishness there is presented a scene of devastation where floods in
their fury had played havoc with many homes, and here are fifteen hundred members of the
priesthood of the Church with their sleeves rolled up, with their boots on, digging filth and
debris from mud-filled basements resulting from a terrible storm that damaged homes and
destroyed valuable possessions of the people. I see other floods where crops were washed
away, animals drowned, farms gutted, and adobe homes melted by a raging river. I see the
people from neighboring wards and stakes come to the rescue&mdash;with food, bedding, clothing
for the needy; scores of truckloads of hay and grain for livestock; wire and posts for fencing;
cash for leveling the farms, and building materials for dwellings for the homeless. And I see
priesthood quorums with saw and hammer, building homes for members in distress.
</p><p>
And I thank the Lord for a people who follow the injunction: "Love thy neighbor as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>),
and, the family enters the newly constructed home, I seem to hear the Master say:
</p><p>
. . . Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it
unto me (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/40#40">Matt. 25:40</a>).
</p><p>
TWO WAYS OF SPENDING THE SABBATH
</p><p>
The curtain rises again on a Sabbath day&mdash;church bells are ringing. The populace, however,
seems motivated by the spirit of "holiday" rather than "Holy Day." All over this great stage
on the Lord's day people are picnicking in the canyon, men are in the fields doing their work;
hunters and fishermen are in the mountains; men and women and children are in long queues
before picture houses, ball games and rodeos. But off in another little corner in this great
stage there is a sacrament meeting in progress. The meetinghouse is filled with worshiping
people keeping holy the Sabbath day. The bishop is conducting, and down in the
congregation, in one side pew is a family of six&mdash;a young couple with four children under
twelve. And then at the conclusion of the meeting it seems the bishop is commending the
young parents for their faithfulness, and the father of this little brood says: "We are happy to
come to sacrament meeting each Sabbath. It is a privilege to worship. We always like to come
together as a family. Our life would not be complete if our play, our work, and our worship
were not all together." And I was grateful for the many who worship on the Lord's day, and I
seem to see Moses coming down from Mount Sinai with the plates on which was engraved:
</p><p>
Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>).
</p><p>
THE LAW OF CHASTITY
</p><p>
And then the scene changes again, and I see a world of sin. Here are displayed the hellholes
of vice and crime. Here are the divorce courts and people filing in and out, notables many
times divorced but unashamed. Homes are broken and children divided, and I hear someone
say that ninety percent of all the divorces that break up these homes are caused by the sin of
adultery, and that a staggering percentage of the people on this stage are immoral and
unrepentant. Backstage is a small picture in contrast. Here is a community of about four
hundred Latter-day Saints far away in the southland. A physician-surgeon, not a member of
the Church, is telling his friend: "Now I've finished five years of practice in this little
community of Mormons. Oh, the Mormons are not perfect but a pretty good sort though. I
have attended them in their childbirths, in their operations, and in all of their ailments, and
after five years I have yet to find the first case of social disease among them." And I seem to
hear the warning of Paul, heeded by these Latter-day Saints:
</p><p>
Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you? If
any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy,
which temple ye are (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Here is the law of chastity lived "in mine own way."
</p><p>
TWO MARRIAGE SCENES
</p><p>
Another scene is presented. It is a world parading in pomp and show, in display and pretense.
Upstage I see a minister standing before a young couple, all elegantly dressed. And I see the
best man, ladies in waiting, the ring bearer, many actors with parts prepared and gowns that
are gorgeous. Large groups of people are on either side of the aisle with curious expectant
faces. And then it seems that I see in another small corner of this huge stage, a young girl and
her mother talking quietly together in their home. I hear the daughter saying: "You have been
a sweet mother to me. I am grateful for your teaching me the beauty and importance of a
temple marriage. I saw Betty's spectacular wedding with all of its flowers, costly gowns, and
expensive appointments. I felt the labored formality of it all, the gasps of the curious
onlookers. Mother, I desire a sweet, simple temple marriage; I want no rice, no old shoes, no
wild demonstration. I want no pageantry no matter how colorful&mdash;marriage to me is a holy
ordinance. What I would like would be for John and me to go through the sweet holy rites of
the temple with just my folks and his, and a few intimate friends, where all is white and calm
and beautiful and serene. Mother, I want no one unsympathetic to be present and nothing to
be done which, in any sense, will mar the solemnity of that sacred occasion. This is a time
when I want no hilarity, no crude or vulgar jokes. And as we walk out together, united for
time and eternity, I want us to face the world with our minds and hearts still on that same
high plane we found in the sealing room of the temple. I want us always to retain that sweet
spirit of prayer and worship and peace. Thank you, Mother, I want to be married in the
Lord's own way."
</p><p>
And as the curtain closes I stand in contemplation&mdash;grateful and happy that in the drama of
life on the great world stage there are here and there episodes of contrasting brilliance and
beauty which show the way to live the commandments of God in his own way.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, let us be true devoted Latter-day Saints. Let us love the Lord and our
fellow men and live the commandments of God that we may have a full and abundant life
leading to exaltation, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
