<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Wisdom and Great Treasures of Knowledge, Even Hidden Treasures</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 127-131</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, we have all appreciated and enjoyed your presence at this conference.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters: I sat one day with an attorney friend, Guy Anderson, across the
directors' room table of my office in Arizona.
</p><p>
In his slow, pleasant drawl, he said, "I came to congratulate you on your call to the
apostleship and to visit with you before your move to Salt Lake City." We talked about what
my call entailed, and then he told me of one of his experiences as a law student at George
Washington University.
</p><p>
<b>Discussion of Word of Wisdom</b>
</p><p>
A number of young members of the Church were students there. Since there were no stakes in
the East at that time, they held a Sunday School class in a rented residence, and Congressman
Don B. Colton from Utah was their teacher.
</p><p>
This particular Sunday morning, they were considering the 89th section of the Doctrine and
Covenants, the Lord's law of health.
</p><p>
Brother Colton had made an impressive presentation on the Word of Wisdom, which is "the
order and will of God in the temporal salvation of all saints in the last days"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/2#2">D&amp;C 89:2</a>).
</p><p>
He emphasized also the further statement of the Lord: 
</p><p>
"In consequence of evils and designs which do and will exist in the hearts of conspiring men
in the last days, I have warned you, and forewarn you, by giving unto you this word of
wisdom by revelation" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord is displeased when his earthly children imbibe in "wine or strong drink" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/5#5">D&amp;C 89:5</a>). He said, ". .
. tobacco is not for the body . . . and is not good for man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/8#8">D&amp;C 89:8</a>) . . . And again, hot drinks, [tea and
coffee] are not for the body" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/9#9">D&amp;C 89:9</a>).
</p><p>
Brother Colton emphasized the promise made by the Lord to those who did observe this law
of health and other commandments. Hear these rich promises: 
</p><p>
". . . all saints who remember to keep and do these sayings, walking in obedience to the
commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones; 
</p><p>
"And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures,
</p><p>
"And shall run and not be weary, and shall walk and not faint.
</p><p>
"And I, the Lord, give unto them a promise, that the destroying angel shall pass by them, as
the children of Israel, and not slay them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-21#18">D&amp;C 89:18-21</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Question unanswered</b>
</p><p>
Then came a question from one of the students: "Brother Colton, the promise is that if one
observes these laws, he shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden
treasures. Many of the men in this university use tobacco and liquor and break all
commandments, including the law of chastity. Yet in some cases they excel academically. So
far as I can tell my obedience to the Word of Wisdom has not made me superior intellectually
to them. How do you account for that?"
</p><p>
Since closing time had come, Brother Colton held this difficult question for the next week.
</p><p>
<b>Experience of congressman</b>
</p><p>
On Friday, as usual, several of the congressmen were eating luncheon at the House of
Representatives' restaurant when Brother Colton joined them. The others began to joke in a
friendly fashion, "Here comes the 'Mormon' congressman; this man from Utah won't drink
nor smoke a cigarette nor even drink a cup of coffee." A congressman from a western state
came to the defense, saying, "Gentlemen, you may joke at Mr. Colton and have your fun at
the expense of the 'Mormon' Church, but let me tell you an experience."
</p><p>
He told a story something like this: 
</p><p>
"I was back in my home state, building political fences, shaking hands with voters, getting
acquainted with my people. Sunday overtook me in a country town.
</p><p>
"I sat in the lobby of the hotel, reading the paper, and through the plate glass window I saw
many people going in the same direction. My curiosity was stirred. I followed them to a little
church and slid unobtrusively into a back seat and listened and observed.
</p><p>
"This church service was different. I had never seen one like it. A man called 'bishop'
conducted the meeting. The singing was by the congregation, the prayer by a man from the
audience, apparently called without previous notice. Soft music was played. All was silent as
one young man knelt and said a prayer over bread, which he and his companion had broken
into small pieces, and then several boys, probably 12 or 13 years of age, took plates of broken
bread and passed it to the congregation. The same was done with little cups of water. After
the choir sang an anthem, to my amazement (for I expected to hear a sermon), the bishop
announced something like this: 'Brothers and sisters, today is your monthly fast and testimony
service, and you may proceed to speak as you feel led by the Spirit. This time is not for
sermons but to speak of your own soul and your inner feelings, and assurances. The time is
yours.'"
</p><p>
The western congressman paused and then continued.
</p><p>
"Never before had I experienced anything like this. From the congregation people arose. One
man in a dignified voice said how he loved the Church and the gospel and what it meant in
the life of his family.
</p><p>
"From another part of the chapel, a woman stood and spoke with deep conviction of a
spectacular healing in her family as an answer to prayer and fasting and closed with what the
people called a testimony&mdash;that the gospel of Jesus Christ as taught by the Church was true;
that it brought great happiness and a deep peace to her.
</p><p>
"Still another woman arose and bore witness of her sureness that Joseph Smith was truly a
prophet of God and had been the instrument of the Lord in restoring the true gospel of Christ
to the earth.
</p><p>
"A man from the choir, evidently a recent immigrant, seemed sensitive about his language. He
was struggling with his v's and his w's and verbs and construction. Two years ago, two
young missionaries in far-away Holland had taught him the restored gospel. He told how
happy his family had been since embracing it, and what a transformation had come in their
lives!
</p><p>
"The old and the middle-aged and the youth responded; some were farmers, laborers; there
were teachers and business and professional men. There was no ostentation, no arrogance, but
a quiet dignity, a warm friendliness, a sweet spirituality.
</p><p>
"Then came in succession several children. They spoke less of their knowledge of spiritual
things but more of their love for their parents and for the Savior, of whom they had learned
much in Primary, Sunday School, and family home evenings.
</p><p>
"Finally the bishop stood and in a few appropriate words of commendation expressed his own
sureness; then he closed the meeting."
</p><p>
The western congressman noted that all around the table were intently listening. He continued:
</p><p>
"Never had time passed so rapidly. I had been entranced. And as each additional speaker had
concluded in the name of Jesus Christ, I was moved&mdash;deeply stirred&mdash;and I pondered: How
sincere! How sweet and spiritual! How sure these people seem to be of their Redeemer! How
much at peace! What security they have in their spiritual knowledge, what strength and
fortitude, and what purposeful lives!"
</p><p>
The congressman said, "I thought of my own children and grandchildren and their
helter-skelter existence, their self-centered activities, their seeming spiritual vacuums, their
routine lives in search of wealth and fun and adventure. And I said to myself with an
enthusiasm new to me, 'How I wish my own posterity could have this sureness, this faith, this
deep conviction. Why, these humble people seem to have a secret that most people do not
enjoy&mdash;yes, that is it&mdash;something worth more than all else, real treasures, hidden treasures.'"
</p><p>
The luncheon ended. The congressmen went back to their offices.
</p><p>
<b>Hidden treasures of knowledge</b>
</p><p>
Elder Colton was now again before his Sunday School class of young college men. He retold
the Friday afternoon story and said that what the congressman had observed were "hidden
treasures of knowledge" promised by the revelation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>).
These mysteries of the kingdom relate to
all truths, not merely to scientific accomplishments and legal cases and other secular things.
He said that "treasures of knowledge" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>) extended far beyond material things, out into the infinite
areas not explored by many otherwise brilliant people. He repeated the Prophet's statements,
which are proverbial among members of the Church: Knowledge is power. The glory of God
is intelligence (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
</p><p>
Knowledge is not merely the equations of algebra, the theorems of geometry, or the miracles
of space. It is hidden treasures of knowledge as recorded in Hebrews, by which "the worlds
were framed by the word of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/3#3">Heb. 11:3</a>); by which Enoch was translated that he should
not see death (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/5#5">Heb. 11:5</a>); by which Noah, with a knowledge no other human had, built an ark on dry
land and saved a race by taking seed through the flood.
</p><p>
Knowledge is that power which raises one into new and higher worlds and elevates him into
new spiritual realms.
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge not unfindable</b>
</p><p>
The treasures of both secular and spiritual knowledge are hidden ones&mdash;but hidden from
those who do not properly search and strive to find them. The knowledge of the spiritual will
not come to an individual without effort any more than will the secular knowledge or college
degrees. Spiritual knowledge gives the power to live eternally and to rise and overcome and
develop and finally to create.
</p><p>
Hidden knowledge is not unfindable. It is available to all who really search. Christ said, ". . .
seek and ye shall find" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>). Spiritual knowledge is not available merely for the
asking; even prayers are not enough. It takes persistence and dedication of one's life. The
knowledge of things in secular life are of time and are limited; the knowledge of the infinite
truths are of time an eternity.
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge of God</b>
</p><p>
Of all treasures of knowledge, the most vital is the knowledge of God: his existence, powers,
love, and promises.
</p><p>
The Christ said: "He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me:
and he that loveth me shall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifest
myself unto him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/21#21">John 14:21</a>).
</p><p>
He further said: "If a man love me, he will keep my words . . . and we will come unto him,
and make our abode with him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/23#23">John 14:23</a>).
</p><p>
And the Prophet Joseph Smith explained: "And this means that the coming of the Father and
the Son to a person is a reality&mdash;a personal appearance&mdash;and not merely dwelling in his
heart" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/3#3">D&amp;C 130:3</a>).
</p><p>
This personal witness, then, is the ultimate treasure.
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge that saves</b>
</p><p>
One may acquire knowledge of space and in a limited degree conquer it. He may explore the
moon and other planets, but no man can ever really find God in a university campus
laboratory, in the physical test tubes of workshops, nor on the testing fields at Cape Kennedy.
God and his program will be found only in deep pondering, appropriate reading, much
kneeling in devout, humble prayer, and in a sincerity born of need and dependence.
</p><p>
These requirements having been fully met, there is no soul between the poles nor from ocean
to ocean who may not positively obtain this knowledge, this hidden treasure of knowledge,
this saving and exalting knowledge.
</p><p>
President Joseph Fielding Smith, speaking at Brigham Young University, quoted from
latter-day revelation: "It is impossible for a man to be saved in ignorance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>), and
then asked the question: 
</p><p>
"Ignorance of what? By that, do we mean that a man must become proficient in his
secular learning&mdash;that he must master some branch of education? What does it mean?"
</p><p>
We mean this: "That a man cannot be saved in ignorance of the saving principles of the
Gospel. We cannot be saved without faith in God. We cannot be saved in our sins . . . We
must receive the ordinances and the covenants pertaining to the Gospel and be true and
faithful to the end. Eventually, if we are faithful and true, we shall gain all knowledge, but
this not required of us in this brief, mortal life, for that would be impossible. But here in faith
and integrity to the truth, we lay the foundation upon which we build for eternity."
</p><p>
Real intelligence is the creative use of knowledge, not merely an accumulation of facts.
</p><p>
<b>The greatest knowledge</b>
</p><p>
The ultimate and greatest of all knowledge, then, is to know God and his program for our
exaltation. We may know him by sight, by sound, by feeling. While relatively few ever <i>do</i>
really know him, everyone may know him, not only prophets&mdash;ancient and modern&mdash;but, as
he said: 
</p><p>
". . . every soul who forsaketh his sins and cometh unto me, and calleth on my name, and
obeyeth my voice, and keepeth my commandments, shall see my face and know that I am"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/1#1">D&amp;C 93:1</a>).
</p><p>
If men qualify, they have this unalterable promise from their Redeemer.
</p><p>
Among the numerous people who have had manifestations is Moses, who saw and knew the
Lord: ". . . the glory of God was upon Moses; therefore Moses could endure his presence."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/2#2">Moses 1:2</a>).
</p><p>
Moses tells of this transcendent experience: "But now mine own eyes have beheld God; but
not my natural, but my spiritual eyes, for my natural eyes could not have beheld; for I should
have withered and died in his presence; but his glory was upon me; and I beheld his face, for
I was transfigured before him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/11#11">Moses 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
And then in his dialogue with Satan, whom he saw also, Moses said: "For behold, I could not
look upon God, except his glory should come upon me, and I were strengthened before him.
But I can look upon thee [Satan] in the natural man? Is it not so, surely?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/14#14">Moses 1:14</a>).
</p><p>
Again, the Lord spoke of hidden treasures of knowledge when he prayed to his Father to
glorify him: "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus
Christ, whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
And he promised: "My sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: 
</p><p>
"And I give unto them eternal life; and they shall never perish" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/27-28#27">John 10:27-28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Key to knowing</b>
</p><p>
The Savior of the world gave this key: "If any man will do his will, he shall know of the
doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of myself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>).
</p><p>
Nicodemus, a highly trained man, failed to know the hidden spiritual things, being unwilling
to perform the works (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/1-8#1">John 3:1-8</a>). He could not have the Holy Ghost, since he would not humbly bow in
baptism. The Holy Ghost is the testifier. It is he who teaches all things and brings to our
remembrance all things the Lord has taught.
</p><p>
Nicodemus asked: 
</p><p>
"How can these things be?
</p><p>
"Jesus answered . . .  Art thou a master of Israel, and knowest not these things?
</p><p>
". . . I say unto thee, We speak that we do know, and testify that we have seen; and ye
receive not our witness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/9-11#9">John 3:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
In one of his prayers Jesus said: "I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because
<i>thou hast hid these things</i> from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/25#25">Matt. 11:25</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
<b>The mysteries of the kingdom</b>
</p><p>
Again, the Lord said: "Because it is given unto you to know the mysteries of the kingdom,
but to them it is not given" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/11#11">Matt. 13:11</a>). Such must be earned.
</p><p>
And then Paul speaks of hidden wisdom: 
</p><p>
"But we speak the wisdom of God in a mystery, even the hidden wisdom, which God
ordained before the world unto our glory: 
</p><p>
"Which none of the princes of this world knew" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/7-8#7">1 Cor. 2:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
"For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so
the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11#11">1 Cor. 2:11</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Secular and spiritual knowledge</b>
</p><p>
To have both the secular and spiritual is the ideal. To have only the secular is like Jude said:
". . . clouds they are without water, carried about of winds; trees whose fruit withereth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jude/1/12#12">Jude 1:12</a>).
</p><p>
Desirable as is secular knowledge, one is not truly educated unless he has the spiritual with
the secular. The secular knowledge is to be desired; the spiritual knowledge is an absolute
necessity. We shall need all of the accumulated secular knowledge in order to create worlds
and to furnish them, but only through the "mysteries of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>) and these hidden treasures of
knowledge (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>) may we arrive at the place and condition where we may use that knowledge in
creation and exaltation.
</p><p>
It is my prayer that we learn to master ourselves by obedience to the Lord's commandments
by the control of our physical appetites, and by placing first in our lives service to God and
our fellowmen, so that the hidden things of the spirit may come to us and that we may attain
perfection with the Father and the Son. Many have seen God in the course of history. All of
us may do so eventually through our righteousness.
</p><p>
I add my witness to the numerous ones already spoken and written and talked of through this
conference of the divinity of Jesus Christ and his work, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
