<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Meaning of Jesus Christ for Our Time</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Paul H. Dunn</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Paul H. Dunn, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 146-150</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brothers and sisters: This is always a very humbling
experience. I too seek the faith of your prayers in my behalf. I have been most uplifted, as I
have sensed you have, by the great messages of this conference, the sweet testimonies that
have been borne, the great truths that have been emphasized again.
</p><p>
These experiences and messages have brought to my attention, as it relates to our
responsibility, an experience I had a few years ago while serving as a religion teacher on the
University of Southern California campus.
</p><p>
<b>Incident at PTA convention</b>
</p><p>
Because of my particular position in directing the institute program, I was invited by that
great institution to participate in what was known as a PTA convention discussing the
problems concerning our youth. I suppose I was invited as a member because of the great
work that this Church does for its young people.
</p><p>
I remember that the president of the university himself was sponsoring a little luncheon to be
held before the conference. As I entered the cafeteria, there assembled around the table were
those who would participate in the meeting that was to ensue. I had not met my colleagues
who were to discuss the problems of youth with me, and this was a chance for us to get
acquainted. I noticed when I went in to take my seat that there were appropriate name cards
identifying each one of us and that I was to be seated next to a full navy commander.
</p><p>
As we sat down, the navy commander leaned over and said to me, "You're the Latter-day
Saint, aren't you?" And I wondered what I had done to tip him off.
</p><p>
I said, "Yes, sir, I am, how did you know?"
</p><p>
"Well," he said, pointing to the cup that I had turned over as I took my chair, "I noticed you
weren't going to partake of that liquid."
</p><p>
I said, "Yes, sir, but I happen to know a lot of people who aren't members of my faith that
don't use that liquid. How would you know?
</p><p>
He said, "Well, it is the way you turned your cup over." He said, "You have that Mormon
twist in your wrist."
</p><p>
<b>A salute to the Church</b>
</p><p>
I immediately started to exercise my own faith as a missionary and attempted to teach him a
little about the Word of Wisdom. He interrupted me and said, "Young man, I didn't invite
this conversation to get a dissertation from you at this time. But I would like to take this
opportunity, if I may, to salute you. May I do that?"
</p><p>
Well, now, to a former PFC, that is great tribute. I said, "Please, sir, go right ahead."
</p><p>
"Well," he said, "I don't mean you personally." I must confess that hurt my ego a little.
</p><p>
He said, "I would like to take this opportunity to salute your church and that great body you
represent here today. As you know, I am directing one of the navy testing programs
educationally throughout the United States, and wherever I go I watch you people with great
interest, and I suppose I have seen many of you without your knowing it, and I would like
you to know, Mr. Dunn, that I feel secure in the presence of the Latter-day Saint people."
</p><p>
He said, "You have something, I don't know what it is [you and I do&mdash;the priesthood, the
Spirit of the Lord which beckons all to come], but," he added, "I feel that one day this
country&mdash;in fact the world&mdash;will look to you for direction. Thank you, sir, for being what
you are and for the great influence of your church."
</p><p>
Can you appreciate in some small measure the thrill that was mine as a representative of
God's true Church? You have had like experiences, and I thought about that again today and
these past days as we have been reminded of our great responsibilities, as parents, as teachers,
and as leaders.
</p><p>
<b>Tribute to parents</b>
</p><p>
I would like to pay a tribute to you wonderful parents who have trained up your children in
the way that they should go, that you might send into the mission field the choice spirits that
you have. My, what a leaven in the worldly loaf they are. And I testify to you that they are
great men and women, testifying to the divinity of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ,
</p><p>
I am located in an area where there is a great cultural and traditional influence, where
intellectualism abounds. I would just like to share a few thoughts that I might direct to those
people, particularly as they relate to this time of year.
</p><p>
As members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, we with many others of the
Christian world have anticipated the coming of Easter and its celebration in commemoration
of the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Meaning of Christ for our times</b>
</p><p>
Anticipating Easter in an era that has been described as "post-Christian"; in an age when
modern science and technology have given rise to the "secular city," as they prefer to call it;
when an analytical philosophy has described as meaningless all propositions that go beyond
certain defined limits of sense experience; when biblical scholarship has mythologized the
New Testament, and a new radical theology has proclaimed the death of God, I think we need
to raise anew the question of the meaning of Jesus Christ for our time. Of course, for many of
our contemporaries, caught up in the cross currents of a predominantly secular culture, the
life, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ can have little or no meaning.
</p><p>
I raise the question&mdash;What is the meaning of Jesus Christ for our times?&mdash;not as preliminary
to the presentation of a legal brief in defense of the fact of the resurrection, nor to afford an
opportunity to argue in support for our belief in the resurrection. This is not the occasion for
religious argument. This is an occasion to bear witness to the hope, the joy, and the faith that
we have in the divine message that Christ lives. Our presence here today is evidence of that
faith, and what I hope to say is intended as an added witness to that faith.
</p><p>
<b>Faith of early Christians</b>
</p><p>
Jesus Christ has meant many things to many people, but there can be no mistake about what
he meant to the early Christians. New Testament faith was based upon the belief that in the
life, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ, God, our Father, in a decisive manner, had
prepared the way for man to enter the world, live the complete life, and again regain his
presence. Motivated by this belief, early Christians went forth to proclaim the gospel, or the "good
news." It was the overwhelming impact of the "good news," centering in the resurrection, that
caused Christians to face the threat of the dungeon, the sword, and the cross. Early
Christianity moved forward under the compelling faith that the resurrected Jesus was Christ,
the Lord.
</p><p>
That the resurrection was central to the early Christian message cannot be doubted. Writing to
the Corinthians, Paul said, "if Christ be not raised, your faith is vain"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/17#17">1 Cor. 15:17</a>).
Read in its context, it is clear that Paul is not trying to prove the resurrection of Christ in this
statement. He is here appealing to the one thing that all Christians accepted in order to prove
another point, namely, that because of his resurrection Jesus was the Messiah, the Savior; and
through the redemptive mission of Jesus, as the Christ, as the Savior, man's own immortality
and eternal life were assured. This was the gospel. This was the "good news." This was the
faith of early Christianity.
</p><p>
<b>Faith today in Christ's mission</b>
</p><p>
Now, after almost two thousand years, in the passing time of a century characterized by a
decline in religious faith, the restored gospel joyfully proclaims anew, with as much
enthusiasm and vigor as did the first century Christians, that Christ is risen. Our confidence in
man's salvation through the atonement of Christ is a matter of faith, not completely
understood, yet the central meaning of Jesus Christ for our time, as for all time, is to be
found in that faith&mdash;faith in man's salvation through the resurrection.
</p><p>
Salvation in this sense is a gift to a man through the grace of God. But those who are familiar
with The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints know that it is also a religion of merit.
Our concern is not only with the future but also with the past, and especially with the present.
Mormonism touches every phase of life; it is a gospel of work, of play, of service, of prayer,
of hope. And belief in immortality looms large in this picture.
</p><p>
<b>What eternal life embraces</b>
</p><p>
Eternal life, however, does not merely embrace the future; it also embraces the past and the
present. This means that the present is determinative of what the future holds for man, both as
an individual and as society. This world, therefore, is not regarded as some condemned region
in space where man awaits transportation to heaven or hell.
</p><p>
Man and the world share a common destiny&mdash;man and the world are to be saved together.
Man's purpose in the world is to progressively know and to live the revelations of God
reflected in his own soul and the creations about him. Man will never be worthy of or capable
of appreciating a more glorious state of existence until he has in some measure learned to
appreciate the meaning, beauty, and problems of the one in which he now finds himself. This
means that while the past and future are important, the present is the greatest of all time,
because it holds the promise of all that is to come.
</p><p>
<b>Jesus taught divine principles</b>
</p><p>
With this view in mind, I raise again the question of the meaning of Jesus Christ for today.
Within this dimension of the gospel we find the meaning of Christ in the very urgent and
serious problems that we face as individuals and as a nation. Some of these problems come
from the past and continue to haunt us; other problems are of modern making and are peculiar
to our age&mdash;peculiar at least in the sense that they are in a new setting. It is in the
imaginative and creative solution of old problems and in the struggle with novel problems
against the gospel of Jesus Christ that he takes on new meaning for us today.
</p><p>
Jesus taught in terms of universal, divine principles, and men were left with the responsibility,
and their free agency, to implement those principles. When he was asked how often another
should be forgiven, he answered with a statement that urged a limitless spending of
forgiveness. When asked what acts were legal on the Sabbath, he answered with a statement
that made it plain that people should be considered over institutions. When asked, "Who is my
neighbor?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/29#29">Luke 10:29</a>)
he answered with a parable in which a neighbor was described as "a certain man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/30#30">Luke 10:30</a>) who was in need of help.
</p><p>
If Jesus had merely given moral rules in terms of the culture of his times, his teaching would
have long since been out of date. But his teachings are bound to no single culture, nor to any
age. Each succeeding age is left to discover a way of making the gospel principles of Jesus
Christ live in terms of its own conception of society. When this is done, we are compelled to
recognize that his ideal goes far beyond not only what man has put into practice but also what
most men have thought possible.
</p><p>
<b>Merging of real and ideal</b>
</p><p>
To speak of our age, therefore, as the "post-Christian" age is a mistake for age, in any real
sense, has not yet the simple reason that the Christian been fully achieved. If the fault is said
to be in Jesus because he was too idealistic for this hardheaded, practical world, our witness is
that Jesus was as much of a realist as an idealist&mdash;the real and ideal merge in his life and
teachings. It is the world that has not been realistic and has not been able to take him at his
word. He said that mankind is a brotherhood. The world has said that mankind <i>ought to be</i> a
brotherhood. We have failed to take his realism seriously, and our problems multiply and
grow in complexity.
</p><p>
In regard to the frustration, futility, and meaninglessness in which an increasing number of
individual lives are submerged, our witness is that the passing years continue to establish the
validity of Jesus Christ's estimate of human personality as the supreme value in the universe.
To the disturbed, wandering youth of our time, we testify that personality, that people, that
human beings are precious, and that life is worth living.
</p><p>
As to the solution of many of the personal problems with which contemporary man is
plagued, our witness is that modernity as well as antiquity give support to Jesus' view that
personality is fulfilled not in the self-centeredness of either the occidental or oriental variety,
but rather in service to humanity. Human experience today, as always, confirms that
whosoever would save his life will lose it, and whosoever shall lose his life in the interest and
service of others shall save it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/39#39">Matt. 10:39</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Solution of personal and social problems</b>
</p><p>
I have said that the meaning of Jesus Christ for our time is to be found in his death and
resurrection, which assures man's immortality. We have also said that the application of his
ideal to the central and crucial problems of our day gives us further insight into his meaning
for us. He stands as an eternal symbol of our Heavenly Father's interest in and suffering for
the needs of humanity. As we see God's will revealed through him for the solution of our
personal and social problems, so our faith is made sure that he will be forever meaningful in
the lives of men.
</p><p>
We believe that the best and most effective efforts being made today to ward the elimination
of ignorance and human suffering are in accordance with the Savior's inspiration and
revelation. In him and his gospel are to be found the faith and hope of the future. So it is
with a deep sense of its permanent and universal meaning that we read his statement as he
departed from his disciples: ". . . lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/20#20">Matt. 28:20</a>).
</p><p>
May the experience of this Easter season make us more responsive to his inspiration and more
conscious of our responsibilities, I pray, as I give you my solemn witness that God lives, that
Jesus is the Christ, in the name of our beloved Savior, even Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
