<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"In the Morning of the Resurrection"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1950, pp. 147-149</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience by the things which he suffered; 
</p><p>
And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation unto all them that
obey him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/8-9#8">Heb. 5:8-9</a>).
</p><p>
Closely allied with this statement of the New Testament is our Third Article of Faith.
</p><p>
We believe that through the atonement of Christ, all mankind may be saved, by
obedience to the laws and ordinances of the Gospel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
EXALTATION THROUGH OBEDIENCE
</p><p>
Just as surely as our Savior became the author of our eternal salvation, so must we through
that same degree of obedience become the authors of our own exaltation.
We celebrate this Easter Sabbath with a knowledge that we shall come forth in the morning of
the resurrection. We likewise know that we shall be judged according to that which we do in
the flesh. We shall not be saved by grace alone. And how grateful I am to my Father in
heaven for the restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ that has taught us the importance of
obedience to his will and to his command.
</p><p>
We sometimes feel that we need further light and knowledge from our Father in heaven in
order to carry out the duties and the responsibilities of our calling. It is my humble conviction
that if we were able to make ourselves entirely submissive to the will of our Heavenly Father,
his direction to us would be complete.
</p><p>
Closely allied with the day which we celebrate today was Christ's ascension to heaven. He
realized well that he had been the stay and the staff of his disciples during his ministry here
upon this earth. It would hardly have been possible for them to carry on in his absence unless
another comforter were given to them, and that comforter was indeed promised them, and the
disciples of old received it. It is my testimony to you today that every son and daughter of
our Father in heaven here upon this earth who lends obedience to the first principles and
ordinances of the gospel receives this comforter. The first principles and ordinances of the
gospel are: first, faith in the Lord Jesus Christ; second, repentance third, baptism by
immersion for the remission of sins; fourth, laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/4#4">A of F 1:4</a>).
</p><p>
Just as John of old records:
</p><p>
...The Holy Ghost whom the Father will send in my name, he shall teach you all
things, and bring all things to your remembrance whatsoever I have said unto you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>).
</p><p>
So he will today. Without that gift and without that power of the Holy Ghost you and I would
not be able to become submissive to the will of our Heavenly Father. We would not know
what his will is, except by the gift and power of the Holy Ghost. Then when we know what
his will is, we must be as clay in the hands of the potter
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/18/6#6">Jer. 18:6</a>) to permit our lives to be molded in
the pattern that the Savior of mankind set for us.
</p><p>
SUBMISSION TO GOD'S WILL
</p><p>
I am grateful beyond measure this day to know that I have the privilege of associating with
men who have been called of God, to lead and guide Israel in these latter days. I know that as
we submit ourselves to the will of our Heavenly Father there comes into our life a
consciousness, a peace that passeth all understanding
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/4/7#7">Philip. 4:7</a>).
It is through submission to the will of
our Father in heaven that we receive all of the blessings that are essential for our welfare and
our happiness and our advancement in his kingdom. Following the resurrection, in which we
shall participate, we shall stand before the judgment bar of God with our record before
us&mdash;one I hope of which we shall be proud, one which will entitle us to associate
with those of our loved ones who have gone to the great beyond, and who will be there to
welcome us. May we all enjoy the blessings and the privileges which we desire through our
obedience to the laws and ordinances of the gospel. If we can become entirely submissive and
obedient to the will of our Heavenly Father, our problems will be solved temporally and
spiritually. When we are called upon to mourn there will come a comfort and a consolation
into our hearts "that passeth all understanding." I stand here before you today to express my
thanks and gratitude to my Heavenly Author for this knowledge, this conviction, this witness
that has come into my life.
</p><p>
TESTIMONY
</p><p>
The birth and the mission of Jesus Christ is just as real to me as was that of my own earthly
father. Christ was born and died for the sins of men. I know his resurrection from the grave
was as real as his life, and that before he ascended to heaven he stood before his disciples and
gave to them a promise of a comforter which would be sent to them. They received the
comforter, and that same comforter has made itself manifest in the lives of thousands and
hundreds of thousands of Saints in this the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times. I know that
comforter exists today and builds us up and strengthens us and qualifies us for every
responsibility and every duty and obligation of life. The power and gift of the Holy Ghost can
draw us close together, can make us united, can make us discern the word of the Lord when
we hear it from his servants, that we will be immediately obedient and susceptible to his will
thus expressed.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE FOR ALL
</p><p>
I want to say that when we hear a sermon on repentance, it is meant for you and me. Sister
Choules of the Southern States Mission addressed an audience at Macon, Georgia, at the
dedication of the chapel, and in that talk she expressed this beautiful thought: "Wouldn't it be
wonderful if we could all sit and listen to a sermon on repentance and not immediately think
of our neighbor?" I knew she had in mind such sermons as we have heard in this conference.
They were intended for you and me.
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to realize that we need repentance, that we need to be obedient and
susceptible to the will of our Heavenly Father; and may he bend us to his will, I pray humbly
in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
