<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Influence of the Gospel on the Family</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder A. Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 30-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, the beautiful singing of this lovely chorus both this morning and
this afternoon has called to mind a statement about music which the Lord made in section 25
of the Doctrine and Covenants. He said: "For my soul delighteth in the song of the heart; yea,
the song of the righteous is a prayer unto me, and it shall be answered with a blessing upon
their heads" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/25/12#12">D&amp;C 25:12</a>).
I pray that we all might be the "righteous" and receive the
promised blessing of the Lord.
</p><p>
For the past three years the fabric of our lives has been interwoven with the life and culture
of the peoples of South America. These are great countries with tremendous potential for
bringing the abundant life to their people. The people are indeed a people of promise and
destiny, and "their day" is near at hand.
</p><p>
We return at this conference time with a firmer conviction that God lives and rules in the
affairs of men and nations and that he has not forsaken the promise he has made concerning
Zion and its people and its protection.
</p><p>
<b>Changes in South American Peoples</b>
</p><p>
During our sojourn in South America we have witnessed some significant changes among
both men and nations. But of all of the changes that occur in the lives of the people whom
the gospel touches, perhaps the greatest change occurs in the life and experience of the
family&mdash;the basic unit in the Church and society.
</p><p>
A recent convert expressed it this way: "Prior to the visit of the missionaries to my home, I
lived what I considered to be the normal role of a husband. I held a job and provided for my
wife and children. When I came home from work, I considered myself free from further
responsibility to them. If I wanted to stay home, I did. If I did not want to stay home, I did
not. Usually it was the latter. Much of my time was spent outside of the home. I considered it
my wife's responsibility to rear the children. She was to see to it that they were fed and
clothed and cared for. Occasionally she would take them to her church, but I felt that they
should be completely free to make up their own minds about religion, as I had been. While I
did not openly oppose their religious activity, I gave them no encouragement whatsoever.
</p><p>
"My wife and I must have loved each other, but I confess, I gave little evidence of it. I really
considered that ours were two separate worlds; I had mine and she and the children had theirs.
I thought that when the boys were older, they could join me in my activities. But until then
they belonged in their mother's world. It was her duty to administer what discipline was
necessary. I did not meddle in her affairs, except occasionally when the situation needed my
husbandly authority, and it usually did not take me very long to settle that. Well," he
concluded, "that was what I called my 'family life.' As I look back on it now, it seems as
though I were almost a stranger in my own house and a part-time husband to my wife."
</p><p>
After such an admission, I pressed him for a description of the changes that had lately
occurred in his life. He gladly explained it this way: "While I was being taught the restored
gospel, I did not think that I could or would or even wanted to change my way of life. Only
after I began to study and pray did I realize that a change would shortly be inevitable.
</p><p>
<b>The Turning Point&mdash;My Testimony</b>
</p><p>
"At length I received a testimony that the gospel of Jesus Christ had indeed been restored and
that there is a living prophet on the earth today. This was the turning point. It was after my
baptism that the changes really began to occur in my, or more properly said, in our lives. For
somehow, now, the oneness that we were supposed to have in our life and marriage actually
became a reality. I think the reason was that I began to understand the sacredness of marriage
and the need of honoring my marriage vows. In church I was taught the importance and joy
of being faithful to my wife and honorable and worthy before my children.
You know," he said, "no one ever told me before that I would find joy in everyday living
merely by keeping the commandments of the Lord. I had been taught that our lot in this life
was sorrow and pain and poverty, that only in the next life would we find the joy we longed
for here.
</p><p>
"As we continued to attend the meetings of the Church, we learned the practical application of
active church membership and how the principles of theology actually find their expression in
everyday life. And now," he added, "we have plenty of opportunity to practice all of the
virtues we were being taught by accepting calls of service in the Church.
</p><p>
<b>I Taught My Sons</b>
</p><p>
"For the first time," he continued, "I realized what my sons could become. I realized that they
could be reared in the kind of atmosphere that produced the missionaries who brought the
gospel to my home. So I set about to teach my sons moral principles. I taught them that it
was wrong to lie, to swear, to steal, to break any of the Ten Commandments. I taught them
love of neighbor, because now I understood its application. I taught them reverence for sacred
places and things. I now encouraged them in their church activity. I taught them that religion
was not just for women, that character and faith in God were the hallmarks of a real man. We
began to have fun together. I became a part of their world. I'm even beginning to speak and
understand their language.
</p><p>
<b>"I Know the Way to Eternal Life"</b>
</p><p>
"I cannot begin to tell you," he said, "all of the new things I have learned about life since
becoming a member of this Church. I now know the purpose of life. I know the way to
eternal life&mdash;the teachings of the Church, even in a short time, have taught me that.
</p><p>
"But it has been in our home that the major changes occurred. I go to work, as usual, but now
I always come home. I am not only an active participant in our family life, but I also preside
by right of holding the priesthood. And I think I am learning something about exercising
authority in love and patience and understanding.
</p><p>
"And you won't believe this," he continued, "but even though I am busier than I ever was (I
am presently a counselor in the branch presidency), I seem to have more time than ever
before. Why, I even find myself occasionally helping my wife in the kitchen, and that's
something I thought I'd never do. Knowing that the family unit is to be eternal has given me
a completely new view of the importance and purpose of family life.
</p><p>
"Well," he concluded, and his eyes were moist with tears of gratitude, "perhaps you can
understand now why I am willing to serve the Lord, work in the Church, help my fellow
man, and share the message that has brought such happiness to my life."
</p><p>
<b>One of the Miracles of Mormonism</b>
</p><p>
We have seen this change occur not in just this one family but in literally hundreds of
families. In fact, the missionaries have told me that it is a common experience for them to
notice that the homes of the people they visit get cleaner each time they call to teach them
more about the gospel, and yet, they have said nothing about cleaning the house. This is one
of the miracles of Mormonism. This and similar manifestations occur continually.
</p><p>
In Job we read: ". . . there is a spirit in man; and the inspiration of the Almighty giveth them
understanding" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/32/8#8">Job 32:8</a>).
What the light of the sun is to the flower, causing it to unfold
from within and turn to the source of light, so the gospel light is to the soul of man. It
touches the inner life of man and without compulsion turns him to the source of light and
truth.
</p><p>
And yet, one cannot find the cause for this by looking at the unfolding of the flower; rather
one must look to the source of light which works the miracle of growth and change. Indeed, it
is the refulgence of the First Vision, the belief and acceptance of which touches the spirit of
man, and he responds to the inspiration of the Almighty.
</p><p>
Family life changes, not because of any outward conditions, but because of inner convictions.
And those who look for the reason for this change in outward evidences look
in vain. It is not to be found there. It lies not in the new buildings being erected. It is not in
the schools we have built throughout the world. It is not found in the church organization,
perfect as it is. It is not in the youth program, the Primary, or Relief Society where social and
cultural programs without peer are carried on. Nor does it lie in the fraternity of the
priesthood quorums. Whoever looks for the key to change in the exterior manifestations looks
in vain, as did Elijah. He heard the voice of the Lord not in the wind, nor in the earthquake,
nor in the fire, but in the still, small voice (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/11-12#11">1 Kgs. 19:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
The power that changes a man's heart is inherent in the testimony that distills upon the souls
of men, witnessing to them that the First Vision of the boy Prophet Joseph Smith was indeed
a divine reality. I quote a part of the Prophet's marvelous vision. He said:
</p><p>
". . . I saw a pillar of light exactly over my head, above the brightness of the sun, which
descended gradually until it fell upon me.
</p><p>
"It no sooner appeared than I found myself delivered from the enemy which held me bound.
When the light rested upon me I saw two Personages, whose brightness and glory defy all
description, standing above me in the air. One of them spake unto me, calling me by name
and said, pointing to the other&mdash;<i>This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/16-17#16">JS&mdash;H 1:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Key to Improvement of Family</b>
</p><p>
Herein lies the key to improvement of the family. Herein lies the reason for expectation of
success. Herein lies the contribution of this Church to the world&mdash;the ideal family.
</p><p>
I bear humble witness that God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ actually appeared to
Joseph Smith the Prophet. I bear testimony that they live, that Jesus Christ is the actual Son
of God, that he is the head of this Church, that he directs it through his chosen prophet and
mouthpiece, President David O. McKay. I bear this witness humbly in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
