<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Motive</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 112-115</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have in my library, I think, the conference addresses so far as they are available back to the
beginning, including the Journal of Discourses, and I think all the conference pamphlets or
discourses published since then. In each one is a statement of counsel, of eternal principles, of
commandments, of practical advice for the day in which we live.
</p><p>
This conference in which we have now sat nearly three days is no exception to that. With you
I have marveled at the breadth and the depth of the advice here given, the need for it, and the
manner in which it touches the needs of the day in which we live. We have
been fed. Our lives have been enriched and steadied and encouraged in all things pertaining to
life, and I feel to express the gratitude of my heart for these recurring conferences when we
get together for reminder and renewal of faith, and of witness, and of instruction in eternal
truth.
</p><p>
Some time ago, as I am sure many of you have done, I saw a rather unusual documentary
film produced by the Bell Telephone system, in which a panel of scientists and others were
reviewing the great breadth of creation: this world, and men, and space beyond. It was
developed as if it were a mystery story, and was called, as I remember, "The Strange Case of
the Cosmic Rays," in which scientists were telling what had been discovered and what the
current thinking was about what had been discovered. They had selected a panel of
distinguished men recalled from history, including some celebrated names. I think Charles
Dickens was among them, and Edgar Allen Poe, and Dostoyevsky, the eminent Russian
writer, men who were, in a measure, sitting in judgment on the work of the scientists.
</p><p>
I made some notes at that time, and although they are cold and not rechecked, they have been
running through my mind. The men of science asked this panel to appraise their findings, first
bringing attention to the fact that the universe is a unified whole, that there is evidence of
planning and intelligence and order and law throughout the entire universe.
</p><p>
Then one of the witnesses, before he would commit himself to an opinion, asked a very
significant question, which one is always disposed to ask in mystery stories: "What is the
motive of it all? You have told us about space. You have told us about the earth. You have
told us about cosmic rays, and life, and atoms, and all the natural phenomena. What is the
motive of it all?" Then they concluded, as I recall, that they did not know enough about the
motive of it all, and suggested that the panel come back fifty years hence and see whether
they were any closer to an answer&mdash;with the scientists themselves conceding that however
much they may have discovered, they were like Newton, who said: "I do not know what I
may appear to the world, but to myself I seem to have been only like a boy playing on the
seashore, and diverting myself in now and then finding a smoother pebble or a prettier shell
than ordinary, whilst the great ocean of truth lay all undiscovered before me."
</p><p>
I think the motive of it all is an ever-present and ever-insistent question: What has been the
motive of this conference? What is the motive of the gospel? What is the motive of all this
teaching, all this traveling, all this missionary endeavor? Of all the work and the effort and
the struggle of life, of all the striving, all the learning, all the living?
</p><p>
Blessedly the Lord God has told us what the motive of it all is, and it is no small motive,
pertaining not only to time nor to life on earth. It is a motive pertaining to eternity, and the
great summarizing sentence of the motive, of course, has already been recalled in this
conference a number of times. The Lord God himself has declared it to be his purpose and his
glory to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
The motive is happiness; it is peace; it is progress; it is everlasting life, and not just a few
short days or a few short years. It is a motive of such consequence and such endlessness that
it transcends all else. It is this for which we do all we do, this for which we gather, this for
which we teach, encourage, and bear witness to each other, this for which we remind each
other of these great and everlasting things of life.
</p><p>
"But when the Pharisees had heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, they were
gathered together.<br />
"Then one of them, which was a lawyer, asked him a question, tempting him, and saying,<br />
"Master, which is the great commandment in the law?<br />
"Jesus said unto him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy
soul, and with all thy mind.<br />
"This is the first and great commandment.<br />
"And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.<br />
"On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/34-40#34">Matt. 22:34-40</a>).
</p><p>
I read into this something, or would like to read into it today, something which is not always
read into it: I think this implies not only that we should love our neighbors, but in a very
sincere and real and unselfish way we should also love ourselves. I think the Lord God must
have intended that we should have a high regard and respect for ourselves as well as a high
regard and respect for other men.
</p><p>
I am thinking of a line from Ruskin, in which he said: "There is no wealth but life." The life
each of us has is, after all, the sum and substance of all that we have in time and in eternity.
And I think no intelligent man would ever deliberately do anything which would not make
him happy. I cannot think of an intelligent man's doing what would make him unhappy. I
think when we err, we err in that we lose our sense of values or our sense of direction, or do
not quite have in mind what will make us happy or unhappy. All the motive all the
commandments, all the counsel of God, all this great effort of living and of life, all the
striving, the learning and all else, should make us basically happy. Our Father had no other
motive for us but our happiness, our peace, and progress and limitless life with our loved ones
everlastingly, ever with accomplishment, ever with growth, ever with opportunity, ever with
the highest possibilities that the Lord God could help his children to realize in life&mdash;this is
the motive, this is the source of happiness, of service, of all we do for each other, of all we
do for ourselves.
</p><p>
Now, as we go from here and ask ourselves what comes of all of this, what the motive of it
all is, and what life is, I think we have the summary in the lines given and so oft repeated, "to
bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>), and no shortsighted decisions and no
short-sighted objectives should ever be the determining factors of our lives.
</p><p>
I was impressed this morning with the counsel of Brother George Q. Morris in advising us to
go forth and live our lives with steady purpose, and not worry too much about the
uncertainties and about the things we do not know. I would leave this counsel with our youth:
We all live in uncertainties, and we always have. All generations have, and if we were so
concerned about the uncertainties that we did not make solid preparations for the future and
turn in a solid performance we should have wasted life. With a calm, quiet peace and
purpose, and with prayer in our hearts, and with the clean living of life and the keeping of the
commandments, we ought to go forward into the future and lay as broad a base and acquire
as much knowledge and prepare ourselves as well, and serve as well as we can or ever could,
despite all ominous threats and all else that seems to disturb the present scene.
</p><p>
From a young missionary's report given a few nights ago came a sentence that was great in
its implications. Speaking of enduring to the end, he said: "We must not only endure, but we
must prevail."
</p><p>
There is great motive; there is great purpose. As has been asked through all the ages, "What is
Man?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/4#4">Ps. 8:4</a>).
I recall a scientist's answer to a great group of men last summer as he suggested some
elements of the answer as to what man was. He endeavored to tell us how many atoms each
man had in his physical anatomy, and we thought we were something very considerable when
he said that we each had an octillion atoms in us in our physical frames. Then he tried to tell
us what an octillion is. He said if it should start to rain peas, just ordinary garden peas, and
rain peas four feet deep over the whole face of the earth, water and land surface included, and
then rain peas four feet deep over 250,000 planets this size, that would be an octillion&mdash;give
or take a few, more or less. We began to feel quite puffed up and important. Then he said if
you squeeze out all the space between all the atoms in and between the electrons and all the
component parts of these atoms, you would then be about as big as a speck of dust. Then we
began to acquire our humility back again.
</p><p>
But beyond all the atoms, he witnessed to us as a scientist, memory is perpetuated; man is
more than a machine; and there is something eternal which persists always
and everlastingly. That, of course, we knew by other witnesses. Life is everlasting, and the
motive we know, and the purposes of our Father we know. His plans we know in sufficient
amount to help us to realize them in their fullest and highest if we will, and I leave my
witness with you as to the truth of the counsel which has been given in this conference, as to
the prophetic leadership which we are privileged in this day and generation to have, and as to
the great motive which supersedes all the transitory things of life, to the realization of which I
pray God we may leave here and rededicate ourselves and teach our children, and devote all
the effort and earnestness we have within us, in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
