<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Book of Mormon: Its Own Silent Witness</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder S. Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1965, pp. 51-53</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<b>Records on Metal Plates</b>
</p><p>
One looks with awe as he contemplates the history of the Book of Mormon. Today the
account of how it was written is entirely plausible to most men. Because of archeological
research it is now known that writing on metal plates was common in the time of Lehi. Men
have written on plates many times. Prophets have sung their prophecies and recorded them,
kings have told of their conquests, and ministers of state have described their relations with
other nations. Even the common accounts of common people have been inscribed. Written on
metal plates, leather, or papyrus, in languages strange to us today, all of these have come to
our attention.
</p><p>
Men have gone to great lengths to certify their discoveries. "At this certain place we dug,"
they would write. And there were present others to verify discovery and to help interpret its
place in history.
</p><p>
This was not so in 1829. At that time books written on metal plates were known to but few
men.
</p><p>
<b>Unique Aspects of the Miracle of Translation</b>
</p><p>
But nowhere in recorded history has a sacred book been buried in the earth and then been
brought forth by a miracle such as this one in which an angel of God visited a young man
and pointed the way to the hiding place and then withheld the record until the man was
prepared to receive it. The prophecies said that the latter-day work would be marvelous and
wonderful. Seldom before has a single act brought forth so much to marvel at. There was the
revelation to the young man; there was the four-year period of instruction; there was the
providential provision of scribes; there was the literal fulfillment of Isaiah's prophecy in
which a learned man said he could not read a sealed book (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/11#11">Isa. 29:11</a>);
there was the
miraculous vision in which three men saw the plates and heard the voice declare that this
work was done by the power of God; there was the earthly view of the plates by eight
earnest, solemn men who saw and "hefted" the plates and knew "of a surety that the said
Smith" indeed had them (see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/eghtwtnss">BM Eight Wit.</a>).
</p><p>
<b>How to Read the Book of Mormon for Confirmation of Its Truth</b>
</p><p>
With all of this the Lord asks but one thing of the reader. Read the Book of Mormon
honestly, prayerfully, with a desire to know its truth; and if the intent is sincere, God will
reveal the truth of it to that person by the power of the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4#4">Moro. 10:4</a>). To their wonderment and
marveling as they discover its truths for themselves many have read and believed. And
further, with that testimony from the Holy Ghost has come the assurance also that Jesus Christ
is the Creator and Lord of this earth, that he is mindful of all those who seek him, that Joseph
Smith was a Prophet of God and by revelation established this, The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
<b>Witnesses Do Not Stand Alone</b>
</p><p>
The young missionaries bear their solemn witness; but as they do it, they do not stand alone,
nor does a listening person need to pin his hopes on their word alone. In their hands as they
speak is the Book of Mormon which bears its own witness. It is as if they said, "We have told
you that the gospel has been restored; now here is a witness which will convince you that we
speak truly. You will know it if you read it sincerely." Those fortunate enough to follow this
advice discover that it is truly a witness for Christ. That is its chief purpose: to bear witness
for Christ to the convincing of Jew and gentile that Jesus is the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>) and that his gospel is
for all men.
</p><p>
The number of people who have picked up the book by chance, read it, and become converted
to its message has been very great. It is a silent witness, on duty twenty-four hours every day
in many unexpected places. But to do its most effective work it must be in many more. Every
home should have it in its library; every place people stop for a moment it should be
available. It is possible that the person who obtains a copy will not read it, but sooner or later
there will be those who will see it, pick it up, turn to the page containing its declared purpose,
and then become lost in the spiritual message of its drama and its history. With marveling in
their souls and wonder in their hearts, they will peruse its pages, receive and believe the
promise at its end, and find the kingdom of God in this living, vibrant Church.
</p><p>
<b>Projects for Making the Book of Mormon Available</b>
</p><p>
For a long time there has been a vast project to make the Book of Mormon available to
everyone who can read. Quorums of the priesthood have placed it where people stay
overnight or await their turn in professional offices. The high priests have done this great
service. Now, from here on, under the direction of the missionary committee of the Church,
the seventies quorums are to continue this act of love. On the firm foundation laid by the high
priests, the seventies will now carry the work further and to more and more people. No one, it
is hoped, will be able to say that he has not had opportunity to read this witness for Christ.
</p><p>
<b>"A Marvelous Work and a Wonder"</b>
</p><p>
Anyone who reads it with sincere purpose and genuine desire to know the truth will have it
borne into his soul that Jesus Christ, the Son of God, is the Creator and Redeemer of the
world. He will also know that Joseph Smith was a Prophet of the Living God, called by the
Lord as the human agent for the restoration of the gospel in the last days. It will be a witness
to a work so marvelous that wonder and joy will spring into the hearts of men as they
respond to its message and its testimony.
</p><p>
In our day we see the fulfillment of a prophecy written more than two thousand years ago:
"Forasmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me,
but have removed their heart far from me, and their fear toward me is taught by the precept
of men: 
</p><p>
"Therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvelous work among this people, even a
marvelous work and a wonder: for the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the
understanding of their prudent men shall be hid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/13-14#13">Isa. 29:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
Let us not falter in the effort to bring about its complete fulfillment to the awe and
wonderment of all men in this day.
</p><p>
The Church is carrying forth its assigned work to teach repentance and salvation to the world,
and its beckoning arms say, "Come." President David O. McKay is the prophet of God on
whom rests the responsibility to guide the work today. It is our equal responsibility to assist
him all we can, and the work will then roll forth as Daniel prophesied until it fills the whole
earth (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/35#35">Dan. 2:35</a>). That it may soon be,
I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
