<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Achievements from Following Counsel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 121-127</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Facing this magnificent congregation of Latter-day Saints I deeply realize the great
responsibility that rests upon me and hence I crave an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
The ancient writer of Proverbs declared:
</p><p>
Where no counsel is the people fall, but in the multitude of counselors there is safety
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/11/14#14">Prov. 11:14</a>).
</p><p>
He also declared:
</p><p>
Give instruction to a wise man and he will yet be wiser; teach a just man and he will increase
in learning (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/9/9#9">Prov. 9:9</a>).
</p><p>
Centuries ago there lived upon this earth a generation of people so wicked and vile that the
God of Israel turned his face away in shame and chagrin, but as a manifestation of his great
love for these people, he sent them a great counselor and prophet. His name was Noah. Noah
stood at the crossroads and admonished, pleaded with, and counseled the people to take the
path of righteousness and virtue, but exercising their free agency, they chose the path of
wickedness and debauchery. A great flood swept over the earth, and they were swept from the
face of it, and the God of Israel looked down upon a cleansed earth.
</p><p>
A GUIDE AT THE CROSSROADS
</p><p>
Throughout all dispensations the God of Israel has placed at the crossroads a great counselor,
a prophet, to teach the people the mind and the will of their Eternal Father, to the end that
they might return to him and dwell with him throughout the eternities to come.
</p><p>
God so loved the world that he sent his Only Begotten Son
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>),
and he, too, stood at the
crossroads. He admonished, he pleaded with the people, and endeavored to teach them the
gospel of salvation, giving his life for the redemption of mankind. After his death and
resurrection, the organization of the Church remained with apostles and prophets, counselors
to the people, endeavoring to teach them the gospel of Jesus Christ. But again the people
chose another path, and after a few centuries they chose to follow the doctrines and the
teachings of men, and a great pall of apostasy was over the earth, and darkness remained
upon the earth for many centuries.
</p><p>
A PROPHET RAISED UP
</p><p>
Once again, as the Lord had promised through his prophets, there would be a restitution of all
things (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>).
A prophet was raised up, a young man who wished to know which of all the teachings
of men might be the teachings of God. And in answer to that prayer the Father and the Son
appeared to him. They told him that all of these doctrines were of men, that they drew nigh
unto God with their lips but their hearts were far away from him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-19#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-19</a>).
</p><p>
So God gave another great counselor to the people, the Prophet Joseph Smith through whom
the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ was restored in its fulness, in its simplicity, and in
addition thereto the priesthood was restored to earth, that power given to men where they may
act as God's agents. The Church was set upon the earth with prophets, apostles, and all of the
officers that existed in former days.
</p><p>
ACHIEVEMENTS FROM FOLLOWING COUNSEL
</p><p>
Evil men took the Latter-day prophet and murdered him in cold blood. Again the people who
had accepted him as a prophet of God stood at the crossroads, but another great counselor was
raised up&mdash;Brigham Young&mdash;upon whom rested the great responsibility of responsibility of
finding another home for the Latter-day Saints and also of finding a place where the roots of
the kingdom should be sunk so deeply that they would never be torn up again. Following
their divinely appointed leader, the people made the long trek over the plains and through the
mighty defiles of these great mountains, and here in the valleys they built churches, homes,
schools, buildings of various kinds, and a temple to their God.
</p><p>
I have wondered many times what it was that made them successful, that made it possible for
them to achieve so highly. In contemplating some of the factors that contributed to their
success and achievements, I have come to the conclusion that they were anxious and willing
to follow counsel. They accepted Brigham Young without any reservations as the servant of
God, God's mouthpiece through whom the Lord made his mind and will known to his
children. And they followed that counsel so closely that they gave no consideration to
themselves in a physical sense. All that mattered was whether or not the counsel of God as
revealed to them through his chosen servant was being carried out fully.
</p><p>
Brigham Young made the following statement to them, and I am sure this statement came
from God as did the statement made by the writer of Proverbs, which expresses the same
thought:
</p><p>
The Latter-day Saints who hearken to the words of the Lord, given to them
touching their political, social, and financial concerns, I say, and say it boldly, that
they will have wisdom which is altogether superior to that of the wisdom of the
children of darkness, or the children of the world. I know this by the revelations
of the Lord Jesus Christ, and by the results of my own actions. They who have
hearkened to counsels given to them in temporal matters, have invariably bettered
their conditions temporally and spiritually (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, pp.
219-220, 1943 edition).
</p><p>
And so counsel, in one sense, divides itself into two categories: That which has to do with
materialistic things and that which has to do with spiritual things. God's prophet was given
revelation from on high to the extent that he was enabled to counsel his people in temporal as
well as spiritual things, and that had to be because this people came here impoverished. They
had no money. All that they had was faith in God and their hands and minds with which to
work, but yet God revealed to them the counsel that was necessary for their temporal success.
That success is now represented in farms, industries, and in various forms of business which
exist today.
</p><p>
FAITH OF A PIONEER
</p><p>
The pioneers did not think much of personal consequence, which is exemplified in a diary
that I read some time ago of one of the Gardner brothers who accepted the gospel in Canada
and after accepting it, he was most anxious to go to Nauvoo and shake the hand of the
Prophet and visit with the Saints, but he arrived in Nauvoo too late. The Prophet had been
murdered, but Brother Gardner visited with the General Authorities and with the Saints, and
in his diary he wrote: "I know that these men are the Apostles of the Lord Jesus Christ, and I
know the people that are following them are indeed Saints."
</p><p>
Returning to Canada he sold his property and made the long trek back to Nauvoo with his
family, just in time to be driven out in the middle of winter. He spent the winter on the plains
of Iowa. He finally made his way into Salt Lake Valley, where after ten years of struggle and
almost starvation he wrote in his diary; "How grateful I am to the Lord, for now my family
are sheltered under one roof. We have clothing, and we have food."
</p><p>
In the midst of this prosperity a messenger sent by the President of the Church requested him
to come to his office at once. As he entered the office of President Young, he met one of the
President's counselors coming out, and the counselor said to him: "Now, brother, don't blame
me for what's going to happen."
</p><p>
In a moment this good brother stood before President Young and the President said to him:
"Brother Gardner, we are calling you on a mission to go and help settle Dixie."
</p><p>
This good man said: "I scratched my head. I spit upon the floor, and mentally I concluded I
had had enough, but another thought flashed through my mind. The servant of God was
calling me to perform a duty." And he answered the President: "I'll be glad to go."
</p><p>
He sold his mill; he sold his farm; he sold most of his livestock and taking a few belongings
and his family in a wagon made the long trek in the middle of winter to what is now St.
George. And from that time on, according to his diary, he did not know very much about
prosperity. He was on a mission to help build up another part of the kingdom and an
interesting comment is that some of the wood that rests in the great Tabernacle organ came
from trees cut by this brother in Pine Valley.
</p><p>
He suffered privation and many physical hardships, yet in his diary I did not find one word of
complaint, rather I found the spirit of gratitude and thankfulness to God because he had found
the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ. He had a testimony that the great counselor who stood at
the head of this Church was a servant of Almighty God.
</p><p>
WASTED FOOD NOW NEEDED
</p><p>
By following counsel closely the pioneers achieved, and I wonder now as we
leave this great conference whether or not you and I are going to follow the counsel of God's
servants who have admonished us in the spirit of the Lord as to what we should do in both
spiritual and temporal matters. I think of the days in 1932-3-4-5 and 6, when the philosophy
was advocated that we should destroy food, that we should cut down on our crop production,
and in the midst of such advice a prophet of God stood at the crossroads, and admonished the
people to continue to produce more and more and to save every pound. Oh, how I wish that
the modern Pharaohs of today had listened to a modern Joseph, for had this country gone
forth with its great potential strength in productivity of food, there would be enough food on
hand to feed a starving world. You might ask the question: How is it possible to conserve
food over a period of ten or twelve years? Well, through modern means of refrigeration and
canning, and other devices, it is possible to conserve food for years. Out of our own
experience in storing the Relief Society wheat we know that wheat can be kept sound for
many years, based upon certain principles.
</p><p>
And so, had the counsel of God's servants in these days been followed there would have been
no difficulty in providing enough food and other necessities of life to help a starving Europe
and a suffering China. Accepting and following the counsel of God's selected and anointed
should be to us the word of God in this day just exactly as was the word of God in the days
of the pioneers.
</p><p>
OBEDIENCE TO COUNSEL REWARDED
</p><p>
I had related to me a rather interesting story of a humble man who lives in the state of
Arizona; it is as follows: Dr. John A. Widtsoe of the Council of the Twelve had been visiting
in the Snowflake Stake and among other counsel he gave to the brethren was this: "Why don't
you drill wells that you might bring more of this arid land under cultivation?"
</p><p>
President Flake of the presidency pondered over the counsel given, and he came to the
conclusion that a servant of God had spoken and that it would be wise to follow such counsel.
Going to a neighboring town he endeavored to secure the services of a well driller. And the
driller said, "Yes, I will drill you a well. I assume you want the usual size pipe, six or eight
inches."
</p><p>
President Flake said: "No, I want a twelve-inch pipe." The well driller replied: "Man, you are
foolish. There isn't enough water in this country to fill a twelve-inch pipe, and furthermore, I
wouldn't take your money to drill a well of that size because it would be a waste of money."
And so he refused to drill the well.
</p><p>
But, undaunted, President Flake went to another well driller in a neighboring community. He
told the man what he wanted. The man said: "Well, it seems foolish, but nevertheless if you
want to spend the money, I will drill the hole and put a twelve-inch pipe in it."
</p><p>
A site was selected for the well on a piece of arid land adjacent to Snowflake, Arizona, and
drilling operations were commenced. After the men had drilled for a few days, a government
man came along, and he said: "Mr. Flake, I think you are foolish in drilling for water here. I
am quite sure that you won't find any. It is my judgment had you gone over here a short
distance the possibilities are that you might have found a little water."
</p><p>
But again, undaunted and believing implicitly in the counsel of one of God's servants, the
drilling continued and after reaching a depth of two hundred feet, a flow of water was struck
in sufficient amount to fill the twelve-inch pipe up within sixty feet of the surface. The
ground was broken, cultivated, and crops were planted. A pump was placed on the well, and
it delivered nine hundred gallons a minute. This year the crops grown on what was arid land
two years ago will pay for the drilling of the well and the pumping equipment installed.
</p><p>
President Flake further indicated that the volume of water has been sufficient, not only to take
care of this year's crop, but also will be sufficient to irrigate a total of 175 acres.
</p><p>
President Flake followed the counsel of one of Christ's apostles and received the blessing for
obedience rendered, which brings us to the conclusion that we should hearken always to the
voices of the prophets to the end that the windows of heaven will be open to us&mdash;spiritually
and temporally.
</p><p>
OBLIGATION OF PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
So much for temporal counsel, but what about spiritual counsel? We have had an abundance
of it during this great conference. Think if you will of the admonitions that have come to us
with reference to the home, the matter of family prayers, the matter of attending that most
important meeting of the whole week, namely, the sacrament meeting. Will you think of your
priesthood responsibilities as servants of God? I say that every man who holds the priesthood
has a responsibility that is very great, and priesthood is of no value to an individual unless he
uses it in the service of God. It does not come to you as an honorary office. It comes to you
that you might serve God and assist him to consummate his plans. And, furthermore, the
priesthood of God, that mantle of authority which rests upon your shoulders and mine, is not
one which can be taken off on Sunday evening and left off during the week and then put on
again the following Sunday morning. Your priesthood is with you wherever you may go, in
the office or the field, and remember that priesthood demands of you lives that are wholly
compatible with it in purity, in service, in hearkening to counsel and in keeping God's
commandments.
</p><p>
A LIGHT TO THE WORLD
</p><p>
We have received admonitions with reference to virtue, the Word of Wisdom, temple work,
and missionary work. I want to say if we will hearken unto all of this counsel we will become
a blessed people, for Brigham Young declared again:
</p><p>
If we hearken to counsel, we shall be the best people in the world; we shall be as
a bright light set upon a hill, that cannot be hid, or like a candle upon a
candlestick (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/14-15#14">Matt. 5:14-15</a>).
(<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, p. 219).
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, never let us forget the admonition that:
</p><p>
. . . to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/22#22">1 Sam. 15:22</a>).
</p><p>
Yes,
</p><p>
Give instructions to a wise man, and he will yet be wiser; teach a just man, and he will
increase in learning (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/9/9#9">Prov. 9:9</a>).
</p><p>
I humbly pray that we can take the counsels of this great conference to heart and exemplify
them in our lives, to the end that we will be a light to the world, for the Lord said to the
Prophet Joseph:
</p><p>
. . . shine forth, that thy light may be a standard for the nations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/5#5">D&amp;C 115:5</a>).
</p><p>
That is our destiny, and we can achieve it if we will follow the admonitions and the counsels
of these servants of the Lord Jesus Christ. I bear testimony to you that they have all of the
same rights and authority to lead the people of the world in righteousness as did Noah, Isaiah,
or any of the apostles of old. I bear testimony to you that the same God who dealt with the
people in the days of Noah is your God and my God, that Jesus of Nazareth was the
Redeemer of the world, and the humble man who was murdered in cold blood for his
testimony in Carthage Jail, Joseph Smith, was God's servant, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
