<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Courage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marvin J. Ashton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marvin J. Ashton, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 23-25</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
A few days ago we had another stimulating experience as we visited with some of our young
friends. Time was taken not only for group discussions and opinions, but for some private talks
as well. We learned again that our choice youth want answers. They want direction. They want
acceptance. One young lady impressed us with her very sincere, "Why can't I be the same every
day? Some days I feel like I'm on top of the world; other times I'm discouraged and am low,
especially on myself."
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, we are living in a day when there has never been a greater need for moral
courage: the courage to continue in righteousness, courage to communicate, courage to have
patience, and courage to have childlike faith. May I briefly review with you these important
areas where courageous reinforcement is essential.
</p><p>
<b>Courage to continue</b>
</p><p>
As we think together of the scope of faithfully continuing in righteousness, important parts must
be: courage not to be diverted, courage not to be misled, courage not to stray, and courage to be
anxiously engaged in good work. From the eighth chapter of John, verses 31 and 32, we are
reminded of the promised blessings in store for those who have the courage to continue. "If you
continue in my word, then are ye my disciples indeed; And ye shall know the truth and the truth
shall make you free." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/31-32#31">John 8:31-32</a>) What a joy it is to be associated with members of the Church, young and
old, who are continuing in the paths of righteousness. It is a thrill to see our youth in far-off
stakes and missions, as well as those nearby, preparing valiantly for temple marriages. Other
thousands inspire us as we see them valiantly continuing in their missionary and military
services. God will help us continue in his ways if we humbly seek his guidance. Directing our
energies in his pathways will bring blessings of genuine joy and happiness. His way is the right
way; the right way is the happy way.
</p><p>
<b>Courage to communicate</b>
</p><p>
We need the courage to communicate through word and deed the great truth, ". . . I am not
ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to everyone that
believeth." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>) Joseph Smith's prayer in the grove was answered because he had the
courage to communicate with unwavering faith. Channels of communication between parents
and youth are being effectively opened and used today. Mothers and fathers are getting to know
their children better because wise leaders have encouraged the strengthening of the family circle.
Where necessary, we challenge our youth to take the lead to see that family home evenings are
scheduled and held so that they might learn not only to communicate with family members, but
also more purposefully with their Heavenly Father. Many of our youth have done this in the past,
and today their parents love them for it. Family home evenings, properly held, will open the
channels of communication not only for family members but for God's Spirit as well.
</p><p>
In our work in the Unified Social Services Program of the Church, nothing gives us more
satisfaction than to help parents and youth become better acquainted or reacquainted and
unitedly start down the paths of safety again together. What a pleasure it was the other day to have a beautiful young 17-year-old high school girl say, "Dad and I no longer have a communication hang-up. Thanks to family home evenings, we are back on the same wave length and are now pretty well tuned in."
</p><p>
<b>A priceless environment</b>
</p><p>
One of the greatest blessings that can come to any child is the benefit of being raised in a home
where the mother and father love each other. A husband's and wife's love should be warm and
sincere. An obvious and sincere love will provide a priceless environment for our children.
Children will learn love as they experience it. Earnest communication with others develops a
feeling of belonging. It will let others know we care.
</p><p>
Love and compassion are not obsolete or old-fashioned. They are virtues that build
understanding and happiness. It is difficult for young people to keep the commandments of God
without sharing a feeling of close relationship with their parents and leaders in the Church. Let
us look for the best in our children and associates. It is the Lord's will that we build up&mdash;not tear
down. Our responsibility is to communicate the positive, emphasize the positive, and not be
parties to promoting the negative.
</p><p>
<b>Courage to have patience</b>
</p><p>
We need the courage to have patience, understanding, and compassion. From some of our
troubled youth in today's complex society, may I humbly make this request for them to their
parents and leaders: "Don't give up on us, don't condemn us, don't resent us. Don't try to get us to
conform through sympathy, embarrassment, or ridicule. Instead, give us reasons; give us
examples; give us your best you." Let us as parents and leaders so live and lead to merit the
gratitude of a grateful teenager's "Thank you for helping me find my way back," or "Thank you
for helping me to remain steady." We must learn through patience and understanding to lead our
friends. Say the encouraging word at the right time and the right place.
</p><p>
What a thrill it was the other day to be visiting with one of our handsome full-time Navajo
Indian missionaries when he said, "The main reason I'm on a mission today is because when I
was a small boy, President Spencer W. Kimball came into our home, patted me on the head,
placed a silver dollar in my hand, and said, 'Take this and start saving for a mission.'" Wrapped
up in that example of leadership are all of the important parts: recognition, encouragement,
challenge, and example. To bring groups back, we must learn to lead the individual back through
patience and love. Good leaders don't give up. Good parents don't give up. Good youth don't give
up.
</p><p>
<b>Need for childlike qualities</b>
</p><p>
We need the courage to be as a child. "Therefore, whoso repenteth and cometh unto me as a
little child, him will I receive, for of such is the kingdom of God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/22#22">3 Ne. 9:22</a>) We need
childlike love, childlike repentance, childlike prayers, and childlike faith.
</p><p>
What a warm experience it was a few weeks ago to kneel with a Latter-day Saint family in
far-away Uruguay, South America, as we shared the thoughts of an 11-year-old girl who led us in
family prayer. Her spirit touched us as she communed with her Heavenly Father in her native
Spanish language. At the conclusion of her lovely prayer, we said to her father, "What was it she said in her prayer about the temple?"
</p><p>
He responded with, "She said, 'Help me, Heavenly Father, to be good enough in the way I live so that some day I can marry in the temple.'"
</p><p>
With this childlike faith and daily, sincere preparation, her heart's desire will be possible.
</p><p>
<b>Promise to faithful</b>
</p><p>
"Verily, thus saith the Lord: It shall come to pass that every soul who forsaketh his sins and
cometh unto me, and calleth on my name, and obeyeth my voice, and keepeth my
commandments, shall see my face and know that I am." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/1#1">D&amp;C 93:1</a>) What a crowning promise
to the faithful! What a blessing for those who will continue! What could be a more effective,
humble prayer for us in this troubled day than to ask our Father in heaven to bless us with
courage&mdash;the courage to so live that we won't be the same every day, but with the Lord's help a
little better each day, step by step. It is my hope for us this day that we may show our love and
courage by keeping his commandments.
</p><p>
I bear witness to you that this is in very deed the Church of Jesus Christ. I humbly pray that we
may courageously continue in his work, walking purposefully in his path, which insures the
abundant life, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
