<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Living in the Bonds of Brotherhood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1946, pp. 67-72</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I could ask for no preface more fitting for what I desire to say this morning, than the singing
of that grand hymn, "Come, Come, Ye Saints." As I sit through the conferences from year to
year, I contemplate the great effort and sacrifice that have gone into the efforts you have
made in coming to these conferences and the seriousness with which you attend, regularly and
faithfully, and in listening to all that is said and the actions taken. I have asked myself the
question as to the purpose, after all, of a general conference, and I am reminded of the words
of the Lord when he gave us, in a revelation, the pattern by which important matters
pertaining to his Church should be presented to the people. This is what he said
</p><p>
. . . let it be done as it shall be counseled by the elders of the church at the conferences,
according to the knowledge which they receive from time to time
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/56#56">D&amp;C 58:56</a>).
</p><p>
<i>Will of the Lord Again Revealed</i>
</p><p>
As in olden times, so in our day, holy men of God speak as they are moved upon by the Holy
Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21#21">2 Pet. 1:21</a>),
and whatsoever they speak when moved upon by the Holy Ghost shall be scripture,
shall be the will of the Lord, shall be the mind of the Lord, shall be the voice of the Lord,
and the word of the Lord, and the power of God unto salvation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/4#4">D&amp;C 68:4</a>). It should be a great comfort
to the Latter-day Saints in this day of which the Lord foretold, when peace should be taken
from the earth, and the devil would have power over his own dominion, to hear the Lord say
in revelation that in that day he would reign in the midst of his people and would have power
over his Saints (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/35-36#35">D&amp;C 1:35-36</a>).
But in this day when the arm of the Lord shall be revealed, they who will not
listen to the voice of the Lord, neither to the voice of his servants, neither give heed to the
apostles and prophets, shall be cut off from among the people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/14#14">D&amp;C 1:14</a>). Some of the most profound
thinkers in our generation, other than Church members, have realized the need for revelations
from the Lord in order to give vitality to the teachings of a church. It was Ralph Waldo
Emerson who said:
</p><p>
The Hebrew and Greek scriptures contain immortal sentences that have been the bread of life
to millions, but they do not have epical integrity, are fragmentary and are not shown in their
order to the intellect. . . .
</p><p>
Nor can the Bible be closed until the last great man is born. . . . Men have come to speak of
revelation as somewhat long ago given and done, as if God were dead. That injury to faith
throttles the preachers and the goodliest of institutions become an uncertain and inarticulate
voice. The need was never greater for revelation than it is today.
</p><p>
<i>The Purpose of Revelation</i>
</p><p>
In our day the Lord has given us the reason and the purpose for which revelations are given.
He said to us in one of the earliest revelations in this day of the restored Church:
</p><p>
Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., . . . and gave him commandments; And
also gave commandments to others, that . . . The weak things of the world shall . . . break
down the mighty and strong ones, that man should not counsel his fellow man, neither trust in
the arm of flesh&mdash;But that every man might speak in the name of God the Lord, . . . That
faith also might increase in the earth; That mine everlasting covenant might be established;
That the fulness of my gospel might be proclaimed. . . Behold, I am God and have spoken it;
these commandments are of me, and were given unto my servants in their weakness, after the
manner of their language, that they might come to understanding. And inasmuch as they
erred, it might be made known; And inasmuch as they sought wisdom, they might be
instructed; . . . And inasmuch as they were humble they might be made strong, and blessed
from on high, and receive knowledge from time to time
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17-28#17">D&amp;C 1:17-28</a>).
</p><p>
And so, obedient to that purpose, there have been in this day, our day, men commissioned of
the Lord with power and authority, and he has given them the inspiration to teach and
proclaim these things to the world for the purpose the Lord has set forth, and he has done it
here in this conference and will continue to do so until the end of the conference, that the
important things might be counseled by the elders of the Church to this people according to
the inspiration and revelation they receive from time to time. As the Latter-day Saints go
home from this conference, it would be well if they consider
seriously the importance of taking with them the report of this conference and let it be the
guide to their walk and talk during the next six months. These are the important matters the
Lord sees fit to reveal to this people in this day in the year 1946.
</p><p>
<i>Foresight of Church Leaders</i>
</p><p>
The divine nature of the activities of this Church was never more attested than in the
developments of this last decade, when, under the inspiration of heaven, our leaders have been
trying to prepare this people against the calamities which were shortly to come upon the
inhabitants of the earth. At the time when the nations of the world were fomenting hate and
racial prejudices, this, the Church of Jesus Christ, was sending missionaries to many of these
nations, preaching the brotherhood of man and the fatherhood of God. We were exemplifying
that brotherhood here at home by the teamwork of priesthood quorums and by ward and stake
groups working on welfare projects and in missionary activities. When a false and inflated
prosperity was abroad in the land, caused by the demands of the recent war, this people,
largely by volunteer labor, were filling storehouses with surpluses that would otherwise have
gone to waste. They were building a grain elevator and storing grain at the
time when wheat was being destroyed because it was not needed. They were, in obedience to
the counsel of the leaders of the Church, filling their own cellars and their own basements
with the commodities necessary to meet the needs that were foreseen in a day to come, and in
order to reduce the drain on the public supply that would otherwise be needed for the
prosecution of the purposes of this government. The things, it seems to me, that we need most
in the world today, are, first, a recognition of the "modern Josephs" represented in the
leadership of the Church today, because of the prophetic vision they have exercised in seeing
this day of want and destruction; and second, we need "modern Pharaohs" in this and other
nations, who will recognize the statements of these leaders of the Church as the mind of the
Lord and the word of the Lord to the world in this day.
</p><p>
An unintentional testimony was given to us recently in the nation's capital by a high-placed
government official when he said after we had explained to him the welfare activities of the
Church "You have done the very thing in your Church that the government is now trying to
do in its present program to provide food for the starving nations of Europe."
</p><p>
As the carloads of foodstuffs and clothing and bedding move down to the seaports to be
transported overseas to feed our needy people, and as the truckloads in our country go to meet
similar needs in that distressed area, I have felt in my heart that surely this is sufficient
evidence of the hand of the Lord being laid bare in behalf of his people.
</p><p>
<i>Tenth Anniversary of Church Welfare Program</i>
</p><p>
Today marks the tenth anniversary of the inauguration or the announcement of the churchwide
activity known as the Church welfare program. I cannot come to this day without looking
back over the days that have passed. I have remembered some of those who lathered this
work, since its inception, who have been called to their eternal home: President Heber J.
Grant, Melvin J. Ballard, Nicholas G. Smith, Campbell M. Brown, J. Frank Ward, Robert L.
Judd, Elias S. Woodruff, Byron D. Anderson. As I think of their passing, I can't help
contemplating what their interest is in the welfare program wherever they are today. I can't
believe that it is less than it was here; and if the Lord gives them the opportunity to exercise
that influence, I am certain they will be exercising it. What of us here? In paying due honor
to what they attempted to build, I wonder if we have remembered their words. We have
repeated often the statement that was given to us by President Grant when this program was
launched. These were his words and you heard them repeated, time and again, when he said:
</p><p>
Our primary purpose is to set up, insofar as it might be possible, a system
under which the curse of idleness would be done away with, the evils of a dole abolished, and
independence, industry, and thrift and self-respect be once more established amongst our
people. The aim of the Church is to help the people to help themselves. Work is to be
re-enthroned as the ruling principle of the lives of our Church membership.
(<i>The Improvement Era</i>, April 1946. p. 209.)
</p><p>
<i>Foundation Stones of Welfare Work</i>
</p><p>
I traveled over the Church by request of the First Presidency with Elder Melvin J. Ballard in
the early days of the welfare program to discuss with local Church leaders the details essential
to its beginning. There were three favorite passages of scripture that he frequently quoted to
the people. One statement that he often repeated was this "We must take care of our own
people, for the Lord has said that all this is to be done that:
</p><p>
. . . the church may stand independent above all other creatures beneath the celestial world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/14#14">D&amp;C 78:14</a>).
</p><p>
And again he taught, after quoting from the one hundred fifteenth section of the Doctrine and
Covenants:
</p><p>
Verily I say unto you all: Arise and shine forth, that thy light may be a standard for the
nations (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/5#5">D&amp;C 115:5</a>).
</p><p>
This is the day of demonstration of the power of the Lord in behalf of his people. And again
quoting the one hundred fourth section:
</p><p>
Therefore, if any man shall take of the abundance which I have made, and impart not his
portion, according to the law of my gospel, unto the poor and the needy, he shall, with the
wicked, lift up his eyes in hell, being in torment
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/18#18">D&amp;C 104:18</a>).
</p><p>
I read these quotations to you today to remind you of the foundation stones on which the
welfare work of the Church has been laid.
</p><p>
<i>Obligation to Care for Our Own</i>
</p><p>
As I have recalled the experiences of the last ten years, I have thought of the welfare work as
a kind of temporal turning of the hearts of the fathers to the children and the children to the
fathers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/6#6">Mal. 4:6</a>).
</p><p>
You who may think that a far-fetched statement, may I remind you of one or two scriptures?
To Timothy, the Apostle Paul said:
</p><p>
But if any [man] provide not for his own, and especially for those of his own house, he hath
denied the faith, and is worse than an infidel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/5/8#8">1 Tim. 5:8</a>).
</p><p>
And again the commandment from Mt. Sinai, and interpreted by the Master, you will
remember, to mean the taking care of aging parents by children:
</p><p>
Honour thy father and thy mother: that thy days may be long upon the land which the Lord
thy God giveth thee (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/12#12">Ex. 20:12</a>).
</p><p>
From these two scriptures I make these two conclusions: In the first place
those who refuse to care for their own are subject to a judgment more severe than that which
would be meted out to one who lost his faith and had become as an infidel; and second, that
those who refuse to honor father and mother in the way the Master explained, are
jeopardizing their tenure upon this land which the Lord has given us. I have thought a great
deal about that. I wonder whether that tenure shall be jeopardized because of the burdensome
taxation that shall increase and grow until we are virtually displaced in our ownership, if we
don't take care of our own, or I am wondering whether the Lord will withdraw his blessings,
as Amulek declared in the thirty-fourth chapter of Alma
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/28-29#28">Alma 34:28-29</a>),
if we refuse to succor those who
stand in need of help (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/4/13#13">Alma 4:13</a>).
</p><p>
And on the other hand, so far as children are concerned, I have remembered what the Apostle
Paul said about that: He predicted a time that would come in the last days, a perilous time
when men should be lovers of their own selves, covetous, disobedient, unthankful, unholy,
without natural affection (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/1-4#1">2 Tim. 3:1-4</a>).
That sounds strangely familiar to the language of the Lord in this day, when he declared:
</p><p>
Now, I, the Lord, am not well pleased with the inhabitants of Zion, for there are idlers among
them; and their children are also growing up in wickedness; they also seek not earnestly the
riches of eternity, but their eyes are full of greediness. These things ought not to be, and must
be done away from among them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/31-32#31">D&amp;C 68:31-32</a>).
</p><p>
I have asked myself if the failure of children to take care of their aging parents, when they
come to a day of want and are in need of sustenance, is due to the failure of parents, in the
day gone by, to teach those same children to avoid the curse of idleness, and to be responsible
in righteousness before our Heavenly Father. Unless we teach our children today correct
principles, they, like some children today, will be thankless and without the natural affection
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/3#3">2 Tim. 3:3</a>)
necessary to cement this society upon a firm, determined foundation. Yes, it seems to me that
in very deed, the welfare plan has been a kind of turning of the hearts of the children to the
fathers and the fathers to the children
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/6#6">Mal. 4:6</a>),
that we might be prolonged upon this land which the
Lord our God has given us (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/12#12">Ex. 20:12</a>).
</p><p>
<i>The Lord's Plan for Security</i>
</p><p>
The Lord has given us in this day the greatest organization upon the face of the earth, with
his power and his authority to direct it. He has given us sound principles; he has shown us the
plan and the way by which want and distress may be done away among us. He has shown us
the way to brotherly love. If the afflictions which have been predicted do come upon us, they
will come upon us because we have not kept the faith and because we have been disobedient
and have thrown away the opportunities that our Heavenly Father has given us to prepare for
the day of calamity which he foretold
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/49-50#49">D&amp;C 45:49-50</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/35#35">D&amp;C 136:35</a>),
over one hundred years ago, would come in this generation.
</p><p>
I remember at the dedication of the grain elevator in 1940 hearing President McKay in an
inspired and prophetic prayer utter these words:
</p><p>
May this be an edifice of service, a contribution of love, and as such we dedicate it unto thee
and ask thy blessings to attend all who have contributed to its erection and all who may
contribute to the keeping of these bins filled with the wheat which is considered necessary to
be preserved preparatory to the judgments that await the nations of the earth.
</p><p>
My prayer is today that those who contribute, and those who receive as well, shall so live in
the bonds of brotherhood and unity and oneness, that the Lord can reign in the midst of his
Saints and be a power over them and a shield, as he promised in the ninety-seventh section of
the Doctrine and Covenants (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/97/18-28#18">D&amp;C 97:18-28</a>)
he would be, if we his Saints would keep his commandments in the day when the
judgments were about to descend upon the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/38#38">D&amp;C 109:38</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/45#45">JS&mdash;H 1:45</a>).
</p><p>
God help us so to live and to keep in harmony with his Spirit that these things may be with
the Saints in our day, I pray humbly in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
