<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Faith in Israel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1947, pp. 72-77</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, this vast congregation, crowding and overcrowding the capacity of
the Tabernacle, seems to me to be a sufficient answer to the query of the
ancient prophet. There is faith in Israel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/32/20#20">Deut. 32:20</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hab/2/4#4">Hab. 2:4</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/18/8#8">Luke 18:8</a>).
</p><p>
NATURAL ENDOWMENTS OF THE PIONEERS
</p><p>
Almost every speaker during this conference has mentioned the pioneers, the heroic men and
women who, a hundred years ago and up to the coming of the railroad, trailed across the
plains and made possible, not only Utah but also the arid and semi-arid wastes of the United
States, for the use of mankind. It is a great story, beautifully told here this morning.
</p><p>
These pioneers were uncommon people. They were not of the common run. It took more than
brawn, muscle, to redeem the desert, and to teach the whole world how the great arid wastes
of the world might be reclaimed. The work of these men has been heralded far and wide, and
all the world has profited by their labors. They were uncommon people.
</p><p>
I knew David McKay [President David O. McKay's father]. It was a great privilege. He was
not a common man. There were notable, fine qualities in him, inborn qualities, such as were
characteristic of the great body of pioneers which made possible that which they
accomplished. They were not men and women of great education though they had as much
education as was ordinarily possessed by the people of that day, both in America and in
Europe. There was a good proportion of school-trained men among them, but remember that a
school can only polish and develop that which a man possesses. Schools do not create the
powers of men. These pioneer people had natural endowments so great as to make it difficult
to understand, how so many such capable people could be gathered together in the making of
this intermountain empire.
</p><p>
PRESIDENT YOUNG'S DEFINITION OF MORMONISM
</p><p>
I have chosen to try to say something about the qualities and endowments of these men in the
words of the foremost of them, their appointed leader, Brigham Young. He was not greater
than the others. He was of the same blood, spiritually and physically, and, fortunately, he left
behind him nearly four hundred discourses taken down in shorthand and published. I grew up
as other young men in Zion, looking upon Brigham Young as a great leader, great colonizer,
but only after I undertook to read his discourses did the character of the man really stand out
boldly before me. He was a great character. Those who labored with him in their respective
fields were equally great.
</p><p>
A stranger came to him one day and said:
</p><p>
President Young, will you define Mormonism for me? I heard you preach in the Tabernacle
the other day. I did not quite understand all that you said, and I wish you would be kind
enough to analyze what you said and simplify it.
</p><p>
Then this leader of the pioneers, of great endowments, brushed aside all the old opinions, the
old methods of defining things, in the realm of religion, all the secondary or derivative
doctrines and answered:
</p><p>
Our religion is simply the truth. It is all said in this one expression: It embraces
all truth wherever found in all the works of God and man, visible or invisible to
mortal eyes.
</p><p>
An ordinary man of lesser mental and spiritual stature would have found refuge in some other
kind of definition. This man dug down to the bottom of the thing. Truth is the foundation of
the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ. He added:
</p><p>
It is more rational for an intelligent being to embrace truth than it is to mix up a
little truth with a great deal of error or to embrace all error and undertake to
follow a phantom.
</p><p>
THE FAITH OF A GREAT LEADER
</p><p>
But, he understood that truth must have a source, a teacher to human beings. No man in all
the world has ever expressed a finer and a greater, more fervent belief in God than did
Brigham Young.
</p><p>
Our faith is concentrated in the Son of God and through him in the Father, and the Holy
Ghost is a minister to bring truths to our remembrance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>), to reveal new truths to us and teach,
guide, direct the course of every mind. Jesus is our captain
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/2/10#10">Heb. 2:10</a>) and leader, Jesus, Savior of the
World, the Christ that we believe in.
</p><p>
Out of that faith came the truth that he held so dear. If we had time, I could read some
eloquent statements about his faith in God and Jesus Christ, never surpassed in the writings of
mankind.
</p><p>
This man was a symbol of all the pioneers, for when I speak of Brigham Young, I speak of
every pioneer. It took and takes strong men, men of capacity, to accept the gospel of the Lord
Jesus. In that respect, we of this age who have accepted the gospel are also uncommon.
</p><p>
But Brigham Young warned the people:
</p><p>
Now we have the truth. We know whence it comes, from God himself, and that brings a
tremendous responsibility to rest upon every one of us . . . Our mortal existence is a school of
experience. The Lord does not compel any person to embrace the gospel, and I do not think
he will compel them to live it after they have embraced it. The volition of the creature is free.
This is a law of their existence, and the Lord cannot violate his own law. Were he to do that
he would cease to be exalted. He has placed life and death before his children, and it is for
them to choose. If they choose life, they receive a blessing of life. If they choose death, they
must abide the penalty. This is the law which has always existed from all eternity and will
continue to exist throughout all the eternities to come. Every intelligent being must have the
power of choice.
</p><p>
Simple words! But what a tremendous burden, if burden it be, they place upon us, the
necessity to live in accordance with the eternal law of God.
</p><p>
THE RELIGION OF THE LATTER-DAY SAINTS A PRACTICAL ONE
</p><p>
Having said all of this (I have picked just a few things out of the record), he emphasized the
fact that the truth which comes from God, and possessed by us, must be used by us properly.
There was no hesitation in that. Truth is not an ornament to be hung on the wall or placed on
the shelf to look at. It must be of daily use for he said:
</p><p>
We need a present, everyday religion. My religion must be with me from one
Monday morning to the next, the year around or it will not answer me. I am
decidedly in favor of a practical religion, of everyday useful life, and if I today
attend to what devolves upon me to do, then do that which presents itself
tomorrow, and so on, when eternity comes I will be prepared to enter on the
things of eternity, but I would not be prepared for that sphere of action unless I
could manage the things that are now within my reach. We must all learn to do
this. There is no life more precious than the present life which we enjoy. There
is no life that is worth any more to us than this life is. It may be said that an
eternal life is worth more. We are in eternity, and all that we have to do is to take
the road that leads into the eternal lives.
</p><p>
And in his application of truth to useful ends, he said many things. For example, concerning
education:
</p><p>
Knowledge is to be sought. It was originally embraced by the Latter-day Saints,
if only slightly understood, and they were counseled to search diligently after
knowledge. There is no other people in existence more eager to see, to hear, to
learn and understand truth . . . Every accomplishment, every polished grace,
every useful attainment in mathematics, music, and all the sciences and arts belong
to the Saints, and they should avail themselves as expeditiously as possible of the
wealth of knowledge that science has offered to every diligent and persevering
scholar.
</p><p>
There is no narrow conception in such a statement, no fence is built around knowledge, no
limitation placed upon it. All truth is ours.
</p><p>
BRIGHAM YOUNG'S VIEWS ON CAPITAL AND LABOR
</p><p>
He entered into the field of economics and became known as a great economic leader. He said
in what might be written in huge letters for the wise men of the earth to read:
</p><p>
Capital and labor, all the capital there is upon this earth, is the bone and sinew of working
men and women. Were it not for that, the gold and the silver and precious stones would
remain in the mountains, upon the plains, and in the valleys and never would be gathered or
brought into use. The timber would continue to grow, but none of it would be brought into
service, and the earth would remain as it is. It is the activity and labor of the inhabitants of
the earth that bringeth forth wealth.
</p><p>
This simple definition of wealth, is fit for colleges and all the nations to ponder. Time and the
ability to labor are the capital stock of the whole world.
</p><p>
EXPRESSIONS AS TO GOVERNMENT
</p><p>
He spoke of political government:
</p><p>
The Constitution and laws of the United States resemble a theocracy more closely than any
government now on earth. We will cling to the Constitution of our country and to the
government that reveres that sacred charter of free men's rights and if necessary pour out our
best blood for the defense of every good and righteous principle.
</p><p>
He laid down the principle which should be the foundation of every government:
</p><p>
Individual self-government lies at the root of all true and effective government whether in
heaven or on earth.
</p><p>
He even spoke of the women and their duties in the world of action&mdash;woman suffrage:
</p><p>
Now, sisters, I want you to vote also, because women are the characters that rule the ballot
box.
</p><p>
I wish they did rule it today. I am not certain they have lived up to the commendation of the
pioneer leader.
</p><p>
HUMILITY A SIGN OF GREATNESS
</p><p>
Great men are humble. No great man takes power and honor unto himself, and so Brigham
Young said:
</p><p>
I have never professed to be Brother Joseph, but only Brother Brigham, trying to
do good to this people. I am no better nor any more important than any other man
who is trying to do good. If I am, I do not know it. If I improve upon what the
Lord has given me and continue to improve, I shall become like those who have
gone before me.
</p><p>
I shall be exalted in the Celestial Kingdom and be filled to overflowing with all
the power I can wield, and all the keys and knowledge I can manage will be
committed unto me.
</p><p>
Then he quoted what President Hunter just quoted, the first part being:
</p><p>
I do not wish anyone to understand that I had anything to do with our being moved here.
That was the providence of the Almighty.
</p><p>
LOYALTY TO JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
Great men are loyal. There is nothing finer in the life of Brigham Young than his loyalty to
Joseph Smith. He spoke of him and said:
</p><p>
A Prophet of God! I honor and revere the name of Joseph Smith. I delight to hear it. I love it.
I love his doctrine . . .
</p><p>
What is the nature and beauty of Joseph's mission? When I first heard him preach,
he had brought heaven and earth together, and all the priests of 
the day could not tell me anything correct about heaven, hell, God, angels, the
devils and there was blindness darkness. When I saw Joseph Smith, he took
heaven, of which he was speaking, and brought it down to earth. Then he took the 
earth and brought it up and opened up in plainness and simplicity the things of
God, and that is the beauty of his mission.
</p><p>
At the last, on his deathbed, the attending physician as he leaned over the bedside heard him
whisper: 
</p><p>
"Joseph, Joseph!"
</p><p>
Of such timber were our pioneers hewn. Of such timber are we or should be. God bless us
and be with us, help us to be like the pioneers we honor, I pray, for the deserts of the world,
in other fields, are formidable today as the deserts of the West were yesterday, in the name of
the Lord, Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
