<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Upon You My Fellow Servants"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 43-45</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Richards, President Clark, my beloved brethren of the General
Authorities, my dear brothers and sisters and friends: I feel very humble in standing before
this great audience today, and I sincerely ask for a solemn prayer in your hearts in my behalf. 
I am grateful to be here with you in this great general conference of the Church. Truly, we
have been spiritually strengthened and built up in our faith.  We come here for that purpose,
and I pray that the Lord will help me that I may say something that will give you strength
and increase your faith and your testimony.
</p><p>
We spend much of our time in our business and temporal affairs, in our educational, social,
and recreational life.  We spend a great deal of our time in government and politics. 
Probably that is as it should be, but I wonder how much time we actually spend in developing
the spiritual side of our lives&mdash;probably, may I say, the better part of our lives?  The older I
become, the more I realize that this is the better side of our lives and certainly the most
important side of our lives.
</p><p>
It is not uncommon for thousands of us Latter-day Saints to bow our heads in prayer and
close our eyes, and to follow the prayer of him who may be mouth. Truly we are a praying
people.  The world has judged us to be a praying people, and we confess that we not only
pray in large gatherings at conference, but we also pray every day of our lives, and we accept
the principle of prayer.
</p><p>
I would like to say a few words about the Aaronic Priesthood.  I am directing my remarks
particularly to those concerned with Aaronic Priesthood boys from twelve to twenty-one. 
There are approximately seventy thousand of them in the stakes of the Church, not counting
the missions.  We also have about that same number of Senior members of the Aaronic
Priesthood, wonderful men who bear the Aaronic Priesthood, or a total of approximately
140,000 men and boys holding that wonderful priesthood, the Aaronic Priesthood, which gives
them the power and the blessing and the authority and the responsibility of acting in the name
of God, our Eternal Father.
</p><p>
I hope, parents, that you will take an interest in these Aaronic Priesthood boys.  Fathers and
mothers, help them on Sunday mornings.  They are sleepy; they are tired; they are growing
boys. Help them to get up on Sunday morning and attend their priesthood meetings. You
wonderful wives of the Senior members, encourage your husbands on Sunday morning to get
up in time to put on their Sunday clothes and go to Church.  That will give to them and to
you great blessings that you will not know any other way.
</p><p>
May I try briefly to pray some of the incidents concerning the restoration of the Aaronic
Priesthood?  I would like to take you back to the beautiful Susquehanna River, near Harmony,
Pennsylvania. Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery, two young men, age twenty-three and
twenty-two, respectively, stood on those beautiful banks of the Susquehanna River in
Pennsylvania. Their faces reflected the seriousness of their thoughts.  It was evident that peace
permeated their entire beings, and every act bespoke humility and faith in God, their Eternal
Father.  They had intentionally secluded themselves from the world that they might seek the
counsel of their Father in heaven.
</p><p>
May 15, 1829&mdash;it was a beautiful day. Winter was over.  Spring was in the air.  Nature had
painted the leaves of the trees with a delicate green.  The song of the birds overhead blended
with the sounds of the river to produce harmonious overtones that added serenity to that
beautiful occasion.  The sun cast its golden rays through the motionless leaves of the
semi-dense overgrowth, making a wonderful study in light and shadow.  All was calm and
peaceful, that day.  It was indeed a sacred spot and a sacred hour.  Cares and worries and
concern were largely overcome by the handiwork of God. The harmonious beauty that
surrounded them contributed to the sacredness of the place and of the occasion, but the
seriousness of their mission made them semi-oblivious to it. They now knelt together in
humble prayer, seeking guidance from God, their Eternal Father.
</p><p>
These two young men were concerned about the principle of baptism for the remission of
sins, and they desired to know more concerning the details of this sacred ordinance.  What
was the proper mode?  How, and to whom, and by whom should this ordinance be
performed?  In their work of translating the Book of Mormon they had become concerned
regarding the problem, as they contrasted the instructions of that sacred book with the
practices of the churches of that day.  They knew, however, that their Father in heaven would
supply the wisdom they now sought.
</p><p>
And while they were engaged in prayer, a messenger, whom God had sent, appeared to them,
and he spoke, unto them.  "I am thy fellow-servant"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1000#1000">JS&mdash;H 1 Endnote</a>).
The resurrected John the Baptist now
stood before them&mdash;he, who had come out of the wilderness crying repentance to the people
of his day; he, who had baptized our Lord and Savior at Bethabara in the River Jordan.  Yes,
this was the same John who on that sacred occasion heard the Father's voice from heaven
declare, "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>). This was the
same John who witnessed the Holy Ghost descend on Jesus; he, the literal descendant of
Aaron who held the keys of the Aaronic Priesthood by right and ordination; he of whom the
Lord said, "No greater prophet born of woman"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/7/28#28">Luke 7:28</a>); he, who had been beheaded
for his courageous denunciation of sin and for his love of truth. Now he stood before them in
majesty; the glory that surrounded him was far more brilliant than the May sunshine. His
presence dispelled all doubts and all fears, and these two young men opened their souls to
partake of his great wisdom.
</p><p>
He then laid his hands upon their heads and conferred upon them the Aaronic Priesthood keys
which he had held throughout the centuries.  The words of that ordination prayer were
indelibly impressed upon the minds of these two young men: 
</p><p>
Upon you my fellow servants, in the name of Messiah I confer the Priesthood of
Aaron, which holds the keys of the ministering of angels, and of the gospel of
repentance, and of baptism by immersion for the remission of sins; and this shall never
be taken again from the earth, until the sons of Levi do offer again an offering unto
the Lord in righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/13/1#1">D&amp;C 13:1</a>).
</p><p>
He then told them that the Aaronic Priesthood was an appendage of the Melchizedek
Priesthood, that it had not the power of the laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost,
but that this power should later be given to them. Then he told these two young men that he
came under the direction of Peter, James, and John, who held the keys of the Priesthood of
Melchizedek, which priesthood, in due time, would be conferred upon them and which later
was conferred upon them.
</p><p>
These two young men were then directed by this messenger to go down into the river, that
beautiful Susquehanna River.  Joseph Smith was instructed to baptize Oliver, and Oliver, in
turn, was instructed to baptize Joseph. They were then to ordain each other to the Aaronic
Priesthood by the laying on of hands.  Joseph ordained Oliver to the Aaronic Priesthood first,
and Oliver then ordained Joseph.
</p><p>
This glorious spiritual experience that followed their baptism and ordination to the priesthood
was accompanied by the spirit of prophecy. As they left this hallowed spot, their hearts were
light. The Aaronic Priesthood was again restored to the earth by an angel of God to his
servants, the first time in many centuries for man to be divinely commissioned with the
priesthood.  This vision demonstrated conclusively that the heavens were not closed and gave
positive proof of the promise of the resurrection.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony that I know this priesthood was restored to the earth. I bear you my
testimony that I know God lives and that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God, our Redeemer
and our Savior, our Elder Brother.  I bear you my testimony that I know this is the true work
that we are engaged in, and I know that Joseph Smith was a Prophet of God.  I know that
President David O. McKay is a true, living prophet of God, our Eternal Father, and I bear
you that testimony, and I know it to be true, and I know it by the power and gift of the Holy
Ghost, that testifies to me that this is true.  I bear you that testimony in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
