<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Stephen L Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Stephen L Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 85-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I believe, my brethren, we have cause for encouragement. Listening to the report of the
Church made by President McKay at the opening of the Conference, and the various other
items which have been mentioned, I believe that we should feel optimistic about the progress
of our work. I do. I think that we are going forward, and I have confidence and faith that we
will meet all the problems and situations which arise.
</p><p>
I thank the Lord always for the principle of continuous revelation. I thank him that he has
made provision for his Spirit to attend all of those who are called to preside in his work, and
I speak not only of the General Authorities, but those who are charged with the responsibility
of presidency in the stakes and the wards, in the quorums in the missions, in the temple, and
in all of our organizations.
</p><p>
I am a firm believer in improvement. I think improvement is the law of life, and I am grateful
that we are not so controlled by practices and conditions of the past that we are not open to
the consideration of ways and means to advance the Kingdom of our Father.
</p><p>
I remember hearing a president of one of our stakes illustrate the point. One of the sister
workers in an organization of the stake said to him, because he was a pretty hard-driving
president, "President, it seems that you are never satisfied." "O, yes I am," he said, "I am
always satisfied that you can do better." And so I am persuaded that such new methods as
present themselves and come regularly through the proper channels will be conducive to the
upbuilding of our Father's work. We have evidences of it. I might submit some of the figures
to attest this, but time will not permit tonight. The whole picture looks to me to be one of
encouragement, one to give us cause for great gratitude in the assurance that the blessings of
the Lord have been upon us.
</p><p>
Now there are opportunities for further perfecting our work, and those opportunities rest in
large measure with our presiding brethren. I would like to say just a word to the presidencies
of quorums. These quorums of priesthood, as you are all aware, are designated of the Lord.
They are substantially the only organizations among us, other than that of the general
organization of the Church, which have been specifically mentioned in the revelations. The
Lord must have set great store by these marvelous institutions which he created. He knew in
the beginning that his priesthood would be the basic foundation of his work. I was thinking
tonight if Joseph and those associated with him in the beginning of the work could witness
what we see tonight, this great demonstration of power, resident within God's Holy
Priesthood, and perhaps they do see it, how gratified they would be.
</p><p>
And here is a great reservoir of power to be utilized for the advancement of our Father's
Kingdom. Upon the quorums rests the largest measure of that responsibility. I am persuaded
that no other organization can or ought to take their place, because they constitute the Lord's
grouping of the manpower of his Church. Upon the presidencies of quorums rests the
responsibility of seeing that their quorums function properly.
</p><p>
We used to have years and years ago, when the Priesthood Committee of the Church was first
organized; many may remember it; President-McKay will, a very concise and comprehensive
definition of a quorum. We used to say it is three things: A class, a fraternity, and a service
unit. And so we sought to group around these headings the responsibilities of the men of the
quorum. And while there has grown out of the original concept a more
elaborate organization, I am persuaded that if we could make our quorums serve the functions
indicated by those three things we should accomplish much for the members and for the
Church.
</p><p>
I am thoroughly persuaded that we can learn the Gospel in our quorums, and thus comply
with the revelation that men are "to learn their duties"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>).
When men profess that some of the
courses of study are a little intricate and difficult, I think of the days in Kirtland when a few
men of meager learning and education had what seems to be the effrontery and boldness to
set about to learn Hebrew, and you will recall how in the School of the Prophets, they
engaged a Professor Seixas to teach them Hebrew in order that they might the better interpret
God's word. We can learn. We can learn by study. We can learn the fundamental things that
we need to know as members of God's Holy Priesthood. And we can learn about the
apostasy, which is essential for us to understand in order that we comprehend in its fulness
the restoration and be fortified to defend the restoration in the latter days.
</p><p>
And I take the liberty of urging you men, through your quorum presidencies, to see to it that
your teachers study, that they receive the instruction which is provided for them, and the
facilities which have been maintained in order to give them a concept of these great truths and
to teach them intelligently to those who come to the classes. The more we make our classes
worthwhile to the members, the more readily will they come, and the greater the value they
will receive from them.
</p><p>
Now, I don't know that it is possible for any organization to succeed in the Church under the
priesthood without adopting the genius of our Church government. What is that? As I
conceive it, the genius of our Church government is government through councils. The
Council of the Presidency, the Council of the Twelve, the Council of the Stake Presidency, or
quorum, if you choose to use that word, the Council of the Bishopric, and the quorum of
Council of the Quorum Presidency. I have had enough experience to know the value of
councils. Hardly a day passes but that I see the wisdom, God's wisdom, in creating councils:
to govern his Kingdom. In the spirit under which we labor, men can get together with
seemingly divergent views and far different backgrounds, and under the operation of that
spirit, by counseling together, they can arrive at an accord, and that accord, (the occasions are
so negligible as not to be mentioned) and therefore I say that accord is always right. That
accord represents the wisdom of the council, acting under the Spirit.
</p><p>
Now, brethren of priesthood quorum presidencies: You need those councils, and I have no
hesitancy in giving you the assurance, if you will confer in council as you are expected to do,
God will give you solutions to the problems that confront you with reference to your
quorums. And he will enable you to find ways and means of approaching the men whom you
would like to reach to bring them into accord with your quorum, and have them enjoy its
spirit. I am sure we can go out and get many of these men. My heart is always troubled for
the unusually large number of our elders who do not ally themselves with the quorum and
secure the spirit and the benefit to be had therefrom. I am not at all persuaded that these are
bad men, but I am persuaded that they are negligent often and forgetful and neglectful, and
they need your care. And the quorum presidency, no matter how many committees you
appoint, the quorum presidency is responsible for every man in the quorum; and I am sure
you cannot be relieved of that responsibility, although you will want the help of all those who
may come to your assistance.
</p><p>
And I am persuaded too that if you approach many of these men in frankness and true
friendship, you will touch their hearts. I have long been persuaded that it is
something of a waste of time to go to a man's home who has been neglectful and spend the
time in talking about the weather or the crops or politics or something else.
</p><p>
I always admired my dear brother, the President of the Church, George Albert Smith. I have
been with him on many occasions. I have seen him meet many old friends, and I frequently
have seen him take their hand, and ask the first question, not how are you getting along,
which usually means how much money are you making, but "How are you feeling in the
Church?" I have seen him ask that of business men. I have been with him on the streets of
this city and had him meet a business man and say, "Well, how are you feeling in the
Church?" It was a direct approach, and one usually that brought a response that probably
made the man search his conscience, and that is what we need to do with these men, to get
them to search their own conscience, and make their own decisions to avail themselves of
these glorious opportunities that we bring to them.
</p><p>
Now, my brethren, I recognize that I can't deal with many problems tonight. There is one
problem that President McKay suggested that I mention to you about the missionaries, and I
fully endorse all that has been said about that great work, and that is, brethren, that we still
think it wise to use some caution in the general advertising of missionary farewells. I don't
need to take the time to tell you the rather strenuous period we have been through in trying to
arrange for our missionary program. It has not been easy. Thank the Lord it is now operating
in good measure and producing results, but it has not been easy; and for the time being, it is
suggested that you follow the directions that were issued sometime ago to avoid newspaper
advertising of our missionary farewells. Times may change, and this instruction may change.
</p><p>
I just want to bear my testimony to the divinity of this great power that you and I hold. I
know that it is genuine. I know that it is authentic. I have no more question about its
authenticity and its derivation than I have of any other fact established by the most concrete
evidence we could ask. Sometimes there are those who when I have laid my hands upon their
head in ordination have asked me for the derivation of my priesthood. I repeat four steps: I
was ordained by President Joseph F. Smith. He was ordained by President Brigham Young.
Brigham Young was ordained by the three witnesses, one of whom was Oliver Cowdery, and
that ordination was subsequently confirmed by the Prophet. Oliver Cowdery and Joseph Smith
were ordained by angelic ministers from the Lord Jesus Christ himself. We don't have to go
into antiquity to establish the authenticity and the genuineness of this power that we hold, and
you and I know, that aside from the evidences of its authentic derivation, we know that there
is an essence within it which makes it more than a mere name. I have felt it and you have. I
know that our Father has given it to his men and boys to establish his work. God help us to
use it effectively in the creation of a better world, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
