<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Power and Influence of the Priesthood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President N. Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 52-54</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Smith, who is presiding at this meeting and all through the conference, has asked me
to conduct, and he has now asked me to say a few words to you this evening.
</p><p>
I am always thrilled and inspired when I meet with the priesthood of The Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints, which is the priesthood of God; and to hear the lovely singing we have had
this evening, and the fine talks to which we have listened, thrills me and inspires me more and
more.
</p><p>
<b>The power of God</b>
</p><p>
The priesthood is the power by which all things were created and the power by which God has
done those things about which Bishop Vandenberg spoke this evening; but for us as individuals,
it is the power of God that has been delegated to us to act in his name in the office which we
hold. And it is a great privilege, a great blessing, and a great responsibility to have that
priesthood bestowed upon us.
</p><p>
Sometimes our young men feel they should have the priesthood when they I reach the respective
ages for ordination as deacons, teachers, and priests, regardless of their situation as to their
activity or how they are living. They should realize what a great privilege it is to hold that
priesthood. When a person receives it, he takes upon himself a very heavy responsibility.
</p><p>
<b>Many called but few chosen</b>
</p><p>
I should like to read just a few words to you, taken from the Doctrine and Covenants: 
</p><p>
"Behold, there are many called, but few are chosen. And why are they not chosen?
</p><p>
"Because their hearts are set so much upon the things of this world, and aspire to the honors of
men, that they do not learn this one lesson&mdash;
</p><p>
"That the rights of the priesthood are inseparably connected with the powers of heaven, and that
the powers of heaven cannot be controlled nor handled only upon the principles of
righteousness.
</p><p>
"That they may be conferred upon us, it is true; but when we undertake to cover our sins, or to
gratify our pride, our vain ambition, or to exercise control or dominion or compulsion upon the
souls of the children of men, in any degree of unrighteousness, behold, the heavens withdraw
themselves; the Spirit of the Lord is grieved; and when it is withdrawn, Amen to the priesthood
</p><p>
"Behold, ere he is aware, he is left unto himself, to kick against the pricks, to persecute the
saints, and to fight against God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/34-38#34">D&amp;C 121:34-38</a>)
</p><p>
I interpret that as referring to those who fail to magnify their priesthood, or who use it as it
should not be used. I know of many cases where a man has gradually failed to magnify his
priesthood and moved away from activity in the Church. As a result, a man who has been very
active loses his testimony and the Spirit of the Lord withdraws from him, and he begins to
criticize those in authority, and to persecute the saints, apostatize, and fight against God.
</p><p>
We also find these words of the Lord in the Doctrine and Covenants: "The Holy Ghost shall be
thy constant companion, and thy scepter an unchanging scepter of righteousness and truth; and
thy dominion shall be an everlasting dominion, and without compulsory means it shall flow unto
thee forever and ever" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/46#46">D&amp;C 121:46</a>)&mdash;that is, if we magnify our priesthood.
</p><p>
<b>Oath and covenant of priesthood</b>
</p><p>
I am sure all of you have read the oath and covenant of the priesthood, and have heard it many
times. To me it is very important.
</p><p>
"For whoso is faithful unto the obtaining these two priesthoods of which I have spoken, and the
magnifying their calling, are sanctified by the Spirit unto the renewing of their bodies.
</p><p>
"They become the sons of Moses and of Aaron and the seed of Abraham, and the church and
kingdom, and the elect of God.
</p><p>
"And also all they who receive this priesthood receive me, saith the Lord; 
</p><p>
"For he that receiveth my servants receiveth me; 
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth me receiveth my Father; 
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth my Father receiveth my Father's kingdom; therefore all that my Father
hath shall be given unto him." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33-38#33">D&amp;C 84:33-38</a>)
</p><p>
I should like to emphasize that these blessings are promised to those who magnify their
priesthood every day in every way.
</p><p>
"And this is according to the oath and covenant which belongeth to the priesthood.
</p><p>
"Therefore, all those who receive the priesthood, receive this oath and covenant of my Father,
which he cannot break, neither can it be moved.
</p><p>
"But whoso breaketh this covenant after he hath received it, and altogether turneth therefrom,
shall not have forgiveness of sins." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/39-41#39">D&amp;C 84:39-41</a>)
</p><p>
The Lord says here that he cannot break his covenant, but if we break ours, there is no promise.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, now let every man learn his duty, and to act in the office in which he is appointed,
in all diligence.
</p><p>
"He that is slothful shall not be counted worthy to stand, and he that learns not his duty and
shows himself not approved shall not be counted worthy to stand. Even so. Amen." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100#99">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>)
</p><p>
"Therefore, blessed are ye if ye continue in my goodness, a light unto the Gentiles, and through
this priesthood, a savior unto my people Israel. The Lord hath said it." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/86/11#11">D&amp;C 86:11</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Leadership to give direction</b>
</p><p>
We are living in a troubled world, as has been pointed out several times this day; and the world
has reason to and every right to expect some leadership somewhere to give direction and
understanding of where to go and what to do. People need to understand that there is a purpose
in life and what that purpose is, and they have every reason to look to the priesthood of God,
which is what you brethren have.
</p><p>
You cannot realize and appreciate the influence the priesthood in this Church could have on the
whole world if every man would magnify his priesthood. Brethren, the priesthood, if magnified,
is a stabilizing influence and strength. It should be. Every wife and mother has a perfect right
and responsibility to look to her husband who holds the priesthood for guidance, for strength,
and for direction. And he has the responsibility of magnifying his priesthood so he might be able
to give this direction, this security, this strength that is needed in the home. And he can do this.
If he will magnify his priesthood, he will be magnified by the Lord in the eyes of his family, and
his influence will be felt for good.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility to sisters</b>
</p><p>
We have a responsibility to our sisters, boys. Every sister should look to a brother who holds the
priesthood, whether he is 12 years of age or older, and she has a right to expect in him a living
example of what the priesthood should be, and to look to him for strength and counsel and
direction and to feel safe with him. Every sweetheart should be able to depend entirely on a
young man holding the priesthood who is going out with her. She should be able to feel he
would do anything, even to the giving of his life, to protect her womanhood and her virtue, and
would never think of depriving her of it, if he is magnifying his priesthood; and he will not be
tempted if he is thinking of the priesthood that he holds and the responsibility that he has.
</p><p>
<b>Strength to act</b>
</p><p>
I should like to read to you just a paragraph from a letter that I received yesterday to show the
importance of living the principles of the gospel and magnifying our priesthood. So many of our
men <i>believe</i>, but haven't the courage or the strength to <i>act</i>. If we could all realize the effect we
have on our associates when we live the gospel teachings, I am sure we would all do better. This
letter comes from a successful lawyer in Los Angeles whom I know fairly well, and he wrote just
to give me this message: 
</p><p>
"As weeks tumble into months and I become engrossed in the fascinating practice of law,
occasionally there comes across the spectrum of this activity a person who is noticeably
exceptional. I have just completed a case in which my adversary was a young man who
exemplified the finest qualities of technical craftsmanship wedded to moral and spiritual
integrity. It didn't come as any great surprise to me when I inadvertently discovered that he is a
dedicated member of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints."
</p><p>
Now this man who writes the letter is not a member of the Church, and the man about whom he
writes is his adversary in court. I know the young man very well. The writer of the letter doesn't
know that I know him, but it shows me, my brethren, that if we magnify our priesthood, if we
live as we should, we will influence the world, and the Lord will magnify us. This is my
testimony to you, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
