<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Future Before Us</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 83-86</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
There are always overwhelming feelings on these occasions.  Two of those that rise to the top
at this time are inadequacy and gratitude for fellowship with you and for any part in the
Church.
</p><p>
I recall reading a statement that President McKay is reported to have made, as he alighted at
the airport of one of the large South American cities on his recent tour: that "there are three
beautiful things in the world&mdash;love and friendship and brotherhood."  They are
all in evidence here and help to feed and sustain us and to send us away
encouraged and enriched.
</p><p>
I am mindful of the glorious principles that have been enunciated here, which, with others,
make this a most satisfying gospel to feed the human soul. Some of these are: faith,
repentance, the assurance of forgiveness with proper repentance; the eternal continuance of
personality, of individual identity; the assurance that we may have everlasting association with
those we love; testimony; the knowledge that no man stands between us and our God; the
assurance of eternal plan and purpose; continuous revelation; free agency; and the fact that
this is an inclusive message and opportunity and gospel and Church, and not an exclusive
one&mdash;that its blessings are to all men who are willing to partake of them, and are not reserved to
a special few predestined by our Father in heaven to have the blessings and benefits.  It is his
purpose to save all his children and to exalt all his children, not merely to warn and turn them
away, but to labor with them in love and in patience, and to bring them back into his
presence, if they will.
</p><p>
A great man has been in our midst here for a few days, one of the notable men of medicine,
Sir Alexander Fleming, whom we have had the pleasure in this community of meeting and
bearing on one or two occasions. He told the story of how, in working in a laboratory in a
London hospital back in 1928, he observed the action of an accidental mold that had drifted
into his laboratory from some source and which had an arresting effect on some germ
colonies that were in the culture in one of his petri dishes.  His statement, as he recorded it in
his diary, was this: "I was sufficiently interested to pursue the subject.  The appearance of the
culture plant was such that I thought it should not be neglected." Thus, penicillin was
discovered and put to immeasurable human benefit.
</p><p>
"I was sufficiently interested to pursue the subject." Well, with a mold so common, so
accessible, one wonders why someone did not see it sooner, why someone did not "pursue the
subject" sooner.  That the world should go so long without such a discovery from such a
common and available source would seem to be but a further indication that there is ever
before us an infinity of undiscovered things and that opportunities are limitless, and that
"revelation" of this kind is continuous, as is direct revelation from our Father in heaven.
</p><p>
The songs of birds that are all around us, we often do not hear.  Two enterprising scientists
not long ago made some "visual recordings" of bird songs with an audio-spectrograph, so that
the human eye could "see" the music that the birds were making, but the human ear could not
hear it as it reached above the range of "normal" human hearing.
</p><p>
Who knows what unseen and unheard things may be all around us?  There are limitless
possibilities; there is infinity before us, and revelation must be continuous. Sometimes we
wonder why others cannot see some of the things that we see.  Sometimes we wonder why
we cannot see some of the things that they see.  There may be many reasons for this.  We
differ in our experience; we differ in our perception; we differ in our preoccupation.  Some of
us have our thoughts fixed on one thing at one time, and some on another.  But there are
great things to be discovered if we will have ears to hear and eyes to see and be sufficiently
interested "to pursue the subject" as was this great man of medicine.
</p><p>
There may be things that some of us do not seas Peter and Paul, seemingly did not always see
the same things (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/2/11-21#11">Gal. 2:11-21</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/3/15-16#15">2 Pet. 3:15-16</a>)&mdash;but
they both loved the gospel; they both lived for it, and both were willing
to die for it.  There are some great fundamentals and requirements and commandments on
which there can be no doubt and no differences, of which the Lord has spoken definitely. 
Beyond this, some, such as Sir Alexander Fleming, see some things that
some of us do not see.
</p><p>
As to free agency: mercifully and wonderfully that was settled in the heavens a long time ago
when Lucifer challenged it.  It is one of the great and glorious principles of the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I recall a comment reported to have been made by President Clark to a graduating class last
spring, in which he said, in substance, that Lucifer must have thought that God was very
"old-fashioned." Lucifer was proposing some very different ways of doing some things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1#1">Moses 4:1</a>). It
seems that he would have done some things in a much more "efficient" manner, if you will
put "efficiency" in quotations.  He would have delivered all our Father's children back to
him&mdash;but in a strait jacket!
</p><p>
The only kind of "efficiency" that the Lord God is interested in for us is that kind of
efficiency which contributes to and promotes the development and growth of his children in
helping them choose for themselves the great things and the right things, the right way of
life&mdash;for the eternal salvation and exaltation of their souls.  And I would say today, keep faith in
freedom.  Avoid the principle of compulsion.
</p><p>
And now for a moment or two, may I yield to the temptation to speak another thought or two
to these young people who are here from Brigham Young University, to these others who are
here in this congregation, and beyond here, to all who will hear or read, and to all those of
this generation, whom they represent, following along the lines of the moving and impressive
instructions of Brother Lee and Brother Petersen this morning: 
</p><p>
It is apparent that man has acquired the power to destroy the works of man.  The instruments
of destruction are ever more fearful with each passing day.  But man has not acquired the
power to destroy the works or the plans or the purposes of God.  All of us at times have our
fears.  All men have their fears, their uncertainties.  But may I say to you: Go ahead and live
your lives.  You are not alone in life. The Lord God is there and ever accessible to you.
</p><p>
This is no time for panic. Our Father made us in his image.  He sent us here. He looked out
at what he had made during the creation, and he saw that it was very good.  It was good, and
it is still good.  He intends happiness for us, and it is not only our privilege but also our duty
to be happy, and we shall be if we have the courage to live as we ought to live and to be
what we ought to be.
</p><p>
Be honest, clean, chaste, humble. Keep your lives well-balanced.  Always reserve some of
your time and means to the things of the spirit and to the service of your Father in heaven as
well as to the things of the mind and the things of physical sustenance.  Work, study, and
pray.  Keep an open mind to truth; keep the faith; live so as to have a quiet conscience.  The
rewarding way of life is to keep the commandments.  The hard way of life is to live contrary
to conscience and contrary to the commandments.
</p><p>
We are in this world, and I do not know anything to do about it except to make the most of
it, to live good and useful and purposeful lives, and to find joy in the opportunity that the
Lord God has given us until the time comes to leave this life, which will be swiftly and soon
enough.  There is no running away from life, no running away from ourselves.  We can run
away from where we are, but not from what we are or from who we are; and all we have to
do is to live a day at a time to the best of our ability.  The weight of the future is not on us
except as it comes moment by moment.
</p><p>
In the words of Thomas Carlyle, "The crash of the whole solar and stellar systems could only
kill you once."  There is no point in living in fear, in panic, or in apprehension.  Endure to the
end, keep faithful, for he who made us and gave us life and who keeps creation in its course
will not forsake us.  And though we have acquired the instruments for destroying the works
of man, if we should be so foolish as to set them loose, yet the power and
the purposes of God as concerning us and all his creations are constant and ever surround us
with their protection and their peace, if we will be partakers of these things.
</p><p>
God lives.  He has eternal plans and purposes for his children.  Jesus is the Christ.  The
gospel has been restored, and despite all the answers we do not know and all the areas where
there may be differences of opinion, we know all we need to know for our everlasting
salvation and exaltation and happiness&mdash;if we will use what the Lord God has given us. 
Truth will triumph; justice will be done; and there will be no good thing lost in the life of
him who will live as best he knows how to live and will partake of these things which our
Father has prepared for us.
</p><p>
May I close with the testimony of a beloved friend, who is not with us, Dr. John A. Widtsoe. 
In one of the closing sentences of his book, <i>In a Sunlit Land</i>, in which he looked back on his life as a
scientist, as a convert, as an educator, as an Apostle, and as a great and humble servant of
men and of God, as a man who had seen much of life from many sides and who had come
forth from it all with a sweet and simple faith&mdash;on the last pages of this book he wrote these
words which he left for the record of posterity: 
</p><p>
During this long life, I have had occasion to test, time and time again, the verity of the
foundations of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.  The answer has always been
the same: Joseph Smith told the truth (<i>In a Sunlit Land</i>, pp. 243-244).
</p><p>
I leave this with you as a witness of my soul this day, to you a choice and blessed generation
of youth.  God bless you and be with you; go forth and live your lives; rely on him; keep
sweet and humble, and his blessings and guidance will be with you.  May he bless you in all
your decisions, I pray, in Jesus' name.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
