<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Give Concern to the Real Values of Life and Less Time to Those Things That Perish</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">(Read by his son, David Lawrence McKay)</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1968, pp. 144-146</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
With all my heart I rejoice with you, my brethren and sisters, for the blessings of the Lord during the inspirational sessions of the past few days. His Spirit has been with us in rich abundance!
</p><p>
During these closing moments of this great conference, I pray that the Lord will guide and direct me in giving you the thoughts that are in my heart.
</p><p><b>
Instructions of conference
</b></p><p>
I am grateful and thankful for the admonitions and specific instructions that have been given by the General Authorities of the Church. As you can testify, they have been guided and inspired by the Holy Spirit in their messages.
</p><p>
With all my soul, I plead with members of the Church, and with people everywhere, to think more about the gospel; more about the developing of the spirit within; to devote more time to the real things in life, and less time to those things which will perish.
</p><p>
I am in hearty accord with the admonitions given during this conference to resist the various temptations in our midst. If members of the Church would adopt these suggestions, that alone would be sufficient to make this people a light upon a hill, a light that could not be hidden (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/14-16#14">Matt. 5:14-16</a>). We refer to such teachings sometimes as "little things," but indeed they are the greatest things in this life. If we were to pay more attention to such advice, and devote more study to the modern revelations as contained in the Doctrine and Covenants, we would grow in appreciation of the magnitude of the great work that has been established in this dispensation.
</p><p>
It is often said that the Church is the greatest thing in the world, and it is! The more attention we give to
it&mdash;realizing how well adapted it is to our individual life, to our home life, and to our social life&mdash;the more we study it from the standpoint of scientific discoveries, from the standpoint of man's destiny, the more our hearts are made to rejoice for God's goodness to us in giving us the privilege of knowing the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p><b>
Faith in Christ
</b></p><p>
What we need today is faith in the living Christ, which is more than a mere feeling, but a power that moves us to action&mdash;a faith that will put purpose into life and courage into the heart. We need the gospel of
application&mdash;a gospel that is preached by noble acts that command the attention and respect even of enemies. A mere belief in Jesus as a great teacher, or even as the greatest man who ever lived, has proved inadequate in combating the ills of society and the world.
</p><p>
Manifestly, the need of the world&mdash;and particularly in the light of present conditions that surround us on every side&mdash;is more than a mere acceptance of the Man of Galilee as the greatest of all men. What is really essential is faith in him as a divine being&mdash;as our Lord and Savior! It is such faith as the apostle Peter experienced when he declared: "Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16#16">Matt. 16:16</a>)
</p><p><b>
Acquire truth and virtue
</b></p><p>
Members of the Church are admonished to acquire truth by study, by faith and prayer, and to seek after everything that is "virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>)
</p><p>
Schools and churches should radiate the fact that there are in life certain fundamentals that never change, which are essential to the happiness of every human soul. Parents and officers in the Church must teach more earnestly and diligently the principles of life and salvation to the youth of Zion and to the world in order to help youth keep in proper balance through the formative period of their lives.
</p><p><b>
Government by priesthood
</b></p><p>
I remind you men who bear the Holy Priesthood to study again that divine revelation, so simply but powerfully expressed, with regard to government by the priesthood: 
</p><p>
"No power or influence can or ought to be maintained by virtue of the priesthood, only by persuasion, by long-suffering, by gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned; 
</p><p>
"By kindness, and pure knowledge, which shall greatly enlarge the soul without hypocrisy, and without guile&mdash;
</p><p>
"Reproving betimes with sharpness, when moved upon by the Holy Ghost; and then showing forth afterwards an increase of love toward him whom thou hast reproved, lest he esteem thee to be his enemy." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41-43#41">D&amp;C 121:41-43</a>)
</p><p>
This is a wonderful admonition and lesson in regard to government, not only in quorums of the priesthood, but also in our home life, and indeed in all phases of association in society.
</p><p><b>
Gospel our anchor
</b></p><p>
Brethren and sisters, the gospel is our anchor. We know what it stands for. If we live it and feel it, if we speak well of it, of the priesthood, of our families, of our neighbors, we shall feel happier, and in reality we shall be preaching the gospel of Jesus Christ. The responsibility has been given to us to convey the gospel to our fellowmen. Some of us wait until some special opportunity is given to us to proclaim the gospel of Jesus Christ, and yet the duty devolves upon each of us to proclaim that good news every day of our lives. We proclaim it in our acts&mdash;in the home, in business, in social circles, in politics; indeed, everywhere that we mingle with men we have the responsibility resting upon us to give the good news to the people of the world.
</p><p>
Let us guard our thoughts and our tongues. One of the best ways of building up our home, be it a domicile, a city, a state, or a nation, is always to speak well of that home, city, state, or nation. Let the tongue be under control at all times.
</p><p>
God bless the members of this Church for their devotion and loyalty, and for their sustaining prayers in behalf of all the General Authorities and officers. You may know, and I wish to assure you, that these prayers are effective.
</p><p><b>
Divine protection real
</b></p><p>
I testify to you, and to all the world, that the inspiration and protecting care of a kind Father in heaven are real! He is close to the Church, and I know with my whole soul that he is not just an absent, far-away source, as some may think. He is a kind Father, solicitous of the welfare of his children, and ready and willing to hear and answer their call. The answer may be negative, as sometimes a wise parent gives a negative answer to the pleadings of a child, but he is ever ready to hear and to answer at a time when it is best for the one concerned.
</p><p><b>
Gratitude for missionaries
</b></p><p>
God bless our missionaries who are in the 78 worldwide missions of the Church. They are splendid young men and women, with strong testimonies of the gospel, who are rich in faith and who are excellent representatives of the Lord and his Church. We are proud of them. We are grateful to our mission presidents and to these missionaries for their willing and able service. We are grateful also for the fathers and mothers and others who support these missionaries.
</p><p><b>
Loyalty of servicemen
</b></p><p>
Words cannot express the heartache and the sorrow that we feel for the sufferings that have come to some homes because of the casualties of war. Our prayers are ever with our young men who are offering their all for human freedom and other inherent rights of man. My heart is filled with thankfulness and gratitude as I listen to reports that have been brought directly to me of their faith in God, of their loyalty, and of the long distances they travel to attend Church meetings. Think what an assurance in Christ, their Redeemer, means to them while they are enduring the temptations, hardships, and horrors of war! It gives them comfort in the hour of homesickness or discouragement; it makes more effective their determination to keep morally clean and fit for service; it gives them courage in the performance of duty; it awakens hope when they are ill or wounded; and if and when they might face the inevitable, it fills their souls with the peaceful confidence that as Christ lived after death so shall they! May God bless and protect these men in the armed forces.
</p><p><b>
Blessing for officers and members
</b></p><p>
God bless you Regional Representatives, stake presidents, bishops, and all officers in the Church who are serving and giving of your time and means for the upbuilding of God's kingdom.
</p><p>
May you fathers and mothers be blessed in your homes; may you seek for wisdom and understanding to give to your children health and character, spotless and unstained. The greatest duty that fathers and mothers have to perform is the religious training and development of their child's character.
</p><p>
May God be with each of you and all people everywhere. May we turn to him and seek for the better and more spiritual values of life. He is our Father; he knows our desires and our hopes; and he will help us if we will but seek him and learn of his ways.
</p><p>
My prayerful blessings go with you as you return to your homes. God help us all to discharge our responsibilities by making an environment in home, in school, in Church, and in our communities that will be uplifting, wholesome, and faith-inspiring, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
