<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Importance of Fast Offerings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder George Q. Morris</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Q. Morris, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 100-102</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I sincerely pray that the Lord will direct me to say that which I
should say to you this morning. He has blessed us through this great conference from the
inspired and powerful address of President McKay through all the sessions. I sincerely pray
that his blessings may be with me, that that Spirit shall be continued.
</p><p>
This is fast day in the Church, the regular monthly fast day, and I should like to dwell with
you for a few moments upon its importance and our relation to it.
</p><p>
In the early days of the Church, there were urgent needs to be met, and so the Prophet Joseph
Smith, who had a plea made him from Kirtland for help for the poor and the needy, told the
Saints to establish a fast day. Each month it was to be observed, and they were to fast for the
day and bring to the one in charge the food that they would have consumed so that it might
be dispensed to the poor.
</p><p>
What a beautiful, simple, direct, and inspired provision the Lord made through the Prophet
Joseph Smith! People were to endure hunger and not partake of food they had but bring that
food that others might not endure hunger.
</p><p>
The Lord revealed to Isaiah the true observance of the fast day; after rejecting the methods
used by Israel at that time, he then points out the right way that the day should be observed.
</p><p>
Is not this the fast that I have chosen? to loose the bands of wickedness, to undo the heavy
burdens, and to let the oppressed go free, and that ye break every yoke?<br />
Is it not to deal thy bread to the hungry, and that you bring the poor that are cast out to thy
house? when thou seest the naked, that thou cover him; and that thou hide not thyself from
thine own flesh?<br />
Then shall the light break forth as the morning, and thine health shall spring forth speedily:
and thy righteousness shall go before thee; the glory of the Lord shall be thy reward.<br />
And if thou draw out thy soul to the hungry, and satisfy the afflicted soul; then shall thy light
rise in obscurity, and thy darkness be as the noon day:<br />
And the Lord shall guide thee continually, and satisfy thy soul in drought, and make fat thy
bones: and thou shalt be like a watered garden, and like a spring of water, whose waters fail
not (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/58/6-8,10-11#6">Isa. 58:6-8,10-11</a>).
</p><p>
What a beautiful description of a day that we should follow once a month for the alleviation
of suffering, for our own spiritual growth and development, and to carry out the purposes of
the Lord that there shall be no want, no suffering, but every attention given to those who are
afflicted and in distress.
</p><p>
I was told the other day (I did not learn any more of the details) that a bishop invited some of
the members of his ward to a banquet, and as one man had his plate presented to him there
was on it a small piece of meat and a small piece of carrot. I do  not know what the man's
impressions were or what questions arose in his mind, but it was
explained to him that that represented the fast offering that he had been giving to the needy.
[Laughter.] Now that was surely a very realistic way of pointing out his relation to the fast
offering and his obligations. And it reminded me of a sobering statement that the Prophet
Joseph Smith made at the funeral of James Adams in 1843, and refers back to the powerful
statement and announcement made by President McKay, that it is by doing the will of God
that we will attain salvation and accomplish his purpose, and in no other way.
</p><p>
Incidentally, as we build up false hopes on something else, there will be a time of terrible
awakening. So the Prophet Joseph Smith declared:
</p><p>
If men will acquire salvation they have got to be subject before they leave this
world to certain rules and principles which were fixed by an unalterable decree
before the world was.
</p><p>
The disappointment of hopes and of expectations at the resurrection will be
indescribably dreadful (<i>DHC</i>, 6:50-51).
</p><p>
It is for us to avoid that dreadful experience that he refers to and keep the commandments of
God and bring to pass the purposes of the Lord. It is not only that we do not obey the Lord
as far as we personally are concerned, but it is a serious sin as well that we frustrate the
purposes of God, at least for the moment; and a condition that he wishes to bring to pass
among his people for the alleviation of suffering, for the comforting of the afflicted, and for
the strengthening of his Church, fails because we do not keep his commandments. That is a
most serious thing. It seems to me that we must take it into account. The first is, in a way,
personal, but the second is rejecting God and blocking his plans and his purposes, by which
he means to bless his people.
</p><p>
I think we may not and must not be casual or indifferent regarding this fast day which is so
common among us. I am sure we are not giving it the thought that it deserves. Many people
seem indifferent. But what a wonderful thing it would be if the stake presidencies and
bishoprics of wards and presidents of branches, through the help of the Lord, could instruct
the people and inspire them all so that they would give in full to the Lord their free-will fast
offering. What a strength and power it would be towards the bringing to pass of the purposes
of God among his people and in the earth.
</p><p>
And the way to do that is simple, if the people would understand and accept this principle and
obey it. I believe it hinges on the one fact, so far as I am concerned, that it is just as
necessary to pay an honest fast offering as it is to pay an honest tithing.
</p><p>
The Lord has told us how we shall pay our tithing and we are able to pay it properly and we
call it a full tithing. The Lord has told us what the fast offering shall be, that it shall be the
equivalent of the food of which we did not partake.
</p><p>
Great strength and power would come to us, so far as having means in the Church (and the
Lord says he wishes to "have meat in his house") to accomplish his purposes. Yesterday we
were advised that we are approaching a million and a half people. Let us consider a million
people and realize that if we paid a full and honest fast offering, joyfully and gladly before
the Lord, there would come into the hands of the servants of God each year, paid by a million
people, the value of twenty-four million meals. What a strength that would be to the great
welfare movement, what a spiritual blessing would come to all of the Church, for God
promises great blessings, and what means would be in hand to bring about the alleviation of
the suffering and the needs of the people!
</p><p>
This thing goes right to the heart of the gospel. The Lord found it necessary to charge ancient
Israel with robbery, that they had robbed him in their tithes and their offerings, and they were
under a curse, but he said,
</p><p>
. . . prove me now herewith, saith the Lord of hosts, if I will not open you the
windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing, that there shall not be room
enough to receive it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/10#10">Mal. 3:10</a>).
</p><p>
I wish to read some of his words, just a few short selections, to emphasize the need of
obeying the law of the fast and giving offerings for the poor and afflicted. They affect our
salvation; they affect the forgiveness of our sins; they affect our souls
being saved. We will not be saved, our prayers will not be answered, and the Lord will reject
us as his disciples if we do not remember the poor and the afflicted.
</p><p>
These are his words directly through his prophets:
</p><p>
Therefore, if any man shall take of the abundance which I have made, and impart
not his portion, according to the law of my gospel, unto the poor and the needy,
he shall, with the wicked, lift up his eyes in hell, being in torment
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/18#18">D&amp;C 104:18</a>).
</p><p>
And now, for the sake of these things which I have spoken unto you&mdash;that is, for
the sake of retaining a remission of your sins from day to day, that ye may walk
guiltless before God&mdash;I would that ye should impart of your substance to the poor,
every man according to that which he hath, such as feeding the hungry, clothing
the naked, visiting the sick and administering to their relief, both spiritually and
temporally, according to their wants
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/26#26">Mosiah 4:26</a>).
</p><p>
Yea, and when you do not cry unto the Lord, let your hearts be full, drawn out
in prayer unto him continually for your welfare, and also for the welfare of those
who are around you.<br />
And now behold, my beloved brethren, I say unto you, do not suppose that this
is all; for after ye have done all these things, if ye turn away the needy, and the
naked, and visit not the sick and afflicted, and impart of your substance, if ye
have, to those who stand in need&mdash;I say unto you, if ye do not any of these things,
behold, your prayer is vain, and availeth you nothing, and ye are as hypocrites
who do deny the faith (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/27-28#27">Alma 34:27-28</a>).
</p><p>
We unto you rich men, that will not give your substance to the poor, for your
riches will canker your souls; and this shall be your lamentation in the day of
visitation, and of judgment, and of indignation: The harvest is past, the summer
is ended, and my soul is not saved! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/16#16">D&amp;C 56:16</a>).
</p><p>
<i>And remember in all things the poor and the needy, the sick and the afflicted, for</i>
<i>he that doeth not these things, the same is not my disciple</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/52/40#40">D&amp;C 52:40</a>).
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to discharge this great obligation in gladness and in joy, with all our
hearts, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
