<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Revelation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 122-126</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I would like to say a few things this afternoon about revelation, which underlies all that God
has done in the earth with his children. I invite you to join your prayers with mine that while
I speak, you and I may both enjoy the spirit of inspiration. That we do so is imperative,
because to talk about revelation without the spirit of inspiration would be futile.
</p><p>
<b>God Communicates with Men</b>
</p><p>
First, as to the Principle:
</p><p>
Prayer is the means by which men communicate with God. Revelation is the means by which
God communicates with men. Revelation is indispensable to an understanding of the gospel of
Jesus Christ. The very nature of the gospel is such that without the active and constant
operation of the principle of revelation, it could not be understood nor could it be had.
</p><p>
The gospel deals with total truth&mdash;". . . knowledge of things as they are, as they were, and as
they are to come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/24#24">D&amp;C 93:24</a>).
Such truth is not to be had through man's ordinary learning
processes. His sensory powers are calculated and adapted to deal only with
the things of this earth. Without revelation, man's intellect is wholly inadequate for the
discovery of the ultimate truth with which the gospel deals.
</p><p>
Paul spoke of this to the Corinthians when he said:
</p><p>
". . . my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in
demonstration of the Spirit and of power:
</p><p>
". . . your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God.
</p><p>
"For what man [continues Paul] knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is
in him? even so the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/4-5,11#4">1 Cor. 2:4-5,11</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Opens the Mind and the Spirit</b>
</p><p>
The principle of revelation is the key which opens the mind and spirit of man to an
understanding of the gospel. There is no other key to such knowledge. Thinkers have
philosophized; poets have dreamed; and scientists have experimented; but only God speaks
with a sure knowledge of all truth.
</p><p>
Some years ago I listened to a lecturer who argued long and deviously and came to the
conclusion that there was no such thing as religious knowledge. Within his premises, he was
right. He had no religious knowledge, and he could not obtain any because he had ruled out
revelation.
</p><p>
It is my witness to you, however, that by the power of God, truth concerning the eternal
verities with which the gospel deals has been in the past, is now being, and will in the future
continue to be communicated to men from heaven by revelation. "Revelation" is the
"governing law of conduct"&mdash;the age-old established rule of action or principle by which God
communes with men.
</p><p>
<b>Man Must be Born Again</b>
</p><p>
Now a word as to the Nature of Revelation:
</p><p>
Since revelation is by nature spiritual man, to receive it, must be spiritually born again. You
will recall how earnestly Jesus sought to put this point over to Nicodemus, repeatedly telling
him that except a man be born again, he could neither see nor enter the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/3-5#3">John 3:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
Man is a dual being. He is composed of a spirit and a body. His body came into being with
his entrance into this world of mortality. His spirit as an individual person was begotten unto
God in the spirit world. Through a long period of growth and development, each person's
spirit came to know God and spiritual things, including the gospel, obedience to which is a
prerequisite to attaining eternal life. Men, however, enter mortality spiritually blind. Never in
this life do they recover memory of pre-mortal spiritual things. What they here learn of them
must be revealed anew.
</p><p>
<b>"To see if they will do . . ."</b>
</p><p>
One of God's purposes in granting men mortal life is that they might be tested ". . . to see if
they will do all things whatsoever the Lord their God shall command them . . . they who
keep their second estate [meaning this mortal estate] shall have glory added upon their heads
for ever and ever" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/25-26#25">Abr. 3:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
Since attaining this glory is conditioned upon obedience to the laws and ordinances of the
gospel, and since men come into life ignorant of these principles and ordinances, justice
demands that they be given opportunity to learn about them. God, being not only just but
merciful, provided revelation as the means by which man might be so advised.
</p><p>
<b>Moral Agency</b>
</p><p>
The Lord also saw to it that men were so constituted that by the proper exercise of their
moral agency with which he also endowed them, it would be natural for them to respond to
revelation. Otherwise, it would not be just to hold them accountable for their failure to
respond thereto.
</p><p>
I know the scriptures say that "the natural man is an enemy to God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/19#19">Mosiah 3:19</a>). And
so he is when he rejects the promptings of the Spirit and follows the lusts of the flesh. But he
is not an enemy to God when he follows the promptings of the Spirit.
</p><p>
I firmly believe that notwithstanding the fact that men, as an incident to mortality, are cast out
from the presence of God and deprived of past memories, there still persists in the spirit of
every human soul a residuum from his preexistent spiritual life which instinctively responds to
the voice of the Spirit of Christ until and unless inhibited by the free agency of the individual.
If I had time, I could cite many authorities on this point.
</p><p>
<b>Manifestations of Revelation</b>
</p><p>
Now, as to the Manifestations of Revelation:
</p><p>
Revelation comes to men in an unlimited number of ways. Three separate mediums are
mentioned in the first recorded account of revelation&mdash;the spoken word, the visitation of
angels, and the power of the Holy Ghost. As a consequence of his transgression Adam was
cast out from God's presence. But he was not forsaken. As he and Eve toiled and prayed, ". .
. they heard the voice of the Lord from the way toward the Garden of Eden"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/4#4">Moses 5:4</a>).
</p><p>
"And after many days an angel of the Lord appeared unto Adam"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/6#6">Moses 5:6</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Holy Ghost</b>
</p><p>
"And in that day the Holy Ghost fell upon Adam, which beareth record of the Father and the
Son" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/9#9">Moses 5:9</a>).
</p><p>
The spoken word has been heard on many occasions. Moses heard it from the burning bush;
Samuel in the temple. The Nephites heard the voice of the unseen Jesus.
</p><p>
<b>Visitations of Angels</b>
</p><p>
As to the visitation of angels, we have many examples. One which moves me as much as any
is the record in the third chapter of Ether of the appearance of Jesus in his spirit body to the
brother of Jared.
</p><p>
You will remember how, as Alma was traveling from Ammonihah to Aaron, an angel
appeared to him and said, referring to the time of Alma's conversion, "I am the same angel
that appeared to you before" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/8/15#15">Alma 8:15</a>).
</p><p>
We read in the 110th section of the Doctrine and Covenants about the visitation to the
Prophet and Oliver of Moses, Elias, and Elijah
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/11-16#11">D&amp;C 110:11-16</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Unspoken Word</b>
</p><p>
Another manifestation of revelation is the unspoken word, a good illustration of which is
given us by Enos. He says: ". . . while I was thus struggling in the spirit, behold, the voice of
the Lord came into my mind again, saying"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/enos/1/10#10">Enos 1:10</a>).
Then he tells us what the voice of
the Lord put in his mind. This is a very common means of revelation. It comes into one's
mind in words and sentences. With this medium of revelation I am personally well
acquainted.
</p><p>
<b>Impelling Impulse</b>
</p><p>
Another medium is an impelling impulse of the nature received by the Prophet when he read
James 1:5 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>).
"Never [said he] did any passage of scripture come with more power to the heart
of man than this did at this time to mine. It seemed to enter with great force into every
feeling of my heart" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/12#12">JS&mdash;H 1:12</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Dreams</b>
</p><p>
Another means is dreams&mdash;Jacob's ladder, for example, Joseph's dream of the sheaves,
Pharaoh's dream of the lean and fat years. There were Nebuchadnezzar's dream, Daniel's
dream, Lehi's dream. Joseph, the husband of Mary, was warned in a dream to take Mary and
Jesus into Egypt.
</p><p>
<b>Visions</b>
</p><p>
Another medium of revelation is visions. You know about Nephi's vision, the Prophet's great
vision recorded in the 76th section of the Doctrine and Covenants, and President Joseph F.
Smith's vision of work for the dead in the spirit world.
</p><p>
<b>Flashes of Ideas</b>
</p><p>
Flashes of ideas that come into one's mind represent another type or manifestation of
revelation. Listen to this statement of the Prophet Joseph:
</p><p>
"A person may profit by noticing the first intimation of the spirit of revelation; for instance,
when you feel pure intelligence flowing into you, it may give you sudden strokes of ideas, so
that by noticing it, you may find it fulfilled the same day or soon; (i.e.) those things that were
presented unto your minds by the Spirit of God, will come to pass; and thus by learning the
Spirit of God and understanding it, you may grow into the principle of revelation, until you
become perfect in Christ Jesus." (<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 151.)
</p><p>
<b>"Study it out"</b>
</p><p>
One of the most familiar types of revelation is the one which the Lord took so much pains to
teach to Oliver Cowdery. The lesson begins in the 6th and 8th sections of the Doctrine and
Covenants and concludes it in the 9th section. Oliver wanted to translate, and the Lord finally
gave his consent. But Oliver didn't translate because he didn't work hard enough. When he
complained about it, the Lord said:
</p><p>
"Do not murmur, my son, for it is wisdom in me that I have dealt with you after this manner.
</p><p>
"Behold, you have not understood; you have supposed that I would give it unto you, when
you took no thought save it was to ask me.
</p><p>
<b>"Ask if it be right . . ."</b>
</p><p>
"But, behold, I say unto you, that you must study it out in your mind; then you must ask me
if it be right, and if it is right I will cause that your bosom shall burn within you; therefore,
you shall feel that it is right.
</p><p>
"But if it be not right you shall have no such feelings, but you shall have a stupor of thought"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/9/6-9#6">D&amp;C 9:6-9</a>).
</p><p>
This is the kind of revelation we can all live by. One need not make serious mistakes in life.
Such can be avoided by following this formula. It will guide us in all our activities if we will
become sensitive to it.
</p><p>
The foregoing are but some of the means of revelation.
</p><p>
In connection with this principle of revelation, the Prophet Joseph Smith further said:
</p><p>
"We consider that God has created man with a mind capable of instruction, and a faculty
which may be enlarged in proportion to the heed and diligence given to the light
communicated from heaven to the intellect . . . the nearer man approaches perfection, the
clearer are his views, and the greater his enjoyments, till he has overcome the evils of his life
and lost every desire for sin; and like the ancients, arrives at that point of faith where he is
wrapped in the power and glory of his maker, and is caught up to dwell with Him"
(<i>DHC</i> 2:8.)
</p><p>
<b>The Great Exemplar</b>
</p><p>
In qualifying to receive revelation, as in all righteousness, Jesus is our great exemplar. He so
qualified himself that he received through revelation "a fullness of the glory of the Father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/16#16">D&amp;C 93:16</a>).
</p><p>
With respect to this point, John the Beloved bore this witness:
</p><p>
". . . I beheld his glory, as the glory of the Only Begotten of the Father . . .
</p><p>
"And I, John, saw that he received not of the fullness at the first . . .
</p><p>
". . . but continued from grace to grace, until he received a fullness . . .
</p><p>
"And I, John, bear record that he received a fullness of the glory of the Father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/11-13,16#11">D&amp;C 93:11-13,16</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Keep Commandments</b>
</p><p>
To me, among the most inspiring passages of all scripture is the comment of Jesus on this
testimony of John's, which, as you will remember, was dictated to the Prophet by the Savior.
After quoting John's testimony, Jesus said to the Prophet Joseph Smith:
</p><p>
"I give unto you these sayings that you may understand and know how to worship, and know
what you worship, that you may come unto the Father in my name, and in due time receive
of his fullness.
</p><p>
"For if you keep my commandments you shall receive of his fullness, and be glorified in me
as I am in the Father; therefore, I say unto you, you shall receive grace for grace"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/19-20#19">D&amp;C 93:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
Now this is Christ's promise to the Prophet, and it is his promise to us.
</p><p>
". . . no man receiveth a fullness unless he keepeth his commandments.
</p><p>
"He that keepeth his commandments receiveth truth and light, until he is glorified in truth and
knoweth all things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/27-28#27">D&amp;C 93:27-28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Receive Light and Truth</b>
</p><p>
We receive a little revelation; we obey it; we receive a little more, obey it, and repeat the
cycle over and over again.
</p><p>
This is the pattern by which the promise of the first paragraph of this great revelation may be
obtained. As you now listen to this promise, let your souls be filled with hope.
</p><p>
"Verily, thus saith the Lord: It shall come to pass that every soul who forsaketh his sins and
cometh unto me, and calleth on my name, and obeyeth my voice, and keepeth my
commandments, shall see my face and know that I am"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/1#1">D&amp;C 93:1</a>).
</p><p>
In these remarks I have, as you of course have noted, omitted any reference to revelation in
connection with the great advances of science in our age. This I have done deliberately. I
know that all men live and learn by the light of the Spirit of Christ; I know that all progress
in science and other fields of secular learning is made possible by the light of Christ. I do not,
however, think that our distinctive message about revelation lies in such fields of learning but
rather in the field of religion.
</p><p>
<b>"God Has Opened the Heavens"</b>
</p><p>
Our message is that we are living in the great and last dispensation of the gospel of Jesus
Christ; that God has opened the heavens anew; that by direct revelation through the means we
have been considering, he has revealed himself, restored his gospel, set up his Church with
power and authority to preach the gospel and administer the saving ordinances thereof; and
that he is now, today, continuing to direct by revelation his great program for the blessing and
the salvation of the human race.
</p><p>
Our great mission is to declare this message with such simple clarity and inspired conviction
that men of all lands will hearken, investigate, and prayerfully seek until, through personal
revelation to themselves, they obtain a saving witness for themselves. That we may
successfully discharge this mission, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
