<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Will of God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 136-138</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
And now, my brethren and sisters, we have come to the closing session of another great
conference of the Church. My soul, with yours, has been filled with thanksgiving and
gratitude to our Heavenly Father for the outpouring of his Holy Spirit throughout the entire
conference. We have heard inspirational and uplifting messages from the leaders of the
Church. I love these associates of the general authorities, and love them in the spirit of the
true meaning of that word&mdash;the love of the brotherhood of Christ. God bless them!
</p><p>
<b>Testimonies of the conference reviewed</b>
</p><p>
During these various sessions of conference, we have had testimony of the Spirit that we are
children of our Father in heaven. We have had testimony that God is a living being. We have
had testimony that Christ, who was crucified and who rose the third day a resurrected being,
is the head of his Church. We have had testimony of the Spirit that he has revealed in this
dispensation the gospel of Jesus Christ, which is again established on earth in all its fullness.
The gospel of Jesus Christ, as revealed to the Prophet Joseph Smith, is in very deed in every
way the power of God unto salvation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>). It gives to every man the perfect life here, and through
obedience to gospel principles it gives us eternal life.
</p><p>
What is eternal life? In that glorious prayer of intercession offered by Jesus, our Redeemer
just before he crossed the brook Cedron and received the traitor's kiss that betrayed him into
the hands of the soldiers, we find these words: "And this is life eternal, that they might know
thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>). To know God
and his Son is eternal life. There is the key. Life eternal is what I desire. I desire it more than
I desire anything else in the world&mdash;life eternal for me and mine, for you, and for all the
world. And there in the words of the Redeemer himself we have the secret.
</p><p>
<b>How may we know Him?</b>
</p><p>
But how may we <i>know</i> him? That is the next question. Has he at any time, or on any
occasion, answered that question? If so, we want the answer, because it is vital. In searching
the record as it is given to us by men who associated daily with the Lord, we find that upon
one occasion men who were listening to him cried out against him. They opposed his works,
as men today oppose him. And one voice cried out and said in effect, "How do we know that
what you tell us is true? How do we know that your profession of being the Son of God is
true?" And Jesus answered him in just a simple way (and note the test): "<i>If any man will do</i>
his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be <i>of God, or whether I speak of myself</i>."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
That test is most sound. It is most philosophical. It is the most simple test to give knowledge
to an individual of which the human mind can conceive. <i>Doing</i> a thing,
<i>introducing it into your very being</i>, will convince you whether it is good or whether it is bad. You may not be
able to convince me of that which you know, <i>but you know it because you have lived it</i>. That
is the test that the Savior gave to those men when they asked him how they should know
whether the doctrine was of God or whether it was of man.
</p><p>
We have answered the question that if we shall do his will we shall know, but now comes the
question, what is "<i>the will</i>"? And therein is the whole essence of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
Just as plainly as Jesus stated and defined what eternal life is, or how we shall know it, just as
plainly as he laid down that test, <i>just as plainly has he expressed what his will is</i>.
</p><p>
<b>The will of God is revealed to the world</b>
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints bears testimony to the world that this <i>will</i> of
God has been made manifest in this dispensation, that the principles of the gospel, the
principles of life, have been revealed. They are in harmony with the principles that Christ
taught in the meridian of time. It is impossible to give here all the principles that constitute
that <i>will</i>, but they are so simple that, as the scriptures say, "the wayfaring men, though fools,
shall not err therein" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/8#8">Isa. 35:8</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Serve mankind</b>
</p><p>
After obeying the principles and ordinances of the gospel, <i>"the will" of God is to serve your</i>
<i>fellowmen, benefiting them, making this world better for your having lived in it</i>. Christ gave
his all to teach us that principle. And he made the statement: "Inasmuch as ye have done it
unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/40#40">Matt. 25:40</a>). This is
the message God has given to us. This Church is God's Church, which is so perfectly
organized that every man and every woman, every child, may have an opportunity to do
something good for somebody else. It is the obligation of our priesthood members, it is the
responsibility of the auxiliary organizations and of every member to serve and do God's will.
If we do, and the more we do it, the more we shall become convinced that it is the work of
God, because we are testing it. Then, <i>by doing the will of God, we get to know God and get</i>
<i>close to him and to feel that life eternal is ours</i>. We shall feel to love humanity everywhere,
and we can cry out with the apostles of old, "We know that we have passed from death unto
life, because we love the brethren" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/3/14#14">1 Jn. 3:14</a>).
</p><p>
<b>He lives!</b>
</p><p>
God does reveal today to the human soul the reality of the resurrection of the Lord, the
divinity of this great work, the truth, the divine and eternal truth that God lives, not as a
power, an essence, a force, but as our Father in heaven. Oh, why do men try to make that
power, recognized by science and religion everywhere, a mere force? I sometimes wish men
would kneel down and try to pray to electricity or atomic power. Imagine trying to pray to
these forces. You cannot do it, and yet they are great and known forces. You can, however,
pray to God the Father, a personal being. God reveals to the soul his existence. He reveals the
deity of the Lord Jesus Christ, who came to make known to us the great reality of the
existence of God and his Son; and in that spirit, and with such witness in my soul, I bear
testimony today that Jesus Christ is the Redeemer of the world.
</p><p>
"I know that my Redeemer lives; <br />
     What comfort this sweet sentence gives!<br />
     He lives, He lives, who once was dead.<br />
     He lives, my ever-living head.
</p><p>
"He lives, all glory to his name!<br />
     He lives, my Savior, still the same; <br />
     O sweet the joy this sentence gives: <br />
     'I know that my Redeemer lives!' "<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; (Samuel Medley)
</p><p>
<b>Blessings for everyone</b>
</p><p>
God help us and all the world to sense the reality that the gospel of Jesus Christ is established
among men, and that through obedience to it the fatherhood of God and the brotherhood of
man may be realities to every mother and father, every son and daughter. God hasten the day
when that testimony will be real in every heart.
</p><p>
God bless you men of the priesthood. May you hold it in dignity and righteousness that comes
from within, not from without.
</p><p>
God bless our friends of the radio and television audience and the managers and owners of
the stations who have made these broadcasts possible. God bless our friends with whom we
associate and who are contributing to the advancement of this great Church. We are grateful
for their fellowship.
</p><p>
God bless us that we may go home with a firmer resolve than we have ever had before to live
the gospel of Jesus Christ, to be kind to our families and to our neighbors, to be honest in all
our dealings so that men seeing our good works may be led to glorify our Father in heaven.
</p><p>
I leave my blessings with you, with the sick and afflicted, with our soldier boys, some of
whom are paying the supreme sacrifice for freedom, with our missionaries scattered around
the world. I pray that God's protecting care will be with them wherever they are.
</p><p>
May God bless you all, and may he guide and help you that righteousness, harmony, and love
for one another may dwell in each home, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
