<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Let There Be Light"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 66-69</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I pray that I may say a few words that will be helpful in connection with the great ideals that
we have already heard during this conference.
</p><p>
I want to mention very briefly an organization in America known as "The America-Christian
Palestine Committee," of which I have the honor of being a member with Right Reverend
Arthur W. Moulton of the Episcopal Church. The two of us are on the executive committee of
this great organization. There are over two hundred different religious sects in the United
States, and many sects here in Utah.  They vary, of course, in their activities, but every group
follows ideals and looks to God for help.
</p><p>
When Christopher Columbus reached this western world in 1492, he in time expressed to the
king and queen of Spain that he was "the agent in the hands of God, to go forth upon the
mighty waters." According to Washington Irving, Columbus when he set foot on the island of
San Salvador uttered the following prayer in Latin.  Translated it reads: 
</p><p>
Oh God, our eternal Father, eternal, eternally an omnipotent creator of heaven and earth and
sea, we glorify thy holy word for our protection and the protection of the world.
</p><p>
That is one of the most singular statements that could possibly be made, for it has been
carried out and the world has been blessed with an organization which is for the world.
</p><p>
The words of Pastor Robinson recall what Roger Williams, the founder of
Providence, Rhode Island, once said. Williams was much disturbed as to his right to
administer the ordinances of the church, and finally he came to the conclusion that there could
"be no recovery out of the apostasy till Christ shall send forth new apostles to plant churches
anew."
</p><p>
Edward Winslow was the third signer of the Mayflower Compact, and it was he who recorded
the following parting words of Pastor Robinson, as the Pilgrims left the shore of Holland for
their long journey: 
</p><p>
Brethren, we are now quickly to part from one another, and whether I may ever live to
see your face on earth any more, the God of Heaven only knows: but whether the
Lord hath appointed that or not, I charge you before God and His blessed angels, that
you follow me no farther than you have seen me follow the Lord Jesus Christ.  If God
reveal anything to you, by any other instrument of His, be as ready to receive it, as
ever you were to receive truth, by my ministry; for I am fully persuaded, I am very
confident that the Lord has more truth yet to break forth out of His holy word. For my
part, I cannot sufficiently bewail the condition of the reformed churches, who are
come to a period in religion, and will go at present no further than the instruments of
their reformation. The Lutherans cannot be drawn to go beyond what Luther saw;
whatever part of his will or good God has revealed to Calvin, they will rather die than
embrace it, and the Calvinists, you see, stick fast, where they were left by that great
man of God, who yet saw not all things. This is a misery much to be lamented; for
though they were burning and shining lights in their times, yet they penetrated not into
the whole counsel of God; but were they now living, would be as willing to embrace
further light as that which they at first received.  I beseech you to remember it as an
article in your church Covenant. "That you be ready to receive whatever truth shall be
made known to you from the written word of God." But I must herewith exhort you to
take heed what you receive as truth. Examine it, consider it, and compare it with other
scriptures of truth, before you receive it; for it is not possible that the Christian world
should come so lately out of thick anti-Christian darkness, and that perfection of
knowledge should break forth at once.
</p><p>
It is interesting to know that God has never forsaken his children. All nations have had
something of the truths of God.
</p><p>
Carlyle in his <i>Heroes and Hero Worship</i> notes that the
"calling of a prophet, the Man of God, the man, that is, who speaks to the people of
God, has penetrated into the secret of the sacred mystery of the Universe. The prophet
is the revelator of what we are to do."
</p><p>
Throughout the ages, the truths of religion have become closely identified with the thoughts
and habits of mankind.  Religion in the most intelligent use of the term confesses the divine
relationship between man and his God. It is more than knowledge and obedience, for its home
is in the deepest nature of man, where, in its allegiance to truth and its devotion to right, it
governs life.
</p><p>
The religious principles of ancient Israel brought about the highest system of ethical life,
which to this day remains the most vital to human conduct.  The elements the Israelitish
character idealized were the homely virtues of a rustic people: industry, frugality, chastity,
uprightness; and then the hardier virtues, like bravery, and a fortitude that can endure all
except defeat.  Finally, the people to whom God spoke in the days of Abraham, Moses, and
the ages after them learned a deep-seated piety, obedience to the declarations of the Lord their
God, and perfect trust in the revelations of him who mode the world and created man.
Superbly did Israel rise to the knowledge of the true and living God.
</p><p>
The early history of Israel shows a people with aspiration for a righteous social order and an
ultimate unification of mankind.  "Of these ideals," says Israel Zangwill, "the race of
Abraham originally conceived and still conceives itself to be the divine medium for a
knowledge of God." The characteristics of the people are made known to us.
</p><p>
The Israelites had their planting and harvest songs, and like the Navajo Indians, they ascribed
all the gifts of nature to a merciful and loving God. The Prophet Isaiah describes the glory of
redeeming the land: 
</p><p>
The wilderness and the solitary place shall be glad for them; and the desert shall rejoice, and
blossom as the rose.<br />
It shall blossom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and singing: The glory of Lebanon
shall be given unto it, the excellency of Carmel and Sharon, they shall see the glory of the
Lord, and the excellency of our God.<br />
Strengthen ye the weak hands and confirm the feeble knees.<br />
Say to them that are of a fearful heart, Be strong, fear not: behold, your God will come with
vengeance, even God with a recompense; he will come and save you.<br />
Then the eyes of the blind shall be opened, and the ears of the deaf shall be unstopped.<br />
Then shall the lame leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb sing: for in the wilderness
shall waters break out, and streams in the desert.<br />
And the parched ground shall become a pool, and the thirsty land springs of water: in the
habitation of dragons, where each lay, shall be grass with reeds and rushes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/1-7#1">Isa. 35:1-7</a>).
</p><p>
We can see on the frescoes in the tombs of the Pharaohs, dams enclosing basins&mdash;"Just as they
are built today," says Emil Ludwig, "and it can be concluded from inscriptions by what
state-craft the water, after the lapse of fixed periods, was conveyed from one basin into
another." We know how the shepherds dug wells and cisterns four thousand years ago and
how the farmer prepared the land for the seed and made the threshing floors. There is an
aqueduct near Jerusalem with an inscription on it written by King Hezekiah about 700 B. C. 
Palestine has been referred to as a "dry and thirsty land"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/63/1#1">Ps. 63:1</a>), and yet the melting snows of
Lebanon, Mermon, and Carmel, as well as other heights sink into the ground and come forth
again as springs of water. Wells became the center of community life, supplying water for
household purposes as well as for the flocks and herds.
</p><p>
There have been holy men, prophets of God, throughout the ages. They have felt the divine,
creative presence of God. They believed in Providence, and felt there was a power around and
beyond them which gave them a concept of their ever-loving Father.  Those holy men knew
their Creator, listened to him, spoke to him, loved him.  Moses communed with him on
Mount Sinai and received from him the commandments which have molded the true concept
of government throughout the civilized world. History knows no more magnificent men than
the prophets of Israel. They were the idealists of the ancient world.  They grappled with the
same problems which we have today: war, hate of one nation for another, hunger, wrong, sin,
and dishonor.  They were the servants of God who gave the world light and guidance which
have lasted to this day.
</p><p>
It is the idealism of the different ages that has saved the world.  There is a hidden reality in
the hearts of men. Truth, beauty, and goodness belong to the ideal world of men's hopes, and
to God they have turned for revealed truth.  The prophets taught man the glory of the
invisible world and gave him the glow of heavenly light. They lived with the eye of faith and
knew that nature and man had glory beyond that which the senses could understand.
</p><p>
A new nation had come into being at the beginning of the nineteenth century.  It had been
ordained of God to accomplish his divine purposes.  The past and the future met within it, for
the formation of the government of the United States was an event ordered of God for the
bringing in of his Kingdom upon the earth. A republic is the highest form of political
institution, De Tocqueville wrote, and this we know to be true. Our government was made up
of different nationalities brought under one government and one flag. Such a republic had
been unknown before in history.  John Winthrop, one of the founders, wrote concerning it: 
</p><p>
It will be a service to the Church of great consequence to carry the Gospel into those parts of
the world to help on the coming of the fulness of the Gentiles.
</p><p>
These words of the early statesman and missionary truly record the suggestion and intention
which brought Englishmen to these shores, and the historic spirit leads us to an understanding
of the exalted purposes of God in this world, who like the ancient astronomers looked into the
sky and sang: "The heavens declare the glory of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/19/1#1">Ps. 19:1</a>). The founders set forth and longed for
a knowledge of how to live life as it should be lived.
</p><p>
When Joseph Smith went into the woods to pray on a spring morning in 1820, "grace was
poured out upon his lips and God blessed him forever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/45/2#2">Ps. 45:2</a>). God came to him and spoke, and with
him was Jesus Christ the Redeemer of the world.  Joseph heard from the divine lips the
message that a new day was at hand.  Out of it came the knowledge of the weaknesses of the
necessities of man's spirit.  The eternal truth that man is himself a God in latent power had
long been forgotten, for the religion of Jesus Christ had taught faith in the possibility of
ascent from height to height.  So the boy prayed for light and understanding.
</p><p>
When we get the spirit of this new age, then it is that we come to understand the divine truths
of the gospel more and more.  Many things make our history beautiful.  The Prophet Joseph
Smith inaugurated a new age of culture and heavenly gifts.  We all know what this means
through our testimonies of divine truths.  In conclusion, may I give just one example of what
I mean.  During the days when the pioneers were working hard to establish their homes and
redeem the soil they gave examples of their culture in many ways. For example, they built a
theatre here in Salt Lake City which became known throughout America and in England,
France, and Italy. Famous actors came to play on its stage. President Brigham Young gave the
people a love for the drama.  It was he who had the theatre built.  One time a noted actress,
Julia Deane Hayne, in leaving to return to New York, gave her good-bye message to President
Young and the people in a very beautiful statement.  The theatre became known to the world
as a place of divine art years before the railroad reached Salt Lake City. It was truly a
creation of pioneer days, the theatre, for it was built by the inspiration of God.  May we learn
more and more every day about the history of the gospel in this day and age of the world, I
ask in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</div>
</div>
