<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 83-85</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved fellow workers, I have a humble desire to come before you tonight, not only
those who are here assembled, but those who are gathering, and have gathered, and are now
in the many meeting places throughout the United States, Canada, and New Zealand. It is
wonderful to be a fellow worker with you in this great missionary cause of the Church. I am
so grateful that this missionary endeavor does not confine itself to what we call the missions
of the world. It has become and is now part and parcel of the work of every stake of Zion, as
well as every mission. It is my hope and prayer tonight that we are not far distant from the
time when there will be less and less differentiation between stake missions and full time
missions.
</p><p>
Brethren, my message to you tonight is that they are one. We are one, and all of us who have
fellowship in this Church are one in promulgating the gospel of Jesus Christ to our
fellowmen, wherever we may be, either at home or abroad. Now that message seems so
simple that you wonder why I would take the precious time remaining in this meeting to
discuss it further. There are, however, some details pertaining to this work which have not
permitted us in the past to proceed with as great a unity as we might.
</p><p>
Into this great missionary movement of the Church have come prominently to the fore what
we now call referrals. Some of our mission presidents love to call it "sharing the gospel," and
in undertaking to carry out this detail of the work there has seemed to be sort of a natural
inclination upon the part of those laboring in the stakes to exclude the full time missions, and
I presume equal thought on the part of the full time missions to preclude sharing their
opportunities with the stake missions.
</p><p>
Brethren, this just must not be! Possibly at the root of this difficulty is the question of
records, of statistics. We become proud of our performance. We want to make a showing. We
want to stand at the head of the list. I wonder if it were possible to devise statistics which
would register what I shall call, for convenience, our unselfishness in this respect? What does
it matter whether the stake mission or the full time mission gets the credit for a baptism? All
we are interested in is the conversion of those who will repent of their
sins, acknowledge Jesus Christ as the Son of God, and accept his gospel as it has been
restored in these latter days in its fulness to the world through the instrumentality of the
Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
Brethren, we must rise above any personal ambitions or desires. How grateful the General
Authorities are for those glorious meetings we have held with these wonderful mission
presidents, as they have come in from the various missions of the Church in the United States
and in Canada, Mexico, Central America, and Hawaii.
</p><p>
Mission president after mission president reported that they had no trouble because where they
worked conjointly with the stake missions they shared the baptisms 50-50, and they did not
ask a question as to whether the success of the stake mission equaled the full time mission,
nor whether the full time mission equaled that of the stake. I was further thrilled, as were all
of my Brethren who attended those meetings, to see how there had come about such a close
correlation of the activities of these two great groups of missions. When it was possible of an
evening for the stake missionaries to divide up with the full time missionaries they would go
out together, and each benefit and profit by the experience and faithfulness of one another.
</p><p>
The stake missionary can bring into the life of our young full time missionaries a stability and
integrity, a devotion, a loyalty, and dedication, that can only come to us through years of
constant service to the Master. And then on the other hand, these young men, thrilled as they
are with their early experiences in the mission field of sensing the power that there is in the
Priesthood which they bear, when they first sense how the Lord has magnified them in their
calling, why the thrill of it just sets them on fire, and that fire carries over to some of us older
ones in the stake missions who enjoyed that same fire many years ago, and we enjoy coming
in such close contact with it now.
</p><p>
And what is the result? Experience after experience in the mission field indicates that those
who have not been touched by the missionary labors of the stake mission, or in other
instances by the labors of the full time missionaries, have been converted by the joint effort of
a stake missionary and a full time missionary laboring for the time being in the same cause
and in the same family, or in the same group.
</p><p>
Now, we do not particularly feel it wise to intermix or to intermingle our missionaries in this
fashion&mdash;at least I feel a word of caution should be given&mdash;except where there is a result to
be accomplished, except that there is a specific purpose concurred in by the president of the
stake mission and the president of the full time mission.
</p><p>
I had hoped during this Conference, along with my close, beloved associate, Brother Gordon
B. Hinckley, that we might have had a meeting of all of the stake mission presidents and the
stake presidents and our full time presidents, in order that we might sit down and plan a
program mutually agreeable by which the greatest possible unity might be brought about in
this matter of cooperating and coordinating the work of these two branches of our missionary
endeavor.
</p><p>
Finally, we came to this conclusion, and I am sure in arriving at it we were inspired, that all
we needed to do was to call it to the attention of you brethren here tonight, and who might
hear us over these 271 stations of this closed circuit network. This is the solution which we
propose&mdash;that you get together without us and work out your own problem in unity.
</p><p>
This is the order of the Church. To the extent that we can so diversify the activities of the
Church so that almost the full load of our responsibilities rests upon us in the wards and in
the stakes of the Church, and we become less and less dependent upon direction, so far as
details are concerned, from General Authorities of the Church, the stronger the Church will
grow.
</p><p>
I want to say in conclusion that that reaches also to the use of our facilities. There should
never be any hesitancy upon the part of a bishop or his custodian to make every facility the
Church owns available to the mission president at his single request in order that we may not
have any lost motion in this work. If there are any costs involved in
the use which the full time missions may make of the facilities of the wards and the stakes,
we want you bishops and you stake presidents to determine whether you would like to absorb
that locally as part of your contribution to the great missionary cause, or want to send the full
time missions a bill for it.
</p><p>
Now we do not want to make that decision for you. All we want is that the facilities which
the Lord has blessed us with in the wards and stakes of Zion be utilized to the fullest extent
for the carrying on of the promulgation of the gospel, regardless of what agency may have
need for it at the moment. Let each agency make its own decision as to its need of these
facilities. A ward should not make this decision for the mission.
</p><p>
Let me say in conclusion that I am sure that as we do this we will not only grow and develop
the strength of our stakes, but we will make it possible for our bishops to fully fellowship
every convert who comes from the mission. I hope there is not a bishop in the Church who
will presume to pass judgment upon what a mission president does in determining who should
be baptized and who should not. I tell you solemnly this evening, my brethren, the presidents
of our missions have read the 37th Verse of the 20th Section of the Doctrine and Covenants
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/37#37">D&amp;C 20:37</a>)
just as often as any bishop, and are just as much impressed with the importance of following
its mandate implicitly, but when a stake president speaks and a convert is baptized, let the
responsibility for that conversion rest upon the stake president and bishop. It does not lie
within the province of any bishop to challenge it any more than it would lie in the mouth of a
mission president to challenge the judgment of the bishop under like circumstances.
</p><p>
God bless us, brethren, and let us go forward as one, united in the work of the Lord, I pray
humbly, in the name of the Lord, Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
