<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Blessings Through Faithfulness</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1952, pp. 121-124</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters&mdash;I have rejoiced in the spiritual messages of this conference. My faith
has been stimulated. I have resolved to be more devoted and more diligent in my service to
the Master. I do not want to take much time this afternoon, and the things that I had thought
of saying, I think I shall reserve for some future time.
</p><p>
I need the strength of the Lord as I talk to you for a few moments, and do solicit an interest
in your faith and prayers, my brothers and sisters.
</p><p>
This conference has been devoted to a love for and an appreciation of the great blessings that
the Church affords to each of us. We have been challenged to devoted service and to live
according to the standards, the ideals, and the teachings of this great Church of ours. I also
hope we have felt the need of searching for the blessings of the fathers that those things
enjoyed by the ancients may be restored to us and enjoyed by us in this the Dispensation of
the Fullness of Times.
</p><p>
I remember that the progenitor of the great Israelite family was not satisfied with the
conditions found in his homeland, and said to secure happiness and peace it was necessary for
him to seek for the blessings of the fathers, and the right to administer the same. He had been
a follower of righteousness, desiring to receive instructions and to keep the commandments of
God, and sought the great blessings of the priesthood, and to be a father of many nations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/2#2">Abr. 1:2</a>).
</p><p>
And as descendants of this great leader, we, too, should be followers after righteousness, and
should seek to know the mind and will of God in order that our lives might conform thereto.
</p><p>
I remember the great devotion of Enoch, who labored constantly and faithfully to perfect his
people that they might behold the face of God, and enjoy his presence. He labored valiantly
as a servant of the Master and while many failed to accept the gospel message of salvation,
there were many who did, and through obedience to the gospel, they were perfected, and were
not only permitted to look upon the face of God but were privileged to dwell in his presence
and became so sanctified that the Lord received them to himself.
</p><p>
Moses the great deliverer of the Israelites, sought through the Holy Priesthood and the gospel
of the Redeemer to perfect and sanctify the Israelites as they wandered in the wilderness, but
they would not obey the great law of the gospel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/23-25#23">D&amp;C 84:23-25</a>).
They could not forget the idolatry and the
fleshpots of Egypt; they sought to worship images and do things that were contrary to what
God would have them do, and as a result this great leader was unable to perfect his people to
behold the face of their God as he attempted to do, therefore God took Moses, the Holy
Priesthood and the gospel, from the Israelites, and in the place of the gospel with its great
blessings, gave them the carnal code of laws.
</p><p>
The Savior came at the appointed time, and this carnal code of laws given as a schoolmaster
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/3/24#24">Gal. 3:24</a>)
to prepare the children of God for his coming, failed in its great purpose.
</p><p>
But the Lord established his work called chosen servants to assist him in the service of the
ministry, and as the Apostle Paul said to the Ephesians,
</p><p>
. . . he gave some apostles; and some prophets; and some evangelists; and some
pastors and teachers; 
</p><p>
For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the
body of Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11-12#11">Eph. 4:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
These devoted servants gave their time and talents willingly to the saving of souls, but
apostasy crept in, and the great work of the apostles and others in a measure, was lost. They
failed to perfect the people to behold the face of their Redeemer
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/23#23">D&amp;C 84:23</a>).
</p><p>
And again in this day, the same officers are in the Church and kingdom of God, and have the
same commission of perfecting the Saints and edifying the body of Christ.
</p><p>
Now, my brothers and sisters, it seems to me we do have a great responsibility as members of
the Church for the Lord has placed upon us the responsibility of carrying this gospel message
to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>).
I do not think we can accomplish the great
purposes the Lord has placed upon us unless we perfect ourselves and sanctify our souls to
enjoy the inspiration and the direction of the Holy Ghost, that each of us is
entitled to as baptized and faithful members of his kingdom. I believe a bishop called to
preside over a ward, needs to perfect and sanctify himself above that of his brethren and
sisters, otherwise he cannot give the quality of leadership required in his ward.
</p><p>
I think that same principle holds true for a president of a stake, and on up to and including
the President of the Church. I am sure that in our beloved President we have an individual
who has well perfected himself, enjoys the love of our Creator, and is inspired of him in the
great ministry and service he renders to his fellow men.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, we need to incorporate into our lives all the refining influences of the
gospel of Jesus Christ. There is much that pertains to the gospel we need to know, and that
we need to use for our own benefit and blessing.
</p><p>
Not so long ago I heard a man excommunicated from the Church indict the leadership of the
Church for their failure to teach the virtues of life as the cause of his downfall. Now, I am
wondering if as leaders of this people, are we failing to teach the simple virtues of life, that
would prevent many of our brothers and sisters from going astray and doing things that cause
them to fail to receive the great blessings of this Church?
</p><p>
We need to consider the principle of honesty. Our beloved President mentioned it in his talk
to the priesthood last evening. We must be honest and sincere as a people. We cannot lie nor
cheat in our dealings. We should not take advantage of our fellow men. We cannot receive
something that we have not worked for and earned. As a people, we need to teach the
principle of honesty; it is a virtue that makes for character and good Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
We need to be true. We need to be chaste
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
We have heard much said about chastity in the sessions of this conference.
</p><p>
Now, my brothers and sisters, there are many other simple virtues that go to make up good
character. Let us consider these simple virtues as important in the perfecting and sanctifying
of our souls, that in obeying these divine principles we may perfect and sanctify ourselves not
only to behold the face of God, but also to be worthy when he comes the second time&mdash;to
enjoy his presence and be with him in the great ministrations that he has to accomplish among
the children of men.
</p><p>
We need also to consider, as parents and particularly couples of the age that can expect more
children in the home, and also our young people who are anticipating marriage, when they
accept the great responsibility of bringing children into this world they cannot take the
position that because they have gone into the temples of our God and been sealed by the
power of the priesthood for time and all eternity, that is all that is necessary to assure to their
children every blessing and benefit it is their right to expect.
</p><p>
I would advocate that every Latter-day Saint young man and woman anticipating marriage, go
into the temples of our God and by the authority of the priesthood be sealed for time and for
all eternity. But I would want them, and I would want all other married couples expecting
children into their homes to remember that they must ever be faithful to their covenants. I
want them to remember that they must utilize their God-given gifts, these heavenly
endowments of the spirit, that each is blessed with, that when children come, they may
receive all parental gifts and blessings that they should enjoy, and have a right to expect being
born under the new and everlasting covenant of marriage.
</p><p>
Now, it is important to us parents to remember our responsibility in respect to all of these
holy ordinances and covenants entered into in the temples of our God. We must keep them
sacred, and do nothing to violate the provisions of these covenants, otherwise the blessings
that are pronounced upon us, and all blessings are predicated upon our
obedience, will not be ours to enjoy and perhaps we shall not bestow to our children the gifts and
endowments they have a right to receive.
</p><p>
And I know, that in addition to keeping sacred and holy these ordinances and being faithful
throughout our lives, we must also develop the native talents God has blessed us with, and
they can be developed in the service of this Church, for if men and women will develop their
talents, they have an opportunity of passing on to their children these great blessings and gifts
of the Spirit. And so, when we consider perfecting ourselves and sanctifying our souls to
behold the face of God and enjoy his presence we must think of our children and their
children's children.
</p><p>
Parents who live righteously and develop every natural gift and talent through service are
entitled to choice spirits from our Heavenly Father and have a greater opportunity to endow
them richly with their own perfected qualities and virtues which should assure their children a
happy and useful life. My brothers and sisters, what joy and happiness would come to us as a
result of our own righteousness? The greatest dividends we could experience would be ours,
and these dividends can only come as we honor the holy ordinances and covenants that we
have entered into. May we do this and be faithful and true in all our obligations and duties I
humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
