<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Some Current Problems</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Merrill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Merrill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1946, pp. 27-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The conditions in the world today are such that every Latter-day Saint faces a challenge&mdash;a
challenge of loyalty to the leadership of the Church and to its teachings and standards. The
forces of evil were perhaps never more rampant and their influence never more widespread
than now. Let us take a brief glance at the gloomy situation.
</p><p>
<i>The Prevalence of Evil</i>
</p><p>
To the eyes of a Latter-day Saint, and judged by his professed standards, the sinful ways of
the world were never more largely indulged in by its people generally than they are today.
Were sex moral standards ever lower? Were selfishness, greed, and crime ever more rampant?
Was religious faith ever colder? Was the desire to get something for nothing ever stronger?
Was the struggle for place and power ever keener? Were family ties ever looser? Were
marriage vows ever more frequently violated? As for America, is not a negative answer to
these questions the correct one? Was not Alexander Pope stating facts when he wrote:
</p><p>
Vice is a monster of so frightful mien, <br />
As to be hated needs but to be seen; <br />
Yet seen too oft, familiar with her face, <br />
We first endure, then pity, then embrace.
</p><p>
Judged by Latter-day Saint teachings and standards, the moral conditions of the country are
most deplorable. And yet, sad to say, our people are by no means quite justified in assuming
a "holier-than-thou" attitude. Worldly sins of every type exist among us. It is
folly to close our eyes and deny the presence of these things. Then I suggest we look the
situation squarely in the face and do something about it. What, does one ask? I answer,
sincerely repent and help our fellow men to do likewise. Investigation will show that
smoking, drinking, gambling, juvenile delinquency, fornication, violation of marriage vows,
broken homes, divorces&mdash;to name a few things only&mdash;are growing evils among us. To the
worldly-minded, most of them are minor matters, devoid of sinful aspects. But to Latter-day
Saints the case is wholly different. We cannot indulge in any of these things with a guiltless
conscience because we have been differently taught. We have divine revelations relative to
them, the Word of Wisdom, for example. Hence we know that indulgence in smoking and
drinking is displeasing to the Lord. Gambling is adjudged a wrong by every moral code.
Marriage is a holy estate requiring sacred vows and imposing binding obligations. If these are
all faithfully kept then within the precincts of the home, there may be heaven on earth a place
where live innocent and joyous children, happy parents, and a united Christian family.
</p><p>
<i>Juvenile Delinquency</i>
</p><p>
According to authentic reports, juvenile delinquency of both boys and girls has greatly
increased during recent years until it has reached alarming proportions. Broken homes and
absence of mothers from their homes are given as major causes. To Latter-day Saints, family
life, home, and children are requisites for greatest happiness and glory, both in this life and in
the life to come. Children are the brightest gems in any woman's diadem. This truth might
well be indelibly impressed on the mind of every wife.
</p><p>
Respecting the duty of parents to the children, the Lord, through his Prophet Joseph Smith
said:
</p><p>
And again, inasmuch as parents have children in Zion, or in any of her stakes which are
organized, that teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance, faith in Christ the
Son of the living God, and of baptism and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the
hands, when eight years old, the sin be upon the heads of the parents . . . And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25,28#25">D&amp;C 68:25,28</a>).
</p><p>
Further in the D&amp;C, we read:
</p><p>
All children have claim upon their parents for their maintenance until they are of age
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/4#4">D&amp;C 83:4</a>).
</p><p>
Thus divine law, as well as civil law, makes the parents responsible for their children. No
Latter-day Saint lives a worthy life in the eyes of the Lord who neglects to do everything
feasible to bring up his children according to gospel standards. Let every parent take heed of
these requirements. Wise Solomon declared:
</p><p>
Train up a child in the way he should go: and when he is old, he will not depart from it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/22/6#6">Prov. 22:6</a>).
</p><p>
Yet there are parents who erroneously and foolishly say that they must let their children grow
up without religious teaching and training in order that they can be free to choose for
themselves when they are grown. This is a doctrine of Satan. It cannot in the least degree
release parents from the responsibility to their children which the Lord places upon them&mdash;a
truth that they will some day certainly learn and, if neglected, to their sorrow.
</p><p>
Let all Latter-day Saints be faithful to their parental duties that their children may be a joy to
them and a credit to the community where they live.
</p><p>
<i>Increase in Divorces</i>
</p><p>
A year ago from this pulpit President David O. McKay discussed the divorce question and
asserted that in the United States divorces had so increased that one marriage out of every six
ended in the divorce court. Recently, it has been publicly said that about fifty percent of the
war marriages of American boys in service are being terminated by divorce. The picture
painted by these figures is a sad and deplorable one. It is indicative of unstable, sinful, and
demoralizing conditions, ruinous to the ideals of marriage, family, and home, a distinctive
blight upon the happy life that every wedded couple may achieve by being true to their
marriage vows. Then is not a marriage failure necessarily an unfavorable reflection upon one
or both of the parties to the marriage&mdash;the ones responsible for the failure? A grave
delinquency is certainly indicated, for the conditions of a happy union have not been met.
</p><p>
What are these conditions, the novice may ask? Since I do not qualify as an expert in these
matters I will not venture to answer the question except to say that if each party to the
marriage contract will faithfully live the Golden Rule in all of his or her relations with the
partner, then the marriage undoubtedly will be successful. A Latter-day Saint marriage is a
union of two equal partners, obligated to build a home where mutual love, respect, trust,
fidelity, tolerance, patience, and kindness are some of the essential operating factors. And in
the home where these prevail the ugly specter of divorce will never enter.
</p><p>
. . . Men are, that they might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
Wedlock is essential to a fulness of joy. Let every Latter-day Saint who enters the holy
precincts of the marriage state do so with a firm determination to live so that all the joys and
happiness obtainable therein may be his realization. Marriage was instituted by God himself.
No one can violate its covenants with impunity.
</p><p>
<i>Smoking and Drinking Decried</i>
</p><p>
And now a few words about smoking and drinking. I am speaking to Latter-day Saints&mdash;to
people who accept the Word of Wisdom as being a divine revelation. This
being true, they cannot indulge in the consumption of liquor or tobacco without having to
some extent at least, a feeling of guilt because the Lord has said liquor and tobacco are not
good for man, and indulgence is therefore contrary to his will and to Church teachings. So
when it comes to smoking and drinking, a Latter-day Saint and a nonbeliever are not on the
same moral plane. The latter is not conscious of sinning; the former is. Why then do
Latter-day Saints indulge? There is a variety of reasons, but perhaps the chief one is that other
people do. We are more or less influenced by the actions of others. A woman wears short
dresses because it is the fashion, not because it adds to the beauty of her appearance. But the
Lord said:
</p><p>
. . . they that knew no law shall have part in the first resurrection; and it shall be tolerable for
them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/54#54">D&amp;C 45:54</a>).
</p><p>
Also:
</p><p>
For of him unto whom much is given much is required; and he who sins against the greater
light shall receive the greater condemnation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/3#3">D&amp;C 82:3</a>).
</p><p>
Is this not a merciful and just standard by which to be judged? I repeat, Church members
cannot justify themselves in violating the laws and commandments of the Lord because
nonmembers do. Indeed, in any case, each person will be held accountable for what he does,
for he is given his free agency. But I call attention to the fact that every person is accountable
for the example he sets and the influence he has with others. Be he ever so humble, his words
and acts will affect one or more of his fellows. Hence, for these words and acts he must give
an account. That his example may be good, particularly for young people, is one reason why
we are so persistent in trying to convert to abstinence all of our older people who indulge in
the use of narcotics.
</p><p>
But let me warn you that smoking and drinking are on the increase among the people, as are
other evils such as juvenile delinquency, gambling, Sabbath breaking, profanity, fornication,
and other types of wickedness.
</p><p>
<i>Movement to Increase Liquor Sales</i>
</p><p>
In view of the whole situation there is need for every Latter-day Saint to buckle on the armor
of righteousness and go forward battling valiantly for the cause of right, Christian morality,
justice, and truth according as the Lord has given us eyes to see and intellects to understand
these things. Satan and his hosts are on the alert to extend his domain and increase his power.
For instance, notwithstanding testimony and facts which prove that the consumption of
alcoholic beverages results in physical, mental, moral, and spiritual evils of many types and
kinds, and that the liquor business is always more or less lawless and corrupting, there is now
a movement on foot in Utah to extend this business, to multiply the avenues
of liquor sales, and to increase the ease with which liquor may be obtained.
</p><p>
The official advocates of repeal in 1933 loudly proclaimed that the saloon would never be
allowed to return. That disreputable joint was a stench in the nostrils of clean-minded people.
Decent women never darkened its doors. But now the proposition is to multiply in Utah by
many fold the places where liquor may be legally dispensed and turn myriads of dining places
and food counters into liquor taverns. Further, we are asked to legalize the sale of liquor at
social and night clubs. All of this would in effect turn every social club and public eating
place into a saloon. Is there anyone who believes these night clubs would be clean,
respectable, law-abiding places? Experienced people know that many of them would be dens
of drunkenness, gambling, fornications, and other vile things.
</p><p>
<i>Better Laws and Enforcement Needed</i>
</p><p>
Will the good people of Utah permit opening the gates of hell wider than they are now? On
the other hand, should they not unite to secure better laws, better enforcement, more
restrictions&mdash;all in the interest of a better and cleaner environment? Nineteen forty-seven is
centennial year. Millions of tourists will come within the borders of this state. Shall they go
away with the impression that Utah has copied Reno? Certainly not!
</p><p>
"Utah, We Love Thee" is the title of a song we joyously sing. Let us prove our love to the
satisfaction of our centennial visitors by cleaning up, fixing up, and painting up, not only
materially, but morally and spiritually as well. In preparation let us at once begin to live a
more genuine Christian life by abstaining from doing evil, by more fully living the Golden
Rule and by intensifying our efforts to be fair, honest, dependable, and just in all our dealings
with our fellow men.
</p><p>
<i>Facts on Use of Alcoholic Beverages</i>
</p><p>
And now a few more facts relative to alcoholic beverages. These are taken from an article
published in <i>The Christian Advocate</i>, February 21, and written by M. E. Lazenby:
</p><p>
Fifty million people in the United States drink alcoholic beverages&mdash;half of all people over
fifteen years of age. Three million of these are excessive drinkers, 750,000 being chronic
alcoholics. Has drinking become public enemy Number One? In pre-prohibition days this
country had 177,000 licensed liquor places; there are now 360,000&mdash;more than twice as many.
In 1944 the American people spent more than seven billion dollars for alcoholic drinks, a sum
about equal to that spent for all educational, religious, and charitable work combined in a
similar period of time, as the following shows:
</p><p>
Add all the money spent in the United States during the school year 1941-42, for educational
purposes, including that spent on all public and private schools, colleges and universities,
professional and special schools of all types, including public libraries and reading rooms of
all kinds. To this sum, add all the expenditures, gifts and bequests to
organized religion for 1942, then add all expenditures from American Red Cross funds by the
national and local chapters from January 1942 to March 1945. To this add the total income of
the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis for the eight months' period ending May 1944;
add the expenditures of the United States health service; add the expenditures by the
forty-eight state governments for benefits in 194l, such as public safety, health, hospitals,
institutions for the handicapped, public welfare, corrections, and recreation; add all the
expenditures of the federal government during the fiscal year 1944 under the Social Security
Act, including old-age assistance, aid to dependent children, aid to the blind, unemployment
compensation administration; add the Department of Labor expenditures for maternal and
child health service and crippled children; add, finally, the expenditures of the United States
Veterans' Administration during the fiscal year 1944. The sum total of all these is
$7,039,914,950&mdash;about the same amount as that spent for alcoholic beverages during 1944.
Can we believe it? The seven billion dollars spent in 1944 for alcoholic beverages drew that
staggering amount from the cash registers of legitimate business. Further, in America four
billion, one hundred forty-seven million pounds of grain and two hundred thirty-eight million,
six hundred fifty-five thousand (238,655,000) pounds of sugar, syrup, and molasses were used
in the manufacture of distilled and fermented liquors. Yet abroad millions of people are dying
for food.
</p><p>
Statistics show that during 1942 there were 28,309 traffic accident deaths, in 25.1 percent of
which the parties involved had been drinking. There are some significant facts relative to
alcohol and crime that are illuminating. The F.B.I. reports for 1932 show that in 596 cities
having a population of 21,660,000, there were 831 arrests for drunkenness per 100,000
population. In 1944 in these cities there were 1,726 arrests for drunkenness per
100,000,&mdash;more than double. The F.B.I. is quoted as saying that our crime bill is
$16,000,000,000 a year and that "twenty-three percent of this is caused by drink."
</p><p>
Further, an officer of the Distillers Produce Corporation, speaking before a Rotary Club,
October 1945, said the liquor traffic industry is spending almost $50,000,000 a year in
advertising, the purpose of which, of course, is to get more men and women and young
people to drink. Whither are we going?
</p><p>
Can Latter-day Saints, wherever they are, in Utah or elsewhere, favor any move that will
make liquor more easy to get or more widely consumed? May the Lord forbid!
</p><p>
I pray that the Lord will give us all a greater desire and a stronger will to live righteously,
and I do it in the name of Jesus Christ, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
