<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Look Into the Past and Future</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1947, pp. 122-124</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: This is a day of grace, a day that brings to our minds the life of our
Savior, Jesus Christ, and the lives of noble men and women who have made the world better
and brought to civilization a knowledge that God lives and Jesus Christ is the Savior of the
world.
</p><p>
CHRIST'S RESURRECTION A TESTIMONY FOR ALL LIVING
</p><p>
I wish to read what thousands of people are reading and thinking today. Thousands of men in
the service of their country who are in Europe and in far-off Asia, are marching according to
orders to the cemeteries, where white crosses bear testimony of the many who have given
their lives for God and country. As they pass through the portals to the cemeteries, they read
certain sentences written in gold. They are taken from the last chapter of Mark:
</p><p>
And when the sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James, and
Salome, had bought sweet spices, that they might come and anoint him.
</p><p>
And very early in the morning the first day of the week, they came unto the sepulchre at the
rising of the sun.
</p><p>
And they said among themselves, Who shall roll us away the stone from the door of the
sepulchre?
</p><p>
And when they looked, they saw that the stone was rolled away: for it was very great.
</p><p>
And entering into the sepulchre, they saw a young man sitting on the right side, clothed in a
long white garment; and they were affrighted.
</p><p>
And he saith unto them, Be not affrighted: Ye seek Jesus of Nazareth, who was crucified: he
is risen; he is not here: . . .
</p><p>
But go your way, tell his disciples and Peter that he goeth before you into Galilee: there shall
ye see him, as he said unto you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/1-7#1">Mark 16:1-7</a>).
</p><p>
Mary and those other women who had gone to the sepulchre left and went down the highway,
knowing in their hearts that Jesus had risen, and it was only a short time before he assured his
disciples that as he had risen, so shall the children of God also rise from the tomb.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY FOR MISSIONARY WORK
</p><p>
This is a day of grace; it is grace unto us because it is divine knowledge that we have. You
brethren who hold the priesthood, you seventies, who are responsible for giving to the world
the message of Christ our Lord, must go forth as never before with your souls ringing with
testimony. All of us bearing this Holy Priesthood must awaken to this great cause of truth.
Live righteously because it is right, and do the things that we have been admonished to do, in
this conference of the Lord. We must remember, brother seventies, that as Jesus of Nazareth,
after his crucifixion, sent his disciples into the world to preach the gospel, so he is sending his
disciples today into the world, and they will be heard.
</p><p>
It is wise and good for us to remember that the Sermon on the Mount undoubtedly was an
ordination message. The Twelve and the Seventies were sent in the very early life of the
Savior into different parts of Palestine. They were to teach the people, and you will note from
this, that the word "seventy" is a very divine word. It is sacred; it literally means "universal"
and comes from one of the oldest words of one of the oldest languages of ancient times.
</p><p>
LOOKING TO THE FUTURE
</p><p>
Think how our attention has been called to the Prophet Joseph Smith, President Brigham
Young, and all the pioneers, who were looking to the future when the gospel was restored and
the priesthood of God given to them. They were told to look to the future because they had to
go forth and bear the power of their priesthood. Think of how they knew&mdash;the vision they
had! We are seated today in a building which is now the largest symphony hall in America,
possibly in all the world. The great symphonies of the world will come here and play to the
world. Great music has already been given. It is only recently that one of the noted architects
of America found here what he called an example of the old Greek classical art; he saw the
beauty of these columns, these long graceful columns, holding this gallery up. How the
pioneers built for the future is a glorious story.
</p><p>
Not long ago a new course of study was inaugurated at St. John's College in Maryland, a
system of academic work which the educators of America said was one of the most forward
looking things in the academic world. Students were to enter that college and read the masters
of history, the masters of literature. Before the people started west from
Nauvoo, a library was to be built by the seventies, and President Joseph Young inaugurating it
through the permission and the blessing of the Prophet Joseph Smith, announced that, "There
shall be erected in the city of Nauvoo a library where the learned may come and read the
great literature of the world."
</p><p>
In 1850, President Brigham Young again had in mind the building of a great library, and
Truman O. Angell became the architect of it. He drew plans for one of the most beautiful
buildings to be erected on the western frontier which should house a large collection of books
for the use of the seventies.
</p><p>
They were looking to the future, to preach the gospel. My brethren, we must keep in mind
always that we must become students of world history. Think of what has already been said
from this pulpit concerning the pioneers, and I leave you this angle of thought which has
already been expressed. It is now known that the five great institutions of civilization, that
came from the very beginning of man's history upon the earth, have been perpetuated up to
the present time. They were perpetuated in this state by the pioneers, and they lie at the root
of our civilization. They are first, industry based on agriculture; second, the home; third, the
state; fourth, the public school system; and fifth, the church.
</p><p>
Paul, the Apostle, was a seventy and a graduate of the University of Tarsus. So were
Barnabus, and the evangelist Luke. They fostered these institutions, and we are to perpetuate
them. We are to live by them, and hold them sacredly as we work our way through life.
</p><p>
My brother seventies, and all the priesthood, may we dedicate our lives as never before to the
perpetuation of this great work, and always know that it is art, knowledge, and religion that
bring spirituality, and it is the spiritual forces that will save the world.
</p><p>
God bless us. May we understand and see as never before, I ask, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
