<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1943, pp. 109-111</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren, if I say anything to you that will be worth while this afternoon, I shall need
your faith and prayers, so please extend them in my behalf.
</p><p>
INTERESTING VISIT TO MISSION
</p><p>
Most of the month of September I spent visiting the North Central States Mission, in
company with President Richards, his wife, and my wife. I bring to you, who are the fathers
of those missionaries, their greetings, and the report that they are all well and happy, and
doing an excellent work.
</p><p>
I went into that mission to find, as I went from place to place that I was asked to meet people
who are not of our faith, in numbers equal, almost, to those of the converted members
resident in the branches. I was faced with the problem of explaining to them why we are
there, and why we are working in the world as we are.
</p><p>
I wonder if it would be well for us to think occasionally about ourselves in that light, what
we want to tell the world. Many of you who are here today are missionaries in the stakes of
Zion, and you are faced with that problem likewise.
</p><p>
As I faced those audiences, I felt impressed to bear testimony to the restoration of the gospel
in this day and age. I remembered that Christ told Peter that he would found His church upon
the testimony that He is the Son of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16-18#16">Matt. 16:16-18</a>).
I remembered also that when the Prophet Joseph
Smith was alive that the world appeared to have a very hazy idea as to the personality of
God. They were shocked and surprised when that lad told them that he had gone into the
woods to ask God for wisdom, and that both God the Father and Christ His Son had appeared
to him, in vision, and that he saw them as glorified Beings
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
PERSONALITY OF GOD
</p><p>
The world was shocked to think that God, after all, might have a personality of that kind; and
generally speaking, I believe, that idea is not to this day accepted, for they rely upon a certain
scripture in the New Testament which says, "God is a God of spirit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/24#24">John 4:24</a>), and they say: "All the
world knows that spirit is immaterial."
</p><p>
I called to their attention the fact that the Prophet Joseph Smith teaches that there is no such
thing as immateriality in the world, and that even spirit is matter
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/7#7">D&amp;C 131:7</a>), and substance; and if God is
a God of spirit, and if spirit is matter, then God is material, and thus can
have a definite form. The scripture which says that God created man in his own image
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>), is a
real and true scripture, and when the Prophet Joseph Smith was given that wonderful blessing,
he saw God in His true form.
</p><p>
While we worship God the Father, His Son Jesus Christ and the Holy Ghost, we have a
different idea as to their personality and being from that which the world at large possesses. It
was the restoration of that truth, among others, that was essential at that time. When we tell
the world that they have gone astray, we do nothing more than quote the word of Christ our
Lord to the Prophet Joseph Smith, and there is no egotism on our own part when we say it.
We accept the responsibility of that announcement in humility and faith.
</p><p>
I found that there are many people who are blessed with that interpretation of God, even
among those who are not of our faith. They are pleased with the thought that God can be real,
that there is no confusion in that scripture, after all, but that he is a definite personality. I
taught them our method of faith in that type of God.
</p><p>
I believe as our many friends who have come amongst us here inquire as to why Mormonism,
that that, perhaps, shall be our first explanation: that God is real, and truly a being, and that
he has restored the gospel.
</p><p>
THE FIRST PRINCIPLES OF THE GOSPEL NECESSARY
</p><p>
Then I taught them that the Priesthood of God was restored through the instrumentality of
heavenly beings, and that we are the custodians of that Priesthood, as we were told by Brother
Richards in his address here at this Conference. I taught them faith and repentance and
baptism.
</p><p>
The law of repentance is a law that is ever active among us. I read that there is nothing so
apparent to man as his own imperfection, that life is a struggle to reduce that imperfection.
No man can compare himself with his ideals and be proud or haughty. The proud and the
haughty are only they who compare themselves with more unfortunate people than they.
There is no place in the heart of man for pride or arrogance, and there is room, every day that
we live, for repentance on the part of man.
</p><p>
Repentance is the recognition of improper ways of living, the resolution to depart from them,
and the final putting in the place of those bad ways of life the correct and superior methods
of doing things. And if there is ever a day in the lives of anyone of us when that type of
repentance does not have place, I will be surprised.
</p><p>
When God told certain of His servants, through the Prophet Joseph Smith, that the thing they
could best do for their own spiritual welfare was to cry repentance to this generation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/15/6#6">D&amp;C 15:6</a>). He
knew exactly what He said, and repentance is the thing that we most need, all of us, every
day of our lives.
</p><p>
Along with the law of repentance comes a law of forgiveness. We are told that though our
sins shall be as scarlet, if we repent, honestly and sincerely, and do them no more, we shall
be washed as white as wool (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/1/18#18">Isa. 1:18</a>).
</p><p>
Now, repentance brings that forgiveness. There are too many of us, however,
who, when we say that we forgive, forget that forgiveness means the washing away of our
remembrance of those things. Forgiveness availeth a man nothing, so long as we who pretend
to forgive hold before our eyes when we consider him, his past record. If we are going to
forgive a person, being convinced of his sincere and honest repentance, offer reinstatement
and forgiveness, we must forget. We must accept him as of today, with a clean heart and an
honest motive, and we must give him his opportunity.
</p><p>
I believe that it is in that spirit that God accepts of us through repentance, and that He will
actually forget our offenses against Him if our repentance is sincere, and our future conduct
honorable and upright, such as to justify His confidence. Wherever you go, you find the past
record of people following them from place to place after we have forgiven them. I would ask
your indulgence to give them an honest "break." That is what repentance means to me.
</p><p>
And then we have to teach those people in the world the necessity for baptism, and our
method of baptism, which is not unique with us at all, because it was one established by
Christ, and it has persisted in certain quarters of the world. But baptism by immersion for the
forgiveness of sin, the remission of sin, is a cardinal principle with us. The why and the
wherefore, we leave with God, for Christ has said it is necessary. "Whomsoever ye baptize
shall be saved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/16#16">Mark 16:16</a>),
and whoever is not baptized and rejects the teaching will be damned. It is
essential, because Christ has said so.
</p><p>
The symbolism is an interesting study, and means much to us. It is only necessary because
Christ has said so, and God established it from the beginning as a principle of redemption for
mankind.
</p><p>
These and many other things we had the pleasure of testifying to these good people, and we
hope that we did them good. We know full well that we ourselves were benefited and blessed,
and I feel that these are cardinal things that we should contemplate every day of our lives. If
we are sincere in our testimony, such contemplation will benefit and bless us, and make us
better.
</p><p>
STRENGTH IN TESTIMONY
</p><p>
The strength and the power of this Church is in the testimony of its members, for Christ said,
"Upon this rock I will build my church"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18#18">Matt. 16:18</a>)&mdash;upon
the testimony that He is the Son of God. In
every generation and every place where the Church has been established, it has been
introduced by that testimony, and so long as that testimony was retained in the hearts of the
members and followers of Christ, strength and power and vigor characterized the organization.
</p><p>
If there ever comes a time that the members of this Church shall fail in that testimony, the
Church will go down to destruction. Fortunately, Christ has told us that He will never take it
from the earth so long as we are faithful, and my faith leads me to believe that there is the
power within this Church to maintain that testimony in vigor and strength; and that God will
keep us all firm in it, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ, our Lord and Redeemer. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
