<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Be Not Deceived</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">President of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1952, pp. 58-60</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I shall take for my text a few verses from the forty-sixth section of the Doctrine and
Covenants: 
</p><p>
"But ye are commanded in all things to ask of God, who giveth liberally; and that which the
Spirit testifies unto you even so I would that ye should do in all holiness of heart, walking
uprightly before me, considering the end of your salvation, doing all things with prayer and
thanksgiving, that ye may not be seduced by evil spirits, or doctrines of devils, or the
commandments of men, for some are of men, and others of devils.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, beware lest ye are deceived; and that ye may not be deceived seek ye earnestly
the best gifts, always remembering for what they are given
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/7-8#7">D&amp;C 46:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
President Clark said we are a singing people, but I am inclined to think, while that is true, we
are not a studious people, that as members of the Church we have not taken advantage of our
opportunities to learn, to make ourselves acquainted with the plan of salvation, the
commandments of the Lord pertaining to our exaltation. We have not considered the Book of
Mormon and the Doctrine and Covenants and the Pearl of Great Price as thoroughly as we
should have done, and that is also true of the Bible.
</p><p>
The Lord in his mercy and kindness sent angels from his presence to reveal gospel and to
make known the record of the ancient inhabitants of this continent, the Jaredites and the
Nephites and Lamanites. Likewise by the inspiration and guidance of his Spirit, he revealed to
the Prophet Joseph Smith many of the precious things that were taken out of the writings of
the prophets, and we have them restored again. But are we reading them? Are we making
ourselves acquainted with these commandments, these precious truths which have been made
known for our salvation? Have we ever stopped to think of the great advantage that we have
over the rest of the Christian world in this fact, that they maintain that the Bible contains the
full word of God, that revelation from him ceased nearly two thousand years ago? Men are
left now to depend upon that written word. But the Lord has revealed to us the history of
these other ancient peoples. He has given unto us the commandments and the revelations that
were given to them, and so earnestly did he feel the responsibility of giving to us additional
information that he sent angel from his presence to reveal it.
</p><p>
Are we, who profess to believe in the mission of the Prophet Joseph Smith, to testify that
angels came to him, and through them that the gospel was restored, the priesthood again
revealed and given to men? Do we feel that we are under any responsibilities to search these
scriptures and make ourselves familiar with them? I wonder. It is my understanding, I hope I
am wrong, that a great multitude of members of this Church have never read the Book of
Mormon, are not acquainted with the Doctrine and Covenants, who have not taken the time to
consider the commandments that have been revealed for our eternal good, and that to our
detriment.
</p><p>
Now we know that there are many spirits abroad in the land
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/1-3#1">D&amp;C 50:1-3</a>), and as the Lord says, some of
their doctrines are doctrines of devils; some are the commandments of men. Are we prepared
by our knowledge and understanding to segregate these doctrines which are of men and which
are of devils, from the truth? Are we living near enough unto the Lord to have that spirit of
discernment, that we are entitled, as we would be through our humility and faith, to know the
truth that would make us free (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>)?
</p><p>
In an earlier revelation, the Lord said: 
</p><p>
"And whoso having faith you shall confirm in my church, by the laying on of the hands, and
I will bestow the gift of the Holy Ghost upon them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/15#15">D&amp;C 33:15</a>). We have the right to the
guidance of the Holy Ghost, but we can't have that guidance if we wilfully refuse to consider
the revelations that have been given to help us to understand and to guide us in the light and
truth of the everlasting gospel. We can't hope to have that guidance when we refuse to
consider these great revelations which mean so much to us both temporally and spiritually.
Now if we find ourselves in this condition of unbelief or unwillingness to seek for the light
and the knowledge which the Lord has placed within our reach, then we are liable or in
danger of being deceived by evil spirits, the doctrines of devils, and the teachings of men.
And when these false influences are presented before us, we will not have the distinguishing
understanding by which we can segregate them and know that they are not
of the Lord. And so we may become prey unto the ungodly, to the vicious, to the cunning, to
the craftiness of men.
</p><p>
We all have a right to know the truth. It is a requirement the Lord makes of every member of
the Church that he know for himself and have a testimony of the truth in his own heart and
not be under the necessity of depending upon anyone else to know that Jesus Christ is the Son
of God or that Joseph Smith is a prophet of God. If there is any person in the sound of my
voice, a member of this Church, who does not know in his heart that the Father and the Son
appeared to Joseph Smith, revealed themselves, and made known again the true doctrine
concerning God, then that person has not lived up to his or her requirements, the
commandments the Lord has placed upon us, for we should know that fact. We should know
that John the Baptist came and restored the Aaronic Priesthood. We ought not to have to
depend upon any other source, only the light of truth which is planted in our hearts by the
Holy Spirit through our faithfulness. We should know that Peter, James, and John came and
restored the Melchizedek Priesthood with all its powers, so that the gospel again could be
preached, the knowledge of God declared, and righteousness again be found in the earth, for
the salvation of all those who would repent of their sins and turn unto God.
</p><p>
I have in my pocket here an invitation sent to me personally; it may be many of you have
received one that was sent to you personally, inviting me to attend one of the churches to
make myself familiar with the doctrines. Now the man who sent this had a perfect right to
send it. He has a right to send this to you and to give you that invitation, but do you have
faith enough, knowledge enough of the gospel of Jesus Christ that you would not be deceived
if you should accept the invitation, and go and listen to the doctrines of the church to which
this man belongs? Do you know the truth?
</p><p>
I have a testimony, definitely, positively, that our Father in heaven restored the gospel of
Jesus Christ, that Joseph Smith told the truth. I know that the Father and the Son appeared to
him, just as well as I know I am here. I know that Jesus Christ is the Son of God, the
Redeemer of the world, the Savior of men who will repent and receive his gospel. Are we all
prepared so that we will not be subject to the cunning craftiness of men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/14#14">Eph. 4:14</a>), to the false doctrines
that are in the world, the teachings that are contrary to the plan of eternal salvation? If we are
not then we need to repent.
</p><p>
I am going to read to you a statement that I made some time ago which I think is true, and
which is a guide to me and I hope may be to you.
</p><p>
So far as the philosophy and wisdom of the world are concerned, they mean nothing unless
they conform to the revealed word of God. Any doctrine, whether it comes in the name of
religion, science, philosophy, or whatever it may be, if it is in conflict with the revealed word
of the Lord, will fail. It may appear plausible. It may be put before you in language that
appeals and which you may not be able to answer. It may appear to be established by
evidence that you cannot controvert but all you need to do is to abide your time. Time will
level all things. You will find that every doctrine, every principle, no matter how universally
believed, if it is not in accord with the divine word of the Lord to his servants, will perish.
Nor is it necessary for us to try to stretch the word of the Lord in a vain attempt to make it
conform to these theories and teachings. The word of the Lord shall not pass away unfulfilled
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/35#35">Matt. 24:35</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/38#38">D&amp;C 1:38</a>),
but these false doctrines and theories will all fail. Truth, and only truth, will remain when all
else has perished. The Lord has said, "And truth is knowledge of things as they are, and as
they were, and as they are to come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/24#24">D&amp;C 93:24</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord bless you, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
