<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Mightiest Work of All</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 29-31</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am happy to say something to my brethren and sisters on this occasion and I sincerely pray
for their faith and prayers. We are all interested in the Christian world today. I have the honor
of being a member of the American Christian Palestine Committee with the Reverend Bishop
Moulton of the Episcopal Church to work for the redemption of Palestine, and its restoration.
A few weeks ago we were asked to write about the Constitution of the United States and what
it means as a civic document. To us all, the Constitution of the United States is a very sacred
document, and it has never been equaled in the history of the world.
</p><p>
I wish to read a paragraph written ages ago by a famous Greek orator whose name was
Isocrates.
</p><p>
"The age in which we live should be distinguished by some glorious
enterprise . . . Let world leaders contrive to put to an end our present troubles. The treaties of peace
are insufficient for their purpose; they may retard, but cannot prevent our misfortunes. We
stand in need of some more durable plan, which will forever put to an end our hostilities and
unite us by the lasting ties of mutual affection and fidelity."
</p><p>
Quoting the words of Herbert L. Willett,
</p><p>
"The divisions of Christendom today are its most conspicuous reproach, and its chief cause of
inefficiency. They present a moral affront to the enterprise inaugurated by Jesus Christ, and
constitute the outstanding limitation of its progress. The divided state of the Church is an
affront to Christianity. We wonder if Christianity can survive; we wonder if the Christian
groups can fight the evils of the social order of our times."
</p><p>
Only the true Church can furnish the program and power to meet the emergencies that
confront the world today.
</p><p>
The Holy Bible is not only the masterpiece of the world's literature, but it is also the most
majestic exposition of religion ever given to man. It contains the writings of the inspired
prophets of God, and embodies the principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ our Lord. It
enlightens us on the great themes of revealed religion: man, scripture, salvation, faith, prayer,
and immortality. God reigns in heaven and in earth, he is the rightful King of nations, and the
Source of supreme good to men. In his image was man created. Great prophets like Moses,
Isaiah, Hosea, Jeremiah, Daniel, Ezekiel, and Micah were divinely appointed servants, and
they wrote the holy scriptures and inspired the peoples of the ancient world to believe in God
and to hope for the Redeemer of the world. They had the highest possible knowledge of
moral and religious laws.
</p><p>
How one loves to read the Ten Commandments, one of the greatest lessons of the Bible. They
were given to Moses, the prophet, hundreds of years before the birth of the Savior.
</p><p>
Then we have such words from the Jewish Talmud which were written soon after the Ten
Commandments. Let me quote to you a few sentences which show the dignity of the
teachings of ancient Jewish writings.
</p><p>
"The name of the Lord shall be loved through thy treatment of thy fellow man.<br />
"Do God's will as thy own will, submit thy will to his will.<br />
"Be not like servants who serve their master for the sake of reward.<br />
"Thy neighbor's honor must be as dear to thee as thy own.<br />
"Keep aloof from grumbling.<br />
"Do not hate the one who reproves thee.<br />
"If you humble yourself, the Lord will lift you up.<br />
"Pass not judgment upon thy neighbor, until thou has put thyself in his place."
</p><p>
However highly we may estimate the truths we have today, it is for us to understand the
gospel. Rudolph Kittel of Leipzig University wrote some years ago: "Some one has got to rise
to give to the world the doctrines of Jesus Christ, our Savior, for the world is in need of
them." This calls to my mind an experience that some of the actors of the old Salt Lake
Theater had one evening. A noted American actor had just closed the play of <i>Hamlet</i>, and was
about to leave to take the train for San Francisco. Standing in the doorway of the so-called
"Green Room," Mr. Clawson, the manager of the old playhouse, asked him to say a few
words. Mr. Edwin Booth stopped for a minute or two, then said: "It is seldom I speak in
public, but I would like to repeat on this occasion the most beautiful words ever uttered.
Bowing his head he said: 
</p><p>
"Our Father which art in heaven,<br />
Hallowed be thy name.<br />
Thy kingdom come.<br />
Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven."
          (See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/9-10#9">Matt. 6:9-10</a>.)
</p><p>
With these words from the Lord's Prayer, Booth turned and said "Goodbye" to the few people
and walked from the theater to the sidewalk where he took a carriage to the depot.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith has done the mightiest work of all: 
</p><p>
We first see Joseph Smith in the woods on the frontier of America praying
as a child might pray, and the Lord appearing to him. Using the words of the Psalmist,
"Grace is poured into thy lips, therefore, God hath blessed thee forever more"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/45/2#2">Ps. 45:2</a>). With the
Father was Jesus the Savior. Joseph heard the voice of God and the divine words: "This is my
Beloved Son" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>). A new day was at hand. From that moment he was heart and mind for the
word of the Lord. What a message for our missionaries of today!
</p><p>
He learned that day that the divisions of Christendom are its most conspicuous reproach and
the chief cause of its inefficiency. They present a moral affront to the enterprise inaugurated
by Jesus Christ, and constitute the outstanding limitation of its progress. Christianity is
weakened by its divisions in facing the problems of today, among which are class hatreds,
race antagonisms, blindness to social justice, the lure of vicious literature, crime-instigating
narcotics, and the spread of military spirit in the world.
</p><p>
The supreme test of religion is revelation. No religion can be persuasive unless it relies on the
principle of revelation. The living Church of Jesus Christ must be revelatory. One readily sees
that the very lifeblood of the Church is the principle and potency of redemption. Christianity
in its pure sense is the religion of redeemed personality. While all true men reveal God, the
complete carrier of revelation can be no other than a chosen personality.
</p><p>
By the power of the Holy Priesthood which he received from heaven, Joseph Smith
established our true relationship to God. Out of this grows the salvation of man&mdash;his true
immortal life.
</p><p>
The nations all bear witness to the need of a light that is not of man. We can give our word
to the world that the forces which are to make the world the world it ought to be are now
within it.
</p><p>
Thousands, yea millions of people are waiting to hear the voice of our Father in heaven.
Millions are turning to God, and we are in these days of world turmoil experiencing a rising
tide of understanding and goodwill that is constantly ebbing and flowing among us all. The
fact that the movement has been reserved for our day fills us with the deepening sense of our
responsibility and duty to make sure that the golden opportunities it offers are not lost.
</p><p>
"It changes everything.<br />
I can see the end of war in this, some day.<br />
I can see the joy of women and little children&mdash;some day.<br />
I can see the cities and great spaces of land full of happiness.<br />
I can see love shining in every face.<br />
There shall be no more sin, no pain, no loss, no death&mdash;<br />
Only life, only God&mdash;some day when the world shall have learned."
</p><p>
          &mdash;Charles Rann Kennedy
</p><p>
I pray God to bless us all this day. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
