<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Closing Address</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 121-124</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The first speaker of this session, Elder Lee, referred to the "shortest designated highway in the
State," and that shortest highway leads to the penitentiary. His excellent discourse and the
inspirational discourses of the other Brethren who have followed him have inspired us all. The
spirit of the Lord is here, and what I am going to say in a few words I hope will be in harmony with
the spirit of those addresses.
</p><p>
That reference to the highway reminded me of something to which we should have called the
attention of 31,000 men of the priesthood last evening.  But now I am glad that I overlooked
it, for here is a better time and place, I think, to mention it.  It refers to a number of young
people who get on that shortest of highways.  For several years we have asked the bishops to
help us to protect them from getting on that highway.  For a while we received help, and then
that help practically ceased. There are two members of the Council of the Twelve appointed
to receive your suggestions and recommendations, but these two members are helpless without
your suggestions.
</p><p>
In brief, many of our young girls, particularly, and not a few of our young boys, leave their
homes, with the consent of parents, sometimes without the consent, and they come to larger
centers in hopes of bettering their financial conditions, probably social conditions; and without
proper guidance, without help, not a few get on that one-way road. And so we have asked
that whenever one of those girls or one of the boys leaves home to come to the city, the
bishop will send word to Elder Spencer W. Kimball or Elder Mark E. Petersen giving the
home town address, and, if possible, the address of the boy or girl in Salt Lake City, Ogden,
or some other center.
</p><p>
The ward teachers should know the name of that boy and the name of that girl, for it is his
duty "to watch over the church always, to be with and strengthen them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>). If
the teacher will notify the bishop that one of the members of his district is leaving home, and
the bishop will inform the committee of the Twelve of the fact, safeguards can be put around
the young person.  They are not bad boys or bad girls, intrinsically, but there are traps into
which they may fall here and be caught in sin, as we have heard. Bishops, will you please do
that? Ward teachers throughout the Church, will you please watch over the Church
always&mdash;over those who are sick, those who need your help, and particularly some of these
discouraged young people?
</p><p>
      I think the thought that I am trying to get over is well expressed by that poem which
the Presiding Bishopric has put into the hands of the lesser priesthood of the Church. It is a
follows: 
</p><p>
"He stood at the crossroads all alone<br />
      The sunlight in his face; <br />
      He had no thought for the world unknown,<br />
      He was set for a manly race.<br />
      But the roads stretched east and the roads stretched west,<br />
      And the lad knew not which road was best.<br />
      So he chose the road that led him down,<br />
      And he lost the race and the victor's crown.<br />
      He was caught at last in an angry snare,<br />
      Because no one stood at the crossroads there<br />
      To show him the better road.
</p><p>
"Another day at the selfsame place,<br />
      A boy with high hopes stood,<br />
      He too was set for a manly race,<br />
      He too was seeking the things that were good,<br />
      But one was there who the roads did know<br />
      And that one showed him which way to go.<br />
      So he turned from the road that would lead him down,<br />
      And he won the race and the victor's crown.<br />
      He walks today the highway fair<br />
      Because one stood at the crossroads there
      To show him the better way."
</p><p>
We are just reminding you bishops of this safeguard.  How effective the protection or
guidance, though, depends upon you, and more upon the ward teacher.
</p><p>
As this conference draws to a close, my heart is full of appreciation.  This has been a great
conference.  Do you know how many have contributed to its success?  I want to point out a
few even at the risk of omitting merited names.
</p><p>
I have mentioned those who beforehand wished to make attractive and beautiful the rostrum
and express their love in flowers.  Again we mention them.
</p><p>
Throughout the sessions we have expressed our gratitude to the radio stations and television
stations, making it possible for tens of thousands to hear the message of the gospel from these
leaders, and how impressively, eloquently they have given their messages.
</p><p>
We have said "thank you" to the members of the choirs, but let me mention them again: The
Brigham Young University choruses, with Brother Ralph Woodward and Brother Crawford
Gates conducting.  Those young people&mdash;you will never forget that picture&mdash;filling the seats
of the choir and overflowing into the galleries, young people with high hopes, young people
with faith, young people of purity.  We appreciate what they did.
</p><p>
And even more impressive, if that could be, our Singing Mothers! I cannot mention the name
"mother" without being overcome with emotion.  Those mothers who furnished that singing
were the mothers of 1600 children! Even their title, "Singing Mothers," tells a story of
sacrifice, a story of love, a story of home.  No wonder they could sing the songs of Zion so
inspirationally under the masterful leadership of Sister Florence Jepperson Madsen.
</p><p>
Then there was the Reno Latter-day Saints male chorus under Ladd R. Cropper,
director&mdash;whose singing inspired 31,000 members of the priesthood last night.  We thank them.
</p><p>
And today the Tabernacle Choir, singing the songs which inspired thousands in Europe. And
when they sing the closing song, try to picture yourself listening to them in London or in Glasgow or
Paris, Switzerland, Holland, or East Germany, and see those audiences filled with enthusiasm,
inspired, as this wonderful choir sang, "Come, Come, Ye Saints." It is said that our "echoes
roll from soul to soul, and go forever and forever." Well, the echoes of those choruses are
rolling in the souls of thousands over in Europe and will continue so to do for a long time to
come.  To Director Cornwall and the organists we again express appreciation.
</p><p>
Not many of you, I think, have noticed how attentive, how considerate, how prompt have
been the ushers under the direction of Bishop Isaacson.  They have spent hours here since
conference began&mdash;during meeting, between sessions&mdash;from morning till night.  We extend
to you ushers thanks for your courtesy, consideration, and the very excellent way in which
you have directed the affairs put into your hands.
</p><p>
I have often spoken about the attention given by our police department. I do not know that
they have ever rendered greater service than they have throughout this conference.  You who
have had to travel around this block have noticed three of our policemen, courteously
watching to see that no accident occurs: here on the south gate two men; at the west gate
another; out at the north gate another; and others at crowded intersections throughout the city. 
To the mayor and city council, chief of police, and to all the members of that force we say
"thank you" this day. To the Red Cross who have been here faithfully to render any help to
those in need, to the fire department, members of which have stood on guard in case of some
accident, to the reporters who have reported the exercises so efficiently and accurately&mdash;to all
of you, we express sincere appreciation.
</p><p>
Now I should like to express appreciation for a group of workers not connected directly with
this conference but who are energetically contributing to the advancement of
the work of the Lord: the volunteer labor missionaries who are down in New Zealand, down
in Hawaii, who will be in Mexico and other places where schools and temples are being built;
we should like them to know that we have them in mind and that they have our blessing, able
businessmen, skilled in carpentry, cement work, steel work.  Not many in the Church know
what they are doing.  But it is a great force of skilled workmen contributing to the upbuilding
of the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
And we shall mention, too, the young men who accept one-year, two-year mission calls to lay
bricks, or to drive trucks, repair machinery, etc.  Young men, we appreciate what you are
doing. It is a great school for you, and you learn much even while you contribute your time
and effort.
</p><p>
Finally, I wish to express gratitude to my beloved associates, the General Authorities, who so
kindly and considerately made mention of my half century of service in the Council of the
Twelve. It was most gracious of you to express your congratulations and particularly your
loyalty.  The words coming from your hearts as they did touched me deeply.
</p><p>
Next to the affection we have for our home and loved ones, we prize the loyalty of friends,
but even more precious is the true feeling of brotherhood in Christ. This choicest of all
blessings in human association in the Church has been most manifest during this conference
ever since our meeting referred to by Brother Kimball of the General Authorities in the house
of the Lord last Thursday morning, and as expressed throughout this conference.  Truly, we
can sense more clearly than ever what John the apostle had in mind when he wrote, "We
know that we have passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/3/14#14">1 Jn. 3:14</a>).
And I wish to tell you auxiliary workers and you members in the priesthood quorums of
stakes and wards, that the Brethren love you just that way.
</p><p>
And what the Primary is doing&mdash;you could see by the reports of the great convention, and
the high percentage of children that they have in attendance at their weekly meetings&mdash;they
are doing just what you brethren have asked them to do.  The Young Women's Mutual
Improvement Association has enrolled every girl in the Church.  They will help you
teachers&mdash;your local Young Women's Association and its officers&mdash;to find out when one of the girls is
moving to another place, and they will be there to welcome them and to try to help them. The
Young Men's Mutual Improvement Association in their competitive games, in their cultural,
inspirational meetings&mdash;what a wonderful work they are doing! So, also, the great Sunday
School cause, and our mothers in Relief Society&mdash;where in all the world can you find so
many groups working so efficiently&mdash;helps in government, as guides to your children&mdash;as
you find in the Church of Jesus Christ!
</p><p>
We are not boasting; we are just stating facts.  We might not say it to you officers of these
auxiliaries, but we love you, and in our hearts are prayers for your success.  And the
priesthood quorums, the deacons and the Aaronic Priesthood, the teachers and the
priests&mdash;there again, every one enrolled, an opportunity for every boy to be active; instead of having
the gang-spirit, where the members try to destroy or to interfere with the ease and comfort of
others, we have them active and rendering service to others.  And that means, as President
Clark stated, over a hundred thousand of them, and the Presiding Bishopric bringing in the
Senior Aaronic members; then the Melchizedek, the elders, seventies, and high priests&mdash;there
is where we touch our home life.
</p><p>
There are three parables to which I shall refer and close, all relating to lost ones.  What I
have said relates to preventing them from getting on the highway that leads to the detention
home or to the penitentiary. Christ gave three parables which you will find in the 15th chapter
of Luke. One is the parable of the Lost Sheep which wandered away from the flock
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/1-7#1">Luke 15:1-7</a>); the
second was the loss of one of Ten Pieces of Silver by a housewife
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/8-10#8">Luke 15:8-10</a>); and the third was the
Prodigal Son (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/11-32#11">Luke 15:11-32</a>).
</p><p>
The first referred to one that just simply wandered because it wanted to seek the best in
sustenance of life; there was no sin involved. It became so engrossed in its
own welfare that it wandered away from the flock.
</p><p>
The second was largely due to carelessness, neglect; and the third was a determination to an
abandonment to a life of indulgence and sin.
</p><p>
Now you will find many in the Church of these boys and girls who drift from the Church because
of other interests.  They are not bad boys. Find them, bring them back into activity in the
fold.
</p><p>
In the second parable, the parents, through carelessness, let the girls go, or the girls defy
parental interference or authority. Often the boys start out with wrong companions. You know
how to deal with them&mdash;get them, too, into activity.
</p><p>
The third, the prodigal son or the prodigal girl who goes down the line, who refuses the
invitation to come back, refuses to enter into the activity of the Church&mdash;such a one, as did
the prodigal son, will go, I suppose, until he comes to himself and then, as President Richards
so eloquently expressed today, the spirit of repentance and the spirit of forgiveness will be
operative.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, may our Heavenly Father sanctify the instructions, admonitions, and
testimonies that we have heard throughout this great and memorable conference.  May he fill
our hearts with love for one another in the true brotherhood of Christ.  May that love in our
homes, in our groups, in priesthood, and in the auxiliaries radiate so-effectively that others
seeing our good lives may be led to glorify our Father in heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>), I pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
