<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"He Is Risen"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 118-122</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Humbly and gratefully I approach this sacred assignment.
</p><p>
As the ancient Apostle declared on the Mount of Transfiguration: ". . . it is good for us to be
here" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/4#4">Matt. 17:4</a>).
</p><p>
I am grateful to President David O. McKay, whom I sustain as a prophet of God, for inviting
Sister Benson and me to attend this great conference, even though we had not expected it, and
even though it is not easy to leave the mission field.
</p><p>
Have you ever attended a mission-wide conference of more than two hundred devoted,
enthusiastic, wonderful missionaries? We were in the midst of a series of such inspiring
meetings when President McKay's cablegram arrived. In fact, we concluded one of these
missionary conferences in Dusseldorf, Germany, only Wednesday, April 1. It was, I believe,
the best April First Day I have ever spent.
</p><p>
We bring you the love and greetings of 2100 of some of the finest young
men and women to be found anywhere, your sons and daughters. They are not perfect, but I
say to you, they are a credit to their loved ones, their communities, and the Church. I know
the Lord loves them and is magnifying them, at times even beyond their natural abilities,
which is one of the most soul-satisfying experiences that can come to man.
</p><p>
We bring you warm greetings from twelve dedicated mission presidents and their devoted
companions.
</p><p>
We also bring you the love and fellowship of tens of thousands of faithful members&mdash;many
of them new in the Church&mdash;from Norway, Sweden, Finland, Denmark, Switzerland, Austria,
and Germany, who love the Lord and his work and rejoice in the brotherhood they enjoy in
the Church.
</p><p>
It is a high and sacred honor to bear witness to the divine mission of Jesus Christ; to
represent his great Church; to be an ambassador of truth to our Father's children; to be called
by a prophet of the Lord to go into the world and proclaim the glad tidings that God has
again spoken from the heavens: that the heavens are not sealed, that God still communicates
with men on the earth, and that the pure gospel of Jesus Christ has again been restored to the
earth in its fullness.
</p><p>
I rejoice in this glorious privilege, thank the Lord for this rich opportunity and blessing, and
bear solemn witness to the truth of these things.
</p><p>
We meet here in this great conference with a prayer of gratitude in our hearts and on our lips
for the privilege of living in this choice period when the light of truth has burst forth. We
meet in a great Christian nation&mdash;a nation with a solid spiritual foundation&mdash;a nation
departing from its basic concepts.
</p><p>
As a people we have just joined with others of the Christian world in the celebration of
Easter. Today flags are at half mast as we mourn the passing of a great patriot, General
Douglas MacArthur, and the sweet wife of our beloved Brother S. Dilworth Young. It is,
therefore, most fitting that we consider together that most glorious event, the resurrection of
the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Testimony: Jesus Is the Christ</b>
</p><p>
I bear witness to you that Jesus is the Christ, the Savior and Redeemer of the world&mdash;the
very Son of God.
</p><p>
He was <i>born</i> the babe of Bethlehem.
</p><p>
He <i>lived</i> and ministered among men.
</p><p>
He was <i>crucified</i> on Calvary.
</p><p>
His friends <i>deserted</i> him.
</p><p>
His closest associates did not fully <i>understand</i> his mission, and they <i>doubted</i>. One of the most
trusted <i>denied</i> knowing him.
</p><p>
A pagan governor, struggling with his conscience after consenting to Jesus' death, caused a
sign to be erected over the cross proclaiming him "JESUS OF NAZARETH THE KING OF
THE JEWS" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/19/19#19">John 19:19</a>).
</p><p>
He asked <i>forgiveness</i> for his tormentors and then willingly gave up his life.
</p><p>
His body was <i>laid</i> in a borrowed tomb.
</p><p>
An immense stone was placed over the opening.
</p><p>
In the minds of his stunned followers over and over echoed some of his last words, ". . . be
of good cheer; I have overcome the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>).
</p><p>
On the third day there was a great earthquake. The stone was rolled back from the door of the
tomb. Some of the women, among the most devoted of his followers, came to the place with
spices "and found not the body of the Lord Jesus"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/3#3">Luke 24:3</a>).
</p><p>
Angels appeared and said simply, "Why seek ye the living among the dead?
</p><p>
"He is not here, but is risen" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/5-6#5">Luke 24:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
There is nothing in history to equal that dramatic announcement: "He is not here, but is
risen."
</p><p>
<b>"He is Risen"</b>
</p><p>
The greatest events of history are those which affect the greatest number for the longest
periods. By this standard, no event could be more important to individuals or nations than the
resurrection of the Master. The eventual resurrection of every soul who has lived and died on
earth is a scriptural certainty, and surely there is no event for which one
should make more careful preparation. Nothing is more absolutely universal than the
resurrection. Every living being will be resurrected. ". . . as in Adam all die, even so in Christ
shall all be made alive" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/22#22">1 Cor. 15:22</a>).
</p><p>
There are those, however, who act as though they do not believe in eternity or a resurrection.
They cower at the thought of nuclear war, and to save their own bodies they would have
peace at any price. Yet the best assurance of peace and life is to be strong morally and
militarily. But they want life at the sacrifice of principles. Rather than choose liberty or death,
they prefer life with slavery. But they overlook a crucial scripture ". . . fear not them which
kill the body but are not able to kill the soul; but rather fear him which is able to destroy both
soul and body in hell" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/28#28">Matt. 10:28</a>).
The Lord could, I suppose, have avoided the war in
heaven over free agency. All he needed to do was to compromise with the devil, but had he
done so he would have ceased to be God.
</p><p>
While it is more difficult to live the truth, such as standing for free agency, some of us may
in the not-too-distant future be required to die for the truth. But the best preparation for
eternal life is to be prepared at all times to die&mdash;fully prepared by a valiant fight for right.
</p><p>
Let us act like men, men who are sons of God, men with a sure knowledge that there will be
a resurrection and a final judgment.
</p><p>
Yes, the resurrection of Jesus Christ is a glorious reality. He became the firstfruits of them
that slept (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/20#20">1 Cor. 15:20</a>).
He truly rose from the tomb the third day, as he and his prophets foretold, and
became in very deed "the resurrection and the life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25#25">John 11:25</a>).
He broke the bonds of death for all of us.
We, too, will be resurrected. Our spirits will be reunited with our bodies.
</p><p>
Later the Risen Lord appeared to other women, to the two disciples on the road to Emmaus,
to Peter, to the Apostles, and "after that," as reported by Paul, "he was seen of about five
hundred brethren at once."
</p><p>
"And last of all," continued Paul, "he was seen of me also"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/6,8#6">1 Cor. 15:6,8</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Resurrection, A Glorious Reality</b>
</p><p>
Yes, Christ's resurrection was abundantly verified. The witnesses are many. Throughout the
forty days following his resurrection the Lord manifested himself at intervals and gave
instructions in the things pertaining to the kingdom of God. Much that he said and did is not
written, but such things as are of record, John assures us, ". . . are written, that ye might
believe that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God; and that believing ye might have life through
his name" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/31#31">John 20:31</a>).
</p><p>
He had told his followers that he must soon ascend unto his Father in heaven. And as the time
of his ascension drew nigh, the Lord in that last solemn interview gave his parting instructions
to his disciples.
</p><p>
And when Christ and the disciples had gone, "as far as to Bethany" where Mary, Martha, and
Lazarus lived, the Lord lifted his hands and blessed them. And while he yet spoke he rose
from their midst until a cloud received him from out of their sight. As the Apostles stood
gazing steadfastly upward, two personages clothed in white apparel appeared by them. They
spoke unto the eleven saying, "Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? this
same Jesus, which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have
seen him go into heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/9-11#9">Acts 1:9-11</a>,
also <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/50-51#50">Luke 24:50-51</a>).
</p><p>
Worshipfully, and with great joy the Apostles returned to Jerusalem. The Lord's ascension
was accomplished. It was truly a literal departure of a material being, as his resurrection had
been an actual return of his spirit to his own physical body. Now the disciples began to
comprehend more fully that he had truly overcome the world. Not that he had displaced
Caesar or even Pilate who ruled over Judea. The great majority of the world's people had still
not even heard of him. Not that man's inhumanity to man was suddenly wiped out. But there
was victory over the grave, always, until then, the final conqueror of all
men.
</p><p>
<b>His Kingdom Not of This World</b>
</p><p>
Then the realization began to dawn on his faithful followers that his kingdom was not of this
world. He had overcome the world of hate, envy, greed, and lust. He had shown the way for
man to break the chains of selfishness and vengeance which had bound him, doomed him to
mediocrity, a prisoner of his own misconceptions. His disciples were quickened with a
realization that this was what he had been teaching them. This was what his life had spelled
out to them. More clear became his ringing words, "Ye have heard that it hath been said,
Thou shalt love thy neighbour, and hate thine enemy.
</p><p>
"But I say unto you, Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate
you, and pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/43-44#43">Matt. 5:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, the Lord Jesus Christ liberated man from the world by the pure gospel of love. He
demonstrated that man through the love of God and through kindness and charity to his
fellows could achieve his highest potential. He lived the plain and sure doctrine of service, of
doing good to all men, friends and enemies alike. His charge to return good for evil is still
the greatest challenge to the mind of man. At the same time it is man's greatest weapon.
</p><p>
<b>Impact of His Life</b>
</p><p>
No other single influence has had so great an impact on this earth as the life of Jesus the
Christ. We cannot conceive of our lives without his teachings. Without him we would be lost
in a mirage of beliefs and worships, born in fear and darkness where the sensual and
materialistic hold sway. We are far short of the goal he set for us, but we must never lose
sight of it; nor must we forget that our great climb toward the light, toward perfection, would
not be possible except for his teachings, his life, his death, and his resurrection.
</p><p>
May God hasten the day when people everywhere will accept his teachings, his example, and
his divinity, yes, when they will accept as a reality his glorious resurrection which broke the
bonds of death for all of us.
</p><p>
Yes, we must learn and learn again that only through accepting and living the gospel of love
as taught by the Master, and only through doing his will can we break the bonds of ignorance
and doubt that bind us. We must learn this simple, glorious truth so that we can experience
the sweet joys of the spirit now and eternally. We must lose ourselves in doing his will. We
must place him first in our lives. Yes, our blessings multiply as we share his love with our
neighbor.
</p><p>
To the extent that we stray from the path marked out for us by the Man of Galilee, to that
extent we are failing in our individual battles to overcome our worlds. But we are not without
his help. Again and again he told his disciples, and all of us, "Let not your heart be troubled"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1#1">John 14:1</a>).
</p><p>
"If ye shall ask any thing in my name, I will do it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/14#14">John 14:14</a>).
</p><p>
"I will not leave you comfortless"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/18#18">John 14:18</a>).
</p><p>
"Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
<b>His Comforting Spirit</b>
</p><p>
We feel his comforting spirit in the sweet prayer of a child and the quiet abiding faith of all
who have let his gospel permeate their lives. What a priceless gift it is that we can know him
through our own prayers and through the sacred and solemn testimonies of those that have
seen him, known him, felt his presence.
</p><p>
On this spring day more than 1900 years after his resurrection, I give you my solemn witness
and testimony that I know that Jesus the Christ lives. He was in very deed raised from the
dead as we shall be. He is "the resurrection and the life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25#25">John 11:25</a>). He appeared unto many in the
Old World after his resurrection and according to modern scriptures, sacred to me and to
Latter-day Saints everywhere, he spent three glorious days before his final ascension with his
"other sheep" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/16#16">John 10:16</a>)
here in America, the new world.
</p><p>
By him and through him and his gospel, God the Father has made it possible for you and me
to overcome the world.
</p><p>
Yes, my friends, Jesus is the Christ. He lives. He did break the bonds of death. He is more
than "a great moral teacher." He is our Savior and Redeemer, the very Son of God. And he
will come again. ". . . this same Jesus, which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come
in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
<b>His Church Restored</b>
</p><p>
Yes, this same Jesus has already come to earth in our day. The Resurrected Christ&mdash;glorified,
exalted, the God of this world under the Father&mdash;appeared to the boy Joseph Smith in 1820.
This same Jesus who was the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, the God of Moses, the
Creator of this earth, has come in our day. He was introduced by the Father to Joseph Smith
in these words:
</p><p>
"<i>This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
The appearance of God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ to the boy Prophet is the greatest
event that has occurred in this world since the resurrection of the Master. As the restored
Church of Jesus Christ we humbly and gratefully bear this witness to all men. This message is
a world message. It is the truth. More than two million members of the Church throughout the
world bear this solemn testimony.
</p><p>
Today thousands of faithful missionaries at home and abroad freely carry this all-important
message to the world. Jesus is the Christ, the Savior of mankind, the Redeemer of the world,
the very Son of God. He is the God of this world, our advocate with the Father.
</p><p>
Today 16,000 missionary-messengers of truth, and the more than two million members of The
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints&mdash;the Mormon Church&mdash;bear witness that God
has again spoken from the heavens, that Jesus Christ has appeared again unto man, that the
resurrection is a reality.
</p><p>
Today I testify to the truth of the message which they bear and add my solemn witness, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
