<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">One Lord, One Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 87-91</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I rejoice with you, my brethren and sisters, in this wonderful conference, and in the inspiring
remarks of our worthy president, President David O. McKay.
</p><p>
We have just listened to Bishop Simpson as he quoted the statement of Jesus, when he said:
"And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>). I ask, free from
what? The false teachings and philosophies and man-made doctrines.
</p><p>
Jesus said: "I thank thee, O Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because thou hast hid these
things from the wise and prudent, and hast revealed them unto babes"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/25#25">Matt. 11:25</a>).
</p><p>
With man's wisdom alone, one cannot know the truth. This is evidenced by a survey taken in
New Zealand last year, in which there were 411 different churches listed. Hence the need of
divine revelation to interpret the teachings of the prophets, and this church is built upon
divine revelation.
</p><p>
<b>A marvelous work and a wonder</b>
</p><p>
I take my text today from the twenty-ninth chapter of Isaiah, where he states: "Wherefore the
Lord said, Forasmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do
honour me, but have removed their heart far from me, and their fear toward me is taught by
the precept of men: 
</p><p>
"Therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvelous work among this people, even a
marvelous work and a wonder: for the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the
understanding of their prudent men shall be hid"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/13-14#13">Isa. 29:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
Where do we find these precepts of men to which Isaiah refers? In these 411 different
religious professions.
</p><p>
Shouldn't the average son of God want to know if he is worshiping God through the precepts
of men? Or, if he is privileged to live until the Lord performs that marvelous work and a
wonder, wouldn't he like to have a part in it?
</p><p>
Compare this situation to Paul's statement to the Ephesians when he said there is "one Lord,
one faith, one baptism" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/5#5">Eph. 4:5</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Difference between man-made and divine doctrines</b>
</p><p>
How things have changed! Why? Because men, without divine guidance, could not agree in
their interpretation of the scriptures. Jesus understood that without divine guidance men could
not properly interpret the scriptures, for he said: "Ye do err, not knowing the scriptures"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/29#29">Matt. 22:29</a>).
Hence the need of the voice of authority to differentiate between the doctrines
that are the precepts of men, as Isaiah states, and the truths revealed from heaven in the
restoration of the gospel, for we did not get our teachings through man's interpretation of the
scriptures, but by the revelations of the Lord to his latter-day prophet.
</p><p>
A whole book could be written on the difference between the man-made doctrines to which
Isaiah refers and the truths revealed from heaven which constitute the marvelous work and a
wonder that the Lord promised through Isaiah would cause the wisdom of their wise men to
perish and the understanding of their prudent men to be hid.
</p><p>
Let me mention a few important corrections the Lord has made in the teachings of men
through the restoration of the gospel.
</p><p>
<b>Teachings on Godhead</b>
</p><p>
When the Lord gave to Moses the Ten Commandments, the first was:  "Thou shalt have no
other gods before me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3#3">Ex. 20:3</a>).
</p><p>
When Joseph Smith had his glorious vision and the Father and the Son appeared to him in the
Sacred Grove in the state of New York in 1820, the Father, pointing to the Son, said: <i>"This is
my Beloved Son. Hear Him!"</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
Thus Joseph saw that Jesus and his Father were glorified persons, as was Jesus following his
resurrection, when he appeared unto his disciples and had them feel the prints in his hands
and the wound in his side, saying: ". . . handle me, and see; for a spirit hath not flesh and
bones, as ye see me have" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/39#39">Luke 24:39</a>).
</p><p>
Now compare this with the teaching of the entire Christian world at the time that Joseph
Smith had this glorious experience. Here is a statement from their creeds: 
</p><p>
"There is but one living and true God, who is infinite in being and perfection, a most pure
spirit, invisible, without body, parts or passions . . . and in unity of this godhead, there are
three persons, of one substance, power and eternity, the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghost."
</p><p>
How could there be three persons in one? How could Joseph Smith or any other prophet have
seen God if he has neither body, parts, nor passions, and is invisible? That means he has no
eyes, so he cannot see; he has no ears, so he cannot hear; he has no mouth, so he cannot
speak; he has no body, so he cannot be seen. This is a fairly good description of nothing.
How is it possible that the entire world was worshiping this kind of a god at the time that the
Father and Son, two glorified personages, appeared to Joseph Smith
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>)?
</p><p>
<b>Condition foretold by Moses</b>
</p><p>
And yet Moses knew that this condition would exist in the world, for when he led the
children of Israel to the promised land, he told them that, in coming generations, they should
be scattered among the heathen nations. "And there ye shall serve gods, the work of men's
hands, wood and stone, which neither see, nor hear, nor eat, nor smell"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/4/28#28">Deut. 4:28</a>).
</p><p>
Then Moses promised them that in the latter days (and we are living in the latter days) when
they were in tribulation, if they would seek after the Lord their God, they would find him if
they would seek him with all their hearts and with all their souls (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/4/29-30#29">Deut. 4:29-30</a>).
</p><p>
Joseph Smith as a boy truly sought after him and was rewarded with the glorious vision to
which I have referred. And for his testimony that God, the Father, and Jesus Christ, his Son,
were two glorified personages, he gave his life. We bear witness to all the world of this great
eternal truth. What knowledge could be more wonderful than to know what we might look
forward to, as Jesus said in the Sermon on the Mount: "Blessed are the pure in heart: for they
shall <i>see</i> God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/8#8">Matt. 5:8</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
How could we see God if he does not exist, has no body, parts, or passions, and is invisible?
</p><p>
To correct this false doctrine should justify the Lord in raising up a prophet in these latter
days, and this gives real meaning to Easter, which the Christian world is celebrating at this
time.
</p><p>
Through the restoration of the gospel through the Prophet Joseph Smith, the Lord corrects
another false teaching, one of the doctrines of men to which Isaiah refers. The Christian world
teaches that children are born into this world with the sin of Adam and Eve resting upon
them, thus denying the atonement of Jesus Christ, as stated by the apostle Paul: "For as in
Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/22#22">1 Cor. 15:22</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Little children redeemed through Christ</b>
</p><p>
Now here is the word of the Lord with respect to this matter in a revelation to the Prophet
Joseph Smith: "But, behold, I say unto you, that little children are redeemed from the
foundation of the world through mine Only Begotten; 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, they cannot sin, for power is not given unto Satan to tempt little children, until
they begin to become accountable before me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/46-47#46">D&amp;C 29:46-47</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Mormon discussed this subject in a letter to his son, Moroni, as recorded in the
Book of Mormon in these words: 
</p><p>
"And now, my son, I speak unto you concerning that which grieveth me exceedingly; for it
grieveth me that there should disputations rise among you.
</p><p>
"For, if I have learned the truth, there have been disputations among you concerning the
baptism of your little children.
</p><p>
"And now, my son, I desire that ye should labor diligently, that this gross error should be
removed from among you; for, for this intent I have written this epistle.
</p><p>
"For immediately
after I had learned these things of you I inquired of the Lord concerning the matter. And the
word of the Lord came to me by the power of the Holy Ghost, saying:
</p><p>
"Listen to the words
of Christ, your Redeemer, your Lord and your God. Behold, I came into the world not to call
the righteous but sinners to repentance; the whole need no physician, but they that are sick;
wherefore, little children are whole, for they are not capable of committing sin;
wherefore the curse of Adam is taken from them in me, that it hath no power over them . . .
</p><p>
"And after this manner did the Holy Ghost manifest the word of God unto me; wherefore, my
beloved son, I know that it is solemn mockery before God, that ye should baptize little
children.
</p><p>
"Little children cannot repent; wherefore, it is awful wickedness to deny the pure mercies of
God unto them, for they are all alive in him because of his mercy.
</p><p>
"And he that saith that little children need baptism denieth the mercies of Christ, and setteth
at naught the atonement of him and the power of the redemption"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/8/4-9,19-20#4">Moro. 8:4-9,19-20</a>).
</p><p>
Shouldn't the whole Christian world welcome this great revealed truth to save them from
following this man-made doctrine that they have been taught?
</p><p>
<b>Marriage for time and eternity</b>
</p><p>
Let me briefly mention another man-made and very important doctrine taught by all the
so-called Christian churches at the time the Lord restored his true Church to the earth in this
last dispensation through the Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
They have universally taught that marriage is for this life only, hence their marriages are all
performed "until death do you part" or "for the period of your mortal lives."
</p><p>
In light of God's restored truth to us, this is a very flimsy and unsatisfactory doctrine. Love is
eternal, and where couples live true Christian lives together, their love for each other and their
children increases with the years.
</p><p>
I like the words of Anderson M. Baten to his wife, Beulah, entitled "Philosophy of Life": 
</p><p>
"I wed thee forever, not for now,<br />
     Not for the sham of earth's brief years; <br />
     I wed thee for the life beyond the tears<br />
     Beyond the heart pain and clouded brow.<br />
     Love knows no grave and it shall guide us dear<br />
     When life's spent candles flutter and burn low."
</p><p>
The apostle Paul indicated that we without our loved ones cannot be made perfect (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/40#40">Heb. 11:40</a>).
The Lord has revealed the fact that marriage ties are intended to be eternal, hence all
marriages in his Church are for time and for all eternity.
</p><p>
<b>Scriptural affirmation</b>
</p><p>
The first record we have of marriage was when the Lord told Adam, "It is not good that the
man should be alone; I will make him an help meet for him . . .
</p><p>
"Therefore shall a man leave his father and his mother, and shall cleave unto his wife: and
they shall be one flesh" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18,24#18">Gen. 2:18,24</a>).
</p><p>
If it was not good for man to be alone before death came into the world, it will obviously not
be good for man to be alone when he is resurrected from the dead.
</p><p>
Jesus also taught this principle, for he said:
</p><p>
"For this cause shall a man leave his father and mother, and cleave to his wife;
</p><p>
"And they twain shall be one flesh: so then they are no more twain, but one flesh.
</p><p>
"What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/7-9#7">Mark 10:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
Both God
and Jesus Christ indicated that the man and his wife should become one flesh, and Jesus
warns: "What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder."
</p><p>
Where is there any scriptural justification to assume and teach that death should annul the
marriage covenant?
</p><p>
The apostle Peter understood that the man and his wife would inherit together the results and
the rewards of this life. He said:
</p><p>
"Likewise, ye husbands, dwell with them according to knowledge, giving honour unto the
wife, as unto the weaker vessel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life; that your
prayers be not hindered" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/7#7">1 Pet. 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Isaiah saw the day when we would have a new heaven and a new earth, when
we would build houses and inhabit them, and plant vineyards and eat the fruit thereof. Then
he adds: "For they are the seed of the blessed of the Lord, and their offspring with them"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/65/17,19-25#17">Isa. 65:17,19-25</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Reality of resurrection</b>
</p><p>
What a comfort to those of us who have buried our little children to know that we will be
privileged in the resurrection to raise our little ones unto manhood and womanhood.
</p><p>
The man-made doctrines of the so-called Christian churches give their members no such
promises of comfort.
</p><p>
I attended a funeral service for an only young daughter of one of my business associates, and
the minister did not hold out one hope to this sorrowing couple that they would ever see or
know their precious little daughter again.
</p><p>
After the funeral, I told my friend that the Lord had something better than that for him if he
would live for it. He has since joined the Lord's true Church and now looks forward to the
privilege of raising that little daughter in the morning of the first resurrection.
</p><p>
In a revelation to the Prophet Joseph Smith, the Lord said, referring to the conditions during
the millennium: 
</p><p>
"And the earth shall be given unto them for an inheritance; and they shall multiply and wax
strong, and their children shall grow up without sin unto salvation.
</p><p>
"For the Lord shall be in their midst, and his glory shall be upon them, and he will be their
king and their lawgiver" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/58-59#58">D&amp;C 45:58-59</a>).
</p><p>
There are many other man-made interpretations of the scriptures that have brought into
existence these 411 different churches referred to in New Zealand. Isaiah prophesied that
when men should serve God through the precepts and doctrines of men, the Lord would
proceed to do a marvelous work and a wonder that would cause the wisdom of their wise men
to perish and the understanding of their prudent men to be hid
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/13-14#13">Isa. 29:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Church that Isaiah promised</b>
</p><p>
I testify that this Church is the marvelous work and a wonder that Isaiah promised when men
would be worshiping through the precepts of men.
</p><p>
Recently, a converted minister joined the Church. He sat in my office and made this
statement: "When I think of how little I had to offer my people as a minister of the gospel
compared with what I now have in the fullness of the gospel as it has been restored, I want to
go back and tell all my friends what I have found. Now," he said, "they will not listen to me.
I am an apostate from their church." But he gave up his ministry and performed menial work
here in the city in order that he might be a member of God's true Church.
</p><p>
We invite all men everywhere to share with us these glorious truths that God has revealed
through his prophet of this dispensation. I repeat the Savior's promise: "Blessed are they
which do hunger and thirst after righteousness: for they shall be filled"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/6#6">Matt. 5:6</a>).
</p><p>
I bear witness to all within the sound of my voice that The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints is in very deed the marvelous work and a wonder the Lord promised
through Isaiah the prophet.
</p><p>
May God bless you all, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
