<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Peace and Brotherhood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Albert Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1958, pp. 47-48</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brothers and sisters: This has been a glorious six
months&mdash;glorious not in the fact that I have been able to meet the challenges which almost
daily pertain to this call, but glorious in the opportunity of teaching the gospel and of meeting
with the Saints.  May I take this occasion to express my gratitude to those who have been so
kind and hospitable to me.
</p><p>
I would like to extend my personal welcome to President Critchlow and Elder Dyer.  I know
the reception they are going to receive from these Brethren. This has been a glorious six
months in association with these men. They have been kind, considerate, and helpful. When
you consider the varied talents they bring and the many walks of life that this group of men
represent, when you know the individual strength and power that they bring, it is a marvelous
thing to me to see the harmonious, intelligent unity that exists among these brethren.
</p><p>
And as I understand it, it is the mission of the Church to develop and extend this unity and
brotherhood throughout the world.
</p><p>
How can peace come without brotherhood?  What is peace?  Is peace the cessation of
hostilities? Is peace a cold, rather than a hot war?  Is peace coexistence? Is peace to live and
let live? Is peace a relationship based on force? Is peace servitude and slavery based on
power?  What is it that brings peace: arms, bombs, pacts, arbitration, and compromise?  What
perpetuates peace: armies and navies, planes and missiles, and anti-missile missiles? What is
the basis of peace? Is it based on a balance of power?  I think that each one of us would have
to answer that it is none of these, and that at best they are but temporary measures.
</p><p>
What is peace based on?  May I try to illustrate it with a story with which I think
many of you are acquainted.  It is entitled "Abram and Zimri" by Clarence Cook.  Two
brothers farmed together.  Abram had a wife and seven sons.  Zimri lived alone.  At harvest
time the crop was divided equally. Zimri lay in bed and thought: "Here am I, just one mouth
to feed, while my brother Abram has a wife and many sons.  I must go to the field and share
my half with my brother, Abram." So he girded himself and went down and gave a generous
third of his portion to his brother.
</p><p>
Abram, on the other hand, thought that same night: "Here am I with a wife and seven
sons&mdash;someone to share my load and to work with me. Here is my brother, Zimri, he works alone
and has no one to help. I shall gird myself and go down to the field and share my portion
with him." And he took a generous third and put it with Zimri's sheaves.
The next morning the sheaves were the same.
</p><p>
The next night, determined to change it, Zimri went again to the field and carried another
third from his pile to his brother, Abram's, and then lay in the field to watch.  Soon Abram
came and took his sheaves and put them with his brother's share.  Then Clarence Cook closes
with these words: "And Zimri arose and caught him in his arms, and wept upon his neck, and
kissed his cheek; and Abram saw the whole, and could not speak; neither could Zimri, for
their hearts were full."
</p><p>
Now, as I read the record of history, there is but one force strong enough to motivate a
universal acceptance of brotherhood. That is, the acceptance of the Fatherhood of God and the
divine Sonship of his Son, Jesus Christ, and thence all men as brothers.  This has been the
power that has united men in the past.  This has been the plan of our Heavenly Father from
the beginning, and it is no illusion. It has worked.  We all know the story of Enoch who
taught this gospel plan to his brethren, and when it was accepted they lived happily&mdash;so much
so that the Lord walked and talked with them, and took them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/69#69">Moses 7:69</a>).
</p><p>
A similar unity of brotherhood occurred on this continent after the Lord had been here and
taught his gospel to the Nephites.  I quote the account of the condition that existed for two
hundred years afterward: 
</p><p>
"And it came to pass that there was no contention in the land, because of the love of God
which did dwell in the hearts of the people.<br />
"And there were no envyings, nor strifes, nor tumults, nor whoredoms, nor lyings, nor
murders, nor any manner of lasciviousness; and surely there could not be a happier people
among all the people who had been created by the hand of God.<br />
"There were no robbers, nor murderers, neither were there Lamanites, nor any manner of
-ites; but they were in one, the children of Christ, and heirs to the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/15-17#15">4 Ne. 1:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
Now, this blessed condition is attainable today, but it is attainable only upon the basis of
accepting God as Father and all men as brothers and living the plan of salvation. My
testimony is that this plan, which the Lord introduced in the beginning with Adam, and that
has successfully brought about true brotherhood in the past, has been restored; that the
priesthood that activates it and operates it is in our midst, and that the leaders thereof in this
Church are servants of our Heavenly Father.  This plan is bringing about a true brotherhood
in this day and it is up to you and me to make it function even more perfectly.  To show our
appreciation for the privilege we have of belonging to this great brotherhood, may we be ever
willing to share it with all of our brothers and sisters, I humbly ask in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
