<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Gospel Our Bulwark</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President N. Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 45-50</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brothers and sisters, it is a privilege indeed to be here and to
participate with you in this great conference where we have felt the Spirit of the Lord, where
we have heard and will hear testimonies of those who have been chosen to lead and direct the
work of the Lord in these, the latter days.  We have been built up in our faith and in our
determination to live lives in keeping with the teachings of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
It is a great blessing to be permitted to associate so closely with these men who know and
bear testimony, by the power of the Holy Ghost, that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, and
that God so loved the world that he gave his Only Begotten Son that whosoever believeth in
him should not perish but have everlasting life (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).  These men love the Lord with all their heart,
mind, and strength, and dedicate themselves entirely to the service of their fellowmen and to
the building up of the kingdom of God on the earth.
</p><p>
I do not suggest that these of any human beings are without fault, but it must be clear to all
the world that men who live righteous lives and lose themselves in the service of the Lord
meet the problems of the world with greater serenity and assurance.
</p><p>
I should like to acknowledge the presence of, and express my appreciation to, these dedicated
stake presidencies, bishoprics, mission presidents, missionaries, officers and teachers in the
priesthood quorums and auxiliary organizations, and all others who are prepared to sacrifice
and spend their time in furthering the cause of truth and righteousness throughout the world.
</p><p>
We meet in these general conferences of the Church for the purpose of being taught the
principles of the gospel, instructed in our duties, and encouraged and built up generally, and
to reason together and strengthen one another.  I sincerely pray that the Spirit and the
blessings of the Lord will attend me and all of us at this time.
</p><p>
<b>The world in travail</b>
</p><p>
It is trite but true to say that never before in the history of the world have we or our young
people been faced with more evil, serious problems, and challenges than we are today. 
Wherever you go, and regardless of whatever news media you pick up or listen to, or
whatever company you may be in, even as we have listened to our speakers in this
conference, we hear discussed and have forced upon our minds the importance of such
questions as divorce and family disintegration, new morality, new freedom, new security, the
"God is dead" theory, war and strife, riots, murders, burglaries, and all kinds of crime and
deception.
</p><p>
It is most important that we be acquainted with the evils of the day and realize how insidious
they are  and accept our responsibility to guard against these evils.  We should realize that the
new morality is nothing more than the old immorality, that the new freedom is nothing more
than disrespect for law and the rights of others and will lead to anarchy.  The new security
gives one the idea that the world owes him a living, and destroys individual initiative and
infringes on his liberty and freedom.
</p><p>
<b>The Gospel of Jesus Christ, the safeguard</b>
</p><p>
I am convinced, my brothers and sisters, that the only way to guard successfully against these
evils is to accept the gospel of Jesus Christ, which offers not only a better way of life but the
solution to these and all other problems facing us today.  In fact, we would have no more war
or strife or any of the evils that I have enumerated if the world would accept God as the
Creator of the world and Jesus Christ as its Savior.
</p><p>
We as leaders and as members of the Church have a heavy responsibility to help our youth to
know and understand that the Bible and the Book of Mormon, which were written on opposite
sides of the world, are records of God's dealings with his people on these two hemispheres. 
They are no fairy tales, but testimonies of many righteous men whose integrity cannot be
questioned. These testimonies have been handed down to us by the prophets from Adam to
the present day. These records show that in every dispensation those who accepted the word
of God and kept his commandments prospered and were happy, successful, and blessed, while
those who denied God and Jesus Christ and refused to accept the gospel have suffered
heartaches, defeat, Godless dictatorship, and general anarchy.
</p><p>
<b>Trust in God</b>
</p><p>
We all know the story of Moses and the Israelites.  We know that when they followed the
instructions of God and kept his commandments, they were blessed and preserved from their
enemies, and how quickly they were left to the buffeting of Satan when they turned away
from and ignored God and his teachings.
</p><p>
Another story with which we are all familiar is that of David and Goliath, how Goliath, that
powerful leader of the Philistines, was slain by David with his sling.  We should remind our
youth of the words of these two men, that show why David was successful and Goliath slain. 
David kept the commandments of God and had complete faith in his power.  Listen to the
boastful words of Goliath and to David's humble, but confident, response.
</p><p>
"And the Philistine said to David, Come to me and I will give thy flesh unto the fowls of the
air, and to the beasts of the field.
</p><p>
"Then said David to the Philistine, Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and
with a shield: but I come to thee in the name  of the Lord of hosts, the God of the armies of
Israel, whom thou hast defied.
</p><p>
"This day will the Lord deliver thee into mine hand" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/44-46#44">1 Sam. 17:44-46</a>).
</p><p>
As a result, Goliath and the Philistines were defeated, and the Israelites were saved by the
power of God.  The scriptures are replete with records of individuals and nations who
succeeded or failed as a result of their faithfulness or disobedience.
</p><p>
Also, we should appreciate and help our young people to understand that the greatest leaders
of recorded history, and of today, in industry and government, have always believed in God.
</p><p>
George Washington, in his first inaugural address, said: "It would be peculiarly improper to
omit in this official act, my fervent supplications to the Almighty Being who rules over the
universe." And in his famous farewell address he said: "Of all the dispositions and habits
which lead to political prosperity, religion and morality are indispensable supports."
</p><p>
Abraham Lincoln, in that oft repeated statement, said "Without the assistance of that Divine
Being,...I cannot succeed. With that assistance I cannot fail."
</p><p>
It is very interesting and significant to know, as pointed out so well by Wendell J. Ashton in
his article in the October <i>Instructor</i>, that Columbus had great faith in God.  This famous
explorer in his report to the king and queen of Spain wrote near the end of his letter: 
</p><p>
"And the eternal God, Our Lord, gives to all who walk in his way victory over things which
appear impossible, and this [voyage] was notably one."
</p><p>
Columbus concluded his letter with the suggestions that "all Christendom ought to feel joyful
and make great celebrations and give solemn thanks" for the privilege of bringing Christ's
message to the peoples of these newfound lands. Because of his faith and courage he was able
to withstand the mutinies and succeed in his mission. (<i>The Instructor</i>, October 1966.)
</p><p>
One of our great industrialists, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., included in his creed under the
heading "I Believe": 
</p><p>
"I believe in an all-wise and all-loving God . . . and that the individual's highest fulfillment,
greatest happiness, and widest usefulness are to be found in living in harmony with his will.
</p><p>
"I believe that love is the greatest thing in the world; that it alone can overcome hate; that
right can and will triumph over might."
</p><p>
<b>The way of God has not failed; it has not been tried</b>
</p><p>
Many who argue that Christianity has failed excuse themselves for their actions by saying that
men who profess God and Jesus Christ are hypocrites and do not live the teachings that they
profess.  Too often men waste their time questioning even the existence of God instead of
accepting his teachings and enjoying his blessings.
</p><p>
It is something like those who try to prove that Shakespeare never lived, that he was not the
author of the Shakespearean plays, some of the choicest of all literature.  While they waste
their time arguing, others are enjoying the beauty and philosophy of his works.
</p><p>
<b>Cornerstones of the law of God</b>
</p><p>
Christ's teachings, which are so important to our happiness, security, and exaltation, may be
summed up in the Ten Commandments, the Sermon on the Mount, Christ's answer to the
lawyer as to which is the great commandment in the law, and the Articles of Faith as given
by Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
Some of the Ten Commandments are: 
</p><p>
"Thou shalt have no other gods before me.
</p><p>
"Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy.
</p><p>
"Honour thy father and thy mother.
</p><p>
"Thou shalt not kill.
</p><p>
"Thou shalt not commit adultery.
</p><p>
"Thou shalt not steal.
</p><p>
"Thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbour" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3,8,12-16#3">Ex. 20:3,8,12-16</a>).
</p><p>
No one will argue that the keeping of these commandments would not make for a better and
happier individual or contribute to a happy and spiritual home, a better community, and a
better world in which to live. You are familiar with the old Chinese proverb that says: 
</p><p>
"If there is righteousness in the heart there will be beauty in the character; 
</p><p>
"If there is beauty in the character there will be harmony in the home; 
</p><p>
"If there is harmony in the home there will be order in the nation; 
</p><p>
"If there is order in the nation there will be peace in the world."
</p><p>
In fact, the Ten Commandments leave us with the impressive message that we are free either
to serve God and keep his commandments or to be ruled by tyrants.
</p><p>
Then we have the answer that Jesus gave to the lawyer who asked him a question, tempting
him and saying: 
</p><p>
"Master, which is the great commandment in the law?
</p><p>
"Jesus said unto him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy
soul, and with all thy mind.
</p><p>
"This is the first and great commandment.
</p><p>
"And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.
</p><p>
"On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36-40#36">Matt. 22:36-40</a>).
</p><p>
Homes are broken, individuals are confused and lost, and prisons are full of men who do not
believe in God and who fail to love their neighbors.  And many argue that we cannot be
honest and compete, that we cannot love our fellowmen as ourselves without their taking
advantage of us, and that we cannot apply the principles of the gospel in dealing with other
nations.
</p><p>
There are those, too, who claim that the gospel is old-fashioned; that men through scientific
development are becoming more and more self-sufficient and need not rely on God.  Others
argue that the gospel is too restrictive, that it takes away our liberty, and that we cannot enjoy
the advantages of a broad education, accept scientific truths, and participate in worthwhile
community activities.
</p><p>
This is just not true.  We know that the Lord has given us the earth and all things therein for
our use and for our benefit.  We have been told to subdue the earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
As members of the
Church we are encouraged to gain an education, to learn what we can, to prepare ourselves to
take our places in the world, and to contribute all we can to the good and welfare of mankind.
</p><p>
We know that great strides have been made in science and in subduing the earth.  We know
that mankind is enjoying conveniences, comforts, and blessings far greater than at any other
time in the history of the world.  However, we must also realize that no scientist or group of
scientists or philosophers has ever, through scientific research, been able to find out or give us
an understanding of the relationship of God to man or where we came from, why we are here,
or even when the spirit enters the body or what happens to it when we die.
</p><p>
<b>Opportunities for education</b>
</p><p>
Elder James E. Talmage, in his book The Articles of Faith, emphasizes the importance of
gaining an education, and we know that it is more important every day.  He says that in the
short span of mortal existence it is impossible for a man to explore with thoroughness any
considerable part of the vast realm of knowledge. It therefore becomes necessary for him to
determine which field of knowledge will be of greatest worth to him in his chosen field of
endeavor and then to learn everything he can about it.  However, he emphasizes the
importance of <i>everyone gaining theological knowledge, as a personal knowledge of God is essential</i>
to the salvation of every human soul.  Therefore, its importance cannot be
overestimated.
</p><p>
This theological knowledge has been given to us by revelation down through the ages from
Adam to our present-day Prophet. However, from the history of mankind we learn that as
man and the world prosper they have a tendency to forget God and to depend on their own
knowledge and strength. As a result, millions of men and women are disturbed and confused,
and many of them are committing suicide. They need something positive.
</p><p>
Let me emphasize again that those who have contributed most to the world are men who have
had a belief in God and have tried to govern their lives accordingly.  How much happier an
individual is who can go to bed knowing that he has been honest with his fellowmen, that he
is morally clean, that he is at peace with God, his Creator.
</p><p>
How much happier are those who live in a community made up of God-fearing people!
</p><p>
In my experience as a bishop, a stake president, and a general authority, I have never had
anyone who understands the gospel and who has an abiding faith in God come to me with
serious personal problems.
</p><p>
J. Edgar Hoover, in his analysis of "The Problems of the Day," says: 
</p><p>
"The basic cause of the present situation is that so many of our young people have no real
sense of moral responsibility which comes from an infinite knowledge of God's teachings. 
The tragic lack of God and prayer in their lives weakens our homes and our nation's welfare."
</p><p>
<b>Faith in God must triumph</b>
</p><p>
Then he emphasizes that either faith in God must triumph in the United States or we will be
dominated by criminals and communists.
</p><p>
Let us go forward with a positive attitude.  Be not ashamed.  Be not influenced by those who
ridicule and those who question and those who deny God.  Let us not be among those who
believe but do not have the courage and the strength to live according to the teachings of the
gospel.
</p><p>
As recorded in John, "Nevertheless among the chief rulers also many believed on him; but
because of the Pharisees they did not confess him, lest they should be put out of the
synagogue: 
</p><p>
"For they loved the <i>praise of men more than the praise of God</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/42-43#42">John 12:42-43</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
Let us enjoy the good things in life. Enjoy the gospel and its teachings. Let us not waste our
time looking for things to criticize in the gospel or in our neighbors. We must look at
ourselves and repent and improve. And let us remember that there is nothing else quite so
sure as that we will one day leave this frail existence. Let us set about to prepare ourselves
for that day.
</p><p>
". . . for . . . the day cometh that all shall rise from the dead and stand before God, and be judged
according to their works" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/41#41">Alma 11:41</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Plan of appropriate action</b>
</p><p>
If we are to stop the onslaught of immorality, divorce and family disintegration, lawlessness,
strife, riots, burglaries, murders, crime, and deception, we must not ask what are <i>they</i> doing
about it. We must ask and answer the question, "What am <i>I</i> doing?" Let us examine
ourselves, acknowledge our faults, and repent where we should.
</p><p>
We must begin by having righteousness in our own hearts, by disciplining ourselves, by
having love and harmony in our homes, and by truly loving our neighbors. Let us have the
wisdom, courage, and determination to say with Joshua:". . . choose you this day whom ye will
serve; . . . but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
I pray that each and every one of us will realize how important it is that we have family
prayer in our home, that we have home evening, that we keep the Sabbath day holy, and
dedicate ourselves to overcoming evil and keeping his commandments.
</p><p>
Let us realize that "this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus
Christ, whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>),
and set about to learn to know God.
</p><p>
I thank God with all my heart that I know as I know I stand here that God lives, that we are
his spirit children, that Jesus Christ is his Only Begotten Son, and that through his atonement
all mankind may be saved by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the gospel as revealed
through his prophets (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us to this end, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
