<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Wanted: Parents With Courage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Victor L. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Victor L. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 31-33</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
In Proverbs we read, "Train up a child in the way he should go: and when he is old, he will not
depart from it." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/22/6#6">Prov. 22:6</a>) Josh Billings
paraphrases this truth: "To bring up a child in the way
he should go, travel that way yourself." Travel that way yourself. How many of us are traveling
that way ourselves?
</p><p>
<b>Adult activities</b>
</p><p>
I listened to a nationally recognized educator speaking on television. Her subject was marijuana.
She said that the use of marijuana was no worse than some other social habits, implying that
there was really nothing wrong with young people's smoking marijuana. Recently a national
figure holding a responsible position in the government, a position of great influence over what
comes into our homes on radio and television, had this to say: "The language I use when I am at
a cocktail party is different from that which I use at home, or at church, and I don't see this as
being hypocritical." The other day in one of our own communities, some fathers, apparently
worked up over some issue, let the air out of the tires of some of the police cars in order to
interfere with enforcement of the law, and then the same fathers had great fun telling about it in
front of their own sons.
</p><p>
<b>Restricted movies</b>
</p><p>
When criticism is leveled at the type of movies shown on the screens today, the movie producers
reply that they only produce what the public will buy. Of 21 movies showing locally recently, I
could find only three that indicated no restrictions on those attending because of material that
might be offensive or objectionable, and these ratings were by the movie industry itself. A scene
in one of those admitting all ages, subject only to parental supervision, brought peals of laughter
from the audience when the drunk tore the blouse from a woman in an exhibition of abject lust.
If this is the kind of entertainment we adults enjoy, how in the world can we teach our children
morality?
</p><p>
In my teens I was told a dirty story by an active church leader. Although my memory for stories
is notoriously poor, that particular one is still with me, and I remember the name of the man who
told it. What kind of example are we as adults? Does our character change with circumstances as
the chameleon changes its colors? Does the language we use change to fit the environment? Do
we go to movies that appeal to our base animal instincts and cause us to grovel in filth with the
authors and actors? Do we break the law because that is the thing the crowd wants to do at the
moment, or are we strong enough to stand on our own principles, no matter what the social
pressure? These are some of the questions we must ask ourselves if we are to train a child up in
the way he should go and travel that way ourselves.
</p><p>
<b>Problems with parents</b>
</p><p>
Throughout the Church I hear the comment from stake presidents and bishops, "If we did not
have problems with parents, we would not have them with the young people." As a people, we
accept today standards of conduct that would have been totally unacceptable yesterday. For
example, the filthy, obscene language that is read and heard under the guise of freedom of
speech is becoming more and more acceptable in so-called respectable society. Pornography has
become a major industry in many parts of the world. The chief psychotherapist at one of
Washington's largest hospitals says, "A normal 12- or 13-year-old boy or girl exposed to
pornographic literature could develop into a homosexual. You can take healthy boys or girls and
by exposing them to abnormalities virtually crystallize and settle their habits for the rest of their
lives."
</p><p>
Some are even saying, "What is wrong with becoming a homosexual?" In one church, a leader
recently performed a marriage between two male homosexuals. As a matter of fact, some of the
world news media made quite a story of it. And yet who is responsible for this moral decay? The
children? Hardly. It is we adults, those of us who permit the sale of filth on our newsstands and
also permit the broadcasting of it over airways.
</p><p>
<b>Questionable publications</b>
</p><p>
Sometime ago, while waiting for my wife to finish her shopping, I looked over the magazine
rack in a new supermarket. With one or two exceptions, the covers of the magazines and
captions of feature articles dealt with sex in one form or another. This was in a family store in a
residential neighborhood. How long do you think these publications would last if we, the adults,
did not buy them? What is happening to us that we permit our standards to erode to such a
degree? It hasn't happened overnight. No, it has happened so gradually and so subtly that most of
us have not even been aware that it has happened at all.
</p><p>
<b>Erosion of standards</b>
</p><p>
I agree with David Klein that this moral erosion started when "western man began to lose his
belief in God as a personal force, as decider of his fate, as ultimate judge of his actions. The idea
that God created man became old fashioned; we evolved . . . Life began to be seen as more or
less accidental; sin became a relative, sociological matter, and to many a pure fiction. He still
believed in right and wrong, and he still knew when he was doing wrong . . . but he no longer
believed he had offended God by it or incurred His punishment."
</p><p>
Quoting further from Mr. Klein: 
</p><p>
"The difference between living this way, and trying to live righteously because God commands it
is profound.
</p><p>
"What used to be an offense against God became 'anti-social'; a sin became a crime . . . Stealing
was bad because honesty was the best policy. You tried to avoid being unfaithful to your mate
because it might harm your relationship. If you attended religious services, it was to respect a
tradition. Virtue became its own inexplicable reward, for there was no other." (David Raphael
Klein, "Is There a Substitute for God?" <i>Reader's Digest</i>, March 1970, pp. 51-52.)
</p><p>
<b>Instability of philosophies</b>
</p><p>
There is no stability to this kind of philosophy. It changes with the shifting sands of time, place,
and circumstance. It is subject to the whims and habits and philosophies of men. No, there is
nothing man can hold onto with the assurance that each principle will withstand the erosion of
society. Permissiveness has become so acceptable in the society in which we live that many of us
are afraid to establish solid, sound guidelines for ourselves as well as for the youth. How
important it is that there be rules and standards by which we live and that these standards be
based on solid foundations. There must be meaning to standards. As Mr. Klein said, "If a parent
must tell a youngster that his life has no meaning, how can he tell him that he should not take
drugs?" (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 53.)
</p><p>
<b>Reversing trends</b>
</p><p>
Unless these trends are reversed, nothing but tragedy lies ahead. Great empires have fallen
because their people have lost their way. What to do about it? Each adult who touches the life of
a young person affects that individual in one way or another. However, the adults who affect the
lives of the youth most profoundly for good or ill are parents. If we are to bring up our children
in the way they should go and travel that way ourselves, we must turn to the basic, simple,
sound, unchanging truths of the gospel of Jesus Christ and make them live in our lives. What we
need today are parents who are converted to the gospel of Jesus Christ; who are willing to apply
it, believe it, and use it; who pay an honest tithing; who are honest with their neighbors and
debtors; who actually sustain the authorities of the Church; and who teach the gospel to their
children in such a way that the children will love the Lord.
</p><p>
<b>Need for exemplary parents</b>
</p><p>
We need parents with courage, who will stand up and speak up for the right, who are actively
involved in government of all levels; parents who are modest in dress, speech, and conduct;
parents who are not ashamed of the gospel of Jesus Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>);
parents who teach their children that
we do have a Father in heaven, that we are his spirit children, that he has placed us here on earth
for a great and glorious purpose, that he loves us, that he has given us commandments along
with our free agency, that we will receive rewards and judgments based on our own actions;
parents who accept all of the commandments as having come from God, to be obeyed for that
reason if for no other; parents who have no other gods before the Lord, (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3#3">Ex. 20:3</a>) who do not commit
adultery, who do not steal, who do not covet their neighbor's wife or husband, who do not bear
false witness against their neighbor; (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/14-17#14">Ex. 20:14-17</a>) parents who love the Lord their God with all their heart, and
with all their soul, and with all their mind, and who love their neighbor as themselves. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37,39#37">Matt. 22:37,39</a>)
</p><p>
It is my conviction, and I bear my witness, that this is the only pathway to the salvation of
mankind, in this life as well as the life to come, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
