<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...Therefore Ye Are Free Indeed"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 100-102</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This experience makes me feel like a Marine lieutenant friend of mine.  He had been in the
last war for four years and when he learned they were considering his recall, he sent the
board a telegram in which he said: "I desire to remind you that I spent four years in the last
war, and I just want you to know I do not want to crowd in ahead of anyone else who wants
the experience.
</p><p>
I am grateful for a great many things this morning.  I am always grateful to be on these
grounds and in this building, for daily association with them has never
dimmed their beauty and their memories for me.  I am grateful for the lovely flowers which
festoon this stand, for many of us learned to love them and what they represent in the islands
of the sea; and I am particularly grateful for the blessing of aloha or love which motivated the
good people who sent them.
</p><p>
I am especially grateful this morning, for freedom.  As a serviceman who had opportunity in
an armed conflict to help defend this nation, as a young American, and as a Latter-day Saint,
I am as grateful for freedom as my intelligence and capacity to understand it allow me to be.
</p><p>
But as I look at you and consider myself, I think of another kind of freedom which is even
more important than that which we here enjoy to assemble and to teach and to worship. This
freedom has no relationship to prison walls, or to any other aspect of physical restraint or
deprivation.  It may, in fact, be employed by one immured in deepest dungeon, penniless and
starving and in ill health.  On the other hand, it may be absent from one who is not physically
restrained, who has an abundance of wealth, health, prominence, I think of the freedom taught
by Jesus to certain of the descendants of Abraham many centuries ago. Having taught them of
his Father, he gave them another great lesson, in these words, many having believed on him: 
</p><p>
If ye continue in my word, then are ye my disciples indeed; 
</p><p>
And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free.
</p><p>
They answered him, [angrily, you see, because they were already free, were they not?] We be
Abraham's seed, and were never in bondage to any man: how sayest thou, Ye shall be made
free?
</p><p>
Jesus answered them, Verily, verily, I say unto you, Whosoever committeth sin is the servant
of sin.
</p><p>
And the servant abideth not in the house for ever: but the son abideth ever.
</p><p>
If the son therefore shall make you free, ye shall be free indeed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/31-36#31">John 8:31-36</a>).
</p><p>
There is a freedom different from and superior to even that which we enjoy today, to meet, to
teach, and to worship.  What is it?  Is it, as some suppose, the right to do as we please?  Do
we find this freedom in indulgence, in unrighteousness, in sin?  Do we find it in giving loose
rein to passion, to emotions, to appetites, to the unrighteous thought or act?
</p><p>
This freedom of which Jesus spoke does not company with unrighteousness nor is it the
product of the evil act.  This freedom, this freedom which he taught as being most important
to mankind, comes to those who in righteousness have faith in God, learn hid law, and seek
to understand it, and who, obedient to it, and with responsibility, seek to do his will.
</p><p>
There are many among us, and throughout the world, young and old (though perhaps we too
often confine the lesson to the young) who have the idea that freedom, the freedom of which
we speak, can be found in unlicensed liberty.  But this freedom which Jesus taught is not the
freedom of irresponsibility or unrighteousness, but the freedom which accompanies obedience.
</p><p>
Is that husband free, for instance, who with disloyalty to his wife and family and with lust in
heart, entangles himself in alliances outside his own home?  Is that father free who, neglecting
his children, turns them away and does not love them and teach them?  Is that man free who
hates his neighbor, and who will not forgive the trespasses his neighbor has committed against
him?
</p><p>
Is that wife and mother free who will not perform the duties of her home with joy in her
heart, realizing this to be her great calling?  Is that woman free who gives her time to selfish
social pursuits of doubtful worth instead of to her neighbor, her community, her Church, her
God, in honest service, when there is so much to do?
</p><p>
Is that boy free who trifles with good habits, who cheats a little in school, who will not
accept sound counsel and loving parental advice, but who, making his own stubborn way (for
he is of the age when he thinks he knows better than they) chooses companions who are on
the wrong path, goes about his activities with them, perhaps even stealing
from some others the most precious things they enjoy? Is the young girl free who thinks so
little of herself that she allows herself to be handled as if she were worth nothing, or who
talks with evil tongue about her friends or acquaintances; who will not be counseled, who will
not be helpful or humble in the home?
</p><p>
The obvious answer is that these people are not free.  True, they have the right to choose, but
they violate their agency in choosing that which denies them the very freedom which God
would have his children enjoy; for how is this freedom achieved?
</p><p>
Let me quote two or three verses of scripture.  In addition to the words of the Lord, telling us
that truth makes us free, he said again as recorded in the Doctrine and Covenants, the sacred
book of the restoration: 
</p><p>
I, the Lord God, make you free, therefore ye are free indeed; and the law also maketh you
free (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/8#8">D&amp;C 98:8</a>).
</p><p>
And He said to us, as John recorded it when he was among men: 
</p><p>
Now ye are clean through the word which I have spoken unto you.
</p><p>
Abide in me, and I in you . . .
</p><p>
. . . for without me ye can do nothing (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/3-5#3">John 15:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
And the Psalmist sang, "And I will walk at liberty: for I seek thy precepts"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/119/45#45">Ps. 119:45</a>).
</p><p>
And again, James: 
</p><p>
But whoso looketh into the perfect law of liberty, and continueth therein, he being not a
forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man shall be blessed in his deed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/25#25">James 1:25</a>).
</p><p>
And finally, and perhaps most importantly, out of the book of 2 Corinthians this simple
statement: 
</p><p>
. . . where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/3/17#17">2 Cor. 3:17</a>).
</p><p>
My humble testimony is that real freedom is not irresponsibility or license, but that real
freedom accompanies faith in God, the understanding of his word, and obedience to it. (And
each of us, I believe, knows personally the difference between the freedom of faith and
obedience, and the bondage of sin.)
</p><p>
God bless us to realize as we seek to learn the marvelous principles of the gospel that he who
will not in his heart forgive, he who will not be clean, he who will not seek to know the
truths of the Lord as they apply not only to the obedience which is a word, but also to the
obedience which is a way of living, is not free.
</p><p>
God bless us that we may have faith, that we may learn his word and live it, in order that we
may have his spirit with us, for ". . . where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/3/17#17">2 Cor. 3:17</a>). In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
