<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Commitment</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Robert L. Simpson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Robert L. Simpson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, p. 67-70</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
During the past few weeks, most of us have either participated in or listened as some rather
serious commitments were made. With a group of eager young Scouts, it was: "On my honor
I will do my best to do my duty to God and my country." These boys were committing
themselves to a better effort.
</p><p>
At a patriotic rally recently, a group of us earnestly vowed a pledge of allegiance to the flag
of our country. Every citizen, whatever his nationality, makes strong commitments to uphold
and honor his government. This is as it should be.
</p><p>
Few, if any, go through life without committing themselves to a sacred trust and promise of
one type or another. In proper perspective and with lofty and worthy objectives, such
covenants can and should be stimulating, motivational, and indeed a most stabilizing influence
among men.
</p><p>
But any and all social or civil promises, commitments, and oaths entered into by man with
man fade into relative insignificance when compared with those promises and covenants
between man and God, the Eternal Father.
</p><p>
Could any commitment be more important than a sacred covenant between mortal man and
his Maker?
</p><p>
A long, long time ago&mdash;yes, even before the foundations of this earth were laid&mdash;the plan
was clear; the process for the successful undertaking of building souls for eternal purposes
was established. The covenant procedure was decided upon as an essential element to that
end.
</p><p>
<b>Commitments to the righteous life</b>
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph has recorded this explicit observation from the Lord himself: "For all who
will have a blessing at my hands shall abide the law which was appointed for that blessing,
and the conditions thereof, as were instituted from before the foundation of the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/5#5">D&amp;C 132:5</a>).
</p><p>
Now, no one is suggesting that it is inappropriate for men to establish some mutual
understandings and contracts from time to time, provided such agreements stimulate, motivate,
and bind us more closely together in a good and worthwhile cause.
</p><p>
<b>The Priesthood</b>
</p><p>
It is expedient, however, that we place first things first, and any agreement that we make with
the Lord through his Holy Priesthood takes precedence over all else, regardless of its source
or its apparent value. Speaking further through the Prophet Joseph, the Lord declares that "all
covenants, contracts, bonds, obligations, oaths, vows, performances, connections, associations,
or expectations, that are not made and entered into and sealed [by proper authority] . . . are of
no efficacy, virtue, or force . . . for all contracts that are not made unto this end have an end
when men are dead" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/7#7">D&amp;C 132:7</a>).
</p><p>
He then gives this reassuring promise: "Behold, mine house is a house of order, saith the Lord
God, and not a house of confusion" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/8#8">D&amp;C 132:8</a>). Then, thinking in terms of eternity, he
states: 
</p><p>
"For whatsoever things remain are by me; and whatsoever things are not by me shall be
shaken and destroyed" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/14#14">D&amp;C 132:14</a>). The sacred agreements that we have entered into with
our Heavenly Father must be kept first and foremost and above all else.
</p><p>
<b>Baptism</b>
</p><p>
Most within range of my voice have taken upon themselves the name of Jesus Christ through
the waters of baptism. By virtue of this sacred ordinance, we have come forth in a spiritual
birth, just as real and necessary as our birth into mortality. Woe be unto that child of God
who would enter such a sacred covenant deceitfully or with ulterior motives. Little better is he
who enters the waters of baptism without the intention of valiance or effort. Nothing is sadder
in all this world than those who, after participating in this great blessing, regard it as of little
or no consequence in their lives and then proceed to lose the possibility of life eternal by
default. There can be no room for indifference in the wake of such an honor and blessing as
that found in the sacred ordinance of baptism.
</p><p>
Indeed, it has been appropriately observed that where much is given, much is expected. All
who have had the privilege of baptism in his appointed way and by his appointed authority
are indeed richly endowed. Commitment of the highest order has been made. The obligation
to bear his name worthily becomes paramount.
</p><p>
As man was being created, surely our Maker must have realized how short our memories and
how weak the flesh in this temporal setting. Consequently, his great plan provided for a
regular reminder to all who took upon them his name in the waters of baptism.
</p><p>
<b>The Sacrament</b>
</p><p>
The sacrament was revealed by the Savior himself, first of all to his very closest associates in
the ministry with the specific instruction that "it is expedient that the church meet together
often to partake of bread and wine in the remembrance of the Lord Jesus" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/75#75">D&amp;C 20:75</a>). It
is, therefore, most important for members of his Church to recommit themselves every week.
</p><p>
Commitment No. 1: That they are willing to take upon them the name of his Son.
</p><p>
Commitment No. 2: And always remember him.
</p><p>
Commitment No. 3: To keep his commandments which he has given them.
</p><p>
These are not idle thoughts and words but rather sacred obligations and
promises entered into with God, the Father, as each worthy member partakes with contrite
spirit and deepest reflections concerning the atoning sacrifice of the Only Begotten of the
Father.
</p><p>
Show me the man, woman, or child who truly and sincerely covenants to take upon himself
the name of Jesus Christ, and I will show you a person who is upright and honest in all of his
dealings.
</p><p>
Show me the man, woman, or child who truly commits himself to always remember, and I
will show you a child of God who is without guile, one who is understanding and quick to
forgive.
</p><p>
Show me the man, woman or child who makes it a matter of daily and hourly endeavor to
keep God's commandments that he has given them and lives that pledge in his every act, his
every word, to the very best of his ability, and I will show you one who radiates the true
Spirit of Christ and who, if unwavering to the end, will inherit eternal life, which is,
according to the Lord, "the greatest of all the gifts of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>).
</p><p>
Unfortunately, there are those who choose to commit themselves by covenant to the
adversary. Conspiring men have formed secret combinations all through the ages to promote
wickedness and evil. Immediately preceding the advent of the Savior on this continent 2,000
years ago, we are told of such a group who "did enter into a covenant one with another, yea,
even into that covenant which was given by them of old, which covenant was given and
administered by the devil, to combine against all righteousness.
</p><p>
"Therefore they did combine against the people of the Lord, and enter into a covenant to
destroy them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/6/28-29#28">3 Ne. 6:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
Times have not changed. Less than two months ago, most of you read the disturbing article in
our newspapers about a group of individuals who have established a so-called Satanic church,
with the sole purpose to participate only in the realms of evil and darkness. They are in open
defiance of and diametrically opposed to all of His holy purposes that bring us together in this
great conference. Without a goodly number of God-fearing men committed to the cause of
truth, these societies of evil could well take over our society.
</p><p>
The only effective tool against evil and darkness is truth and light, particularly truth and light
held in the hands of those bearing God's Holy Priesthood: worthy, dedicated men such as I
see before me here today.
</p><p>
No man or boy who has accepted the commitment of priesthood can stand idly by, for if we
do not abide in this covenant with the Lord, if we are less than anxiously engaged in doing
something about it, he says: ". . . ye are not worthy of me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/15#15">D&amp;C 98:15</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The oath and covenant of Priesthood</b>
</p><p>
The oath and covenant of the priesthood stands singularly supreme among God's covenants
with his children. The Spirit of the Lord is companion to the priesthood. ". . . all they who
receive this priesthood receive me, saith the Lord . . .
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth me receiveth my father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/35,37#35">D&amp;C 84:35,37</a>). These reassuring promises
from the Lord, as though there were not enough, are climaxed by what has to be the most
generous reward ever accorded to mortal man. He confirms his part of the contract as
repayment for complete faithfulness in these words: "And he that receiveth my Father
receiveth my Father's kingdom&mdash;therefore all that my Father hath shall be given unto him.
</p><p>
"And this is according to the oath and covenant which belongeth to the priesthood"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38-39#38">D&amp;C 84:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
Oh, my dear brothers and sisters, can't we see the folly of any course except it be that course
which is priesthood-centered and pointing toward eternal life? The yoke is easy, the burden is
light, the Savior tells us (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/30#30">Matt. 11:30</a>). The only difficult way is the cobblestone byway of
periodic indifference, broken covenants, and half-hearted effort.
</p><p>
If ours has been the commitment of baptism, then stand up tall and bear his name with honor
and dignity, for the promise is that as we prove faithful over a few things, he shall make us
rulers over many things (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/52/13#13">D&amp;C 52:13</a>).
</p><p>
If our commitment is in the form of the sacrament, may we partake each time worthily, that
we may always have his Spirit to be with us (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/77#77">D&amp;C 20:77</a>). Such is the unqualified promise from our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
If ours is the commitment to honor the priesthood, may we do so nobly, using it for the
blessing of mankind, that our inheritance may indeed be "all that the Father has" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>).
</p><p>
The commitment we make through our covenants with the Lord is serious business. All else is
secondary. His rewards are certain, for he has declared for all to hear: "I, the Lord, am bound
when ye do what I say, but when ye do not what I say, ye have no promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
Let every father stand fearlessly at the head of his family and accept Joshua's challenge that
has stood through the ages: ". . . choose you this day whom ye will serve . . . but as for me
and my house, we will serve the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
May we commit ourselves without reservation. May ours be the whole armor of God, that our
calling and election may be made sure (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/10#10">2 Pet. 1:10</a>), I pray humbly in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
