<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Exaltation through Obedience</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 34-36</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I appreciate the prayers that have been offered in behalf of those who shall part in this
conference, and I pray that I shall receive my share of those blessings which have been asked.
</p><p>
I appreciated the privilege of attending the Los Angeles Temple dedication with the other
General Authorities of the Church, and I also want to express appreciation for the sustaining
vote in my behalf of this assembly today, for I feel that is a very personal help and support to
me in my work.  I also wish to sustain with you the General Authorities and
others whom we have sustained in this conference, especially President McKay as the
President of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, who holds the keys of the gospel
at this time through which we may receive the blessings of the Lord of salvation and eternal
life which are promised through the gospel.
</p><p>
On that memorable occasion which we read of in the Book of Mormon, in Third Nephi, when
Christ spoke from the heavens so that all could hear, he said,
</p><p>
Yea, verily I say unto you, if ye will come unto me ye shall have eternal life. Behold,
mine arm of mercy is extended towards you, and whosoever will come, him will I
receive; and blessed are those who come unto me.
</p><p>
And continuing further, he said: 
</p><p>
. . . And whoso cometh unto me with a broken heart and a contrite spirit, him will I
baptize with fire and with the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/14,20#14">3 Ne. 9:14,20</a>).
</p><p>
All are invited to come unto him that they may have eternal life.  The glory of God is". . . to
bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>). The Lord
wants only to bring us back into the presence of God.  For that purpose he has established the
priesthood on the earth.  He has established his kingdom with just laws and ordinances,
through obedience to which we may obtain eternal life in the presence of our Father in
heaven.
</p><p>
All God asks of us is that we keep his commandments, that we obey the laws and ordinances
of the gospel.  These laws are not unjust, as are some which are given by corrupt rulers. They
are simple laws which bring nothing but happiness to those who obey them.
</p><p>
Prophet Joseph Smith makes the following comparison: 
</p><p>
Were a king to extend his domination over the habitable earth, and send forth his laws
which were the most perfect kind, and command his subjects one and all to yield
obedience to the same, and add as a reward to those who obeyed them, that at a
certain period they should be called to attend the marriage of his son, who in due time
was to receive the kingdom, and they should be made equal with him in the same; and
fix as a penalty for disobedience that every individual guilty of it should be cast out of
the marriage feast, and have no part nor portion with his government, what rational
mind could for a moment accuse the king with injustice for punishing such rebellious
subjects?  In the first place his laws were just, easy to be complied with, and perfect:
nothing of a tyrannical nature was required of them; but the very construction of the
laws was equity and beauty; and when obeyed would produce the happiest condition
possible to all who adhered to them, beside the last great benefit of sitting down with
the royal robe in the presence of the king at the great, grand marriage supper of his
son, and be made equal with him in all the affairs of the kingdom
(<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 52).
</p><p>
Then the Lord has said, "Behold, mine arm of mercy is extended towards you" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/6/5#5">Jacob 6:5</a>).
This means to all the inhabitants of the earth, not just to the few who then heard his
voice, but to all the children of God, to the ends of the earth, to those of all nations,
regardless of time or place of their life on the earth. Yes, his invitation reaches to those who
lived before his ministry on the earth, who then or even now dwell in the world of spirits, to
those who are yet to be born on the earth.  Most important of all this invitation is to us, to all
of this generation, to you and to me.  Are you willing to accept his invitation, can you offer a
broken heart and contrite spirit, are you willing to seek him?  He has said,
</p><p>
. . . seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/11/9#9">Luke 11:9</a>). Seek
ye first the kingdom of God and his righteousness; and all these things shall be added
unto you (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith said, "Search the scriptures," as Brother Kirkham has told us this
morning.
</p><p>
Search the revelations, which we publish, and ask your Heavenly Father in the name
of His Son Jesus Christ, to manifest the truth unto you, and if you do it with an eye
single to His glory nothing doubting He will answer you by the power of His Holy
Spirit.  You will then know for yourselves and not for another.  You will not then be
dependent on man for the knowledge of God
(<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 11).
</p><p>
The Lord is constantly making it easier to find him.  He has established his Church with the
divine authority to teach and administer in the ordinances thereof.  He has established the
missionary system to teach and to seek out those who wish to accept his invitation to eternal
life.
</p><p>
It was a glorious privilege to listen to the testimonies of the mission presidents who have
gathered here at this conference.  Surely they are men of God, and they, too, will testify that
as they work they receive more for their labors.  I testify to you that our missionaries are in
good hands.
</p><p>
Those who accept His invitation are surely blessed.  It is a real thrill to see the joy expressed
by these converts; many through tears of joy tell how wonderful it is that they have been
privileged to receive the gospel.  Some tell of the joy they received in going into the waters
of baptism, that joy is increased again to a climax when they have the privilege of coming to
the temple and enjoying the blessings of the sealing ordinances.
</p><p>
The Lord has recently provided more temples to make it easier for men to accept his
invitation, including the new Los Angeles Temple.  Not only does it make it easier for us, but
it also leaves more of the people of the earth without excuse. And woe unto him who has the
gospel taught to him and has all these opportunities given to him and does not avail himself
of the blessings of the Lord.  This may also be a fair warning to those who have the
opportunity given to them to go forth to teach the gospel, and do not avail themselves of that
opportunity.  They too shall surely forfeit great blessings.
</p><p>
Foreign missionaries are not the only ones who have the privilege of teaching the gospel, for
it is our privilege to teach the gospel in our own lives, as well as those who are called to local
missions.  I heard of a man who lived in Salt Lake City in the same house for seventeen
years before joining the Church. When he was asked why he had not joined sooner, he
replied, "No one asked me."
</p><p>
I talked with a man in Ogden who had lived in the same place for about fifty-five years and
had recently accepted the Lord's invitation.  He told me no one had asked him before, either.
</p><p>
The invitation to receive eternal life requires more than mere acceptance of baptism.  When
we receive the Holy Ghost which reveals unto us the truth, it is then our responsibility to
extend his invitation to others.  This is one case where the more you give to others, the more
you receive unto yourself. Then give generously in teaching the gospel.  Accept of his
invitation to receive him, that you with your family and friends may return unto our Father in
heaven, exalted in his kingdom.
</p><p>
May the blessings of the Lord be with us, for I bear unto you my testimony that this is the
gospel of Jesus Christ through which we may receive eternal life and become exalted in the
kingdom of our Father in heaven.  May these blessings be upon us, I pray, in the name of
Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
