<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">To Magnify the Priesthood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 106-107</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I had given up the expectancy of having this privilege of bearing my
testimony to you this afternoon, and I haven't the courage to take time to make an extended
speech or any extensive remarks. I trust that the Spirit of God may help me to bear a true
testimony to the truth of the gospel, and when I say testimony, which seems to be the spirit of
this conference, I mean that I testify that Jesus Christ is the Son of God; that he and the
Father appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith; that through the visitation of heavenly beings
and the inspiration that came from God, a real and true interpretation of the plan of life and
salvation was returned to the earth; that through heavenly beings there came back to the earth
the priesthood which authorized men to perform the functions that are essential to the
exaltation of people in the kingdom of God; and that to regulate the use of that priesthood the
Church was set up according to the will of God and the pattern which Jesus Christ gave us
when he ministered in the earth.
</p><p>
That I honestly and sincerely believe to be true, and I feel that the fact of its truth has been
revealed to me by the Spirit of God. The spirit of this conference has been testimony. Christ
told Peter that upon the revealed testimony that He is the Son of God, he had built his
Church, and the gates of hell could not prevail against it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16-18#16">Matt. 16:16-18</a>).
</p><p>
I honestly believe, brethren and sisters, that if we can properly instill into
our own hearts and the hearts of our children this testimony to the degree that it will impel
them to live true to the principles of the gospel, to the covenants that they have made in the
waters of baptism and in the temples of God, and to the promises that are implied, if not
actually made, when one receives the priesthood, that the Church will never be in danger.
</p><p>
The power of the Church is in the administration of the priesthood offices, of course, and in
the faith that the people have. I believe that testimony comes from faith and prayer and
righteous living, and that the best way to get it is to live true to the teachings of the gospel, to
pray about it, and to exercise our faith to that end. And then I believe further that if we can
get that testimony truly in our hearts, that all men who accept ordination into the Melchizedek
Priesthood or the Aaronic Priesthood for that matter, will exert every possible power within
them to magnify that calling. There is not the least doubt in my mind that any man who holds
the Melchizedek Priesthood, who lives to magnify that calling, should never yield to any of
the temptations of his satanic majesty.
</p><p>
I feel that whenever men give way to those temptations, it is an indication of really either a
weak testimony or a lack of testimony of these wonderful things. We who hold the priesthood
have the problem of planting that testimony in the hearts of others. We do it by the
way we live and by what we teach.
</p><p>
I heard a testimony just a week ago from a very fine man who has recently come into the
Church. He was first impressed by the life of certain members of the Church whom he met.
He became interested and investigated. He had a son fourteen years of age who likewise was
interested in the missionaries and attended their meetings in the branch. The son came home
one day and to the utter surprise of his father said, "Father, I have a testimony," and this man
said, "Now in our church nobody ever testifies."
</p><p>
It is in Christianity a forgotten art practically, but with us it is the most essential thing of our
whole program, brothers and sisters, that we should gain that testimony; that we should live
true to it, and that when we accept responsibility in the priesthood we should magnify it.
</p><p>
Now we who keep records know that there is a large percentage of men who have been
ordained to the Melchizedek Priesthood who are not magnifying their callings. We have a
program, brothers and sisters, that we have been advocating for sometime, to which reference
was made today, to try to interest those people and bring them to pray and study that they
may come to understand these things and then go forth to reclaim their privileges as members
of the Melchizedek Priesthood.
</p><p>
Of course there is plenty of incentive for it. To those of you who were here last night I
recommend again the passages in the Doctrine and Covenants that Brother Romney read to
you, that he who receives these callings in the priesthood and magnifies them fully can
eventually attain to the powers of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33-38#33">D&amp;C 84:33-38</a>).
That is the incentive, brothers and sisters. When we
go to these people, we must go in love and kindness, helpful as we can in the hope that they
will listen to us.
</p><p>
I pray that God will bless us that we may understand individually our own problems,
understand that the privileges of membership in the Church of Jesus Christ are individual
privileges, and that no man should let the conduct of another man prevent his using these
privileges to his own exaltation. If people who come into the Church could come
understanding that it is an individual problem pure and simple with them, then these other
things that they observe at times would have no effect upon their lives.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, we have the problem not only of our own people, but also of
assimilating and absorbing and helping the many people who are being baptized into the
Church. May God help us to do all these things, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ, our
Redeemer. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
