<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Going Steady"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 13-17</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
With you, my brothers and sisters, I have been very deeply impressed by the conference
session this morning. I do not know when I have been so deeply touched by the words of a
prophet of God as I have been this morning by the remarkable address of our President.
</p><p>
I love this President. He is the prophet of Almighty God. I bear you my solemn testimony he
is the prophet, seer, and revelator of the Almighty for us today, and I testify to you that if we
follow in his footsteps and accept his teachings the Lord will bless us and prosper us and
guide us throughout our days.
</p><p>
And I have been so deeply touched, with you, by these other two addresses that we heard. I
am so grateful for these testimonies pertaining to the Savior of the world. I
love Jesus Christ. I love him as my Redeemer and my Savior. I know that you love him
likewise, but I know that our love for him is interpreted strictly in terms of our service to
him. "He that hath my commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/21#21">John 14:21</a>).
So said the Savior.
</p><p>
I would like to talk with you today in a projection of some of the ideas presented to us by
President McKay. These words that he gave us, that we must be preachers of the Word, and
be evangelists for the Lord, are so filled with meaning for us all. I hope each one of us will
take these words to heart. Each one of us is a minister. Each one of us is an evangelist for
Christ.  Where is your ministry?
</p><p>
I would like to talk with you about your ministry among your own children, because you are
ministers of the Lord unto your children, and if you will do your duty by your children, you
will be as saviors on Mount Zion to them 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/obad/1/21#21">Obad. 1:21</a>). But if you fail in your responsibility in serving
the Lord pertaining to your children, they may go astray, and the Lord has said that their sins
shall be upon the heads of the parents
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25#25">D&amp;C 68:25</a>).
</p><p>
A few days ago I received a letter. It is like some other letters I have received, and I would
like to read a part of this letter to you. It comes from a mother. She says: "I have a daughter
who is 15. Her boy friend is 16. They have been going steady for over a year. We have just
now learned that they are in serious trouble. For the first few months of their friendship they
dated only occasionally. Then they decided to 'go steady.' That was the beginning of their
trouble. It seemed they were always in each other's company. Now my little 15-year-old girl
is soon to become a mother, and we are all just brokenhearted."
</p><p>
This letter is typical of a nationwide problem, one which has become of major concern to
both federal and local officials, and which poses a difficult situation for school executives in
many parts of the nation. It is a situation which is forcing an increasing number of young
people into child marriages and child divorces, with broken hearts and broken lives, and the
problem is a growing one.
</p><p>
In the September 6, 1959 issue of <i>Parade</i> magazine there appeared an article with pictures
discussing this problem. It was entitled, "Married Teenagers." One of the pictures showed a
17-year-old mother of triplets. The article discussed conditions in Dallas, Texas, and reported
that in the schools of that city there are 480 married children: 459 in senior high schools, 12
in junior high schools, and 9 in elementary schools.
</p><p>
The Family Service Society of San Bernardino County in California reports that from the year
1940 to 1958 the number of marriages involving two teenagers increased twelve times, and
the marriages involving one teenager increased six times. The average age of these children is
17 for girls and 18 for boys, but many of them involve 13, 14, and 15 year-old girls, and 14,
15, and 16 year-old boys.
</p><p>
The <i>U.S. News &amp; World Report</i> for December 12, 1958 reports that there are child mothers,
some married and some not, in twenty-two of the twenty-three high schools in the city of
Washington, D. C., as well as in four of the elementary schools of that city.
</p><p>
The Associated Press, in a nationally published article written out of Washington by Roger
Greene, dated August 9 of this year, reports: "An all-time record of babies born out of
wedlock&mdash;more than 200,000 a year&mdash;has set off a new storm of controversy over ebbing
standards of American morality . . . Latest figures show the rate of such births per 1,000
unmarried females has tripled in the last two decades, with a particularly alarming rise among
teenage girls . . . 5,000 illegitimate babies are born each year to girls under 15 . . . A tragic
byproduct is that at least 20,000 young unwed mothers sell their babies on the 'black market'
annually, with price tags ranging from $1,500 to $3,000."
</p><p>
<i>Life</i> magazine recently carried an article on this trend toward child marriages resulting from
the present dating tendencies of American children. After showing what leads up to these
tragic marriages, the article discussed the divorces which result. It quoted Judge Willard
Gatling of Charlotte, North Carolina on the subject. Said the judge: Teenage marriage has
almost no possibility of succeeding. Ninety percent are total failures."
</p><p>
The fact is that neither the boy nor the girl at this tender age is in any way prepared for
marriage. The boy and girl want what they think is the fun, but they do not want the
responsibility. Said one youngster quoted in Life magazine: "I'm a party boy. I just ain't cut
out to be married."
</p><p>
What are the reasons for these early child marriages? Why do we have so many of these
adolescent tragedies? Let me list a few of the reasons.
</p><p>
1. Early dating. Unfortunately this early dating is often encouraged by parents, school
officials, and occasionally by some church groups. Children are actually urged at times to date
when they are but 11, 12, and 13 years of age.
</p><p>
2. Early dating soon grows into early steady dating. Some go steady at 13 and 14, while many
do so at 15 and 16.
</p><p>
3. Steady dating is encouraged by steady dancing where one boy dances with one girl all
evening.
</p><p>
4. Early steady dating demands the use of automobiles. In North Carolina, where one study
was conducted it was learned that many ninth grade girls, 13 and 14 years old, dated only
boys with cars, and many of those boys were under 16, which is the legal driving age. One
13-year-old boy said, "I asked a girl of my age for a date. She asked me if I drove a car. I
said no. 'Well,' she said, 'come back and ask me when you do.'"
</p><p>
5. Early steady dating and the free use of automobiles by children lead to early intimacies and
immorality. Said one girl who was asked about this subject: "We loved each other so much,
and we were together just all the time. And there's not much to do, you know&mdash;the drive-in
movies, and the movies downtown, and that's about all. So after you've seen all the movies,
you just park the car and if you're in love&mdash;well, that's it."
</p><p>
6. Early intimacies bring early child marriages.
</p><p>
7. Child marriages bring on divorce, as Judge Gatling said, in ninety percent of the cases.
</p><p>
Writing in <i>Better Homes and Gardens</i> magazine recently, Howard Williams discussed the
great moral breakdown of the so-called "enlightened era," and said: "Promiscuity, illegitimacy,
heartbreak, and misery are all that the enlightened era has brought us. Let's put an end to
them."
</p><p>
But how can we put an end to them? In order to do so we must see the problem clearly. To
help us in our study permit me to ask some pointed questions of you as parents.
</p><p>
1. How early should young people date? Do you think it is wise for 12 and 13 and 14
year-old children to date?
</p><p>
2. Should schools or other public organizations sponsor dances for early teens and require that
only couples come? Should schoolteachers force early dating upon these youngsters? By what
right do they exclude children from school-sponsored socials because they or their parents
oppose dating at this early age?
</p><p>
3. At what age should girls begin wearing lipstick and dressing and acting like grown-ups? At
12 or 13, or even younger? This may seem like a trivial thing, but does not the early use of
lipstick mean an early invitation to dating, and does not early dating so often lead to early
tragedy?
</p><p>
4. Should little boys and girls kiss and neck? The youngsters themselves should think
carefully about that question. They may kid themselves into thinking that early necking is a
sign that they have now grown up. But is it? In reality it is but the first step to the more
serious and tragic petting which drags so many 13, 14, 15, and 16 year-old children down into
a loss of virtue and into forced marriages or illegal operations.
</p><p>
5. When should young people begin going steady? Should it be while they are yet in junior
and senior high school? Or should steady dating be reserved for the time when young people
are actually considering marriage, and are old enough to consider it sensibly and realistically,
and are capable of carrying on the responsibilities of marriage?
</p><p>
6. After their first ruinous experience in child marriage and child divorce, do the young
people consider that in the future they might desire a good marriage, a permanent one, with a
respectable and well-established partner? And do they consider that when they come to that
age, the good fellows and the desirable girls may not wish to marry someone else's castoff?
</p><p>
What are some of the remedies for this situation? First and foremost I believe that it lies in
large part in the parents' assuming their proper role as guardians of their children. Parents
need not forever be slaves to the philosophy that they must obey their children in every whim.
Parents must assume the position of leadership in the family. They must make the basic
decisions of family life and not leave these decisions to the spoiled children of the household.
</p><p>
In an article in a recent issue of <i>This Week</i> magazine, under the caption, "Don't Let Them
Grow up Too Fast," the author referred to a study made in North Carolina, where parents got
together to slow down early dating and early marriage in that state. The parents formed a
league to do so. The article said: "The kids themselves approve of the slow-down program.
They don't want to be pushed into adulthood. And far from resenting clear-cut rules and
regulations they appreciate guidance and discipline.
</p><p>
"One 14 year-old girl said: 'Since my parents joined the league, they've begun telling me
what I can do and what I can't do, and frankly, it's a big load off my mind. And anyway,
isn't that what parents are for?'"
</p><p>
Parents must screen the playmates and dating partners of their children. Parents must decide
when the child is old enough to date. Parents must provide chaperonage for early social
activities of their children. Parents must make certain that their children have a proper
conception of true values, moral, economic, and religious.
</p><p>
It is an interesting thing that studies made in the Family Service Agency of San Bernardino
showed that among divorcees forty-three percent never went to church at all; thirty-five
percent went occasionally; and only twenty-two percent attended church with any regularity.
</p><p>
Parents must decide on the use of the family car by their youngsters. In this connection they
must be obedient to the law, and not permit their children to drive until they reach legal age.
</p><p>
They might also have in mind the paragraph about automobiles contained in an article by
Jacob M. Braude, circuit court judge in Chicago, who listed the fifteen chief causes of
juvenile delinquency, and said: 
</p><p>
"A boy or a girl under 21 has no business owning a car, period. These young people simply
don't have the sense of moral and social responsibility that should go hand in hand with the
ownership of an automobile.
</p><p>
"Now I don't mean by this that it is wrong for properly licensed boys or girls to drive the
family car under effective parental supervision . . . But the key to the automobile problem is
proper adult supervision&mdash;and this is difficult, indeed, when the juvenile himself owns the
car. Youngsters who buy automobiles legitimately are faced with the constant drain of buying
gas and maintaining the car, a problem that too many of them solve with a siphon hose or
money stolen from home. A large percentage of the sex offenses can also be traced directly to
juvenile ownership of cars."
</p><p>
Parents must be exemplary themselves.  How can they expect their children to respect them if
they themselves are not respectable, or if they themselves are not obedient to law and order? 
How can parents expect their children to accept their discipline if the parents refuse to
discipline themselves?
</p><p>
And then parents, as adult citizens and taxpayers, must express themselves on school problems
which affect their own children. They must become vocal and active members of
parent-teacher groups and other organizations which can sway opinion and policy with respect
to the social life of their children at school. Parents must cooperate with law and enforcement
officers in their efforts to preserve law and order in their communities.
</p><p>
Parents must develop good character in children, a love of righteousness, faith, a respect for
other people, and they must help their children to overcome selfishness, and to live for the
future, and not for the momentary lusts or so-called pleasures of today.
</p><p>
Does it seem that I lay too much upon the parents? Not when you realize that the parents hold
the key to the situation.
</p><p>
The Boy Scouts of America engaged the Institute of Social Research of the University of
Michigan to make a study of adolescent young people. That study showed that the vast
majority of young people&mdash;ninety-four percent&mdash;desire and expect that
their parents will provide leadership for them and give them guidance; ninety-five percent said
they are willing to take parents' rule on what time to come in at night; eighty-seven percent
are willing to accept their parents' advice pertaining to money; seventy-six percent accept
their parents' guidance in personal problems; sixty-two percent accept their parents' advice on
how to act when out in a crowd; ninety percent believe that when parents make rules, those
rules are for the benefit of the youngsters, and not for the convenience of the parents.
</p><p>
But the survey also showed a tragic note&mdash;the parents do not live up to the expectations of
the youngsters. They fail to provide the leadership their own children expect of them.
</p><p>
When the study endeavored to find out how many parents plan family activities to include the
children, it was discovered that only seventeen percent provide such activities regularly; sixty
percent only occasionally; and twenty-two percent not at all.
</p><p>
All of this points up the wisdom of the Lord in laying upon the parents the responsibility of
rearing and training their own children, and adding that if they fail to do so, the sin be upon
the head of the parents.
</p><p>
Now I ask you&mdash;do you want an early child marriage for your youngster, with only a ten
percent chance of that marriage being successful? Do you want to take the chance on
immorality that forcefully confronts you if you permit your child to date early, and especially
if you permit the child to date steadily?
</p><p>
Are you willing to assume the full guardianship of your own child, and protect that child
from its own whims and the whims of others?
</p><p>
Are you willing to stand at the crossroads with your child and protect him or her from the
temptation and degradation that usually accompanies early and steady dating? Are you willing
to do for your child what the Lord asks you to do, to rear that child as a faithful Latter-day
Saint, a good citizen, and give him an opportunity to work out his future successfully?
</p><p>
You as parents hold the key to the situation. You are the custodians and the guardians of your
own children. If you do not guard and protect and rear them, who will?
</p><p>
I humbly and earnestly pray that we will assume the responsibility which is ours, and love our
children well enough to train them and guide them, and give to them the leadership and
direction which most young people expect of their parents, and this is my humble and earnest
prayer, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
