<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Who Would Justify&mdash;A Little Sin?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder ElRay L. Christiansen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">ElRay L. Christiansen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 68-70</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I humbly pray, my brothers and sisters, that what I say may give encouragement and fortitude
to someone. We have had some marvelous addresses given, some wonderful music, all of
which should inspire us to go forth and live better lives.
</p><p>
I believe that each of us needs a spiritual checkup just about as often as we need a physical
checkup; that each of us, the young, and the rest of us, needs to make an appraisal of himself
as a member of the Church of Jesus Christ, and as the head of a family, or as a member of a
family, from time to time to determine the degree of our fidelity and our allegiance and
adherence to the accepted rules and doctrines of the Church.
</p><p>
One of the ancient prophets of whom Elder Kimball spoke, had this day in mind&mdash;when he
said: 
</p><p>
"Yea, and there shall be many which shall say: Eat, drink, and be merry, for tomorrow
we die . . .<br />
"And there shall also be many which shall say: Eat, drink, and be merry; nevertheless, fear
God&mdash;he will justify in committing a little sin; yea, lie a little, take the advantage of one
because of his words, dig a pit for thy neighbor; there is no harm in this; and do all these
things, for tomorrow we die; and if it so be that we are guilty, God will beat us with a few
stripes, and at last we shall be saved in the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/7-8#7">2 Ne. 28:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
Is this prediction of Nephi coming to pass in our day? Are there those of us who would
justify ourselves in committing a little sin? Are there those of us who would yield to the
enticement and the pressure of acquaintances and associates to "eat, drink, and be merry," on
certain occasions? Would we, for instance, when in the company of certain others, forsake
principles, propriety, and decency in order to conform with and be accepted by the group? So
called social drinking, for example? Would we forsake the high principles of conduct which
we as a people espouse and yield to the unapproved practices when we know that to do so
weakens one's character, discredits his family name, and will bring sorrow and unhappiness in
place of joy and peace?
</p><p>
"We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all
men . . . If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after
these things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
This being the case&mdash;this being our standard, could it be then that any of us would lie a
little, or take advantage of one because of his words, perhaps by misquoting or exaggerating
what he said? Are there any of us who would figuratively dig a pit for his
neighbor, hoping that he will fall into it? Perhaps by taking unfair advantage of him, by
shrewd maneuvering, thinking that as long as one gets away with it that he is a trustworthy
and honest man.
</p><p>
"Make of yourself an honest man," said Carlyle, "and then you may be sure that there is one
rascal less in the world."
</p><p>
Are there any of us who would justify ourselves in any of these things, these wrongdoings? If
there be, let us repent as of today. Farther on, this same great prophet, Nephi, points out that
those who feel justified in sinning a little, being enticed by the vain practices of the world, are
placing themselves in a position where, he says, "the devil cheateth their souls, and leadeth
them carefully down to hell"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/21#21">2 Ne. 28:21</a>).
How well put that is, and how true!
</p><p>
The evils and the vanities of the world, and the corruption thereof are thrust close to our
lives. Enticings and pressures to depart from the right are found on every hand. Some of these
wrongdoings are almost glorified.
</p><p>
Realizing this, we must, as Latter-day Saints, young and old, be firm for that which we know
to be right, and in the right be steadfast and immovable. Each of us must set his own course.
Each household must determine whether its members will follow the worldly pattern of loose,
reckless living, or be obedient to the commandments of the Lord.
</p><p>
When the tribes of ancient Israel inclined their hearts toward the worship of heathen gods,
forsaking God-given principles, you remember that Joshua, their leader, fearing for his people,
". . . gathered all the tribes of Israel to Shechem, and called for the elders of Israel, and for
their heads, and for their judges, and for their officers; and they presented themselves before
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/1#1">Josh. 24:1</a>).
Then it was that he pointed out to them what was happening among
them, and admonished them to put away their strange gods and their evil ways, and he called
upon them to repent, exhorting them to serve the Lord God of Israel with sincerity. Then in
the majesty of his calling as a prophet, he said to them, ". . . choose you this day whom ye
will serve; . . . but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
Just as Israel in that day had to make that decision, so must that decision be made by us
today. I must make that decision. You must make that decision. For example, in this day of
widespread desecration of the Sabbath, when it is considered merely a part of a weekend, and
when it is used by many for amusement and pleasure-hunting, shopping, etc., do I, do you,
serve the Lord by being where we ought to be, doing what we ought to do, on his holy day?
</p><p>
Again, when friends or acquaintances urge the use of tobacco or intoxicating liquor, do we
yield just to be sociable? If I and my house are determined to serve the Lord in the law of
health, there will be no yielding to such pressures.
</p><p>
When marriage is contemplated, will the plan be a temporary legal arrangement where eternal
association is forfeited, or will it be administered according to the ordinances of God;
according to his sweet and wonderful way of making possible a grand family reunion in the
resurrection? That is the question we must determine when it comes to that occasion, or
before it comes to that, for we must plan ahead of time for that great episode in our lives.
</p><p>
One other matter&mdash;the destroying sin of unchastity and moral laxity has been one of the
dominant factors in the downfall of many proud people and many great empires. Among the
people today, this same destroyer of happiness presents a dismal picture for the safety and
peace of this and future generations.
</p><p>
A few years ago the First Presidency issued a warning to the Latter-day Saints and to the
world generally against this sin. Among other positive statements they made, they said this:
"The doctrine of this Church is that sexual sin, the illicit sexual relationship of men and
women stands in its enormity next to murder. The Lord has drawn no essential distinction
between fornication, adultery, and harlotry or prostitution. Each has fallen under his solemn
and awful condemnation. You youth of Zion," they pleaded, "you cannot associate in illicit
sex relationship, which is fornication, and escape the judgments and punishments of the Lord
which he has declared against this sin. The day of reckoning will come just
as certainly as night follows day."
</p><p>
A similar warning was given to those husbands and wives who break the moral laws. Then,
by the right they have as leaders of the Church of Jesus Christ, spokesman for the Lord
himself, they gave this solemn warning, along with a plea for strict morality: "By virtue of the
authority vested in us as the First Presidency of the Church, we warn the people of the
degradation, the wickedness, the punishments that attend upon unchastity. We urge you to
remember the blessings which flow from the living of a clean life. We call upon you to keep,
day in and day out, the way of strict chastity, through which only God's blessings can be
achieved and received, and his Spirit abide with you. How glorious it is to him who lives the
chaste life. He walks unfearful in the glare of the noonday sun, for he is without moral
infirmity."
</p><p>
Now, will we listen to those who would minimize the seriousness of this transgression and
who would have us believe that the Lord has changed his mind in regard to it? Will we listen
to those who say that chastity is outmoded and old-fashioned? Each of us must stand for and
encourage such principles as honesty, trustworthiness, virtue. Let us turn a deaf ear to the
advocates of wrongdoing, and be prepared with Joshua to say, as he did to his people: ". . .
choose you this day whom ye will serve; but as for me and my house we will serve the
Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
May we so do, I pray humbly, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
