<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Be Ye Clean"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bruce R. McConkie</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bruce R. McConkie, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1952, pp. 125-126</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Just this brief word: 
</p><p>
Be clean, be pure, be chaste, for no unclean thing, no impure thing, and no unchaste thing can
inherit the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
God spoke to Father Adam and said,
</p><p>
. . . teach it unto your children, that all men, everywhere, must repent, or they can in
nowise inherit the kingdom of God, for no unclean thing can dwell there, or dwell in
his presence (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/57#57">Moses 6:57</a>).
</p><p>
The voice of the Lord was given by Amulek, saying,
</p><p>
. . . no unclean thing can inherit the kingdom of heaven; therefore how can ye be
saved, except ye inherit the kingdom of heaven? Therefore, ye cannot be saved in your
sins (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/37#37">Alma 11:37</a>).
</p><p>
And when Christ summarized the plan of salvation to the Nephites, he did it by saying,
</p><p>
And no unclean thing can enter into his kingdom; therefore nothing entereth into his
rest save it be those who have washed their garments in my blood, because of their
faith, and the repentance of all their sins, and their faithfulness unto the end.
</p><p>
Now this is the commandment: Repent, all ye ends of the earth and come unto me and
be baptized in my name, that ye may be sanctified by the reception of the Holy Ghost,
that ye may stand spotless before me at the last day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/19-20#19">3 Ne. 27:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
No unclean thing can inherit the kingdom of heaven. ". . . Be ye clean that bear the vessels
of the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/5#5">D&amp;C 133:5</a>).
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
