<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">They of the Last Wagon</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 154-160</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters; I should like in the beginning to add my testimony to the many that
we have heard during this conference&mdash;my testimony that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ,
the Redeemer of the world the firstfruits of the resurrection
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/20#20">1 Cor. 15:20</a>); that Joseph Smith was a
prophet; that through him the gospel was restored and likewise the priesthood, the authority
delegated to man on earth to represent Deity here among us; and that the Prophet has been
followed down to and including our present President, George Albert Smith, by men who
possessed the keys of the last dispensation as conferred upon Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
The matter that I shall give you today is very dear to my soul. Since I should like to say what
I have to say in the best way I can say it, I have written it down and shall read it. I hope that
what I shall say will be in harmony with the spirit of this great conference, I think the
greatest I have attended in its high spiritual tone.
</p><p>
TRIBUTE TO PIONEERS
</p><p>
At the near close of this one hundredth year of the entering into these valleys
of your fathers and your mothers, some of yours and mine, I wish to speak a few further
words of humble tribute and thanksgiving to them, and especially to the meekest and lowliest
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/29#29">Matt. 11:29</a>)
of them, those great souls, majestic in the simplicity of their faith and in their living
testimony of the truth of the restored gospel, to those souls in name unknown, unremembered,
unhonored in the pages of history, but lovingly revered round the hearthstones of their
children and their children's children who pass down from generation to generation the story
of their faith and their mighty works, and the righteousness of their lives and living, those
souls who worked and worked, and prayed and followed, and wrought so gloriously.
</p><p>
I would not take away one word of praise or gratitude, honor or reverence from the great men
who led these humble ones of ours. They were mighty men in brain and brawn, in courage
and valor, in honesty and in love of truth, living near the Lord&mdash;Brothers Brigham and Heber
and Wilford and Willard and Charles, the two Orsons and Parley, and John and George and
Erastus and Lorenzo and Daniel and Joseph and Jedediah, and a host of other giants, each and
all richly blessed with the Lord's divine love and with that gift of the Holy Ghost that made
them leaders truly like unto Moses of old
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/91#91">D&amp;C 107:91</a>).
I yield, we yield, to no one in our gratitude for
them and for their work of directing the conquest of the wilderness and of saving men's souls.
Their names shine lustrously on those pages of history which record only the doings of the
makers of epochs&mdash;those choice spirits, chosen before the foundation of the world, to be the
leaders and builders of dispensations of God's dealings with men; and these leaders of ours to
be the builders of that dispensation which of old was named the Dispensation of the Fulness
of Time. Unnumbered eternities will remember and honor them.
</p><p>
But I should like now and here to say a few words about those who trod after where those
giants led, some in the same companies that the Brethren piloted, some in later companies
following that year and the years after, some in the fateful handcarts with their un-excelled
devotion, heroism, and faith, all trickling forward in a never-failing, tiny stream, till they
filled the valley they entered and then flowed out at the sides and ends, peopling this whole
wilderness-waste which they fructified, making it to fulfil the ancient prophecy that the desert
should blossom as the rose (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/1#1">Isa. 35:1</a>).
</p><p>
THEY OF THE LAST WAGON
</p><p>
I would like to say something about the last wagon in each of the long wagon trains that
toiled slowly over the plains, up mountain defiles, down steep, narrow canyons, and out into
the valley floor that was to be home&mdash;this last wagon: last, because the ox team that pulled it
was the smallest and leanest and weakest, and had the tenderest feet of any in the train; it was
slow starting, and slow moving; last, because worn and creaking, it took more time to fix and
to grease, for young Jimmy generally had trouble in getting the wagon jack
under the "ex"; last, because its wind-rent cover was old and patched and took hours to mend
and tie up to keep out the storm; last, because the wife, heavy with child, must rest till the
very moment of starting; last, because sickly little Bill, the last born, poorly nourished, must
be washed and coaxed to eat the rough food, all they had; last, because with all his
tasks&mdash;helping little Bill, cooking and cleaning up the breakfast,&mdash;Mother was not able to help
much&mdash;Father took a little longer little longer to yoke his cattle and to gird himself for the
day's labor; last, because his morning prayers took a few more minutes than the others
spent&mdash;he had so many blessings to thank the Lord for and some special blessings to ask the
Lord to grant blessings of health and strength, especially for his wife, and for little Bill, and
for the rest, and then the blessings for himself that his own courage would not fail, but most
of all for the blessing of faith, faith in God and in the Brethren who sometimes seemed so far
away. For they were out in front where the air was clear and clean and where they had
unbroken vision of the blue vault of heaven. The Brethren had really visioned the glory of the
Lord, who walked near them, put his thoughts into their minds; his spirit guided and directed
them, petitioned thereto by the thousands of Saints who were back in Winter Quarters, back
in Iowa, back in the States, and beyond, even across the waters, for the faithful poured out
their souls in fervent prayer to Almighty God that the Brethren should be inspired. The Saints
buoyed up the Brethren out in front with encouragement, with praise, and sometimes even
with adulation. Knowing the Brethren were prophets of God, the Saints gave them full
confidence, daily, almost hourly, expressed. The Brethren lived in a world of commendation
from friends and the tried and true Saints. Rarely was their word or their act questioned by
the faithful Saints. This was as it should be and had to be to carry out the Lord's purposes.
</p><p>
But back in the last wagon, not always could they see the Brethren way out in front, and the
blue heaven was often shut out from their sight by heavy, dense clouds of the dust of the
earth. Yet day after day, they of the last wagon pressed forward, worn and tired, footsore,
sometimes almost disheartened, borne up by their faith that God loved them, that the restored
gospel was true and that the Lord led and directed the Brethren out in front. Sometimes, they
in the last wagon glimpsed, for an instant, when faith surged strongest, the glories of a
celestial world, but it seemed so far away, and the vision so quickly vanished, because want
and weariness and heartache and sometimes discouragement were always pressing so near.
When the vision faded, their hearts sank. But they prayed again and pushed on, with little
praise, with not too much encouragement, and never with adulation. For there was nearly
always something wrong with the last wagon or with its team&mdash;the off ox was a little lame in
the right front shoulder; the hub of the left front wheel was often hot; the tire of the hind
wheel on the same side was loose. So corrective counsel, sometimes strong reproof, was the
rule, because the wagon must not delay the whole train. But yet in that last wagon there was
devotion and loyalty and integrity, and above and beyond everything else,
faith in the Brethren and in God's power and goodness. For had not the Lord said that "not
even a sparrow falleth unnoticed by the Father, and were they not of more value than
sparrows?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/29-31#29">Matt. 10:29-31</a>).
And then they had their testimony burning always like an eternal fire on a holy
altar, that the restored gospel was true, and that Joseph was a prophet of God, and that
Brigham was Joseph's chosen successor.
</p><p>
When the train moved forward in the early morning sun and the oxen with a swinging pull
that almost broke the tongue got that last wagon on the move, the dust in the still morning air
hung heavy over the road. Each wagon from the first stirred up its own cloud, till when the
last wagon swung into line, that dust was dense and suffocating. It covered the last wagon and
all that was in it; it clung to clothes; it blackened faces; it filled eyes already sore, and ears.
The wife, soon to be a mother, could hardly catch her breath in the heavy, choking dust, for
even in the pure air she breathed hard from her burden. Each jolt of the wagon, for those
ahead had made wagon ruts almost "ex" deep, wrung from her clenched lips a half-groan she
did her best to keep from the ears of the anxious, solicitous husband plodding slowly along,
guiding and goading the poor dumb cattle, themselves weary from the long trek. So through
the long day of jolting and discomfort and sometimes pain, sometimes panting for breath, the
mother, anxious only that the unborn babe should not be injured, rode, for she could not
walk; and the children walked, for the load was too heavy and big for them to ride; and the
father walked sturdily alongside and prayed.
</p><p>
When in the evening the last wagon creaked slowly into its place in the circle corral, and the
Brethren came to inquire how the day had gone with the mother, then joy leaped in their
hearts, for had not the Brethren remembered them? New hope was born, weariness fled, fresh
will to do was enkindled; gratitude to God was poured out for their knowledge of the truth,
for their testimony that God lived, that Jesus was the Christ, that Joseph was a prophet, that
Brigham was his ordained successor, and that for the righteous a crown of glory awaited that
should be theirs during the eternities of the life to come. Then they would join in the songs
and dancing in the camp, making the camp's gaiety their own, as much as Mother's condition
would permit.
</p><p>
Then the morning came when from out that last wagon floated the la-la of the newborn babe,
and mother love made a shrine, and Father bowed in reverence before it. But the train must
move on. So out into the dust and dirt the last wagon moved again, swaying and jolting,
while Mother eased as best she could each pain-giving jolt so no harm might be done her, that
she might be strong to feed the little one, bone of her bone, flesh of her flesh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/23#23">Gen. 2:23</a>). Who will dare
to say that angels did not cluster round and guard her and ease her rude bed, for she had
given another choice spirit its mortal body that it might work out its God-given destiny?
</p><p>
My mother was one of those babes so born in 1848, ninety-nine years ago.
</p><p>
Another morning came, when courageous little Bill, who, with a hero's heart, had trudged
through long days of hot sun and through miles of soggy mud in the rain, his little body
drenched, little Bill, weak and wan, must be crowded in to ride with Mother, for he was sick
from a heavy cold. Months before, on that cold winter's night when they had fled Nauvoo for
their lives to escape the fiendish wrath of a wild mob, Bill became dangerously ill with
pneumonia, which left him with weak lungs. This old illness now returned. He grew worse
and worse. The elders came and prayed he might get well. But the Lord wanted little Bill
with him. So a few mornings later a weeping mother and a grief-stricken father and that last
wagon swung into place in the line, leaving beside the road, under some scrub brush a little
mound, unmarked save for heaped-up rocks to keep out the wolves, a mound that covered
another martyr to the cause of truth.
</p><p>
So through dust and dirt, dirt and dust, during the long hours, the longer days&mdash;that grew into
weeks and then into months, they crept along till, passing down through its portals, the valley
welcomed them to rest and home. The cattle dropped to their sides, wearied almost to death;
nor moved they without goading, for they too sensed they had come to the journey's end.
</p><p>
That evening was the last of the great trek, the mightiest trek that history records since
Israel's flight from Egypt, and as the sun sank below the mountain peaks of the west and the
eastern crags were bathed in an amethyst glow that was a living light, while the western
mountainsides were clothed in shadows of the rich blue of the deep sea, they of the last
wagon, and of the wagon before them, and of the one before that, and so to the very front
wagon of the train, these all sank to their knees in the joy of their souls, thanking God that at
last they were in Zion. "Zion, Zion, lovely Zion, beautiful Zion, Zion, City of our God." They
knew there was a God, for only he could have brought them triumphant, militant, through all
the scorn, the ridicule, the slander, the tarrings and featherings, the whippings, the burnings,
the plunderings, the murderings, the ravishings of wives and daughters, that had been their lot,
the lot of their people since Joseph visioned the Father and the Son.
</p><p>
But hundreds of these stalwart souls of undoubting faith and great prowess, were not yet at
their journey's end.
</p><p>
Brother Brigham again called them to the colors of the kingdom of God, and sent them to
settle the valleys, near and remote, in these vast mountains of refuge. So again they yoked
their oxen and hitched up their teams, and putting their all in the covered wagon, this time
willingly, unwhipped by the threat of mob cruelty and outrage, they wended their slow way to
new valleys, again trusting with implicit faith in the wisdom and divine guidance of their
Moses. The very elements obeyed their faith, faith close kin to that which made the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/3#3">Heb. 11:3</a>).
</p><p>
These tens of thousands who so moved and so built were the warp and the woof of Brother
Brigham's great commonwealth. Without them Brother Brigham had failed his mission. These
were the instruments&mdash;the shovelers, the plowers, and sowers and reapers, the machinists, the
architects, the masons, the woodworkers, the organ builders, the artisans, the mathematicians,
the men of letters, all gathered from the four corners of the earth, furnished by the Lord to
Brother Brigham and the prophet leaders who came after, that he and they might direct the
working out of His purposes. These wrought as God inspired Brother Brigham and the other
prophets to plan, all to the glory of God and the up-building of his kingdom.
</p><p>
Upright men they were, and fearless, unmindful of what men thought or said of them, if they
were in their line of duty. Calumny, slander, derision, scorn left them unmoved, if they were
treading the straight and narrow way. Uncaring they were of men's blame and censure, if the
Lord approved them. Unswayed they were by the praise of men, to wander from the path of
truth. Endowed by the spirit of discernment, they knew when kind words were mere courtesy,
and when they betokened honest interest. They moved neither to the right nor to the left from
the path of truth to court the good favor of men.
</p><p>
CONTRIBUTIONS OF HUMBLE SOULS
</p><p>
So for a full hundred years, urged by the spirit of gathering and led by a burning testimony of
the truth of the restored gospel, thousands upon tens of thousands of these humble souls, one
from a city, two from a family (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/3/14#14">Jer. 3:14</a>),
have bidden farewell to friends and homes and loved ones,
and with sundered heartstrings, companioned with privation and with sacrifice even to life
itself, these multitudes have made their way to Zion, to join those who were privileged to
come earlier, that all might build up the kingdom of God on earth&mdash;all welded together by
common hardship and suffering, never-ending work and deep privation, tragic woes and
heart-eating griefs, abiding faith and exalting joy, firm testimony and living spiritual
knowledge&mdash;a mighty people, missioned with the salvation, not only of the living, but of the
dead also, saviors not worshipers of their ancestors, their hearts aglow with the divine fire of
the spirit of Elijah, who turns the hearts of the fathers to the children and of the children to
the fathers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6#5">Mal. 4:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
And thousands upon thousands of these tens of thousands, from the first till now, all the elect
of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/34#34">D&amp;C 84:34</a>),
measured to their humble calling and to their destiny as fully as Brother Brigham and
the others measured to theirs, and God will so reward them. They were pioneers in word and
thought and act and faith, even as were they of more exalted station. The building of this
intermountain empire was not done in a corner
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/26#26">Acts 26:26</a>)
by a select few but by this vast multitude
flowing in from many nations, who came and labored and wrought, faithfully following their
divinely called leaders.
</p><p>
WE MUST RISE BY OUR OWN LABOR
</p><p>
In living our lives let us never forget that the deeds of our fathers and mothers are theirs, not
ours; that their works cannot be counted to our glory; that we can claim no excellence and no
place, because of what they did, that we must rise by our own labor, and that labor failing we
shall fail. We may claim no honor, no reward, no respect, nor special position or recognition,
no credit because of what our fathers were or what they wrought. We stand upon our own
feet in our own shoes. There is no aristocracy of birth in this Church; it belongs equally to the
highest and the lowliest; for as Peter said to Cornelius, the Roman centurion, seeking him:
</p><p>
. . . Of a truth I perceive that God is no respecter of persons: But in every nation
he that feareth him, and worketh righteousness, is accepted with him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/34-35#34">Acts 10:34-35</a>).
</p><p>
So to these humble but great souls, our fathers and mothers, the tools of the Lord, who have,
for this great people, hewed the stones and laid the foundations of God's kingdom, solid as
the granite mountains from which they carved the rocks for their temple, to these humble
souls, great in faith, great in work, great in righteous living, great in fashioning our priceless
heritage, I humbly render my love, my respect, my reverent homage. God keep their
memories ever fresh among us, their children, to help us meet our duties even as they met
theirs, that God's work may grow and prosper till the restored gospel of Jesus Christ rules all
nations and all peoples, till peace, Christ's peace, shall fill the whole earth, till "righteousness
shall cover the earth even as the waters cover the mighty deep"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/11/9#9">Isa. 11:9</a>). Let us here and now dedicate
all that we have and all that we are to this divine work. May God help us so to do, I humbly
pray in Jesus' name, his Son. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
