<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Conforming to Priesthood Principles</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Robert L. Simpson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Robert L. Simpson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 96-99</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren of the priesthood: With you I thrill at the testimonies of these young men of
the Aaronic Priesthood. How grateful we are for the testimonies of youth and for the great
spirit that they carry. Dennis, Mark, and Jeffery, we thank you. We are grateful for the
strength of youth. Oh, that three billion people could be receptive to these testimonies and
know what the gospel of Jesus Christ can do for the youth of the world!
</p><p>
<b>"Living Water"</b>
</p><p>
You know, brethren, throughout history men have always been looking for the easy way.
There have been those who have devoted their lives to finding "the fountain of youth," a
miracle water which would bring everlasting life. Today men are still seeking for similar
treasures, some magic "fountain" that would bring forth success, fulfillment, and happiness.
But most of this searching is in vain, because they are looking for shortcuts. Unless they turn
to him who offered the Samaritan woman at Jacob's well a drink of "living water" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/10#10">John 4:10</a>), then their
searching will indeed he in vain, for he told her: ". . . whosoever drinketh of the water that I
shall give him shall never thirst; but the water that I shall give him shall be in him a well of
water springing up into everlasting life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/14#14">John 4:14</a>). It is only this "living water," the gospel
of Jesus Christ, that can and will bring a happy, a successful, and an everlasting life to the
children of men.
</p><p>
The "living water" that the Son of God offers is a set of divine principles. These principles
are proven principles&mdash;they are priesthood principles which, when applied, can result in the
blessings of eternity. How well you and I learn and practice these priesthood principles is not
just important, young men; it is <i>everything</i>. Everything worthwhile in your life, everything
you hope and dream for, is embraced in priesthood principles.
</p><p>
<b>The tragedy of Cain</b>
</p><p>
The scriptures tell of some who have tragically disregarded priesthood principles. In the very
beginning we can see Cain, a man whose birth gave his mother a great deal of joy, for she
said, "I have gotten a man from the Lord." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/16#16">Moses 5:16</a>). However, Cain departed from
the principles taught to him by his parents and began to love Satan more than God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/18#18">Moses 5:18</a>). "And
Cain went into the field, and Cain talked with Abel, his brother. And it came to pass that
while they were in the field, Cain rose up against Abel, his brother, and slew him.
</p><p>
"And Cain gloried in that which he had done, saying: I am free." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/32-33#32">Moses 5:32-33</a>).
</p><p>
Cain's observation of a newfound freedom was false doctrine straight from the adversary. In
reality he enslaved himself to a life of deceit and a life "shut out from the presence of the
Lord." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/41#41">Moses 5:41</a>). Cain brought this tragedy to his own life by disregarding priesthood
principles. He refused to be his "brother's keeper" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/9#9">Gen. 4:9</a>), and in so doing he sold his soul to the father of lies and murder.
</p><p>
<b>Saul's disobedience</b>
</p><p>
We can also look to Saul, the promising young ruler of Israel who had every requirement of a
great leader. Yet Saul disobeyed priesthood principles. He was given specific instructions by a
prophet of God to lead the armies of Israel against the city of Amalek (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/1-9#1">1 Sam. 15:1-9</a>). But Saul rationalized
and compromised those instructions. He acted on his own volition. He did that which he
reasoned should be done rather than that which the prophet Samuel had instructed him to do.
</p><p>
On subsequent occasions Saul further violated priesthood principles (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/13/8-14#8">1 Sam. 13:8-14</a>), but just as with Cain,
these misdeeds brought only tragedy and sorrow. Finally, Saul took his life by falling upon
his own sword during a battle with the Philistines
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/31/1-4#1">1 Sam. 31:1-4</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_chr/10/4#4">1 Chr. 10:4</a>).
</p><p>
While the disregarding of priesthood principles has and does bring anguish and sorrow into
people's lives, obedience to the principles of righteousness is that "living water" which brings
a life of everlasting joy and fulfillment. The scriptures tell of many who have drunk of this
living water" and received everlasting joy. One of the prime examples of a man who knew the
value of adhering to priesthood principles and had the courage to live accordingly is Noah.
</p><p>
<b>Man free to act</b>
</p><p>
In the face of ridicule and even at the peril of his life, Noah remained steadfast to the
principles of the priesthood. The scriptures describe Noah's devotion in these simple,
straightforward terms: "Thus did Noah; according to all that God commanded him, so did he"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/6/22#22">Gen. 6:22</a>).
</p><p>
"And thus Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord; for Noah was a just man, and perfect in
his generation; and he walked with God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/8/27#27">Moses 8:27</a>). Noah tasted of the joy of life
because he adhered firmly to the principles of righteousness.
</p><p>
In our time the distinction is just as clear; the "living water" on the one hand, sorrow and
tragedy on the other. As the Lamanite prophet Samuel declared, ". . . for behold, ye are free;
ye are permitted to act for yourselves; for behold, God hath given unto you a knowledge and
he hath made you free.
</p><p>
"He hath given unto you that ye might know good from evil, and he hath given unto you that
ye might choose life or death; and ye can do good and be restored unto that which is good, or
have that which is good restored unto you; or ye can do evil, and have that which is evil
restored unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/14/30-31#30">Hel. 14:30-31</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Sure test of truth</b>
</p><p>
The choice seems clear and obvious, but the sure test of truth must be applied by each of us.
We must apply the principles of the priesthood in our own lives. To be taught truth is not
enough. We must participate to be sure of the doctrine, to be certain of its truth. Only practice
can bring peace of mind and that personal testimony which enables some to stand and declare,
"I know that God lives." Young men, if you take just one thought home with you tonight, let
it be this: There stands not one man who speaks this kind of assuring testimony who did not
have to first earn that right by compliance to priesthood principles.
</p><p>
Young men, no greater security can ever come into your life than the strength and power that
comes through personal testimony. Your parents cannot give it to you without your
cooperation. Neither can the Lord force it upon you, for that would be a violation of an
eternal law called free agency.
</p><p>
<b>Rules of the game of life</b>
</p><p>
Yes, that is the name of the game, free agency, and you are the team captain. You must direct
the action in your life; and to do it intelligently, you must decide where the goal line is. You
must decide which "plays" will work best to achieve that goal. Each day should mean another
point or two scored in your favor. Which direction is the goal you seek? Why don't you think
of a few major goals this very moment&mdash;can you think of one or two? Now ask yourself this
question: "What are the rules in this vital game of life?" There is only one worthwhile
direction. There is only one set of rules and we meet here tonight to better understand that
direction and those rules, for they are centered in priesthood principles.
</p><p>
<b>Choosing life's goals</b>
</p><p>
What do you young men who hold the priesthood of God really want out of life? What do
you see that is really worthwhile on that goal line that you are striving to cross? Would I be
right in assuming that you would like a good portion of happiness in your life? Why, of
course you would. Of what value is freedom to you, or perhaps peace of mind? I am certain
that Heavenly Father would also like to see happiness be your lot, for he has said: ". . . men
are, that they might have joy" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
Did you know that the gospel could guarantee freedom, for "the truth shall make you free"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>)? The Savior of the world, I am sure, was talking about peace of mind when he
said: "Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto
you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
Would you be interested in a guarantee of good health and physical strength to carry you
along life's highway? There are some dramatic promises contained in the eighty-ninth section
of the Doctrine and Covenants (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-21#18">D&amp;C 89:18-21</a>). Those who will observe God's rules of health may have all of
those promises fulfilled.
</p><p>
Is knowledge one of your goals? The gospel teaches that man is saved no faster than he gains
knowledge, and I am sure the Lord would have you use that knowledge intelligently, for "the
glory of God is intelligence." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
</p><p>
Are you interested in a financially sound future? You can be, if you stay out of debt and
spend wisely. This has been the counsel of the Church leaders from the beginning.
</p><p>
Most young men of the Aaronic Priesthood would rather be industrious and progressive than
lazy. The welfare plan of this great Church tells us to re-enthrone work as a ruling principle
in our lives and to abolish the dole, which is a something-for-nothing program. There is no
place for it in the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Then, of course, you would have as a goal the practicing of pure religion, undefiled, caring
for the widows and the fatherless (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>). Heavenly Father has given us the law of the fast, that the
unfortunate might be provided for, and also a declaration that inasmuch as we do it unto one
of the least of these, we have done it unto him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/40#40">Matt. 25:40</a>); pure religion, undefiled, all a part of the
gospel of Jesus Christ and implemented in the law of the fast.
</p><p>
<b>Rewards of conformance</b>
</p><p>
We are all just human enough to ask the questions: What is in it for me? Is it worth the
effort? What will the end result be? If the word of the Lord means anything to us at all, then
the reasons for compliance are overwhelming, for in the seventy-sixth section of the Doctrine
and Covenants, the Lord tells us explicitly about those who conform to priesthood principles
in this life. May I quickly review some of the conditions and rewards that will most certainly
be yours as you decide to conform and then do something about it. The seventy-sixth section
of the Doctrine and Covenants says your friends and associates hereafter will be just like you:
</p><p>
Those who receive the testimony through compliance.
</p><p>
Those who were baptized in the right way by the proper authority.
</p><p>
Those who kept the commandments and received the Holy Spirit as a constant companion.
</p><p>
Those also who, with you, prepared themselves for entrance into the House of the Lord, there
to be "sealed by the Holy Spirit of promise" for all eternity to those who are nearest and
dearest, the family unit.
</p><p>
Yes, it is they to whom the Father has promised all things.
</p><p>
It is they who will be anointed priests and kings of the Most High.
</p><p>
It is they who will receive of his fullness and of his glory.
</p><p>
This remarkable revelation further continues that "they are gods, even the sons of God." Does
that mean anything to you? Is that worth striving for?
</p><p>
It states that all things are theirs, and "they are Christ's." As though that were not enough, it
further states that they "shall dwell in the presence of God and his Christ forever and ever."
Indeed, "These are they who are just men made perfect, whose bodies are celestial, whose
glory is that of the sun, even the glory of God" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/50-70#50">D&amp;C 76:50-70</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Compliance with priesthood principles</b>
</p><p>
I challenge you Aaronic Priesthood bearers to commit yourselves here and now to such a
reward hereafter. How can anything be more important than this? The very next time you are
faced with the decision of going along with the crowd in something that seems questionable
or standing firm in what you know to be right, just remember that you are a priesthood
bearer. Your commitment is to God; you must never defect to the enemy&mdash;you must remain
above such things. By so doing, you will find new strength. You will be given new power.
You will discover the deep-down joy that comes with compliance to priesthood principles.
</p><p>
I testify to you that there is no success, no joy, no true fulfillment for us in this life or in the
eternities unless our lives are in compliance with priesthood principles. This is the "living
water" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/10#10">John 4:10</a>) which can and should be a "well of water springing up into everlasting life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/14#14">John 4:14</a>).
</p><p>
I testify of the divinity of Him who offers the "living water" through compliance with the
principles of the priesthood, and I do so in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
