<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder ElRay L. Christiansen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">ElRay L. Christiansen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 74-78</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It brought great joy to my heart, as it would to yours, to hear the report of President Waite on
the progress of that great temple in which we shall worship God and participate in the higher
ordinances, performing those ordinances and receiving those powers and blessings that will
entitle us and qualify us, if we are faithful, to receive the greatest of all the gifts of God,
eternal life.  I am sure that the people in the Los Angeles area are grateful that they have an
opportunity to participate in the raising of the funds to build that great temple, for I feel we
should participate with our hearts and our hands and our means in these great
accomplishments.
</p><p>
Now, my brethren, I come before you tonight in humility and with hope and a prayer that I
may say something that might encourage someone.  This group here represents the priesthood
leadership throughout the Church.  The Lord has established and ordained a divine program
for the benefit of his children, and it is through you leaders, as well as the others in the
Church, that he must operate and proceed in order to bring about his purposes, to establish
faith, and to help his children qualify for life in the Celestial kingdom of Heaven.  It is almost
overwhelming to me, when I think of it, to realize that the progress of his plan is determined
largely by the effectiveness of the leadership throughout the Church, and in accordance to
their devotion.
</p><p>
Not only does his plan provide a way of salvation for the living, but also the means and
power whereby those who have died without a knowledge of the gospel may also be saved. 
This shows the love of God for all mankind, and the justice that he renders to all. Our
obligation as members of the Church is not alone to the living, but likewise to the dead.  For
the dead, it is a program of love and Christ-like service on the part of the living.
</p><p>
John Taylor, the President of the Church, at one time made this statement: "We are here to
cooperate with God in the salvation of the living and in the redemption of the dead, in the
blessing of our ancestors and in pouring out the blessings upon our children and their
children.  That is the object of our existence," he said.
</p><p>
It is pleasing to witness the devotion of so many of the saints in this vicarious service on
behalf of the dead.  Last Wednesday in the Salt Lake Temple, 1364 endowments were given
on behalf of the dead, besides hundreds of baptisms and sealings for the dead that went on
during that same day.  In the other temples this same program of activity is carried on day by
day on behalf of the dead, and, of course, great numbers of the living come and receive their
blessings as well.
</p><p>
Even with this great concourse of people that comes to the temples, the
Lord is way ahead of us.  He has helped us in these last days to provide modern means of
recording, of microfilming and of research throughout the libraries of the world, and has thus
speeded up the work of making available records for research purposes. 
The inflow of microfilm records into the Genealogical Library approximates now 150,000 to
200,000 pages per day. Truly, the Lord has come to our help! But, sad to say, my brethren, a
hundred thousand family group sheets are being held in the archives awaiting the endowment
ordinances for the male names on those sheets.  The endowment, of course, must be done
before these parents and their children can be sealed together.  The endowment work for the
sisters' names on those sheets has already been done.  The sisters are far ahead of the
brethren in this endowment work for the dead.
</p><p>
The fact is, there are in the Salt Lake Temple alone, more than 100,000 surplus male names
waiting there for some selfless individuals to engage in these ordinances in their behalf.  At
least another hundred thousand male names are in the files of the other temples in the Church. 
The dead, we are told, should bury the dead, but it takes the living to redeem the dead
through this vicarious service.
</p><p>
President Brigham Young, pleading for the cause of the dead, once made this statement: 
</p><p>
"What do you suppose the fathers would say if they could speak from the dead?  Would they
not say, 'We have lain here thousands of years, here in this prison house, waiting for this
dispensation to come? Here we are, bound and fettered, waiting and waiting . . .'" "Why," said
Brigham Young, "if they had the power, the very thunders of heaven would be in our ears, so
that we might realize the importance of this work!  All the angels in heaven are looking at
this little handful of people and stimulating them to the salvation of the human family . . . 
When I think upon this subject," he said, "I want the tongues of seven thunders to wake the
people.
</p><p>
(Of course, it would mean just the brethren now, since the sisters are way ahead of us.)
</p><p>
Now, brethren, in order to have the endowment work done for these two hundred thousand
men like you, who are waiting to have their wives and children sealed to them&mdash;in order to
get the endowment done for these surplus names, it has been suggested that the Melchizedek
Priesthood in the various temple districts, through their quorums, organize themselves and
assume greater responsibility in this activity, and take upon them the responsibility of bringing
to an equal number the male and the female names in the temples; and to encourage your
wives to permit you and urge you to attend these temple sessions on your stake days until
there is an equalized number of male and female names in the temples.  Then after that is
accomplished, with the new system that is being adopted, of placing most all the names in the
temples in the temple files, where anyone may come and use them, it will make much easier
the process of balancing the male and the female names and maintaining that balance.
Bishoprics and the stake presidencies would do well to give their genealogical chairman their
active assistance in these things.  I feel that it is not sufficient merely to announce that "next
Wednesday is our stake temple day." I think it would be helpful if at times the bishoprics and
stake presidencies could announce that on their temple days, the presidency of the stake, the
high councilmen, and the bishoprics will join with the priesthood and go to the temple.  Many
stake and ward leaders are doing this with satisfying results.  If that could be done the
endowment work for these names would soon be completed.
</p><p>
I am convinced through observation that where members of the ward go to the temple
consistently the problems of the bishopric are reduced and minimized to a very few
comparatively, and I am sure that if the parents will go to the temple at regular intervals it
will result in happier, more harmonious home life.  We do not feel like being ugly and coarse
and selfish after we have gone to the temple and participated in those great and holy
ordinances. We feel better, we are better men, we are better women, and I am sure that if we
would go regularly, we would become better fathers and more considerate husbands and our
lives would have a more purposeful meaning.
</p><p>
I believe it was Melvin J. Ballard who made this statement: "If you would be
eternally rich, invest in the human soul." When I was at the Logan Temple, a group of men
from one of the stakes which was assigned to spend the day there had come together in a car
and after the morning session had gone out to the entrance planning to go home.  One of them
needed to go, he thought, but the stake president came along and learned of their intentions,
so he said to them, "Well, now, brethren, if you need to go, you had better go, but when you
are travelling over those hills by the Bear River and you imagine that you hear some
mourning, it could be those five men who had thought you were going to stay here and do the
work for them today." Well, they twisted a little bit.  We noticed they walked out to the gate,
and there they had another conference, as they shifted their weight from one foot to the other. 
In about five minutes they came back into the temple to make redemption possible for five
more persons.  Those men had the proper feeling for the dead, who along with the living have
a right to the blessings of eternal life.
</p><p>
Now, may I say something about one or two other matters.  We are desirous of keeping the
temples themselves clean and immaculate.  Everything about the temple should be clean and
wholesome. Those who come to the temple should be clean in mind and in body and their
temple clothing should be fresh and clean.  Cleanliness becometh the House of the Lord.
</p><p>
If those who attend the temple have their own clothing, they will find it is more convenient
for them and surely it is proper and appropriate.  What better gift could be given to our
children at the time of their marriage than their temple clothing.
</p><p>
May I speak on one other matter, briefly.  Many, too many, of our young boys and girls are
being married somewhere other than in the House of the Lord.  It is a sad situation when we
live in the shadows of these temples, when we know the history, the sacrifices, the faith and
devotion of those who made these blessings and privileges possible, to have our young people
married in the courthouses and other places, leaving their blessings behind them.  A few of
them wish to be married civilly with the intention of going into the temple later.  That is a
risky procedure.  Many of them, most of them, will forsake their blessings and their divine
destiny by so doing.  I am convinced that the time to be married right is when we are
married.
</p><p>
Now these conditions call for the sympathetic interest, understanding and help of every leader
in supplementing the help and the teaching of the parents. The faces of our boys and girls
should be turned towards the temple early in their lives, that is the time to do it! I feel that
we make a mistake if we wait until they fall in love with and become engaged to someone
who will not take them to the temple, before we begin to point out to them the blessings that
await them in the House of the Lord.  When they are five or six or seven years of age, that is
the time for parents to begin instructing their children.  Otherwise, they will be lured into the
ways of the world and their blessings may be lost and the eternal association with their loved
ones may never be realized.
</p><p>
I was walking past the new Relief Society Building a few days ago, and I passed by two little
girls.  They appeared to be about eight years of age.  They were looking admiringly at the
temple, and one of them said, "What do they do in there?" The other said, "I don't know what
they do in there, but I know this, that when I get married I am going to be married in there."
Now, those little girls were only eight years of age but the one had been properly taught
somewhere by someone because her mind was made up.  Those who are not taught and
encouraged early in their years are often difficult to teach.
</p><p>
When I see the stake reports, I think&mdash;my goodness, if I were a bishop again, what I would
do!  I would try to become intimately acquainted with every one of these young people.  I
would talk with them, confer with them, privately and individually, from time to time, and
find out what their plans are.  I would find out who their associates are.  I would desire to
know who their boyfriends or girlfriends are; who they are going with "steady,"
and what kind of a person their boyfriend or girlfriend is.  I would
encourage them to select wholesome associates.  I would want to know where they go at
nights.  I would warn them against the pitfalls, the enticements and allurements that are
rampant in the world, which would lead them away from the desirable.  I would talk to them
and explain about marriage, even though they are in their early teens, and compare the civil
ceremony with that which they receive in the temple and explain it in general so that they
would know.
</p><p>
I am convinced that if we wait until after they fall in love to give them direction, we are
usually too late to help them.  I would tell them what President Woodruff said at one time,
when he uttered these words: 
</p><p>
"Why, bless your souls," he said, "if you live here in the flesh a thousand years and live in
poverty and when you get through if, by your acts, you could secure your wives and children
in the first resurrection, to dwell with you in the presence of God, that one thing would amply
pay for the labors of a thousand years." He knew whereof he spoke.
</p><p>
I believe that when children see their parents hustling and bustling to get ready to go to the
temple; Dad coming in from work in the fields or from the office, taking a bath and getting
his clothes ready; Mother having them all pressed, both hurrying off to the temple on their
stake temple days or night, they become aware that temple work is important.  That is one of
the best ways to convince young people that the temple work should be important in their
lives.  I feel that parents ought to do that.
</p><p>
Let us, brethren, as leaders in the various organizations and quorums and wards, collaborate
with the families. Sometimes parents do not teach well enough.  We must pick up then, from
where they leave off in the process of preparing the youth for their blessings. If I were a
bishop I would toss and turn at night and be unable to sleep, if I had not organized my forces
in the ward and made every effort personally and through my associates to contact these
young people while they are approachable and before they get into questionable habits.
</p><p>
I hope every one of you saw or will see that film last night, entitled "The Bishop."
</p><p>
The temple presidencies and workers are conscious of the need of providing in these holy
places, an atmosphere of kindness, an atmosphere and a feeling of patience and of love, so
that those who come will long remember their visit and will want to come back again. We
recognize the need of administering the ordinances in an impressive manner; of being reverent
and dignified ourselves, and of making welcome those who come.
</p><p>
The temple presidencies are desirous of making each temple a house of prayer and meditation. 
What a wonderful place the temple is, if we come in the right mood, to meditate, silently and
offer up our thanks to the Lord.
</p><p>
We are desirous that each temple be a house of faith, a house of learning, a House of God. 
In a revelation to the Prophet Joseph Smith, given at Nauvoo in 1841, the Lord said this: 
</p><p>
"And verily I say unto you, let this house be built unto my name" . . . (speaking of the
Nauvoo Temple) . . . "that I may reveal mine ordinances therein unto my people; 
</p><p>
"For I deign to reveal unto my Church things which have been kept hid from before the
foundation of the world, things that pertain to the dispensation of the fullness of times.
</p><p>
"And I will show unto my servant Joseph, all things pertaining to this house," (some people
ask, "Where do we get these ordinances." Well, there is the answer.) The Lord said, "And I
will show unto my servant Joseph all things pertaining to this house, and the priesthood
thereof, and the place whereon it shall be built"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/40-42#40">D&amp;C 124:40-42</a>).
</p><p>
In the 55th verse of that Section, the 124th, the Lord continues: ". . . that you may prove
yourselves unto me that ye are faithful in all things whatsoever I command you, that I may
bless you, and crown you with honor, immortality, and eternal life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/55#55">D&amp;C 124:55</a>).  That is the purpose of
these temples.
</p><p>
May we learn our duty and do our duty as leaders in making these blessings possible, both to
the living who come under our direction, and to the dead, I humbly pray,
bearing testimony that these things are of God.  I do it in the name of Jesus Christ, our Lord.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
