<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Report from the Correlation Committee</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Gordon B. Hinckley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Gordon B. Hinckley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 72-74</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, I have been asked to give a report of progress on the organization of the
coordinating program.
</p><p>
Brother Lee has made reference to Paul's analogy to the Church as a body whose various
members have need one for another (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/14-27#14">1 Cor. 12:14-27</a>).
In furtherance of that analogy the correlation committee
and its associated subdivisions might be likened to the nervous system whose responsibility is
to keep the various aspects of the great teaching program of the Church operating
harmoniously together.
</p><p>
Fundamental to the very program of the Church is the teaching of the gospel to the
membership of the Church. In fulfillment of the obligation which was laid
upon the Church in its inception, there has developed within the Church a system of great
teaching organizations&mdash;the priesthood quorums, both Melchizedek and Aaronic, the far-flung
church school system, and the auxiliaries: the Relief Society, the Sunday School, the Primary,
and the MIA, all of which play so important a part in the education of our people.
</p><p>
If it were possible, I would like to place before you on a chart the organization of the
correlation program, but since we have outside the Tabernacle where only our voices reach
eight to ten men for every man who is here tonight, I shall have to present the mechanics of
the organization verbally. (See accompanying chart.)
</p><p>
I should like you to picture in your mind's eye the First Presidency at the top of an imagined
chart and below that the Council of the Twelve, then beneath that is a subcommittee of the
twelve known as the church correlation committee, comprised of four members of the Council
of the Twelve who have been given responsibility for this work.
</p><p>
Associated with the correlation committee is an executive secretary, Brother Antone K.
Romney. Associated with him are three other dedicated men. They, together with the heads of
the various teaching organizations, constitute the body found next, below the correlation
committee on the chart I am trying to describe for you. This body is known as the all-church
coordinating council. It is comprised of the members of the correlation committee and their
associates (Brother Romney, Brother Reed Bradford, Brother Vaughn Hansen, and Brother B.
West Belnap), the Presiding Bishop of the Church, the chancellor of the Church School
System, the general superintendent of the Deseret Sunday School Union, the president of the
Relief Society, the president of the Young Women's Mutual Improvement Association, the
general superintendent of the Young Men's Mutual Improvement Association, and the
president of the Primary Association, together with a secretary.
</p><p>
This group, representing the great teaching organizations of the Church, stand together as the
all-church coordinating council to bring about the harmony of which Brother Lee spoke.
</p><p>
Operating under the direction of the all-church coordinating council are three groups or
subdivisions which constitute what we have come to describe as executive planning
committees, one for children, one for youth, and one for adults. One of the twelve serves as
chairman of each of these committees, with a secretary in each&mdash;Brother Belnap for the
children's committee, Brother Hansen for the youth group, and Brother Bradford for the adult
committee. Associated on each of these committees are men and women of great ability,
extensive experience in the Church, and proven devotion, who constitute respectively,
planning organization for children, for youth, and for adults.
</p><p>
Now, working with each of these executive planning committees are three other groups, one
tied to each of the three. These are task committees, chosen from over the Church because of
their experience, their devotion, and their ability. It is their assignment, and I think the word
<i>task</i> fits the assignment, to review carefully the entire curriculum of the Church, past and
present, to become acquainted with all courses of study and activity programs used now and
used in the past. This is a tremendous undertaking. This study will become the foundation
upon which will be built a program of coordinated study and activity for the entire Church in
all the world, including all age groups.
</p><p>
I hope I have made reasonably clear the mechanics of the all-church coordinating program
designed to further harmony and orderly sequence in the teachings and activities of the
organizations of the Church.
</p><p>
Now, let me quickly review it as we proceed from the top&mdash;the First Presidency, the Council
of the Twelve, the correlation committee, the all-church coordinating council, three executive
planning committees each with a task committee of curriculum study, whose responsibility it
is to dig and study and conduct research, out of which will come coordinated courses of study
and programs of activities that will build testimony in the hearts of the
Latter-day Saints from the day they are old enough to attend classes.
</p><p>
I desire in conclusion to say a word of appreciation for the magnificent service of those who
have been called to serve on the various committees. Many have been released from positions
of great priesthood responsibility including those of stake president and bishop; men and
women have been released from general boards to work quietly in the background to bring
about this great work of correlation which shall bless the lives of the Latter-day Saints
throughout the earth.
</p><p>
God bless them in their labors and bless us with a sense of appreciation for their devotion, I
ask in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
