<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Nobility of Character Essential to a Great Nation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 16-21</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall prosper, and shall be led to a land of
promise (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>).
</p><p>
That inspired promise made over two thousand years ago, referred to America, in loyalty to
which every true American can say in his heart:
</p><p>
Breathes there a man, with soul so dead,<br />
Who never to himself hath said,<br />
This is my own, my native land!<br />
Whose heart hath ne'er within him burned,<br />
As home his footsteps he hath turned,<br />
From wandering on a foreign strand!
</p><p>
A GOD-BLESSED LAND
</p><p>
In the giant forest of the Sequoia National Park there is standing even today, a living tree that
was three thousand years old when Columbus discovered America. One cannot stand by the
side of this, in all probability the oldest living thing in the world, without wishing that it had
the intelligence and power to tell the story of the races and peoples who for forty centuries
have lived, flourished, and decayed in this choicest, most wonderful of all lands. The origin
and the rise of the Incas might have antedated this old tree's birth, and possibly the coming of
the Jaredites might have preceded by a few hundred years this ancient tree's beginning, but
the downfall of the Jaredites, the beginning, rise, and end of the Nephites, the influx of
European peoples, the conquest of Mexico, the subjugation of the Indians, and the flourishing
of European civilization, have all come within the life-span of this awe-inspiring,
death-defying, divinely created thing. Nations have risen and nations have perished in the
Americas&mdash;a land on which it is decreed no king shall ever hold sway.
</p><p>
To each and all of these nations the land was a blessed land, and today is even more glorious
than ever. No observer can travel from the sun-kissed beaches of the Pacific to the wooded
hills and power-producing rivers of New England without being thrilled by the greatness of
these United States. The painted deserts of the West, flower-carpeted in springtime, and
holding hidden beauty and entrancing interest in every season&mdash;the inspiring monuments of the
Rockies, harboring snows as reservoirs for crops in valleys below&mdash;the colorful canyons,
painted only by the Creator Himself&mdash;the fertile food-producing valley of the
Mississippi&mdash;the mighty forests of the Northwest&mdash;the navigable rivers&mdash;the climate, varying to
suit all needs and conditions&mdash;all these and a thousand other equally glorious and productive
features bear witness to the age-old declaration that this is a "land choice above all other
lands" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>),
and inspire every patriot to say, "This is my own, my native land." Millions of
Americans today declare with Winthrop: "Our country, to be cherished in all our hearts, to be
defended by all our hands."
</p><p>
America, and this includes Canada and the Southern Republics, was a choice land when the
Jaredites left the land of Shinar approximately four thousand years ago. So was it fourteen
hundred years later when Lehi and his colony formed the nucleus of a nation, prospered on
the bounty of the country, and after a thousand years perished because of transgression.
</p><p>
America was a great land when the stately Indian chiefs ruled their tribes, which thrived from
the Behring Sea in the north to the Panama and the towering Andes in the south.
</p><p>
Today, yielding to the demands of the greatest economic era since the dawn of her creation
America is demonstrating the vastness of her resources and the extent of her natural
possibilities as never before. Well may we sing:
I love thy rocks and rills,<br />
Thy woods and templed hills;<br />
My heart with rapture thrills<br />
Like that above.
</p><p>
This country is not only the choicest of all lands, but now the preserver of true liberty, and
the hope of civilized man!
</p><p>
However, as I have already implied, a country may be ever so great and fruitful, yet a nation
subsisting upon it be impotent and decadent. As Lyman Abbott has truly said:
</p><p>
The greatness of a nation is measured, not by its fruitful acres, but by the men who cultivate
those acres; not by great forests, but by the men who use those forests; not by its mines, but
by the men who work them.
</p><p>
God has made America fruitful; man must make and keep the nation great.
</p><p>
INTEGRITY FUNDAMENTAL
</p><p>
The foundation of a noble character is integrity. By this virtue the strength of a nation, as of
an individual, may be judged. No nation can ever become truly great, and win the confidence
of other peoples, which to further its own selfish ends will, for example, consider an
honorable treaty as "a mere scrap of paper." No nation will become great whose trusted
officers will pass legislation for personal gain, who will take advantage of a public office for
personal preferment, or to gratify vain ambition, or who will, through forgery, chicanery, and
fraud, rob the government or be false in office to a public trust.
</p><p>
Honesty, sincerity of purpose, must be the dominant traits of character in leaders of a nation
that would be truly great.
</p><p>
"I hope," said George Washington, "that I may ever have virtue and firmness enough to
maintain what I consider to be the most enviable of all titles&mdash;the character of an honest man."
</p><p>
It was Washington's character more than his brilliancy of intellect that made him the choice
of all as their natural leader when the thirteen original colonies decided to sever their
connection with the mother country. As one in eulogy to the father of our country truly said:
</p><p>
When he appeared among the eloquent orators, the ingenious thinkers, the vehement patriots
of the Revolution, his modesty and temperate profession could not conceal his superiority; he
at once, by the very nature of his character, was felt to be their leader.
</p><p>
Men of sterling statesmanship, unknown or renowned, who strive to emulate his strength of
character constitute today as always the greatest asset of our mighty and much beloved United
States.
</p><p>
Also bearing record to integrity and honor as being an indispensable element in a truly great
nation is the life of the immortal Lincoln, in whom was "vindicated the greatness of real
goodness, and the goodness of real greatness," to whose character the passing centuries can
add only more brilliant luster.
</p><p>
The purest treasure mortal times afford<br />
Is spotless reputation: that away,<br />
Men are but guilded loam, or painted clay.<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;                            (<i>Richard II</i>, Act I, Sc. 1 )
</p><p>
THE AMERICAN HOME
</p><p>
A second essential, fundamental element in the building and in the perpetuity of a great
people is the home. "The strength of a nation, especially of a republican nation, is in the
intelligent and well-ordered homes of the people." If and when the time ever comes that
parents shift to the state the responsibility of rearing their children, the stability of the nation
will be undermined, and its impairment and disintegration will have begun.
</p><p>
The increasing divorce rate in the United States today is a threatening menace to this nation's
greatness. Race suicide and tandem polygamous relationships made possible by lax divorce
laws are enemies of an ideal national life. The increase throughout the United States in the
percentage of divorces is alarming, and this insidious evil is increasing in the Church itself.
There are too many couples in the Church who, when difficulties arise, seek the remedy in
divorce courts.
</p><p>
In the well-ordered home we may experience on earth a taste of heaven. It is there that the
babe in a mother's caress first experiences a sense of security; finds in the mother's kiss the
first realization of affection; discovers in mother's sympathy and tenderness the first assurance
that there is love in the world.
</p><p>
A week or so ago conditions made it necessary that I share a Pullman with forty soldier
boys&mdash;gentlemen they were, a credit to any nation. In course of a conversation, one of them
remarked: "My dad's hair too is white"; then he added in a tone that expressed the depth of
his feeling: "How I should like to see that old gray head this morning!"
</p><p>
He and his companions were en route for an encampment to complete their training before
embarking for overseas. They are enlisted to defend not only the free agency of man but the
rights and sanctity of home and loved ones. Such an affection for home and loved ones as felt
by that soldier boy will make death preferable to surrender to an enemy who would destroy
all that true American soldiers hold dear.
</p><p>
A NATIONAL NUISANCE
</p><p>
At this point I must mention an insidious evil that is destroying, termite-like, the foundation
of character as well as that of the home and nation. I refer to the appalling increase in the use
of tobacco, particularly among the young. Of its uselessness, expensiveness, injuriousness to
health, I will say nothing. I shall refer only to its undermining effect on character and to its
slovenliness.
</p><p>
Respect for another's rights and property is fundamental in good government. It is a mark of
refinement in the individual. It is a fundamental Christian virtue. Nicotine seems to dull, if
not kill completely this trait of true culture, and women are fast becoming its pitiable 
victims, and the worst offenders in society. There are still a few trains that carry non-smoking
compartments, a few eating places with signs, "No smoking." In violation of such placards, it
is not infrequent, however, to see a woman with utter disregard for the feelings of her
fellow-passengers, the first in a car to light a cigarette. On one occasion, when the conductor
politely called a woman's attention to the fact that a smoking car was in the rear, she blandly
replied: "Oh, I'm quite comfortable where I am, thank you!"
</p><p>
It is not uncommon now to see bureaus, dressing tables, desks, mantles, and other pieces of
furniture in first-class hotels marred by burning cigarettes. Ashes litter costly carpets. Railroad
stations, theatre and hotel lobbies are littered with burnt-out matches, stubs of cigarettes, and
cigars. Smoking has become our nationwide nuisance number one. If men and women must
smoke, and it seems that many are now slaves to that habit, then for the sake of cleanliness
and neatness, and pride of our country, as well as of consideration for others, let them refrain
from marring furniture, and from strewing ashes and burnt-out matches and cigarette stubs in
buildings where people assemble either for pleasure or instruction. Because of thoughtlessness
in this regard, many of our public places are littered as unkept barns.
</p><p>
I appeal to young men and women of the Church to refrain from this obnoxious habit. To
bishops, I would say: Choose no person to act as either an officer or teacher in your quorums
or auxiliaries who is guilty of using tobacco. If teachers cannot teach by example, their
precepts will be as "sounding brass and tinkling cymbal"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/1#1">1 Cor. 13:1</a>).
</p><p>
CHASTITY AN IMPORTANT FACTOR
</p><p>
I mentioned the home as the most important factor in building a great nation. The most
vicious enemy to home life is immorality. At the present time social workers are greatly
concerned over the number of young girls between fifteen and nineteen who seem to have lost
all sense of decency and who shamelessly sacrifice themselves on the altar of lust. Of this
evil, Victor Hugo writes impressively:
</p><p>
The holy law of Jesus Christ governs our civilization; but it does not yet permeate it; it is said
that slavery has disappeared from European civilization. That is a mistake. It still exists; but it
weighs now only upon woman, and it is called prostitution.
</p><p>
Life and social order have spoken their last word to her. All that can happen to her has
happened. She has endured all, borne all, experienced all, suffered all, lost all, wept for all.
She is resigned with that resignation which resembles indifference as death resembles sleep.
She shuns nothing now. She fears nothing now. Every cloud falls upon her and all the oceans
sweep over her!
</p><p>
This corroding evil is just as demoralizing to the young man as it is to the young woman. In
the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints there is no double standard of morality. The
young man should approach the marriage altar just as fit for fatherhood as his sweetheart is
worthy of motherhood.
</p><p>
And what has all this to do with the greatness of a nation? The answer is apparent. Pure water
does not flow from a polluted spring&mdash;nor a healthy nation from a diseased parentage.
</p><p>
Chastity, not indulgence, during the pre-marital years, is the source of harmony and happiness
in the home, and the chief contributing factor to the health and perpetuity of the race. All the
virtues that make up a beautiful character&mdash;loyalty, dependability, confidence, trust, love of
God, and fidelity to man&mdash;are associated with this diadem in the crown of virtuous
womanhood and of virile manhood.
</p><p>
The word of the Lord to His Church is: Keep yourself unspotted from the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, America is a "land choice above all other lands"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>). It is the responsibility of Americans to
build a mighty and superior nation. The history of the nations of the past proves that nations
in the most fruitful and most productive of all lands may become senile and decadent.
</p><p>
While our sons, sweethearts, and husbands are offering their lives in defense of the God-given
gift of free agency and for the right to live without the domination of tyranny, let us in the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints as citizens of our beloved country, use our
influence to see that men and women of upright character, of unimpeachable honor are elected
to office, that our homes are kept unpolluted and unbroken by infidelity, that children therein
will be trained to keep the commandments of the Lord, to be "honest, true, chaste, benevolent,
and virtuous, and to do good to all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
Cherishing such ideals, we can with all our hearts
say with the poet Longfellow:
</p><p>
Thou, too, sail on, O Ship of State!<br />
Sail on, O Union, strong and great!<br />
Humanity with all its fears,<br />
With all the hope of future years,<br />
Is hanging breathless on thy fate!
</p><p>
In the present crisis of the nations of the globe I pray that this great nation and the Dominion
on the north may be truly the harbor of freedom, and a safe guide to the confused peoples of
the world.
</p><p>
May the members of the Church of Jesus Christ, preaching the restored gospel, ever
remember the Savior's injunction: "Ye are the light of the world. . . . Let your light so shine
before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father which is in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/14,16#14">Matt. 5:14,16</a>).
</p>
</div>
</div>
