<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Sanctify Yourselves</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1956, pp. 48-50</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters, it is not an idle hope that I express when I ask you to join
your faith and prayers with mine.  It is the only way, I believe, that I can say a word to you
today that may be helpful and inspire an effort to approach more nearly the life that our
Heavenly Father would like us to live.
</p><p>
Before I talk about what I had in mind, I would like to say to the singers today that I
appreciate very much the music which they have rendered, and I have great interest in their
group for two reasons: One is that my grandfather was chosen by the President of the Church
to carry the gospel to Scandinavia; another is that I discovered in reading the genealogical
history of one line of my heritage, that it was carried back to the Norsemen who came into
England such a long, long time ago.
</p><p>
Now I admit that this student in carrying it back had to use ten-league boots over some of the
stretches, but I hope it is true nevertheless.
</p><p>
I had thought that I would begin today by bearing my testimony to the restoration of the
priesthood, the organization of the Church, and to a return of a true interpretation of the
gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
President Richards has done that so beautifully that all I will ask is that you let me
incorporate his testimony in mine, because I believe from the bottom of my heart that what he
has said is true.
</p><p>
Many of us who are here today are bearers of the priesthood.  We are all, or nearly all of us,
members of the Church in which that priesthood functions for the development and well-being
of people.  I presume we are all here to try and gain a little better understanding of the gospel
plan and a greater enthusiasm for it, a greater determination to carry its teachings into our
daily lives.
</p><p>
We have been told that we are the children of God, our Heavenly Father, that we had a
conscious spiritual existence before we came here. The gospel plan is one which God and his
Son Jesus Christ developed, which if properly followed by the spirits who come into the
earth, would lead them back not only to the presence of God but also to an exaltation in his
presence, all of which has been explained to us today. The gospel includes many things that
we should do. Some phases of its expression are in the form of "thou shalt not" do this or
that.  Others are in the positive form of "thou shalt" do this and that. Of course, it is our
purpose to learn what they are and properly interpret them and integrate them into our daily
living.
</p><p>
The first great commandment that was given to Adam and Eve in the Garden of Eden,
according to recorded history, the revealed words which we have, was to multiply and
replenish the earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
In my recent visits to the stakes over the last two or three years, I have
tried to keep a record of the percentages of the people who were married as members of the
Church, who were married in the temple. I discovered that about fifty-five percent of the
marriages were celebrated in the temple.  Forty-five percent of them were of people who had
not the inclination to go to the temple for that purpose.
</p><p>
I feel in my heart that it was the intent of God that when marriage should be celebrated, it
should be done with the vow and promise that it would never be broken, so that the great
privileges of exaltation which are promised us could be realized throughout eternity. It is an
unfortunate thing that many of these marriages are hastily contracted and not sealed by the
powers of the priesthood. Consequently, many of them break up and result in disaster.
</p><p>
Now how are we going to find out the things that we should do to make a marriage like this
perpetual?  We have to return to the gospel of Jesus Christ and put its teachings into practice. 
Could we make a perfect effort at that, of course, we would eventually attain to the powers of
God, for that is the promise which he has given us.
</p><p>
Our purpose in coming here today is to learn something about it and how, perhaps better, we
can do those great things.
</p><p>
I would like to read to you a scripture found in the Doctrine and Covenants which I think
expresses the purpose of the gospel: 
</p><p>
Therefore, sanctify yourselves that your minds become single to God, and the days
will come that you shall see him; for he will unveil his face unto you, and it shall be
in his own time, and in his own way, and according to his own will
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/68#68">D&amp;C 88:68</a>).
</p><p>
Then, in another section we read: 
</p><p>
For you shall live by every word that proceedeth forth from the mouth of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/44#44">D&amp;C 84:44</a>).
</p><p>
The recorded revelations that we have-the modern ones-we find in the Doctrine and
Covenants and the Pearl of Great Price, but there are many revealed expressions of the
doctrine and will of God, our Heavenly Father, in the Bible, so we have the three sources.
John says in his writings,
</p><p>
Search the scriptures; for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are they
which testify of me (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/39#39">John 5:39</a>).
</p><p>
It is my firm conviction that when we come to understand really the scriptures, we discover
that every single purpose therein is to testify that Jesus Christ was to come, is the Son of
God, and was to work out a redemption for us. He prepared the plan that we should follow. 
It is our purpose to learn it and then to try to live by every word that has proceeded from the
mouth of God.
</p><p>
You will remember the first scripture says,
</p><p>
Therefore sanctify yourselves. . .
</p><p>
I met a member of the Church one time who said that salvation does not depend upon men's
acts at all, and he quoted the scripture, ". . . by grace are ye saved . . .
</p><p>
"Not of works, lest any man should boast"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/8-9#8">Eph. 2:8-9</a>).
This does not seem quite like that,
does it?  We are saved from death and given the privilege of a resurrection and through the
grace and gift of God we have the privilege of sanctifying ourselves, thus earning an
exaltation.
</p><p>
So that is our problem, brethren and sisters.  Let us read the scriptures; let us discover in
them the way of life that will lead us back to the kingdom of God.  Let us put forth every
effort and sanctify and purify our lives. And, brethren and sisters, let us be more interested in
the effect upon ourselves than that which we think we observe sometimes in our neighbors.
</p><p>
There are many of the provisions I have said which say, "thou shalt not" do this and that, and
many of us are prone to judge our neighbors, thinking only of the things that they should not
do which we think they do; but there is a positive side to this which far outweighs that, it
seems to me, as far as we individually are concerned. We should be not interested in the
failures of our neighbors but in their successes and in our own successes in coming nearer to
God our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
The first great principle is love.  We are to love God our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
Then the next principle to it is we should love our neighbor as ourselves
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37-39#37">Matt. 22:37-39</a>).
If we could just do
that, we would glory in the successes of our neighbors; and while we would feel bad if they
made mistakes, we would not judge them, entirely, on the mistakes they made, but would
balance against them the efforts towards righteousness that they demonstrate.  Then if their
righteous conduct should outweigh the other side, we would be happy, would we not? That is
the way we would like people to think of us. That is the way we would think of them.  We
would extend mercy to them.  That does not mean feeding them and clothing them; it means
helping them to adjust their lives to the will of God, our Heavenly Father, and to give aid and
succor. Spiritual aid and succor is more important than temporal aid at times. We should
extend both, of course, but most certainly, if we love our neighbor, we are going to extend to
him our spiritual aid and comfort in the spirit of mercy.
</p><p>
God said to Adam that he should cultivate the soil and live by the sweat of his brow
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/3/19#19">Gen. 3:19</a>) and that
still is the responsibility of every one of us.  How can we feel that we have completely done
the will of God if we are not diligent in providing for ourselves and for those who are
dependent upon us? Is there ever a time in the life of a man, who is able to do so, when he
should not provide for himself?  Diligence, then, is another phase of this great program that
God gave us, a practical, everyday program for everyday living, which when properly carried
into effect has its spiritual reaction just as definitely as anything else, and the man who meets
his obligations to his fellows is likewise sanctifying his soul.
</p><p>
The positive side of this has so many different headings that it is impossible for me to try to
deal with all of them, but there is still another side that I try never to forget, and that is that
to sanctify one's soul one should gain control over the God-given urges and propensities of
one's body, and there are so many of us who fail in that.  That is so often the cause of
disruption in marriage relationships; people fail to live true to the covenants which they make
in marriage simply because the urges of the body are too strong for them, and they do not,
apparently, seek the spirit of God in an effort to gain control.
</p><p>
I have said so many times, and I repeat it, that I believe self-control, perfect self-control,
would be the greatest victory that any person born into this earth could gain; and with perfect
self-control and a knowledge of the plan which God prepared for us, which we can only find
by searching the scriptures and listening to the authorized priesthood of God, we would be
able to sanctify our souls, would we not?
</p><p>
To sanctify means to make holy, and only holy things can come back to the presence of God,
our Heavenly Father. So, sooner or later, if we enjoy the privilege of association under the
influence of Jesus Christ and the Father, it will be because we sanctify ourselves, that our
minds may be single to God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/68#68">D&amp;C 88:68</a>).
If we had that single purpose, to please God, we would strive to
learn how, and then to do just exactly what would be required.
</p><p>
For you shall live "by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/4#4">Matt. 4:4</a>). That
is the key, brethren and sisters. Let us learn what it is; and when we learn it, let us not try to
find loopholes in the recorded statements that will justify our failure, but let us determine
through prayer and humility to reach a proper understanding of the plan and then live it as
nearly perfectly as we can.
</p><p>
May God bless us, I pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
