<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1944, pp. 147-149</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren: I pray for the good spirit spoken about by Elder Romney. It is a great privilege
and a blessing, and certainly a great inspiration, to be in attendance at a session of the
Conference. This opportunity is becoming increasingly more precious.
</p><p>
I rejoice in the fact that the messages of this Conference have gone out to the nation, and
have reached the homes and the firesides of the families in this Intermountain region. The
reports given and the remarks made indicate that the Church moves on. It is solid, sound, and
progressive. It will continue to move on, and go forward to meet the demands and the
requirements made upon it.
</p><p>
The coming forth of Mormonism is the greatest event of modern times, and it will be so
regarded in the future by the unprejudiced writers of history. It has survived every storm of
opposition; it has never gone backwards; it has never retreated from its high aims and
purposes.
</p><p>
We have been urged by previous speakers to adhere to fundamentals. Such admonition, it
seems to me, is timely in a day of war and upheaval. It is so easy for a people to side-step
fundamentals. This is especially true in times of stress when they become impatient and lose
their powers of endurance. What could be more fundamental than the doctrine of the
resurrection, discussed with such force and eloquence this morning? What could be more
fundamental than the Ten Commandments mentioned by President George Albert Smith, and
by Elder Spencer W. Kimball this afternoon? The violation of these commandments has
brought destruction and sorrow, not only to men, but nations. What could be more practical
and fundamental than the Sermon on the Mount, quoted in part by President McKay the other
evening?
</p><p>
Judge not, that ye be not judged.
</p><p>
For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: and with what measure ye mete, it shall
be measured to you again (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/1-2#1">Matt. 7:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
It is a sound doctrine, brethren; it is fair and just.
</p><p>
What could be more basic to human welfare than Joseph Smith's declaration, in the Articles
of Faith, that men will be punished for their own sins and not for Adam's transgression
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/2#2">A of F 1:2</a>). It
places upon men the responsibility for their soul's salvation. Such a teaching is productive of
good works, and conducive to right living. The responsibility resting upon the Church has
never been greater. It rests heavily upon the ministry of the Church. It calls for a great
service, an unswerving devotion, and a supreme faith.
</p><p>
The wayward and the careless must be warned and admonished in the spirit of kindness and
brotherly love. Some of them are our neighbors and friends. Our love for them demands that
they be brought back into the fold of Christ. Their faith must be revived, nourished and
strengthened.
</p><p>
Without that simple, trusting and abiding faith, characteristic of a true Saint,
no one can know God or comprehend the Gospel; and there is no substitute for the Gospel.
All the theories, sophistries, and plans of men devised to the contrary have failed, and will
continue to fail.
</p><p>
PRESENT CONDITIONS DEPLORED
</p><p>
As a result the world stands today on the brink of despair and destruction. Characteristic of
our day and time is the weakening of the moral fiber of men and women, referred to many
times by the speakers: a departure from long and well-established standards of conduct, a
disregard for the old-fashioned virtues, despite the fact that they are sacred and binding upon
humanity, and have been itemized and set up by holy prophets for the guidance of God's
children.
</p><p>
There has been a breaking away from Church and religion; skepticism, unbelief, and fidelity
have become the boast of the learned and the sophisticated. What does it mean, my brethren?
Does it mean that the pillars of civilization are crumbling?
</p><p>
I read recently a book written by Dr. Frank Munk called <i>The Legacy of Naziism</i>. In it he
makes this statement, which is the concluding paragraph in the book:
</p><p>
A world is adrift&mdash;Europe has completely lost its moorings. Economically, socially, spiritually,
only the grass-root things remain. We must begin anew. A new civilization is being born in
blood and unspeakable suffering. Ultimate and eternal values alone will survive the carnage.
</p><p>
He concludes his book by quoting a verse from the famous speech of Paul to the Athenians
when he said:
</p><p>
He giveth to all life, and breath, and all things. And has made of one blood all nations of men
for to dwell on all the earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/25-26#25">Acts 17:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
In his book he also speaks of a chance, with the inference that it is to be a slight chance, that
the accumulations of centuries in art, literature, culture, and in human progress can be saved.
</p><p>
"Things are not altogether well with us," said the Archbishop of Canterbury recently, when
speaking to the British nation. "The decline in honesty has been very sharp and steep," he
said, "and our standard of conduct in matters of sex is very lax. These things," he points out,
"will bring terrible consequences, if we will not change our outlook, or in the old phrase,
repent." Old England with its culture, with its power and wealth, mighty in achievement,
along with an unparalleled history, like other nations, must repent or perish.
</p><p>
A short time ago I read a book written by Beverly Nichols, in which he discussed organized
vice, the curse of drink and the widespread outbreak of criminality in England and America.
The author said: "The facts as I have stated them are true, and the reason they are true is
because the parents in question have failed most criminally to set before their children the
picture of Christ." He then calls attention to the fact that once that picture hung on the wall,
but the repercussions of war blew it off.
</p><p>
"The time has come," he concluded, "to hang that picture once more on the wall, to see if we
can learn any message from the eternal eyes." Surely a great inspiration will come from a
picture so beautiful and so stainless. There is nothing left, my brethren, to direct and sustain
humanity except the perfect life of Jesus, His Gospel of peace and love, and his matchless and
powerful leadership.
</p><p>
I quote in closing the words of scripture from the book of Revelation:
</p><p>
Fear God, and give glory to him; for the hour of his judgment is come: and worship him that
made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and the fountains of waters
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/7#7">Rev. 14:7</a>).
</p><p>
May we do so, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
