<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">One Church, One Gospel, One Savior</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 12-16</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brethren and sisters, this has been a most inspirational hour. I
am sure that the Lord has manifested through his servant the course that he wants his children
to follow and pursue here in mortality.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, do you believe God is the same yesterday, today, and forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/13/8#8">Heb. 13:8</a>)?
</p><p>
Do you believe he is a God of order in all things?
</p><p>
Do you believe that he governs the universe by the application of divine law?
</p><p>
Many would answer these three questions as follows: some in the affirmative, some not sure,
and possibly some negatively. Those who are not spiritually inclined might indicate that they
believe there is a God, a higher intelligence which governs the universe, and they point out
some of the evidences that are found in the many forms of nature&mdash;the orderly sequence of
the seasons, each in its place, spring, summer, autumn, and winter, and to the creation of
storms based upon the application of divine principles; the sun, the moon, and the stars all
held in their orbits by the application of the laws and powers best known to the Creator.
</p><p>
The scientist in his laboratory slowly unravels the wonders of the creation which evidences
the existence of a divine being by whom the universe was created, by whose hand the animal
world, the vegetable world, and the mineral world are ruled.
</p><p>
I wish to submit another question: What of man and woman, son and daughter of the Creator
of the universe, created in his image, according to Genesis 1:27
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>)?
</p><p>
So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; male and female
created he them.
</p><p>
Then another question: Is there a definite set of laws for the spiritual and the mental growth
and progress of man to the end that he might enjoy salvation and exaltation in the kingdom of
our heavenly Father? Again some may answer in the affirmative; some may doubt; some may
have a negative attitude.
</p><p>
Definitely fixed laws and powers govern nature, planets, and the universe which can only be
changed by the will of God. Man, the greatest of God's creations, can and does fix the laws
that govern his mortal life regardless of any divine plan that was devised for his good. He is
blessed with intelligence far above all the other creations. Hence, he knows the difference
between good and bad, and being blessed with the divine gift of free agency, can decide what
course he will pursue in life.
</p><p>
Recently, a noted reverend doctor declared, "There is nothing to the <i>One Church Idea</i>," which,
from my point of view, is an admission by the reverend doctor that there is not anything to
the idea of a divine plan for the blessing of our heavenly Father's children. There are many
who think as the reverend doctor, and they say, "After all, we are all striving
towards eternal life. It makes no difference which path we follow, for our destination is the
same." To advocate there is but one God, one faith, and one baptism is considered by many to
be narrow and unjust.
</p><p>
In this day and age the words of Paul are applicable when he declared to the Galatians: 
</p><p>
I marvel that ye are so soon removed from him that called you into the grace of Christ unto
another gospel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/1/6#6">Gal. 1:6</a>).
</p><p>
The concept of the Godhead has changed since the days of the Savior. He said: 
</p><p>
. . . he that hath seen me hath seen the Father...
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/9#9">John 14:9</a>).
</p><p>
The idea of one Church, one gospel and in fact, one Savior, in the minds of many, is a
fallacy.
</p><p>
It would not be consistent thinking to believe that God is orderly in the governing of the
universe and indifferent and disorderly in providing a plan of life and salvation for his
greatest creation, namely, his children.
</p><p>
But in the midst of all of this confusion and so-called broadmindedness by the teachers of
man-made religions, the voice of a young Prophet was heard, coming from western New
York, a young man who again declared that there is one Church, one God, one faith, one
baptism (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/5#5">Eph. 4:5</a>).
This young man dared to tell the world that he actually saw the Father and the Son.
He reaffirmed to the world that God was a personage with body, parts, and passions; that
Jesus Christ, the despised Nazarene who was crucified upon Calvary's hill, actually lived. He
conversed and talked with him. He received definite instructions and among other things, the
resurrected Savior said: 
</p><p>
. . . they draw near to me with their lips, but their hearts are far from me...
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/19#19">JS&mdash;H 1:19</a>).
</p><p>
This young American Prophet boldly declared to the world that an angel had appeared to him
and entrusted to his care an ancient record which contained the history of the dealings of the
Lord with the people that lived upon this, the American continent in ancient times, and there
was contained in this sacred record the divine plan of salvation given to mankind through
Jesus Christ when he visited the people upon the American continent.
</p><p>
He declared to the world that John the Baptist appeared to him and conferred upon him the
Aaronic Priesthood; that Peter, James, and John, the former apostolic Presidency, bestowed
upon him the Melchizedek Priesthood; that Elijah came and gave him the keys for the work
of the dead, Moses the keys of gathering, and Elias the return of the spirit of the gospel.
</p><p>
In fact, he declared to the world that the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ had been restored to
the earth with the priesthood of God and all the offices and officers that existed in the ancient
Church.
</p><p>
The reaction to his divine message and tidings of great joy was received with scorn. He was
looked upon as a bigot, narrow-minded. Finally, he sealed his testimony with his blood.
</p><p>
Now, let us go to the law and the testimony
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/8/20#20">Isa. 8:20</a>)
to determine whether or not the claims of the
Prophet Joseph were false or true. All Christians accept the Bible as the law and the
testimony.
</p><p>
First: Did the Savior establish one Church or many churches?
</p><p>
Second: Were there definitely assigned officers in the Church?
</p><p>
Third: Was there divine authority upon the earth and one gospel?
</p><p>
Reading from 1 Corinthians, 12th Chapter, 28th Verse: 
</p><p>
And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondarily prophets, thirdly teachers,
after that miracles, then gifts of healings, helps, governments, diversities of tongues
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/28#28">1 Cor. 12:28</a>).
</p><p>
Here we see the servant of God speaking of <i>the</i> Church, one church not many churches.
</p><p>
And again we read in Ephesians 5:23: 
</p><p>
For the husband is the head of the wife, even as Christ is the head of the church: and he is
the saviour of the body
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/5/23#23">Eph. 5:23</a>).
</p><p>
One Church, only one, of which Christ was the head.
</p><p>
Therefore as the church is subject unto Christ, so let the wives be to their own husbands in
everything (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/5/24#24">Eph. 5:24</a>).
</p><p>
Here is evidence where Christ is the head of the Church, one Church not many churches.
</p><p>
And again in Ephesians 4, Verses 4 and 5: 
</p><p>
There is one body [one church], and one Spirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your
calling; 
</p><p>
One Lord, one faith, one baptism
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/4-5#4">Eph. 4:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
These are a few of the evidences found in the law and testimony which bear out the great
truth&mdash;there was but one church organized by the Savior during his ministry, and in the
establishment of his Church, there was but one organization, and in that organization there
were definitely assigned officers endowed with divine authority from on high.
</p><p>
We read from Ephesians 2:20 and 21: 
</p><p>
And are built upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself being the
chief corner stone; 
</p><p>
In whom all the building fitly framed together groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20-21#20">Eph. 2:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
Here twelve men were duly ordained and set apart as the Twelve Apostles of the first Church.
We read in Mark 3:14, that he ordained the twelve, ". . . that they should be with him, and
that he might send them forth to preach"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/3/14#14">Mark 3:14</a>),
the gospel, to represent this great organization, the
one Church, and proclaim the gospel to the known world of that time.
</p><p>
We read in Acts 11:22: 
</p><p>
Then tidings of these things came unto the ears of the church which was in Jerusalem: and
they sent forth Barnabas, that he should go as far as Antioch
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/11/22#22">Acts 11:22</a>).
</p><p>
Here we see a duly authorized servant of God being sent by the Church by those who were in
authority in Jerusalem to Antioch to take care of Church affairs.
</p><p>
The Savior makes it very clear when he stated to the people in Matthew 7:13-14 (speaking of
one Church, speaking of one organization with definitely ordained servants in the same, and
one gospel): 
</p><p>
Enter ye in at the strait gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to
destruction, and many there be which go in thereat: 
</p><p>
Because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto life, and few there be
that find it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/13-14#13">Matt. 7:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
This statement of the Savior to the world is definite and clear to the point that there can be
but one way, his way, through his organization, the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ&mdash;the one
Church.
</p><p>
In his Church are found according to Paul in his message to the Ephesians 4:11: 
</p><p>
And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors
and teachers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>).
</p><p>
Christ was a high priest after the order of Melchizedek. We read in Hebrews 3:1: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the Apostle and High
Priest of our profession, Christ Jesus
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/3/1#1">Heb. 3:1</a>).
</p><p>
In other words, all of the Apostles received the Melchizedek Priesthood. They received their
apostolic calling from Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
We find in Luke 10:1, where there are seventies spoken of and who were sent out two and
two to every city and place, whither he, the Church, would come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/1#1">Luke 10:1</a>).
</p><p>
In Acts 15:2, we read where Paul and Barnabas were going to settle a certain dispute, and
they were sent up to Jerusalem to consult the Apostles and the elders about this question,
elders in the Church (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/15/2#2">Acts 15:2</a>).
</p><p>
We find in Philippians 1:1: 
</p><p>
Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at
Philippi, with the bishops and deacons
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/1/1#1">Philip. 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
There were bishops in the organization of the Church as Christ established it.
</p><p>
In Luke 1:5, we read of Zacharias, the priest
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/5#5">Luke 1:5</a>). We read of this same priest in Luke 1:8
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/8#8">Luke 1:8</a>).
</p><p>
In Ephesians 4:11, Paul speaks of ordained teachers
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>).
In Philippians 1:1 the deacons are
mentioned (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/1/1#1">Philip. 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
In Ephesians 4:11, are found evangelists or patriarchs
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>).
</p><p>
As we carefully peruse the law and the testimony, we find there was but one Church
organized by the Christ. He gave to the world but one gospel plan for the salvation and
exaltation of mankind, and the priesthood of God and in it officers duly ordained and
authorized to serve in his kingdom upon the earth, his Church&mdash;one Church.
</p><p>
There were certain initiatory ordinances that had to be met to gain citizenship in the kingdom
or membership in the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ. This was best illustrated on the Day of
Pentecost when a multitude of people were gathered together, and Peter bore his testimony so
strongly and impressively as to the mission of the crucified Savior that that great multitude
arose as one man and asked the question, "Men and brethren, what shall we do?" Peter
answered them: 
</p><p>
Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of
sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38-39#38">Acts 2:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
Here are the principles and the ordinances whereby the children of our heavenly Father might
enjoy membership in the one Church, the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I might digress long enough to say that there are different forms of baptism upon the earth, I
speak specifically of baptism by pouring or sprinkling for children. As I understand the words
of Peter on the Day of Pentecost, baptism was for the purpose of forgiving sins. Small
children are not guilty of sins because they do not know the difference between good and bad,
and the Savior said, "Suffer little children to come unto me . . . for of such is the kingdom of
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/18/16#16">Luke 18:16</a>).
</p><p>
It was a great source of inspiration and encouragement to future generations when Peter
promised in a distant day the gift of the Holy Ghost or the spiritual baptism would be
available to those afar off and those who were afar off, I believe, are the people that live in
this generation.
</p><p>
And coming back to the Apostles of Christ's day, they observed a falling away&mdash;the apostasy
was underway, for Paul declared to the Galatians: 
</p><p>
I marvel that ye are so soon removed from him that called you into the grace of Christ unto
another gospel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/1/6#6">Gal. 1:6</a>).
</p><p>
The Apostles were blessed with prophetic vision for we read in Acts 3:19: 
</p><p>
Repent ye therefore, and be converted, that your sins may be blotted out, when the times of
refreshing shall come from the presence of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/19#19">Acts 3:19</a>).
</p><p>
And continuing on in Acts 3:20 and 21: 
</p><p>
And he shall send Jesus Christ, which before was preached unto you: 
</p><p>
Whom the heaven must receive until the times of restitution of all things, which God hath
spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/20-21#20">Acts 3:20-21</a>)
</p><p>
The apostasy was foreseen, and God revealed there would be a restitution, a restoration of all
things before the second coming of the Christ.
</p><p>
I think all Christians will admit that Christ atoned for all men hence all men will enjoy the
blessings of the resurrection.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith taught the world that in the plan of the gospel as it is represented in
Mormonism, there will be a place for all of the Lord's children on the basis of merit as
revealed in Revelation 20:12: 
</p><p>
And I saw the dead, small and great, stand before God; and the books were opened: and
another book was opened, which is the book of life: and the dead were judged out of those
things which were written in the books, according to their works
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/20/12#12">Rev. 20:12</a>).
</p><p>
Modern revelation teaches us in the 76th Section of the Doctrine and Covenants, that all men,
the sons and daughters of God, will enjoy a place in one of the glories prepared for them,
according to their deeds in the flesh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/111#111">D&amp;C 76:111</a>).
</p><p>
I ask you if this is narrow. I ask if this is bigotry. But I want to say to you, brethren and
sisters, this is the broadest plan of salvation that has been given to the world since the Savior
was crucified for the sins of all men: 
</p><p>
For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in
him should not perish, but have everlasting life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
It is a glorious truth and blessing to enjoy membership in the Church, the one Church of the
Lord Jesus Christ restored to the earth in exactly the same form as it existed when Christ
established it first twenty centuries ago. Each and every one of us can testify by the Spirit of
the Holy Ghost that we know that God is the same yesterday, today, and forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/13/8#8">Heb. 13:8</a>); that he is a
God of order in all things; and that he spoke personally to the Prophet Joseph and assigned
him the great task to establish upon the earth the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ, the one
Church, the one gospel, and teach the world that there was but one Savior, the Son of God.
</p><p>
Personally, I am not ashamed of the restored gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>) as it has been
given to us through his Prophet. I want to testify to you that there is but one Church, and that
is the Church that carries his name, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. I want to
testify to you, brethren and sisters, that there stands at the head of this one Church of the
Christ, a Prophet, an Apostle, who has all the same rights, keys, and authority that were
enjoyed by Peter in the beginning, and that the same is equally true of the Twelve, and all of
those who preside in high places in this great organization.
</p><p>
Certainly, when God the Father declared: 
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life
of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>),
</p><p>
he devised a plan whereby this could be done, and an organization through which it could be
accomplished, namely the organization of the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
That is my testimony to you. I thank God for it. I hope that every member of this Church will
have that same witness in his heart and that the children of men, as the prophet of God called
all men this morning to repent of their ways and accept of this divine plan and thus prevent
the catastrophe which now faces the world. If the world will follow this divine counsel, there
is no question but what we can live in the Spirit of the Christ, namely, the spirit of peace, for
which all nations are struggling.
</p><p>
May God bless us. May we express our appreciation day by day for our membership and our
many opportunities for salvation and exaltation in the kingdom of God, I humbly ask, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
