<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Father's Day</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Sterling W. Sill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Sterling W. Sill, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 107-110</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Each year on the second Sunday in May we set aside a very special day which we call
Mother's Day. This is a day for honoring our mothers, and is traditionally a day of family
unity and happiness. On this day we put on our best clothes and perform our most thoughtful
acts to honor and please our mothers.
</p><p>
Two days ago was a kind of special Mother's Day to me, inasmuch as it was my mother's
birthday, and though she has long since departed this life, I am very grateful for the privilege
which is mine to remember and honor her.
</p><p>
Closely associated with Mother's Day, we set aside another special day on the third Sunday in
June which we call Father's Day. The importance of both of these great days was given
divine emphasis and approval some 3,400 years ago when God descended in fire upon Mt.
Sinai, and to the accompaniment of lightnings and thunders, said&mdash;
</p><p>
Honour thy father and thy mother . . . (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/12#12">Ex. 20:12</a>).
</p><p>
As I understand it, the observance of this commandment brings more benefit to the children
than to the parents, for when we honor an ideal, our lives are uplifted by it. It has been said
that "the sins of the fathers are visited upon the children"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/5#5">Ex. 20:5</a>), but that may also apply to their
virtues; for, as the poet said&mdash;
</p><p>
When the high heart we magnify<br />
And the sure vision celebrate<br />
And worship greatness passing by,<br />
Ourselves are great.
</p><p>
In President McKay's great book <i>Gospel Ideals</i>, he said, "The other night I dreamed about my
mother." And then he said, "I would like to dream about my mother more often." That is, in
his dream, his mind went back and relived those important experiences when he learned from
his mother the lessons of life that helped to prepare him for his present high place in the
world. Each time we relive some sacred experience, that experience is renewed in vitality, and
we are able to reabsorb the original good.
</p><p>
It was while trying to relive my own mother's devotion on her birthday, that I selected the
title for what I would like to say to you this morning. The title that I think would please her
most is "Father's Day." And I don't mean the Father's Day that comes on the third Sunday in
June. I mean the Father's Day that comes on the first day of each week, when we try to
honor and please our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul has reminded us that
</p><p>
. . . we have had fathers of our flesh which corrected us, and we gave them
reverence: shall we not much rather be in subjection unto the Father of spirits and
live? (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/12/9#9">Heb. 12:9</a>).
</p><p>
The relative importance of this great day that we call the Sabbath might be indicated to us by
the frequency of its reoccurrence. That is, we have one day to honor Washington, one day to
honor Lincoln, one day for Thanksgiving, one day for our nation's birthday. And then our
Father in heaven, in his wisdom, has set aside one-seventh of all of the days to honor God.
This day is also set aside primarily for our benefit. When one honors a wonderful mother, he
tends to make her standards his own, and when one honors God he tends to become like God,
and thereby helps to bring about his own eternal exaltation.
</p><p>
These fifty-two Father's Days have also come down to us from that awe-inspiring day on
Sinai thirty-four centuries ago when out of the fire God said&mdash;
</p><p>
Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>).
</p><p>
In fact, it has been thought that our civilization could never have survived for half a century
if it had not been for this one day in seven that we call Sunday. This is the day when we try
to reach a pinnacle in our lives by living at our best. This is the day when we pay particular
attention to the washing of our bodies. This is the day when we put on our best clothes and
think our best thoughts and read our best books. This is the day when
we associate with the people we love the most. This is the day for which we usually reserve
the best meal of the week. This is the day when we lay aside the cares that usually concern us
during the other six days while we go to the house of prayer and let our minds reach upward
to try to understand the things of God and eternity. This is the special day when we worship
God, and honor Him in our lives. The proper observance of the Sabbath is the process by
which we put our lives in harmony with Deity.
</p><p>
Because President McKay has loved his mother and tried to please her, she has been enabled
to help guide and enrich his life. And because President McKay has honored and loved his
Heavenly Father, God has been able to magnify him and make him great.
</p><p>
One thing that greatly disturbs me as I go around a little bit is the consciousness of the great
number of people who are losing their opportunities and their blessings by the misuse of the
Sabbath day. All of our lives we have heard of the great wonders that can be accomplished by
even fifteen minutes a day devoted to well-directed study and concentrated thought. We know
of many who have raised themselves to great heights of achievement by this simple means.
But think how wonderfully we can upgrade our spirituality by making effective use of "The
Lord's Day" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/12#12">D&amp;C 59:12</a>),
which he has set aside especially to enrich our lives.
</p><p>
Alexander Hamilton once gave the secret of his extraordinary success and we can apply his
formula to the observance of the Sabbath day. Mr. Hamilton said: "Men give me some credit
for genius. But all the genius I have lies in this. When I have a subject in mind I study it
profoundly. Day and night it is before me. I explore it in all its bearings. My mind becomes
pervaded with it. The result is what some men call the fruits of genius, whereas it is in reality
the fruits of study and labor."
</p><p>
It is a thrilling idea to think of the possibility of becoming a "genius" in the things of the
spirit, a "genius" in the work of the Lord. This can actually be brought about by devoting our
minds and our hearts to the important considerations for which this one day in seven was set
aside.
</p><p>
It is still true that, "As a man thinketh in his heart, so is he"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/23/7#7">Prov. 23:7</a>). Everything starts from that one
beginning.
</p><p>
Mind is the master power<br />
That molds and makes,<br />
And man is mind.<br />
And evermore he takes the tools of thought<br />
And fashions what he wills,<br />
Bringing forth a thousand joys, a thousand ills.<br />
He thinks in secret, and it comes to pass<br />
Environment is but his looking glass.
</p><p>
                    James Lane Allen<br />
                    <i>Morning and Evening Thoughts</i>
</p><p>
Someone has made this challenging proposition: "How would you like to create your own
mind?" But isn't that exactly what each of us does? William James said, "The mind is made
up by what it feeds upon."
</p><p>
This idea was strikingly illustrated to me sometime ago in conversation with a friend who
said, "But I am just not religious," and he shrugged his shoulders as if to say, "There is
nothing that I can do about it." With the hope of helping him, I said, "Bill, I am sure that
what you say is true, that you are not religious. But have you ever thought about the
circumstances that brought that situation about? How could you ever hope to be religious?
You don't study religion; you don't read the scriptures; you don't go to church; you don't
pray to God; you don't think about him; you don't meditate about religious things. How could
you ever hope to be religious?"
</p><p>
Someone once said to a small boy, "Who gave you that black eye?" The boy said, "No one
gave me that black eye. I had to fight for it." That is what we must do for every worthwhile
thing in our lives. We must fight for them. Certainly we must earn the right to be religious.
</p><p>
I told my friend about a little toy clown that I saw at Christmas time. It was a little plastic
figure that had a lead weight in the crown of his head which could always be depended  upon
to bring him to an upside-down position. If you laid him on his back, he would
immediately flip up on his head. If you stood him on his feet, he
would quickly reverse his position and light on his head.
</p><p>
But isn't that exactly our own method of response? We can absolutely depend upon this fact,
that wherever we place the weights of our interest, that will be the place at which we will
more or less automatically respond; for example, my friend was very much interested in
athletics; he spent his Sundays and other free time reading about and participating in various
kinds of sports. He told me that he could quote the batting averages of every important major
league baseball player in the United States, and at the same time, he confessed that he could
not quote one single verse from the word of God.
</p><p>
My friend thoroughly understood the importance of taking a vitamin pill every day, but he
had no conception of the desirability or the methods for developing spiritual health and
vitality. Someone once said, "I never put religion out of mind. I was so open-minded it fell
out."
</p><p>
Our spiritual health must always be primarily our own responsibility. A physician judges the
health by the appetite, and our spirituality may be judged the same way. It is easy to ruin our
appetite for the things of God when we build bars in our homes instead of altars. By the
desecration of the Sabbath Day we may become more interested in a horse race than in the
celestial kingdom.
</p><p>
William James said, "That which holds our attention determines our action." That rule applies
to a prize fight or the celestial kingdom. We ourselves choose the interests that will shape our
destiny. But no life can in its final analysis ever really be successful that is primarily
concerned with its own shallow pleasures and narrow interests, but can find no time for the
author of our lives and our blessings. Someone said&mdash;
</p><p>
No time for God,<br />
What fools we are<br />
To clutter up our lives<br />
With worthless things<br />
And leave without the Lord of life<br />
And life itself.<br />
No time for God?<br />
Better to say<br />
No time to eat, to sleep, to live, to die.<br />
Take time for God<br />
Or a poor misshapen thing you'll be<br />
To step into eternity<br />
And say to Him<br />
I had no time for Thee.
</p><p>
Only when we make God and his word central in our lives, can we develop that wonderful
religious talent that will lead us back into his presence.
</p><p>
In 1935, Clarence Day, Jr., wrote a play entitled, <i>Life with Father</i>, and I would like to borrow
that title this morning to apply to your eternal life. In Section 76 of the Doctrine and
Covenants, the Lord names those who will qualify for the celestial kingdom. He says&mdash;
</p><p>
These shall dwell in the presence of God and his Christ forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/62#62">D&amp;C 76:62</a>).
</p><p>
Wherefore, as it is written they are gods, even the sons of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/58#58">D&amp;C 76:58</a>).
</p><p>
These are they whose bodies are celestial, whose glory is that of the sun, even the
glory of God, the highest of all, whose glory the sun in the firmament is written
of as being typical (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/70#70">D&amp;C 76:70</a>).
</p><p>
Then by way of contrast, I would like to offer for your consideration the prospect of "life
without father." Suppose that we should become a part of that innumerable company who will
spend eternity in the telestial kingdom, of whom it is said, "Where God and Christ are, they
cannot come, worlds without end"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/112#112">D&amp;C 76:112</a>).
</p><p>
I would just like to point out in passing that that is a very long time to be excluded from
association with those we would like most to be with.
</p><p>
One of the most devastating of all human emotions is the sense of being alone, of not being
wanted, of being unworthy. Suppose that sometime we find that because we have weighted
our interests in the wrong places, that we have become unfit for the presence of God and have
therefore lost our greatest blessing. A peculiar thing happens when we stand on our heads so
to speak, for then it seems to us that all the world is upside-down, and we are then unable
properly to appraise values.
</p><p>
The most valuable thing in life is life itself. The greatest gift of God is eternal life,
that is, "Life with Father." Therefore, these fifty-two wonderful days have been set aside
especially to help us prepare for that magnificent experience which lies just beyond our
mortality. One of our most inspiring hymns says&mdash;
</p><p>
We feel it a pleasure to serve Thee,<br />
And love to obey Thy command.<br />
                    William Fowler
</p><p>
And one of the most important of those commands has to do with our observance of that
great day on which we try to please God, the day I like to think of as "Father's Day," the
divine command concerning which not only came down to us across the ages from the fires of
Sinai, but it has been given anew by the direct command of God in our own day. For God
has said again to us in substance, in our own interests,
</p><p>
Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>).
</p><p>
May God help us so to do, I pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
