<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Put Your Hand to the Plow</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Howard W. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Howard W. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 16-18</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Not long ago we were traveling through the air so high above the white clouds that they
looked like a blanket of snow beneath us. The sky was blue, and the sun was shining, and
then we commenced our descent for landing. As we came down through the clouds, a new
scene came into view. The earth had been plowed for planting, and the sun was shining on
the fields, some plowed in one direction and some in another. It made the earth appear as a
great giant checkerboard. We came down and down and then, when within a few hundred feet
of the ground, I saw a man laboring in the field, his hands fixed to a plow drawn by a horse.
My thoughts turned to that closing verse in the ninth chapter of Luke in which the Master
said: 
</p><p>
"No man, having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom of
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/62#62">Luke 9:62</a>).
</p><p>
Christ made this statement as he traveled to Jerusalem. Three men had expressed their
willingness to follow him and become his disciples. The first of these said to him: "Lord, I
will follow thee whithersoever thou goest.
</p><p>
"And Jesus said unto him, Foxes have holes, and birds of the air have nests; but the Son of
man hath not where to lay his head"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/57-58#57">Luke 9:57-58</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus had no definite place of residence. He went from place to place teaching and doing
good. It was necessary that the men who were called and set apart for the work should devote
their time and attention and forego worldly affairs. The work of the Master set the great
example. The second man was also willing to follow. "But he said, Lord, suffer me first to go
and bury my father.
</p><p>
"Jesus said unto him, Let the dead bury their dead: but go thou and preach the kingdom of
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/59-60#59">Luke 9:59-60</a>).
</p><p>
Does this statement sound severe? The Master made it clear that the work of the kingdom was
to take precedence over all other things. Then the third man stepped forward and said: "Lord,
I will follow thee; but let me first go bid them farewell, which are at home at my house"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/61#61">Luke 9:61</a>).
</p><p>
Not one of the three was willing to follow him without first returning to their worldly affairs.
The answer of Jesus is one of the great aphorisms of biblical literature. "No man, having put
his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/62#62">Luke 9:62</a>).
</p><p>
In his teachings the Master used homely figures of speech, those having familiar, everyday
character. The words "his hand to the plough," unfolds a picture before us with which we are
all familiar&mdash;a strong man with sinewy arms and a firm step, guiding the blade straight and
true, his eyes intent upon the plough, looking ahead to the furrow to be cut. Hour after hour
he toils, never looking backward except to see that the furrow is straight.
</p><p>
In addition to "ploughing" the Lord often mentioned the words, "sowing" and "reaping." He
made mention of "reaping the harvest," and when that comes to our minds we think of a
happy time and a time of rejoicing. The Lord said: "Lift up your eyes, and look on the
fields; for they are white already to harvest.
</p><p>
"And he that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal: that both he that
soweth and he that reapeth may rejoice together"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/35-36#35">John 4:35-36</a>).
</p><p>
Before there can be a reaping of the harvest, there must have been a sowing of the seed.
When we think of sowing, our minds turn to the parable spoken by the Savior: 
</p><p>
"Behold, a sower went forth to sow; 
</p><p>
"And when he sowed, some seeds fell by the way side, and the fowls came and devoured
them up: 
</p><p>
"Some fell upon stony places, where they had not much earth: and forthwith they sprung up,
because they had no deepness of earth: 
</p><p>
"And when the sun was up, they were scorched; and because they had no root, they withered
away.
</p><p>
"And some fell among thorns; and the thorns sprung up, and choked them: 
</p><p>
"But others fell into good ground, and brought forth fruit, some an hundredfold, some
sixtyfold, some thirtyfold"  (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/3-8#3">Matt. 13:3-8</a>).
</p><p>
Sowing of seed is important; otherwise, there would be no harvest, and as stated in the
parable, there must be good ground to bring forth a good harvest. Plowing must have been
done before the sowing or there would have been no seedbed.
</p><p>
Of all the work of the field, plow-work is the heaviest labor. It is primary and
fundamental&mdash;it is pioneer toil. A seed may be dropped anywhere, and there is no resistance, but put the
blade of the plow into the ground and a thousand forces join to oppose the change. To disturb
the conventional, to overturn the traditional, or to attempt to make changes in the deep-rooted
way of doing things in the lives of individuals, requires toil and sweat. The heaviest work in
the kingdom of God is to turn the hard surface of the earth which has been baked in the sun
or covered by the growth of nature. What a great change comes over land which has been
cleared and plowed&mdash;row after row of evenly spaced furrows, the subsurface loosened and
exposed to the sun and air and the rains from heaven, ready to be broken up and planted to
seed. The wilderness is conquered and subdued.
</p><p>
Those who become disciples of the Master and put their hands to the plow without turning
back prove themselves to be worthy plowmen. By turning over the old surfaces of tradition,
they prepared the fields for the introduction and the spread of Christianity into the world.
</p><p>
We do not need to go back to the time of Christ, however, to find fields to plow. Fields exist
today all over the world, and missionaries have been called and have put their hands to the
plow. Nearly 15,000 stake and full-time missionaries are now in the fields. Furrows are being
cut and seeds planted and every day we see the results of the harvest.
</p><p>
And there is the field of education. Hundreds of plowmen are preparing the field for the
harvest. They are teaching the principles of truth to our young men and young women in the
Church educational system. About 63,000 high school students are presently enrolled in
seminary classes, 9,500 college students are participating in the institute program of religious
education, and approximately 17,000 students are enrolled in Church schools. In all, about
90,000 young people are being given direction in life by those who have put their hands to
the plow.
</p><p>
Not many years ago we entered into the field of assisting those in need by the great welfare
program. The plowshares were driven in and the soil turned over, disclosing the hidden
possibilities of our arising to full stature in being our brothers' keeper
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/9#9">Gen. 4:9</a>). Men and women have
joined in the labor of the field, and thousands have been helped and aided in the Lord's way,
when in need.
</p><p>
We have in Church leadership great plowmen with firm hands and stout hearts&mdash;stake
presidents and mission presidents&mdash;determined men who work in the fields. Bishops, branch
presidents, heads of priesthood quorums and auxiliary organizations are toiling in their
assigned fields. Close at home and in distant countries new lands are being
broken up by these plowmen, and the subsurface exposed to the light of the gospel of Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
Is it hard work? Of course, but that which is worthwhile is seldom easy. As individuals we
have a responsibility to plow. Some accept the opportunity, but some shrink from the
responsibility. Some of those who commence cut only a short furrow and then leave the field
for what appears to be escape from the toil to follow the false illusion of the ease which they
had left behind. Their plowshares are left to rust in the furrow.
</p><p>
Whatever the past may have been in our individual lives, it is gone. The future lies ahead, and
we must face it with resolution. There is always a point from which we can begin. Even
though we may have been faithful in the past, if we turn away, that faithfulness will profit us
nothing. "No man, having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit for the kingdom
of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/62#62">Luke 9:62</a>).
</p><p>
There is danger in looking backward. One must keep his eyes ahead in order to cut a straight
furrow. When the plowman commences to look backward, he cuts a crooked furrow, and his
work is spoiled. We cannot continue to walk forward when at the same time we are looking
backward. It makes no difference what object or occasion causes us to look backward, the
backward glance commences the backward turning, and may be the beginning of our
disendowment in the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
As plowing requires an eye intent on the furrow to be made and is marred when one looks
backward, so will they come short of exaltation who prosecute the work of God with a
distracted attention or a divided heart. We may not see clearly the end of the furrow, but we
dare not look back. Eternity stretches on ahead, challenging us to be faithful.
</p><p>
"And thus, if ye are faithful ye shall be laden with many sheaves, and crowned with honor,
and glory, and immortality, and eternal life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/75/5#5">D&amp;C 75:5</a>).
</p><p>
God lives. I witness that Jesus is the Christ; that the gospel has been returned to the earth;
that Joseph Smith was the servant and prophet raised up for the purpose of the restoration;
that there lives today a prophet to reveal to us God's will in all things, and with all my heart I
sustain President David O. McKay as that prophet, seer, and revelator.
</p><p>
May we put our hands to the plow and not look backward, that we may be fit for a place in
the kingdom of God, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
