<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Teach Your Children</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 10-12</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Richards, President Clark, and my beloved brethren and sisters: I
sincerely hope that I may have an interest in your prayers in the endeavor to give you one or
two thoughts that I have in my mind. It is needless to say that the Presiding Bishopric is
deeply interested in all the young men of the Church who hold the Aaronic Priesthood.  Are
fathers and mothers holding a weekly home evening where they sit down with their children
and discuss the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and what it will mean to them in their lives?
</p><p>
I think it would be a most inspiring story&mdash;it is a true story&mdash;to tell of Jesus the Christ, at
the age of twelve, being invited by Joseph and Mary to go into Jerusalem wherein they were
to pay their taxes, and while there the Christ went into the temple. Immediately he entered
into discussion with learned men.  In the meantime, Mary and Joseph started homeward. 
They soon discovered that the Christ was not with them.  They returned to Jerusalem and
found him in the temple.  Mary was sorrowful because Christ had not been with them, but he
said to them,
</p><p>
How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
</p><p>
I think the young men who will eventually hold the Aaronic Priesthood, who have in their
hearts the words, "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?" as the priesthood
is bestowed upon them, will be anxious to go forward and render the assignments that will
come to them.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing in the home to discuss with our young people the history of John the
Baptist, a yet young man who had an assignment from on high.  The beloved John the
Apostle said, "There was a man sent from God, whose name was John"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/6#6">John 1:6</a>), and John
was sent among the people to preach repentance and baptism for the remission of sins, to tell
them that Jesus the Christ was to appear, and in the course of time confer upon them the Holy
Ghost.
</p><p>
Our sons should know of the crucifixion of the Christ and his resurrection; that after the
resurrection he appeared on this, the American continent, and established the Church of Jesus
Christ as he had established it in far-off Jerusalem.  I think if our young people had that
history and had it in their hearts and understood fully the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ as it
has been restored through the Prophet Joseph Smith, it would so impress them that they
would endeavor to live it in every way.
</p><p>
It would be most inspiring and wonderful to tell these young people something about the
Apostles who lived in the days of Jesus the Christ, and who were selected by him, particularly
of Peter, James, and John who were actually the presidency of the first Church established by
the Christ.  They should know and understand that the Church of Jesus Christ was actually
organized by Christ in the days of these apostles.
</p><p>
They should know something of the Book of Mormon&mdash;how Joseph Smith received the
same&mdash;and in that wonderful book we find the story of the Christ and his gospel in its fulness.  It
is an interesting thing to tell them, too, how that same Christ appeared among the Nephites,
and among other things the Nephites heard God the Father saying, "Behold my Beloved Son,
in whom I am well pleased, in whom I have glorified my name&mdash;hear ye him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/7#7">3 Ne. 11:7</a>),
and thereby, came the establishment of the great Church of Jesus Christ here upon the
American continent.
</p><p>
Thereafter, I think it is a fine thing to discuss with these young people and point out to them
that the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ was lost because men were seeking different
doctrines, that the priesthood had been taken away, and there was darkness upon the earth.  It
would be inspiring to discuss the Prophet Joseph who went to the Lord and
asked the Lord wherein he might find the true Church, and in reply the Lord appeared and
introduced the Christ himself, saying, "This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
It would be a source of inspiration for our young people to know that the Aaronic Priesthood
was brought back to the earth through John the Baptist and bestowed upon Joseph Smith and
Oliver Cowdery and also that the Melchizedek Priesthood was restored by Peter, James, and
John, the Apostles of Jesus the Christ in a former day. These young people should know that
these are realities, that they actually happened, and then there will be a desire to live the
gospel and enjoy all of the blessings therein.
</p><p>
As parents, we have great responsibilities, as President McKay has already pointed out to us. 
I suggest that sometime you read in the Doctrine and Covenants, section 68, verses 25-28
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25-28#25">D&amp;C 68:25-28</a>),
with reference to our responsibilities as parents. The Lord made it very clear, as far as our
sons and daughters are concerned, that we should teach them the doctrine of repentance, faith
in Christ, the Son of the Living God, baptism, and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on
of hands.  Then the Lord went on and said this to us in conclusion: "And they shall also teach
their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
</p><p>
We should read to them about the appearance of John the Baptist to the Prophet Joseph when
he said this: 
</p><p>
Upon you my fellow servants, in the name of Messiah I confer the Priesthood of
Aaron, which holds the keys of the ministering of angels, and of the gospel of
repentance and of baptism by immersion for the remission of sins; and this shall never
be taken again from the earth, until the sons of Levi do offer again an offering unto
the Lord in righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/13/1#1">D&amp;C 13:1</a>).
</p><p>
These young men are ordained members of the Aaronic Priesthood at the age of twelve.  In
the minds of many people, this may seem questionable; but it should not be, because if they
will but read or hear the words and repeat them and remember them, the words of Christ,
when he spoke to his mother and said: "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's
business?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
I am sure that every deacon will have that same attitude.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing if a father will tell his son what it means to pass the sacrament and
what it means to be called by the bishop to go out and collect the fast offerings for the good
of those who are in need.  It is an inspiring lesson that ought to be taught to these young men
to the end that day by day they will endeavor to live the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and
actually have in their hearts his spirit. It is a marvelous thing to talk to these young men
about the Prophet Joseph, who at the age of fourteen asked the Lord, "Lord, where may I find
the Church of the Christ?" and in answer thereto, the Father and the Son appeared, and the
Father said, "This is My Beloved Son.  Hear Him!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
And Joseph, at the age of fourteen, heard
these words of the Christ and received direction from on high as to how the Church should be
established.
</p><p>
It is well to remember that many of these young men who hold the Aaronic Priesthood at the
age of fourteen are called to be teacher&mdash;to go out among the people and teach them the gospel
of the Lord Jesus Christ, with a member of the Melchizedek Priesthood, and to render such
other service as the bishop may feel is necessary.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing to think of the priests, these young men who at the age of sixteen
become active in the same assignments as did John the Baptist.  It is marvelous to know that
these young men have the right to preach repentance, perform the ordinance of baptism, and
bless the Sacrament. John the Baptist did not have the privilege of blessing the Sacrament
because he had passed on, and the Sacrament of course was established just before Christ was
crucified.  So these young priests of today have opportunities that John the Baptist did not
enjoy.  We also read in the Book of Mormon: "After they had prayed unto the Father in the
name of Christ, they laid their hands upon them, and said: 
</p><p>
"In the name of Jesus Christ I ordain you to be a priest, (or, if he be a teacher)
I ordain you to be a teacher, to preach repentance and remission of sins
through Jesus Christ, by the endurance of faith on his name to the end. Amen"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/3/2-3#2">Moro. 3:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
Responsibility devolves upon bishops, bishops' counselors, fathers and mothers, that we
should impress upon these young men the sacredness of blessing the Sacrament, and what the
Sacrament means and its purpose; and also the privilege of performing the ordinance of
baptism. If these young men understand the full meaning of the Sacrament and preaching
repentance, they will become so interested that they will try to live lives in harmony with
Jesus the Christ and say, as he said: "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
</p><p>
So, brethren and sisters, as parents we have great responsibility, as President McKay has
already pointed out, in our homes; and I think one of the greatest responsibilities that falls
upon us, and one we should follow closely, is the matter of holding a home evening with our
young people.  Call on some of them to pray.  Give some of them the assignment to tell us
something about faith, something about the gift of the Holy Ghost, and something about the
matter of holding the Aaronic Priesthood. If that is done, there is no question that these young
people will meet all of the requirements that come to them through the gift and the power of
the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
Only last Sunday, I attended a conference where many of these young people had the
opportunity of bearing testimony.  It was a great thrill to hear them say that they know that
Jesus the Christ lives&mdash;that they know that this is his Church.  Some might question it
because of their age; but nevertheless if they receive the gift of the Holy Ghost, they will
have that knowledge.
</p><p>
I recall the time when I was baptized and confirmed a member of the Church at fast meeting.
I had a peculiar feeling, and something came to my soul that gave me happiness and
joy&mdash;something that I had never experienced before. On the way home, I said to Mother: "I had a
peculiar feeling, Mother, when the bishop laid his hands upon my head and confirmed me a
member of the Church, and said, 'Receive the Holy Ghost.'"
</p><p>
"Son, what was the feeling?"
</p><p>
I said, "A feeling of happiness, a feeling that filled my soul&mdash;something I have never had
before."
</p><p>
She said, "What did he say to you, Son?"
</p><p>
I said, "'Receive the Holy Ghost.'"
</p><p>
So mother said to me, "Son, without a doubt the Lord was good enough to bestow upon you
the gift of the Holy Ghost" and from that time until this time I have known that Jesus the
Christ lives.  I know that Joseph Smith was a prophet of God. I know our President here is a
prophet of God, and those who assist him.  I know that these twelve men are all apostles,
each one of them, with the same power and privileges and rights that Peter, James, and John
enjoyed in their time and age.
</p><p>
So, parents, it is a wonderful thing that your sons who hold the Aaronic Priesthood will have
the feeling and the desire to go forward and to render every service that is required of them,
that they may follow the admonition in the fourth section of the Doctrine and Covenants,
verse 3: 
</p><p>
Therefore, if ye have desires to serve God ye are called to the work
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/3#3">D&amp;C 4:3</a>).
</p><p>
And they are called if they receive the Aaronic Priesthood, especially if you and I will so
encourage them and teach them.
</p><p>
So, fathers and mothers, I think, too, of what the Lord has said to you and me, as parents,
when he said this: "And they [speaking of us] shall also teach their children to pray, and to
walk uprightly before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
So there is no question about prayer; there is
no question about walking uprightly before the Lord, but that he will bless them and inspire
them and lead them on, and that every one of them will have the same feeling as the Christ
had at the age of twelve, when he said: "Wist ye not that I must be about my Father's
business?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
This I pray will be the blessing of every member of the Aaronic Priesthood, and
every young person who has membership in this Church, which I humbly ask and pray for in
the name of Jesus Christ, our Savior.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
