<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Special Privileges</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 12-16</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I join with you my brethren and sisters in expressing to our Father in heaven our thanks and
gratitude for our great leader and president who stands at the head of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter day Saints here and now. I hope that we shall all have that faith in his
admonitions which will permit us to go forward and enact in our lives the teachings which we
thus receive through the mouthpiece of our Heavenly Father, here on this earth.
</p><p>
DIVINITY OF THE WORK
</p><p>
I know that I speak the thoughts of all who are here assembled when I say that we uphold
and sustain President David O. McKay as our prophet, seer, and revelator. And so it is with
great humility that I stand here before you and in his presence, in the presence of my
brethren, to bear my testimony to you of the divinity of the work in which we are engaged.
</p><p>
I am grateful for the unity which exists among the General Authorities of this Church, and I
know that there is, thus, an example set to the people of the Church by which they could very
well profit. That same unity should extend into every stake and into every ward, every
mission, every branch of the Church. I am grateful for the sustaining power and influence that
comes into my life and assists me in my work as a result of your faith and prayers, my
brethren and sisters. I am grateful for the affection, the sustaining power and influence, the
faith and prayers of my brethren with whom I have the privilege to associate day by day, and
acknowledge before you and my Heavenly Father that our ministry would be empty were it
not for these sustaining influences. I know with all my heart that God lives and that Jesus is
the Christ, and I want for nothing but to dedicate my life, my energy, to proclaiming this
testimony to the world, to let my fellow men know that there can be no joy in life, and
certainly no salvation hereafter, unless we understand the laws of God, given to us for our
happiness and our salvation, and in turn lend obedience to them.
</p><p>
OBEDIENCE TO LAW
</p><p>
I feel to repeat the revelation given us by the Prophet Joseph Smith, which President McKay
has already quoted you this morning,
</p><p>
There is a law, irrevocably decreed in heaven before the foundations of this world,
upon which all blessings are predicated,
</p><p>
And when we obtain any blessing from God, it is by obedience to that law upon which
it is predicated (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/20-21#20">D&amp;C 130:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has said:
</p><p>
I, the Lord, am bound when ye do what I say; but when ye do not what I say, ye have
no promise (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
President McKay has told us here this morning the responsibilities we have resting upon us as
fathers and mothers in Israel. I testify to you that if we do that which we have been
commanded, our children and our children's children will be blessed and will be encouraged
to walk in our footsteps and will be crowned eventually with us in the glory of our Father's
kingdom.
</p><p>
For a long time past I have been tremendously impressed with the fact that God is no
respecter of persons (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/34#34">Acts 10:34</a>),
that his Church and kingdom here upon this earth is governed and
regulated and controlled by law, and that that law is your law; it is my law; and to that law
there are no exceptions.
</p><p>
We have been told in the scriptures that,
</p><p>
For there is no respect of persons with God.
</p><p>
For as many as have sinned without law shall also perish without law; and as many as
have sinned in the law shall be judged by the law
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/2/11-12#11">Rom. 2:11-12</a>)
</p><p>
I say that those of us who have received the law must of necessity be judged by it and be
responsible for any disobedience we contribute to it.
</p><p>
For not the hearers of the law are just before God, but the doers of the law shall be
justified (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/2/13#13">Rom. 2:13</a>).
</p><p>
That is the law of the gospel, and so, as we understand these simple fundamental laws of the
gospel, we must live them; we must teach them to our children; we must be bound by them;
and we must claim no exemption for ourselves.
</p><p>
NO SPECIAL PRIVILEGES
</p><p>
Brother Widtsoe, who is absent from our midst today, has recently written, "Full happiness
within the Church demands that men comply with all its laws, regulations, and ordinances.
Obedience is incomplete if a person decides to obey one and disobey another gospel
requirement. Usually, an attempt to select some practices and ignore others leads to a
weakening of the will for righteousness, and soon complete disobedience sets in"
(<i>Joseph Smith</i>, p. 166). I am sure we will accept that as true, that we must do nothing which weakens
our will.
</p><p>
I have a feeling that sometimes we are inclined to exempt ourselves from the law. We seek
special privileges. I don't know whether it has become so common in the world for men
politically and socially to claim exemptions from the operation of the civil law as applied to
them that they think maybe, within the realm of the kingdom and Church of God they are
likewise entitled to special privileges. I am sure of one thing, that President McKay does not
claim any special privileges for himself, and that the General Authorities follow his example,
and we know and we believe that we are bound by the law.
</p><p>
STRICT CONFORMITY
</p><p>
I believe it is time when many of us should feel that it is important to hew strictly to the line,
to keep our own houses in order. So I ask you in light of these suggestions, should we insist
upon going on a mission or sending our sons unless we are worthy? Can we meet the
requirements that have been laid down for those entitled to go? Should we ever feel it
necessary to call upon our bishop or our stake president for a recommend to go to the temple
if we know that we have not first met the law in respect thereto and have made ourselves
worthy to receive this special privilege? Some of us may feel that we can impose upon the
bishop a little bit, that we will be forgiven. I wonder how many of us realize that we cannot
expect, if we go to the House of the Lord unworthily (whether we go there for our own
endowments or to do vicarious work for those who have preceded us), the same efficacy will
attach to our work as would to the work of those who go to the House of the Lord worthily.
Let us think about that, and in place of asking for a special privilege, see that we keep the
laws of God in our own homes and in our own lives, and encourage our own sons and
daughters to do likewise in order that they might go to the House of the Lord worthily.
</p><p>
The same could be said of the Word of Wisdom, the payment of tithes, fasting. We have
carried on in the Church, all this year, a great campaign connected with the welfare program
of the Church to encourage our people to fast. I say to you today that there are none of the
blessings of the fast that can come to you and me unless we fast. We must all fast in the same
manner. There is no exception to the requirement that we do fast if we are ultimately going to
have a real interest in the kingdom of our Heavenly Father, as King Benjamin once said
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/18#18">Mosiah 4:18</a>).
</p><p>
In speaking of charity, Brigham Young and the Twelve said, in April, 1842, while building
the temple in Nauvoo: 
</p><p>
This is not all. It will be in vain for us to build a place where the Son of Man may lay
his head (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/8/20#20">Matt. 8:20</a>),
and leave the cry of the widow and the fatherless unheard by us ascending
up to the orphan's God and the widow's Friend. It is in vain we cry "Lord, Lord" and
do not the things our Lord hath commanded
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/6/46#46">Luke 6:46</a>),
to visit the widow, the fatherless, the
sick, the lame, the blind, the destitute, and minister to their necessities (<i>DHC</i>
4:591).
</p><p>
I call attention to prayer. Can we accomplish the purposes that President McKay has outlined
for us with reference to our children if we do not pray, as a family, in the home, bring into
our homes and into the lives of our youths the spirit as well as the power and inspiration of
prayer? And so I say that no home should be surprised if its children do not receive the same
strength and courage that other children reared in a home of prayer receive, if they are reared
in a household which is a stranger to prayer.
</p><p>
HONESTY IN DAILY LIVES
</p><p>
Some of us claim the privilege of withholding support from our bishop, our stake president,
and some of us feel that for one reason or another it is not incumbent on us to sustain the
General Authorities of the Church, each man in his office and calling. But I say to you that
we cannot fail to respond, especially those of us who hold the priesthood and our wives and
our families, to the requirement which God has written into his law in respect thereto and
receive the blessings that might otherwise be ours. In our daily lives it is impossible for us to
cheat a little and still be honest.
</p><p>
The commandment is to pay every man his dues, and no man can get to heaven who
justly owes his brother or his neighbor, who has or can get the means and will not pay
it; it is dishonest, and no dishonest man can enter where God is (Brigham Young and
the "twelve," April 1842, <i>Ibid.</i>, 593).
</p><p>
It is impossible for us to take advantage of one another in any way, shape, or form and still
have that brotherly love which should characterize the membership of the Church of Jesus
Christ. We could go on and review all of the activities of life and come to the same
conclusion on each. It is therefore proper for us today to
</p><p>
Bring forth fruits meet for repentance,
</p><p>
And think not to say within yourselves, We have Abraham to our father; for I say unto
you, that God is able of these stones to raise up children unto Abraham
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/8-9#8">Matt. 3:8-9</a>).
</p><p>
For the promise, that he should be the heir of the world, was not to Abraham, or to his
seed, through the law, but through the righteousness of faith
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/4/13#13">Rom. 4:13</a>).
</p><p>
In other words, no matter whether we today boast of being of the seed of Abraham, just as
the house of Israel did in the days of old, we are nevertheless to be justified only by our
obedience to the law of God.
</p><p>
And if ye call on the Father, who without respect of persons judgeth according to
every man's work, pass the time of your sojourning here in fear
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/1/17#17">1 Pet. 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
We must never forget.
</p><p>
That which breaketh a law, and abideth not by law, but seeketh to become a law unto
itself, and willeth to abide in sin, and altogether abideth in sin, cannot be sanctified by
law, neither by mercy, justice, nor judgment. Therefore, they must remain filthy still
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/35#35">D&amp;C 88:35</a>).
</p><p>
Be not deceived; God is not mocked: for whatsoever a man soweth that shall he also
reap.
</p><p>
For he that soweth to his flesh shall of the flesh reap corruption; but he that soweth to
the Spirit shall of the Spirit reap life everlasting
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/7-8#7">Gal. 6:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
I hope and pray, my brethren and sisters, we shall as a result of this great conference go to
our homes, to our work, to our wives, and to our families, and realize and appreciate that we
must teach the law as it has been revealed to us in these latter days and then lend strict
obedience to it, and dedicate our lives to our families and to our children that they might
likewise be obedient, and this I humbly pray in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
