<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Test of Love</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 88-90</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
One of the most quoted New Testament texts is this from John: "For God so loved the world,
that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but
have everlasting life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
It is comfortingly familiar&mdash;the love of God simply stated&mdash;and what he did about his love
is the evidence of it: He sent his Only Begotten Son that whoso believeth in him should have
everlasting life.
</p><p>
<b>Love is expressed by action</b>
</p><p>
Suppose God had loved the world in a passive way? Suppose he hadn't sent his Son? Suppose
he hadn't given us his gospel? Suppose he hadn't set out to save mankind or redeem us from
death? Suppose he had let his children drift without plan or purpose or counsel or
commandments? Would that have been love?
</p><p>
The point I hope to make, for a particular purpose, is the evidence, the proof, the test of love.
</p><p>
An editorial recently read in a medical magazine had an intriguing title: "Love Is a Verb."
And from this the writer turned his attention to the importance of doing, of proving, of
performing. The proof of any principle is what it does, and the proof of any person is what he
does&mdash;how he acts, what he becomes&mdash;not simply what he says.
</p><p>
"Love Is a Verb."
</p><p>
We might paraphrase and say that service is a verb, that life is a verb; for it is in doing, in
living, in learning, and not just in words that we perform our purpose. No one really proves
himself or his principles in neutrality or indifference or inaction. No one proves himself by
merely thinking or simply sitting.
</p><p>
The writer of the article referred to above said that in some primitive languages, with their
fewness of words, the description of the movement of game, for example, is described simply
by one word: <i>running</i>. Perhaps we could say much more with fewer words by simply
indicating the action: <i>living, doing</i>. ". . . when a noun replaces a verb there is a disadvantage .
. ." because a noun is static, and life is movement. Some people "assign an intrinsic value to
'things' like purity and gratitude . . . They take credit for possessing nominal virtues. Or they
punish themselves for having vices . . . [but] we communicate with others in verbs . . .
Gratitude has not even been born until it has been actually conveyed in word or deed"
</p><p>
The same could be said for sanity, said this same physician. It "is not structural but
functional. It is not something one has or is. It is a measure of what one does." (William B.
McGrath, M.D., in <i>Medicine at Work</i>, February 1966.) If we do sane things, we are sane. If
we don't do sane things, we are not sane.
</p><p>
<b>Actions speak louder than words</b>
</p><p>
Actions do speak louder than words.
</p><p>
As to a young person who was speculating upon whether or not she loved someone, there is
the reminder that love is not simply a noun and not simply a sentimental feeling. The proof of
love is what one is willing to do for the loved one. The proof of love is how one behaves.
</p><p>
Dr. John A. Widtsoe turned his attention to this subject at times: "The full and essential nature
of love we may not understand," he said, "but there are tests by which it may be recognized.
</p><p>
<b>Love and truth</b>
</p><p>
"Love is always founded in truth . . . Lies and deceit, or any other violation of the moral
law, are proofs of love's absence. Love perishes in the midst of untruth . . . Thus, the lover
who falsifies to his loved one, or offers her any act contrary to truth, does not really love her.
</p><p>
<b>Love does not injure</b>
</p><p>
"Further, love does not offend or hurt or injure the loved one. By that test any human venture,
past and present, may be measured for its real value. Cruelty is as absent from love . . . as
truth is from untruth.
</p><p>
<b>Love is a positive force</b>
</p><p>
". . . love is a positive active force. It helps the loved one. If there is need, love tries to
supply it. If there is weakness, love supplants it with strength . . . Love that does not help is
a faked or transient love.
</p><p>
<b>Love gives</b>
</p><p>
"Good as these tests are, there is a greater one. True love sacrifices for the loved one . . .
That is the final test. Christ gave of Himself, gave His life for us, and thereby proclaimed the
reality of his love for his mortal brethren and sisters. The mother gives of her own flesh and
blood, and jeopardizes her very life, for her child. In family relationships there must be
mutual sacrifices among husband, wife, and children, else true love is not there." (Dr. John A.
Widtsoe, <i>An Understandable Religion</i>, Ch. 8.)
</p><p>
<b>Love is honest</b>
</p><p>
Thus, anyone who would induce someone to do that which it is unworthy to do, or to take
advantage, or rob someone of virtue, or embarrass, or hurt, really doesn't love the person he
professes to love. What he feels under such circumstances is something less than love. The
proving is in the doing.
</p><p>
<b>Virtues are positive forces</b>
</p><p>
And so it is with all the virtues. Either we live pure lives or we don't. Either we think pure
thoughts or we don't. Purity isn't simply a noun. It is a verb. It is the living of a certain kind
of life. It is the thinking of certain kinds of thoughts. Its proof is in keeping the
commandments.
</p><p>
Goodness is not theory, it is fact.
</p><p>
We may think of tithing as a principle and discuss it and approve it, but if we are really
convinced and converted, we will pay our tithing.
</p><p>
We may think well of the missionary system, but it works only because some leave home and
sacrifice and serve sincerely&mdash;not merely because it is a good organization or idea.
</p><p>
We may think and talk of chastity as a virtue, but if we are converted and convinced, we will
live chaste lives.
</p><p>
If we love our children we won't neglect them or let them run loose. If we love our children
we won't leave them ignorant of the law, or of the commandments, or ignorant of how to
behave, or unacquainted with sound habits of work, or ignorant of courtesy and acceptable
conduct.
</p><p>
If we love our children we will urge them to prepare as fully as they can for life, persuade
them to acquire all the training and education possible. If we love our children we will keep
as close to them as possible and do our utmost to keep them free from sin and from anything
that would clutter or scar their lives.
</p><p>
As parents there is no greater obligation that is ours&mdash;and neglect is not the evidence of love.
Part of love is doing our duty in love and loyalty, "by persuasion, by long-suffering, by
gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned; 
</p><p>
"By kindness, and pure knowledge" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41-42#41">D&amp;C 121:41-42</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus said: ". . . lovest thou me? . . . Feed my sheep" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/16#16">John 21:16</a>).
</p><p>
Elsewhere it is written: "If ye love me, keep my commandments" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/15#15">John 14:15</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Doers of the Word</b>
</p><p>
Abstract qualities of character don't mean much in the abstract. It is how we live, how we
serve, how we teach our children, what we do from day to day that both indicate what we are
and determine what we are; and all the theory and all the speculation, all the quoting of
scripture, all the searching of the mysteries, and all the splitting of hairs, and all the
knowledge of the letter of the law don't in the final and saving sense amount to very much
unless we live the gospel, unless we keep the commandments, unless we prove the principles,
unless we live lives of effectiveness, sincerity, and service.
</p><p>
<b>The best evidence</b>
</p><p>
Sometimes we hear someone say, "My life is my own. I am going to do with it as I please."
But no one's life is his own. Too much of others has gone into the making of all of us.
</p><p>
We cannot hurt ourselves without hurting others. A sorrow, an illness, a disgrace, an accident,
trouble, or difficulty of any kind&mdash;any loss to loved ones is a loss to family and friends. We
are too much a part of one another for this not to be so.
</p><p>
If we love our parents, wouldn't the evidence of it be to do something about it: to be grateful,
to help to care for them in their need, to honor them by being honorable, to take them into
our confidence&mdash;not to worry them?
</p><p>
The best evidence of love for parents would be active evidence of kindness, consideration,
appreciation, respect for their teachings and counsel.
</p><p>
The best evidence of love of country would be not what we say&mdash;or say we feel&mdash;but
serving it, keeping the laws, preserving its principles.
</p><p>
The best evidence of love for our Father in heaven would be living lives of honor and
reverence, not taking his name in vain, living useful, righteous lives; and keeping his
commandments.
</p><p>
As to those who say they love the Church&mdash;the best evidence of that love would be serving,
doing, giving of ourselves, living its standards, keeping the commandments.
</p><p>
God help us to be members not of record only, but members who place doing and serving and
living the requirements of the gospel above our comfort or convenience.
</p><p>
"Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven, but he
that doeth the will of my Father which is in heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/21#21">Matt. 7:21</a>).
</p><p>
It is important to believe; it is important to be; but it is also important to do.
</p><p>
<b>Conviction expressed by conduct</b>
</p><p>
Even the devil believes (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/19#19">James 2:19</a>).
"Conviction is worthless unless it is converted into
conduct." (Thomas Carlyle.)
</p><p>
Thank God for the gospel, for the personal and literal reality of him who made us in his own
image, for his Son our Savior, and for the blessed plan of everlasting life with our loved ones.
</p><p>
Thank God for his patience, for his understanding, for his comfort, for his commandments,
for it would be a disillusioning life to be running loose without knowing what was expected
of us&mdash;or why. Thank God that he sent his Only Begotten Son to show us the way, to
redeem us from death, to lead us to everlasting life.
</p><p>
With you I offer gratitude and a pledge to do my best to demonstrate love for our Lord and
Savior and his Father who gave us life by living the kind of lives that they would have us
live, and leave my witness with you of the truth of that which gathers us here together, in the
name of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
