<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John H. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 43-46</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am very happy, my brethren, to have the opportunity of being in this conference to hear the
words of inspiration, counsel, and instruction that have come to us. I trust that I may be able
to say something that will be helpful and that I may be humble in the things that I say.
</p><p>
I heard of a speaker who, in telling of his experiences in delivering a sermon, said that as he
stood before a congregation he felt he was a great waterfall pouring out the word of the Lord
into the hearts of the thirsty people. A man who was standing by him said, "Brother, from
where I was sitting in the audience you didn't look like much of a waterfall. In fact what I
saw looked more like just a trickle."
</p><p>
INCREASE IN VISITORS TO TEMPLE SQUARE
</p><p>
As you know, I am connected with the Temple Square Mission. We have many thousands of
people coming there. We thought that the war would interfere with this mission, that we
would not have very much to do. We were mistaken. During the months of January, February,
and March of last year, when the grounds and tabernacle were open, we had something like
forty-three thousand people. This year during the same three months when the tabernacle has
been closed, we have had something like fifty thousand people. Three times as many people
are going out with the guides this year as did last year. In the same three months of last year
we sold two hundred seventy-six copies of the Book of Mormon. The three months of this
year we have sold five hundred thirty-six copies of the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
I am giving you this information because a number of people, principally members of the
Church, thought that because the tabernacle is closed no one would come to visit with us and
that we would not be able to do the type of work that we were able to do previously. In fact,
among our own membership we often hear it said that the closing of this very historical
building is a great calamity and that we are failing to reach the people whom we should
reach.
</p><p>
I grant you that the opportunity of coming into this building is a choice one. Inside this
building there are a sacredness, a spirit of worship, and a quietness that reach into the hearts
of men and women and in some way go down deep into their souls. It makes them remember
the great faith and courage of our pioneers who made it possible to have this building, this
block, and this city of ours. However, I am quite sure that many of us forget that the Block is
also a sacred spot and that in it there is the spirit of worship, that God is here with us, and
that all men and women who come within our gates are blessed and may feel the inspiration
of the Lord as they come among us.
</p><p>
CLOSING OF THE TABERNACLE
</p><p>
I surely wish our people could realize this fact and not feel that all has been lost simply
because the tabernacle has been closed. Seemingly, we have no objections from our friends.
We have any number of army men and civilians who, when we say the building has been
closed because of the war emergency, say that that is the right thing to do. The only
opposition that we have, seemingly, comes from our own membership. The work that we are
doing in the Block is of immense value to the people who come here. The guides are having
the same opportunity of preaching the gospel. We ask our guides to make an hour the
maximum and about forty or fifty minutes the minimum of time to hold the people as they
take them through the Block. So our guides are using the fifty and sixty minutes, just as they
have always used in preaching the gospel of Jesus Christ. When men and women go away, I
am quite certain they go away with a more kindly feeling concerning the Church of the Lord
that has been established in these latter days. Without any doubt we are doing a work that is
valuable in spreading a knowledge of the gospel among the people.
</p><p>
STORY OF A CONVERSION
</p><p>
Because of the nature of our work we have the opportunity of seeing people change their
viewpoint, changing their way of life, rearranging their thinking in regard to the religious
problems of the day. We have people coming into the Church because of their contact here.
Recently, we had a very intelligent and outstanding woman visit with us. Much of her life had
been spent in France. She came on the Block and went around with one of our guides and
was so impressed that she came again. She was going down to California and thought she
had better stay here long enough to hear more about the Gospel. So we taught her the
Gospel; and one of our guides was so considerate that she took her to some of our meetings
and young people's gatherings. The woman kept coming back. Then we talked things over
with her, and one day we said to her, "You know we have the Word of Wisdom in the
Church; it has to do with smoking and drinking and the use of tea and coffee"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/5-9#5">D&amp;C 89:5-9</a>). It was quite a
surprise to her, and in a way shocked her because the use of some of these things had been a
part of her life. She asked, "Is that one of the teachings of Joseph Smith?" We answered,
"Yes, that is one of the revelations which were given to him." "Well, if Joseph Smith said
that, that is what the Lord wanted His children to do; I am going to do it." So since then she
has left all these things alone. She continued her investigation and is now a humble, faithful,
and sincere member of the Church.
</p><p>
You know you have to change, turn around, think differently and do things differently when
you come into the Church of Jesus Christ. I wish all of us as we think about things could say
in our hearts, "Well, if the Prophet Joseph Smith said that, and it was given to him by the
Lord, we will do it just as he wants us to do."
</p><p>
A FATHER AND MOTHER CHANGE THEIR VIEWPOINT
</p><p>
One day a father and mother came onto the Block. They followed several of our groups. As
they went around the third or fourth time, they thought that perhaps the people behind the
counter would wonder why they were going so often. So they made this explanation: "We
have a son who is over in England in the military work. One day he wrote to us and said that
he had met the Mormon missionaries who are now in the army and said, 'They surely are a
splendid lot of fellows.'"
</p><p>
Nothing more was said by the son about his companions until some time later when they
received a letter saying that he had joined the Mormon Church. "We were so ashamed and
embarrassed," said the mother, "that we just could not go out and meet our friends or talk
about things, because of our son's joining a church that had such a bad name and reputation
as the Mormon Church." I could not blame her so much because of the many lies which have
been told about us.
</p><p>
Several days later they decided to come to Salt Lake and find out for themselves just what
kind of church their son had joined. "We have been in the city a few days and have gone
around with the guides several times and have bought some Church works. Things look very
different to us now. We have enjoyed our visit and admire many of your teachings."
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us. May we catch the spirit of missionary work. May we be helpful to the
men and women who are around us that no one shall go into the presence of God and have
any complaint to make because we Latter-day Saints were untrue to the testimony and the
obligations resting upon us to help our friends to see and understand the beauties of the
Gospel of Jesus Christ, I humbly ask in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
