<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...With a Whole Heart"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 69-71</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay this morning gave recognition to the servicemen who had traveled many
miles to be here, some coming from Texas and Oklahoma. I trust I shall be in order if I ask
those servicemen to stand at the present moment, please, wherever you are. [About
seventy-five to one hundred stood.] Thank you very much. That is a glorious sight, and I
commend you for your evidence of faith in having a desire to mingle
here in this great conference where you will receive a spiritual uplift, where the word of the
Lord goes forth in truth and in power.
</p><p>
The servicemen of this Church are in a position to do great missionary work with their fellow
men by just living the gospel, maintaining the standards and ideals of the Master.
</p><p>
Customs may change, but principles do not. On one occasion we are told that the Master
</p><p>
. . . went up into the temple, and taught.<br />
And the Jews marveled, saying, How
knoweth this man letters, having never learned?<br />
Jesus answered them, and said, My doctrine is not mine, but his that sent me.<br />
If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God,
or whether I speak of myself
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/14-17#14">John 7:14-17</a>).
</p><p>
The principles the Master taught in the temple almost two thousand years ago are just as true
today and important to the welfare of our lives as they were to the people whom he taught.
There is a promise that if any man will do the will of the Father he shall know of the
doctrine, whether it be of God. This is evidence to me that a man may receive a positive
assurance of truth if he will but humble himself before the Lord and do the will of the Father.
</p><p>
Yes, the gospel of Jesus Christ is positive. Here in the sessions so far, we have heard
everyone who has spoken bear witness and testimony regarding the truth which they have
spoken. It is a marvelous thing to have a testimony of the gospel of Jesus Christ. It was
possible to receive a positive assurance, or testimony, in the days of the Master; so it is
possible today, for this is an eternal truth. Many times we hear the statement: "The gospel is
true; I know the gospel is true." I have a witness and testify to you also that I know this thing
called Mormonism is true, for it embodies the full gospel of Jesus Christ. When individuals
have that testimony, though there may be periods of confusion&mdash;periods of deliberation&mdash;they
are always able to come through, provided the roots of their testimony are deep within their
hearts.
</p><p>
The Psalmist declared,
</p><p>
Blessed are they that keep his testimonies, and that seek him with the whole heart
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/119/2#2">Ps. 119:2</a>).
</p><p>
I have a witness that this gospel must go to all people and that all people must come to a
knowledge of the truths which are taught from this pulpit before they can bend the knee and
bow the head and confess that Jesus is the Christ.
</p><p>
Recently I saw the testimony of a young mother manifest as she had her three young sons
around her. She had just become a widow, her husband having suffered a dreadful disease for
three years. Only the light and knowledge of the gospel had given her hope and courage. Yes,
the roots of her testimony were deep.
</p><p>
Through the restoration of the Church and kingdom of God, we understand our responsibility
to take the gospel to all the world, working with those who are nonmembers of the true
Church. Also we are to labor patiently with members who have become somewhat delinquent
and dilatory to their duties, their testimonies having been weakened through inactivity or other
reasons. A keen interest is manifest in this reactivation program and much good is being
accomplished.
</p><p>
Some months ago it was my privilege to attend what we term a men and wives meeting. On
the stand was a husband who had been reactivated. His wife was with him. Their seven
children sat with them. The wife was with child. They had a son in Korea, and they had lost a
little girl some six years before. The wife stood in the pulpit that morning expressing sweet,
humble gratitude that there was now spirituality in their home and happiness because the
priesthood was being honored. Truly, happiness was reflected in the faces of those lovely
children who sat with them. Then the husband related briefly some of his experiences. He told
how he had been born in a little town just north of Logan, Utah, where I should judge
ninety-nine percent are members of the Church. His mother passed away when he was six
years of age. The children had been farmed  out to various relatives, and this boy was with an
aunt and uncle until he was thirteen years of age. At twelve he had
been ordained a deacon because he had been obedient to the teaching and training received
through attending Primary and Sunday School and all the services he could attend. When he
became thirteen, his father decided to move into the backwoods of Wyoming, where they
were some distance from a Church. There was no transportation, so he didn't attend his
meetings. He got out of the habit of going to Church, he said, and took up other habits. Later,
he married a lovely woman who had faith, who had a precious spark in her heart and her
soul. She continued to yearn for the day when he would see the light and would know this
gospel as the Master had taught it.
</p><p>
He said, "I have done many things that I am ashamed of. I smoked, I drank&mdash;and stronger
than beer on occasion. I am not proud of it. I have not been the father that I should have been
to these children. There has not been true happiness in our home; I have not been the husband
that I should have been to my good wife; but I stand here today to testify to you that I would
not return to that old life for all the gold in Fort Knox. I have not missed a Sacrament
meeting from that time to this, which is five years, except when I have been in Salt Lake City
attending general conference."
</p><p>
How grateful I am that the gospel can work in the lives of individuals when they have the
desire, when they understand the meaning of being doers of the word, referred to in President
David O. McKay's message at the opening of this conference.
</p><p>
May we all, I pray, have the desire to demonstrate by our works that we truly are followers of
the Master. May our testimonies be cultivated and fed by the spirit of truth to remain strong,
regardless of trials or obstacles, that we may be able to rise above them, even as John on the
Isle of Patmos, who recognized that he was there because of the word of God and the
testimony of Jesus Christ:
</p><p>
I John, who also am your brother, and companion in tribulation, and in the
kingdom and patience of Jesus Christ, was in the isle that is called Patmos, for the
word of God, and for the testimony of Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/9#9">Rev. 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, customs may change, but principles do not; for assurance, knowledge, and testimony are
eternal principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ today as they were yesterday; I so testify to
you in all sobriety. May God bless us to live in accordance with his glorious eternal truths I
humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ, our Savior. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
