<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Reviewing the Revelations</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 21-24</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, I feel it is a great privilege to be in your presence here today, in
the presence of my Brethren, and to be under the inspiration and leadership of our Prophet
and those who are associated with him in the Presidency of the Church, and I have felt here
this day the power and the inspiration of the Spirit as it has been manifested in what has been
said.
</p><p>
A number of years ago there was a noted historian sent to Salt Lake City, to study the
customs and the way of living of the Latter-day Saints. He remained here many years among
our people and published a book in the year of 1922 telling of his findings. I should like to
read a paragraph or two from what he said about our people. He never knew the Prophet
Joseph Smith. He could only tell of his work by the results as it was manifest among the
people who were guided by the revelations from God which their prophet had received. I
quote: 
</p><p>
"Who can explain Joseph Smith? What are the 'revelations from God'? What is their test? Is
it not beyond all reason that a lad, born of poor parents devoid of any save the commonest
education, too poor to buy books, should have accomplished what he did in less than forty
years, unless there was some great reason for it?
</p><p>
"Let anyone, even a literary genius, after forty years of life, try to write a companion volume
to the Book of Mormon, and then almost daily for a number of years give out 'revelations'
that internally harmonize one with another, at the same time formulate a system of doctrine for
a Church, introduce many new principles, resuscitate extinct priesthoods, and formulate a
system of Church government which has no superior upon earth . . . to deny such a man a
wonderful power over the human heart and intellect is absurd. Only fanatical prejudice can
ignore it. However he may be accounted for by the reasoning mind, Joseph Smith, the
Mormon Prophet, was one of the wonders of his time." (George Wharton James.)
</p><p>
One of the great distinguishing characteristics of the Latter-day Saint people is that they are
governed by revelations from God, and whether people come into our midst, or whether we
go out into the world, this characteristic remains a distinguishing factor.
</p><p>
I recall that some few years ago in one of the communities of Oklahoma a minister, in an
effort to discredit the effects of our missionary work in that area had an article placed in a
daily newspaper, from which I quote a part. He said: "The first thing that you should know is
that these missionaries are a part of a church that claims to have a revelation and a prophet."
</p><p>
How well he placed the facts. Yet it seems rather strange that a Christian minister would
make such a statement in derision, for revelation and the prophets have ever been a part of
God's plan to convey commandments and teachings of righteousness unto his children. There
are others, like this minister, who feel that we have no right to receive revelation, but if we
do not receive revelation for the guidance and direction of the true Church of Jesus Christ,
then we do not have the oracles of God, and if we do not have the oracles of God, then we
are not the people of God.
</p><p>
But this is not the fact, for over and over again God has revealed his will unto this, his
people, through his servants, the prophets. In the first section of the
Doctrine and Covenants, which is a book of revelations given through the Prophet Joseph
Smith unto the Latter-day Saints, the Lord has said: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
These commandments are revelations from God which provide the laws and ordinances of the
gospel, and by obedience to them will exalt man in the presence of our Heavenly Father. The
Prophet Jacob, one of the Book of Mormon prophets, speaks of the need of revelation in this
manner. He says: 
</p><p>
"Behold, great and marvelous are the works of the Lord. How unsearchable are the depths of
the mysteries of him; and it is impossible that man should find out all his ways. And no man
knoweth of his ways save it be revealed unto him; wherefore, brethren, despise not the
revelations of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/4/8#8">Jacob 4:8</a>).
</p><p>
Again Moroni, another Book of Mormon prophet, speaks of those who would deny revelation.
</p><p>
"And again I speak unto you who deny the revelations of God, and say that they are done
away, that there are no revelations, nor prophecies, nor gifts, nor healing, nor speaking with
tongues, and the interpretation of tongues;<br /> 
"Behold I say unto you, he that denieth these things knoweth not the gospel of Christ; yea, he
has not read the scriptures; if so, he does not understand them.<br />
"For do we not read that God is the same yesterday, today, and forever, and in him there is
no variableness neither shadow of changing?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/7-9#7">Morm. 9:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
The revelations from God are a great expediency in leading man unto eternal life and
exaltation. Yet in every age, where God's will has been expressed unto his people, there have
been those who have failed to obey and who have in some instances rebelled against the
revealed word of God.
</p><p>
This was true with the greatest of all prophets, Christ the Lord. Early in his ministry
multitudes of people followed him everywhere, for he blessed them, raised their dead, and fed
their hunger.
But, upon that occasion when he announced to them for the first time that he was the Son of
God and that he would reveal unto them the mind and will of the Father, that he was the
living bread sent down from heaven, they turned and walked no more with him, seeing the
people turn from him because of revelation, he turned to his disciples and said, "Will ye go
away also (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/6/67#67">John 6:67</a>)?"&mdash;but
his nearest disciples led by Peter, did not leave him, for they accepted his
revelations; gone, however, were the crowds of people who had followed him on the shores
of Galilee and the hillsides of Judea. From that day forth, save for his closest disciples, he
walked alone.
</p><p>
Unfortunately, in the early days of the Church not all of the Latter-day Saints accepted the
revelations. I suppose that as each revelation was given to the Prophet Joseph Smith, and it
was made known unto the people, just that many more of the weak Saints rebelled and turned
away from the Church. This became one of the great problems to our people in the days of
Kirtland and Missouri, for some of the members and leaders alike opposed and did all that
they could to prevent the coming forth of further revelation, and the progress of the Church.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith, speaking of this at Far West, had this to say: "Many men will say
I will never forsake you, but will stand by you at all times, but the moment you teach them
some of the revelations (mysteries) of the kingdom of God that are retained in the heavens
and are to be revealed to the children of men when they are prepared for them, they will be
the first to stone you and put you to death."
</p><p>
The Prophet continued in this very significant meeting to make this further statement: "Would
to God, brethren, I could tell you who I am! would to God I could tell you what I know! but
you would call it blasphemy, and there are men on this stand who would want to take my
life." Continuing further, he said, "When God offers a blessing, or knowledge to a man, and
he refuses to receive it, he will be damned." Thus by the implied remarks of the Prophet, the
rebellion of the weak Saints in the days of Kirtland and Missouri continued, yes, even unto
the days of Nauvoo. They seemed, unfortunately, not to understand the
things of God, which had been revealed.
</p><p>
When the work of the Prophet Joseph Smith was completed, when he had received the keys,
powers, and ordinances, and had conferred them upon the heads of the Quorum of the Twelve,
when he realized and sensed that the time had come when he would give his life for his work,
he seemed to speak, upon occasion, more emphatically than ever before with regard to the
truth of the revelations which he received, indicating that there were those within the Church
then who opposed and did not accept all the revelations which God had given through him.
These were his words upon the memorable occasion of one of his last addresses to the Saints.
</p><p>
"Oh! I beseech you go forward and make your calling and election sure&mdash;when did I ever
teach anything wrong from this stand? When was I ever confounded? I want to triumph in
Israel before I depart hence and am no more seen. I never told you I was perfect&mdash;but there
is no error in the revelations which I have taught." (May 12, 1844.)
</p><p>
I have mentioned these things, my brethren and sisters, only in reflection to bring it down to
us today. Can we say, with regard to revelation, in a similar sense, that those who fail in the
Church today to accept and live fully the revelations given are somewhat rebellious perhaps
not in the same antagonistic manner which was manifest in the early days, but nevertheless
rebel within themselves against the word of the Lord. There are some who perhaps sense the
great value of these God-given truths, yet fail in their appropriation. They will not let go for
fear of losing something greatly worthwhile, but still hold back when it comes to fully
accepting the revelations from God.
</p><p>
May I consider with you for a few moments some of the vital revelations given through the
Prophet Joseph Smith and perhaps as we go back to our homes from this great conference of
the Church we can regenerate in our own thinking the desire to conform more closely to the
commandments which the Lord has required of us through these revealed writings. I refer to a
revelation with regard to the magnifying of the priesthood found in section 84
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/1-120#1">D&amp;C 84:1-120</a>) and section
121 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/1-46#1">D&amp;C 121:1-46</a>), given at Kirtland, Ohio, in 1832, and at Liberty, Missouri, in 1839, and when we find
that perhaps two thirds of the elders who hold the Melchizedek Priesthood, are found not to
be in their priesthood meetings each Sunday morning, we realize the need of greater
adherence to this instruction. Would we say that those who are not fully living in accordance
with this revelation are perhaps opposing the divine will of our Heavenly Father as it is
expressed through his prophets?
</p><p>
There is the revelation given on tithing and offerings at Far West, Missouri, in 1838
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/119/1-7#1">D&amp;C 119:1-7</a>). Would
you say, my brethren and sisters, that a man, especially one who holds the Melchizedek
Priesthood, and who does not pay an honest tithing is rebelling against the revelations of God?
</p><p>
What about attendance at Sacrament meeting? I remember as a young man being placed in a
bishopric, and of being told we ought to achieve twenty percent attendance at Sacrament
meeting. Today the current average attendance is thirty-three percent, and yet each Sunday
finds sixty-seven out of one hundred of our people not attending their Sacrament meeting.
Would you say that this failure to attend, on the part of some, is something of a rebellion
against this revelation given at Jackson County, Missouri, in 1831
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/1-24#1">D&amp;C 59:1-24</a>)?
</p><p>
Then what about the revelation on virtue and the receiving of the Holy Ghost, given in
Liberty Prison in 1839, when the Prophet revealed to us that if we would have the
companionship of the Holy Ghost, our lives must be virtuous and we must live constantly
under that influence (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/1-46#1">D&amp;C 121:1-46</a>)?
Would you say that those who have evil thoughts and would permit
unclean practices to come into their lives are opposing the will and the revelations of God on
purity of life?
</p><p>
There are still other revelations&mdash;the reiteration of the Ten Commandments at Kirtland, Ohio,
in section 42 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/1-93#1">D&amp;C 42:1-93</a>);
the great principle of righteous dominion, in section 121, wherein we are to live
with our fellow men in kindness, in long-suffering, in meekness, and love unfeigned, in the
true spirit of brotherhood as becomes a Latter-day Saint
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41#41">D&amp;C 121:41</a>); the revelations on temple work in
sections 124 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/1-145#1">D&amp;C 124:1-145</a>),
127 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/1-12#1">D&amp;C 127:1-12</a>),
and 128 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/1-25#1">D&amp;C 128:1-25</a>),
given in Nauvoo, Illinois, in 1841 and 1842.
</p><p>
Are we doing all that we can in accordance with these revelations, and if we are not are we
inwardly opposing them? My brothers and sisters, you be the ones to answer that for
yourselves.
</p><p>
Then there is this last one I will refer to, the revelation on harmful indulgences&mdash;the Word
of Wisdom (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/1-21#1">D&amp;C 89:1-21</a>)&mdash;and we see the manifest desire of many within the Church to twist the meaning
of this great revelation, and those who do this, are they rebelling against the will of God as
they did in the earlier days?
</p><p>
I bear record to you, my brethren and sisters, that these revelations have been given to us for
our enlightenment, for our growth, that we may return to the presence of our Heavenly
Father. They are a distinguishing characteristic of the Latter-day Saints. We are to use them
for our upbuilding and growth within the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Would it not be profitable to review the revelations&mdash;to learn afresh&mdash;to "know our duty"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>)
and then where needful adjust our lives <i>fully</i> to the laws and commandments of God?
</p><p>
I bear record to the truthfulness of the revelations given to the Prophet Joseph Smith. In the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
