<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Work of Conversion</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 81-85</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
May I read again the beautiful words which have just been sung to you by our wonderful
choir.
</p><p>
The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want.
</p><p>
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures: he leadeth me beside the still waters.
</p><p>
He restoreth my soul: he leadeth me in the paths of righteousness for his name's sake.
</p><p>
Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for thou art
with me; thy rod and thy staff they comfort me.
</p><p>
Thou preparest a table before me in the presence of mine enemies: thou anointest my head
with oil; my cup runneth over.
</p><p>
Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me all the days of my life: and I will dwell in the
house of the Lord for ever (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/23/1-6#1">Ps. 23:1-6</a>).
</p><p>
That is a great testimony. I am grateful that the choir sang this number, giving this testimony
of the psalmist because this has been a conference of testimonies&mdash;testimony after testimony
to the divinity of the Lord Jesus Christ testimony after testimony to the goodness of the Lord
our Father to all men who will follow him and really make him their shepherd. People who
thus follow him, testify anew day by day indeed that the Lord is their shepherd; they shall not
want and say, "Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me all the days of my life: and I will
dwell in the house of the Lord for ever."
</p><p>
I remember also that this choir has sung words from Isaiah, "All we like sheep have gone
astray" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/53/6#6">Isa. 53:6</a>).
And then I remember this beautiful story of the Savior: 
</p><p>
How think ye? if a man have an hundred sheep, and one of them be gone astray, doth he not
leave the ninety and nine, and goeth into the mountains, and seeketh that which is gone
astray?
</p><p>
And if so be that he find it, verily I say unto you, he rejoiceth more of that sheep than of the
ninety and nine which went not astray.
</p><p>
Even so it is not the will of your Father which is in heaven, that one of these little ones
should perish (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/12-14#12">Matt. 18:12-14</a>).
</p><p>
The work of the Church is a work of conversion. This has been well demonstrated by the
testimonies and the wonderful addresses which have been given here, and by the appeals
which have been made for further conversions. We seek for conversion of ourselves, of our
children, and of all mankind who will listen to us&mdash;conversion to the point where we and
they will be willing to accept the teachings and commandments of the Lord our Savior and by
following them work out our salvation. As the Lord says here, ". . . it is not the will of your
Father which is in heaven, that one of these little ones should perish"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/14#14">Matt. 18:14</a>).
</p><p>
But in spite of all the work that is done in the Church in the way of conversion and teaching,
and so much wonderful work is done, there are some instances where people go in reverse
and fall away. Sometimes they accept the teachings of false leaders and false teachers who
lead them astray.
</p><p>
Often I have asked myself why it is that some people apostatize from the truth. I have never
believed that a person falls away suddenly, all at once, any more than a person who has been
righteous and honest all his life would go out and suddenly rob a bank. There is some
preparatory work done in advance. There is some "softening-up" process which leads to the
apostate condition. Big sins generally are preceded by little ones, and I believe that this is true
with respect to people who fall away from the truth.
</p><p>
Seeds are sown, seeds of doubt, disbelief, distrust, disrespect. These seeds are watered; they
are nurtured, and finally they become fully developed until they produce their evil fruit.
</p><p>
Who sows these seeds of doubt and distrust? They are sown in many ways. I might mention a
few.
</p><p>
I have heard of a man who claims to be a very good Latter-day Saint. He claims that he loves
the Church, but he also loves the world, and he lives as close as he possibly can to the line of
disobedience without actually violating the letter of the law. He does not realize that he must
avoid even the very appearance of evil. He does not realize, possibly, that by living as close
to the line of disobedience as he can he sows seeds of doubt and distrust in the minds of
others.
</p><p>
There are those who live in open rebellion against the word of God and violate the
commandments continuously and intentionally, and of course they always leave doubt in the
minds of others, with some disrespect for them themselves.
</p><p>
And then there are the seeds that are sown by some of our teachers and preachers within our
own organization who like to advance some new doctrine, or some new interpretation, or
some speculative theory, or advance something that is sensational, because to advance the
sensational seems to feed their ego inasmuch as they become the center of a discussion.
</p><p>
Most of our teachers and preachers are wonderful. They teach the truth; they bring about
conversions in the minds and hearts of those who listen to them. But there are these few
teachers who sow seeds of doubt by speculative and unsound doctrines, and as they do so they
"soften up," to use the army expression, some of their hearers who might later be taken over
by the apostate teachers who come among them.
</p><p>
It is my full belief that whenever any of us accepts a position of any description in the
Church, we accept along with it the responsibility of that office, whatsoever it may be. I
believe that if a person accepts a position as a teacher in one of our organizations, or if he
accepts the responsibility of preaching from the pulpit, such person accepts the responsibility
which goes with that call. He becomes a representative of the Church in that position. Every
teacher and every preacher therefore is duty-bound, upon accepting such a call, to represent
the official views and doctrines of the Church, and to teach those official doctrines in his class
or from the pulpit, with the one thought in mind that conversion is to come about in the
hearts of those who listen to him. I do not believe that conversion to the truth comes through
the teaching of half-truths or untruths.
</p><p>
Our classrooms and our assembly rooms have been built at great expense with only one
thought in mind, and that is that in them we may teach the truth so that we may convert those
who come there, so that they in turn will live the gospel and work out their salvation in the
earth.
</p><p>
I do not believe that the classrooms or the pulpits of our Church are for laboratory purposes
in which to experiment with new doctrines and speculative notions. They are exclusively for
the use of those who are willing to convert men and women and boys and girls to the truth.
</p><p>
There is only one man in all the world who has the right to introduce a new doctrine to this
Church, and that man is the President of the Church. So teachers, until you become the
President of the Church, will you be willing to content yourselves with the present officially
accepted doctrines of the Church?
</p><p>
I do not believe that we can escape the responsibility of starting someone off on the wrong
way if we teach wrong principles. I do not believe that any of us can afford to take that
responsibility.
</p><p>
I do not believe, therefore, that we can bring into our classes or our sermons views and
doctrines which are not accepted and officially advocated by the Church.
</p><p>
I do not believe that any teacher in any organization has the right to discard the prescribed
lesson course and substitute in its place magazine articles, philosophical discussions, lectures,
or any other extraneous matter.
</p><p>
I do not believe that we can bring into our classrooms or sermons the philosophies and
doctrines of uninspired men of the world, no matter how well educated they may be, and
present them as accepted truth.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should accept every theory advanced by men of science as though it were
true. These men change their minds much too often for that.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should bring into our classes and sermons the doctrines of other churches
and teach them as accepted truth.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should teach the doctrines of the British-Israel or similar organizations,
sensational though they may be, presenting them to our people as though they were true.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should give time in our classes to discussions of the alleged
interpretations of the measurements of the Great Pyramid of Egypt, fantastic and unreliable as
they so often are.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should accept the current views that the lost ten tribes have been found in
the northern nations of Europe or that they have been named, indexed, and classified.
</p><p>
I do not believe that we can accept the peculiar notion that the mythical Odin of the North
was in reality the Savior of the world performing his work among the northern nations of
Europe or the ten tribes.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should give credence to the highly speculative theories about Book of
Mormon geography.
</p><p>
I do not believe that there were two Hill Cumorahs, one in Central America and the other one
up in New York, for the convenience of the Prophet Joseph Smith, so that
the poor boy would not have to walk clear to Central America to get the gold plates.
</p><p>
I do not believe we can be good Latter-day Saints and question the integrity of Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
I do not believe we can be good Latter-day Saints and question the testimony of the eleven
witnesses of the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
I do not believe you have a testimony of the truth if you question the accuracy of the
translation of the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
I do not believe you have the facts or are being honest with yourself if you question the
Manifesto as it appears in the Doctrine and Covenants.
</p><p>
I do not believe we should try to establish our personal fads as Church doctrine. I do not
believe my eternal salvation will be affected in any way if I eat white bread or white sugar. I
do not believe the doctrines of the Church are in any way involved in whether my whole
wheat is stoneground or steel-cut.
</p><p>
I do not believe we can be good Christians, regardless of the denomination, if we refuse to
believe that Jesus Christ died on the cross. I do not believe anyone can be a good Christian,
regardless of denomination, if he questions the reality of the literal, physical resurrection of
Jesus Christ on the third day after his crucifixion.
</p><p>
I do not believe we can be good Christians of any denomination and reject the Old Testament.
I do not believe we can be good Christians of any denomination and reject the epistles of the
New Testament.
</p><p>
I do not believe we can be good Latter-day Saints, or that we are loyal to this Church, if we
accept alleged revelations of men and women who claim to have received them for the
membership of the Church when we know that the Lord designates the President of the
Church as the only one on earth to whom he will reveal his mind for the Church at large.
</p><p>
I do not believe that we can be good Latter-day Saints or good Christians of any
denomination and accept the teachings of some that death was a mistake that it can be
avoided, and that we can achieve immortality without passing through death, just by following
the teachings of some false prophet.
</p><p>
I do not believe that we can ignore the teachings of the Savior when he said,
</p><p>
. . . there shall be no disputations among you, as there have hitherto been; neither shall there
be disputations among you concerning the points of my doctrine, as there have hitherto been.
</p><p>
For verily, verily I say unto you, he that hath the spirit of contention is not of me, but is of
the devil, who is the father of contention, and he stirreth up the hearts of men to contend with
anger, one with another (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/28-29#28">3 Ne. 11:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
On the other hand, I do believe most positively that if we bring false teachings into our
classes or sermons we do our people a great disservice, for we confuse their minds, we make
them doubt the truth when it is given to them, and we "soften them up" for the attacks of
apostate teachers who come among them.
</p><p>
I do believe positively that whenever we teach any speculative notion or try to unravel any
mystery, or advance any doctrine not accepted by the Church, we contribute to the spiritual
delinquency of those whom we influence.
</p><p>
I do believe that whenever we by our acts or our teachings reflect discredit upon the Church
or its doctrines, we contribute to the spiritual delinquency of those about us.
</p><p>
I do believe that God will hold us accountable for every act and word by which we contribute
to the spiritual delinquency of other people.
</p><p>
I do believe that the President of the Church is in very deed the mouthpiece of God on earth,
the prophet, seer, and revelator of the Lord, and that he and he alone has the right and power
to give to the Church any new doctrines or new interpretations of existing doctrines.
</p><p>
I do believe that Jesus Christ is the Son of the Eternal God, Creator of heaven and earth, that
he died on the cross and was resurrected the third day, literally and physically.
</p><p>
I do believe positively that as we all die, even so, through the power of Jesus the resurrected
Christ, we, too, will literally and physically be resurrected.
</p><p>
I do believe that the revealed doctrines and teachings of the Christ will save us without any
additions by unauthorized persons.
</p><p>
I do believe that the Lord has given to the Latter-day Saints a fair amount of intelligence. I
do believe that he expects us to use that intelligence in studying his revealed word and
following his prophets here on earth, so that we will not be tossed about by every wind of
doctrine.
</p><p>
I do believe that he expects our teachers and preachers to use the common sense he has given
them to teach the simple truth which saves, rather than the speculations and theories of men,
which only confuse the mind and lead some of our people right out of the Church.
</p><p>
I do believe that by proper teaching of the revealed truth we can convert ourselves and our
children and all others who are willing to listen to us.
</p><p>
I do believe that people are converted to the truth only by the truth and not through the
teaching of half-truths and untruths.
</p><p>
I do believe that only in loyally teaching and living the true principles of the gospel can we
fulfil the responsibility which God has given us, and this is my testimony in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
