<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Life's Laboratory</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Carl W. Buehner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Carl W. Buehner, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1956, pp. 115-118</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I suppose you wonder what I might say, and I
will tell you I am wondering that myself. I have been looking for another interpretation of the
scripture that says the first shall be last and the last shall be first. In this case the last is about
the last.
</p><p>
I certainly enjoy my work in the Church, and with the others I would like to bear my
testimony to the divinity of this great work. It is wonderful to meet with the brethren, to feel
their strength and their power. I wish you had the same privilege that we have of meeting
with them. It is also a great privilege to travel in the stakes of the Church and meet you
wonderful people in the areas in which you live.
</p><p>
Since hearing Brother Moyle today and Brother Bennion last Friday, I have had the feeling
that our members living in countries far away from us seem much nearer to us, and hearing
the choir sing yesterday, representing the countries of Scandinavia, I could not help thinking
what a wonderful representation they were of the people and how proud the Scandinavians
would have been had they been able to hear this choir sing from this tabernacle.
</p><p>
I have been equally thrilled by the marvelous music today. Brother Petersen had two foreign
expressions that revealed his gratitude for the Scandinavian choir, but in the language that
these people can understand, I can say in three words: It is wonderful!
</p><p>
I have been thinking a little of the great day in which we live and some of the marvelous
things we observe, some things that are blessings to us, some that might tend to destroy us,
and others that might lead to our self-preservation. I have been thinking of the scientist or the
inventor who sits in his laboratory with his test tubes, his chemicals, his minerals, and all of
the devices to measure time, speed, weight, etc., and ponders over some of the remarkable
things that he has produced.
</p><p>
The atomic bomb that we have heard about during this conference is not very large. It is said
that the one dropped at Bikini lifted ten million tons of water ten miles into the air. It is
almost impossible to imagine such power. The H-Bomb exploded at Eniwetok all but wiped
out a whole island in the Pacific Ocean, leaving a crater 175 feet deep and one mile wide. It
is said that the power from this bomb exceeded the power of all the bombs dropped during
World War II on Germany and Japan combined.
</p><p>
You may have read recently that a one pound slug of polished uranium, which is about the
size of a golf ball, contains more power than all the TNT you could put into Yankee Stadium.
</p><p>
What man is doing is tremendous. I think of the speed and ease with which we travel.
Compare this with the way Christopher Columbus and his crew crossed the ocean in the
<i>Nina, Pinta</i>, and <i>Santa Maria</i>&mdash;fifty-one days, twenty-four hours a day. Have you ever multiplied
that? He traveled and discovered a new land at the rapid speed of two miles an hour! Coming
to conference, I am sure some of you walked five miles an hour to get a seat here.
</p><p>
I read in the paper recently that a jet plane had traveled 1,900 miles an hour and had gone
into the air fourteen miles and broken the sound barrier&mdash;whatever that is. I have had a jet
ride. I know how it feels to travel five hundred miles an hour in the air. It is thrilling and
exciting. Another jet plane went all but four times that fast. We are living in a great day!
</p><p>
What man has been able to accomplish through his own intelligence is infinitesimal when
compared to the power of the Creator.
</p><p>
We, too, are living as it were in the great laboratory of life. We are being tried and tested.
We are seeking the combinations by which we can progress and prove ourselves. We are
living in this world filled with good and evil, with right and wrong, with truth and error, and
with light and darkness. You have heard today that there are false teachers, false doctrines,
false prophets; and here we have been placed. Reference was made last evening in the general
priesthood meeting to the great privilege of having a mortal body. It means that we kept our
first estate. We are now being tried in life's laboratory to see whether or not we can keep our
second estate; and it is not an easy thing. We are being tempted all the time; even the best of
us are subject to temptation.
</p><p>
Think what we experience going through life and what it means to us. It has been said that
we have the right to exercise our own free agency. I trust that this experience will enable us
to select the things that will be constructive and that will bring us nearer to the Lord. It is
said in the scriptures that the earth was covered with darkness, and gross darkness covered the
minds of the people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/60/2#2">Isa. 60:2</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/23#23">D&amp;C 112:23</a>).
I am grateful for that day when the light from heaven came again and
the gospel was restored. Think of the advantages that men have now in this great laboratory
to seek out the truth and get together those ingredients that will help us gain a testimony of
the divinity of this great work.
</p><p>
Men of science have done great things. Men living in life's laboratory can also accomplish
great things. We shall not all be saved; some will be destroyed. We do not all think the same
way. We shall not all get the right combinations and arrive at the same great purpose for
which we have been brought here. But I hope, brethren and sisters, that all of us will have a
desire to seek out those things that will eventually gain for each of us eternal life in the
kingdom of our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
When you contemplate the power of the Almighty compared to the power that man seems to
have been able to assemble, think of this: 
</p><p>
And worlds without number have I created; and I also created them for mine own
purpose; and by the Son I created them, which is mine Only Begotten . . .<br />
. . . For behold, there are many worlds that have passed away by the word of my
power. And there are many that now stand, and innumerable are they unto man; but all
things are numbered unto me, for they are mine and I know them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33,35#33">Moses 1:33,35</a>).
</p><p>
Think also of the power of the resurrection, when the elements that have gone back to mother
earth can be assembled and united with the spirit to form a perfect, resurrected body; the
power to save and exalt in the kingdom of our Heavenly Father. As has already been said,
and not one sparrow shall fall unnoticed, neither shall one hair of the head be lost (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/29-31#29">Matt. 10:29-31</a>)&mdash;and
that is comforting to some of us, too.
</p><p>
God the Father and his Son have revealed themselves in this Dispensation of the Fulness of
Times. I would like to read a quotation or two from the extracts of the history of the Prophet
Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
The first verse tells why he wrote this: 
</p><p>
Owing to the many reports which have been put in circulation by evil-disposed and
designing persons, in relation to the rise and progress of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, all of which have been designed by the authors thereof to militate
against its character as a Church and its progress in the world&mdash;I have been induced to
write this history, to disabuse the public mind, and put all inquirers after truth in
possession of the facts, as they have transpired, in relation both to myself and the
Church, so far as I have such facts in my possession
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1#1">JS&mdash;H 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
He continues by relating where he was born, when he was born, telling about the other
members of his family, and about a great religious revival that took place in the area into
which they had moved. I would like to continue from there: 
</p><p>
While I was laboring under the extreme difficulties caused by the contests of these
parties of religionists, I was one day reading the Epistle of James, first chapter and
fifth verse, which reads: <i>If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to</i>
<i>all men liberally, and upbraideth not; and it shall be given him</i>.<br />
Never did any passage of scripture come with more power to the heart of man than
this did at this time to mine. It seemed to enter with great force into every feeling of
my heart . . .<br />
So, in accordance with this, my determination to ask of God, I retired to the woods to
make the attempt. It was on the morning of a beautiful, clear day, early in the spring
of eighteen hundred and twenty. It was the first time in my life that I had made such
an attempt, for amidst all my anxieties I had never as yet made the attempt to pray
vocally.<br />
After I had retired to the place where I had previously designed to go, having looked
around me, and finding myself alone, I kneeled down and began to offer up the desire
of my heart to God. I had scarcely done so, when immediately I was seized upon by
some power which entirely overcame me, and had such an astonishing influence over
me as to bind my tongue so that I could not speak. Thick darkness gathered around
me, and it seemed to me for a time as if I were doomed to sudden destruction.<br />
But, exerting all my powers to call upon God to deliver me out of the power of this
enemy which had seized upon me, and at the very moment when I was ready to sink
into despair and abandon myself to destruction&mdash;not to an imaginary ruin, but to the
power of some actual being from the unseen world, who had such marvelous power as
I had never before felt in any being&mdash;just at this moment of great alarm, I saw a
pillar of light exactly over my head, above the brightness of the sun, which descended
gradually until it fell upon me.<br />
It no sooner appeared than I found myself delivered from the enemy which held me
bound. When the light rested upon me I saw two personages, whose brightness and
glory defy all description, standing above me in the air. One of them spake unto me,
calling me by name and said, pointing to the other&mdash;<i>This Is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/11-12,14-17#11">JS&mdash;H 1:11-12,14-17</a>).
</p><p>
I think the great message of the ages still is that God lives, that he is mindful of us, his
children, that he is all-powerful, that his Son is the Savior and Redeemer of the world.
</p><p>
Other messengers came also. I should not take more time, but just let me describe one other
who came to the earth. Two or three years had elapsed since the time that the Father and the
Son had appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
While I was thus in the act of calling upon God, I discovered a light appearing in my
room, which continued to increase until the room was lighter than at noon-day, when
immediately a personage appeared at my bedside, standing in the air, for his feet did
not touch the floor.<br />
He had on a loose robe of most exquisite whiteness. It was a whiteness beyond
anything earthly I had ever seen; nor do I believe that any earthly thing could be made
to appear so exceedingly white and brilliant. His hands were naked, and his arms also,
a little above the wrist; so, also, were his feet naked, as were his legs, a little above
the ankles. His head and neck were also bare. I could discover that he had no other
clothing on but this robe, as it was open, so that I could see into his bosom.<br />
Not only was his robe exceedingly white, but his whole person was glorious beyond
description, and his countenance truly like lightning. The room was exceedingly light,
but not so very bright as immediately around his person. When I first looked upon
him, I was afraid; but the fear soon left me.<br />
He called me by name, and said unto me that he was a messenger sent from the
presence of God to me, and that his name was Moroni
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/30-33#30">JS&mdash;H 1:30-33</a>).
</p><p>
Actually these heavenly beings have been sent in this great Dispensation of the Fulness of
Times. I would commend that you accept the testimonies of the brethren who have spoken
during this conference concerning this great thing, the restoration of the gospel, and I am sure
if you can accept them, you will have a conviction, a knowledge, and an understanding that
this great latter-day work is divine.
</p><p>
May we all, always, young people and all of us, have a desire to ask, to knock, to seek, and
to put together those combinations that will help us eventually gain a home in the celestial
kingdom of our Heavenly Father, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
