<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"And This Is My Gospel..."</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 23-27</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
In President McKay's address this morning he told of a picture that hung in the Huntsville
meetinghouse, a picture of President John Taylor under which were the words, "Where the
kingdom of God is not, there is nothing." That statement encourages me to talk about
something about which I have been thinking for a long time. If the Lord is willing and I
might have his Spirit, I would like to speak about a subject which I will introduce by quoting
a question asked by a missionary, and a statement from a great thinker. The missionary asked,
"Since the restored Church claims that it is necessary to have the same organization that
existed in the primitive church, particularly Twelve Apostles, how then can we claim that the
kingdom of God and the gospel were upon the earth before the time of the Savior when they
had no Apostles?"
</p><p>
The statement which I wish to read is from Napoleon I, while he was in exile in 1817. It
reads as follows: "I could believe in a religion if it existed from the beginning of time, but
when I consider Socrates, Plato, and Mohammed, I no longer believe."
</p><p>
There are those who believe that the kingdom of God was not established until after the
advent of the Savior and that the gospel of Jesus Christ was not upon the earth until the time
of his advent.
</p><p>
As I have thought of that question of the missionary about the organization of the Church,
and about Napoleon's statement, three questions have formulated themselves in my thinking:
The first, How old is the kingdom of God and the gospel upon the earth? The second, What
are the essentials of a gospel dispensation in the world? And third, What officers are
necessary in an organization to constitute the Church and kingdom of God? I realize that to
answer those questions fully would take much more time than is allotted to me, so I shall
comment only briefly and make a few observations in answer to these questions.
</p><p>
In the Lord's revelation to Abraham he spoke of the purpose in sending spirits upon the earth,
to ". . . prove them herewith, to see if they will do all things whatsoever the
Lord their God shall command them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/25#25">Abr. 3:25</a>),
with a promise that if they would keep
their second estate they should have glory added upon their heads forever and forever.
</p><p>
In the first chapter of the writings of John, the nature of that glory spoken of in the revelation
to Abraham is implied. John said,
</p><p>
But as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the sons of God...
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/12#12">John 1:12</a>).
</p><p>
In a modern revelation that same statement is repeated with slight variation and then clarified,
in these words: 
</p><p>
But to as many as received me, gave I power to become my sons...
</p><p>
And verily, verily, I say unto you, he that receiveth my gospel receiveth me; and he that
receiveth not my gospel receiveth not me.
</p><p>
And then the Lord proceeds to define the fundamental principles of the gospel in these words:
</p><p>
And this is my gospel&mdash;repentance and baptism by water, and then cometh the baptism of
fire and the Holy Ghost, even the Comforter, which showeth all things, and teacheth the
peaceable things of the kingdom
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/4-6#4">D&amp;C 39:4-6</a>).
</p><p>
The gospel plan, as these scriptures would indicate, was laid in the heavens before the earth
was organized and spirits were placed upon it.
</p><p>
That this gospel and the essentials of salvation have been upon the earth in every dispensation
from the time of Adam, there can be no doubt. In an early revelation to Moses, which we
have contained in the Pearl of Great Price, the Lord, speaking to Adam, said this: 
</p><p>
If thou wilt turn unto me, and hearken unto my voice, and believe, and repent of all thy
transgressions, and be baptized, even in water, in the name of mine Only Begotten Son, who
is full of grace and truth which is Jesus Christ, the only name which shall be given under
heaven, whereby salvation shall come unto the children of men, ye shall receive the gift of the
Holy Ghost, asking all things in his name, and whatsoever ye shall ask, it shall be given you.
</p><p>
Then there follows an account of the baptism of Adam, and this declaration by a voice
speaking out of heaven to Adam: 
</p><p>
Behold, thou art one in me, a son of God; and thus may all become my sons
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/52,68#52">Moses 6:52,68</a>).
</p><p>
In writing to the Galatians, the Apostle Paul said,
</p><p>
And the scripture, foreseeing that God would justify the heathen through faith, preached
before the gospel unto Abraham, saying, In thee shall all nations be blessed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/3/8#8">Gal. 3:8</a>).
</p><p>
He was speaking of the ordinance of baptism in Moses' day when he wrote these words to the
Corinthians: 
</p><p>
. . . how that all our fathers were under the cloud, and all passed through the sea; 
</p><p>
And were all baptized unto Moses...
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/10/1-2#1">1 Cor. 10:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
And then of the children of Israel under the leadership of Moses, Paul again wrote to the
Hebrews, and said,
</p><p>
For unto us was the gospel preached, as well as unto them: but the word preached did not
profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/4/2#2">Heb. 4:2</a>).
</p><p>
All of these statements thus recorded in the Bible have been confirmed by modern revelation.
</p><p>
Just as in the dispensations of Adam, Abraham, and Moses were those fundamental teachings
given and those fundamental ordinances of the gospel administered, so we hear the Savior
speaking to Nicodemus,
</p><p>
Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
To suppose that God would initiate ordinances on which salvation would be conditioned, and
then allow four thousand years to pass without any authority or any
organization to administer those ordinances, is untenable to the thinking man. A thinking man
would have to conclude with Napoleon, "Unless a religion existed from the beginning, I
cannot believe."
</p><p>
Now for just a moment, let's take a hasty look at the Church organizations that have existed
in each of these dispensations from the beginning. To Adam was given ". . . dominion . . .
over every living thing that moveth upon the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>). The government in his
time was patriarchal, the priesthood ruled. Men holding the priesthood ruled by direct
revelation and commandment. In Enoch's time likewise, his government was patriarchal. Zion,
the City of Holiness, was established, and Enoch gave a perfect economic law, known to us as
the Order of Enoch (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/57#57">D&amp;C 76:57</a>).
There was likewise a similar government from Noah to Abraham, as we
are informed by modern revelation in these words,
</p><p>
The order of this priesthood was confirmed to be handed down from father to son, and rightly
belongs to the literal descendants of the chosen seed, to whom the promises were made
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/40#40">D&amp;C 107:40</a>).
</p><p>
From Moses to the Prophet Samuel, Israel was governed by judges, who were from among
the people. And then you will recall, because they were "peculiar"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>) in that type of government,
they sought for a king, to be like other peoples
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/8/5-22#5">1 Sam. 8:5-22</a>); a king to rule over them in secular matters,
while a prophet would continue to guide in spiritual affairs. You will recall that Saul was then
chosen, followed by David, and by Solomon, and then the division of the children of Israel
into the kingdom of Judah and the kingdom of Israel under Rehoboam and Jeroboam.
</p><p>
With the advent of Jesus, the Jews were in a state of apostasy, and you will recall he chose
twelve men to be his special witnesses, and to one of these twelve, Peter, he gave the keys to
the kingdom of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18-19#18">Matt. 16:18-19</a>).
The significance of that commission of the keys of the kingdom to Peter
is better understood in the words of a revelation given to us by the Prophet Joseph Smith,
when the Lord said this, speaking of the Prophet Joseph,
</p><p>
Unto whom I have given the keys of the kingdom, which belong always unto the Presidency
of the High Priesthood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/81/2#2">D&amp;C 81:2</a>).
</p><p>
In other words, Peter, holding the keys of the kingdom, was as much the president of the
High Priesthood in his day as Joseph Smith and his successors, to whom also these "keys"
were given in our day, are the presidents of the High Priesthood, and the earthly heads of the
Church and kingdom of God on the earth.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul describing the Church organization in his day said,
</p><p>
And God hath set some in the church, first apostles, secondarily prophets . . . after that . . .
helps, governments . . . etc. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/28#28">1 Cor. 12:28</a>).
</p><p>
But in all of these Church offices we are told again in the revelations
</p><p>
. . . there is never but one on the earth at a time on whom this power and the keys of this
priesthood are conferred . . . (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/7#7">D&amp;C 132:7</a>).
</p><p>
We are living today in the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times, and we were given a
statement, inspired by the Lord, to the Prophet Joseph Smith in these words, which make
some explanation of what the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times contemplated. He said,
</p><p>
. . . for it is necessary in the ushering in of the dispensation of the fulness of times, which
dispensation is now beginning to usher in, that a whole and complete and perfect union, and
welding together of dispensations, and keys, and powers, and glories should . . . be revealed
from the days of Adam, even to the present time. And not only this, but those things which
never have been revealed from the foundation of the world . . . shall be revealed . . . in this,
the dispensation of the fulness of times...
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/18#18">D&amp;C 128:18</a>).
</p><p>
The Apostle Peter spoke of that, in referring to this same Dispensation of the
Fulness of Times, when he said there would be a
</p><p>
. . . restitution of all things, which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets
since the world began (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>).
</p><p>
It seems clear then that were the Church organization today to be devoid of that which Jesus
gave, therefore, in the way of organization, this dispensation would fail by that same token to
be an established kingdom of God upon the earth in the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times
in which was to be restored "all things." Undoubtedly the organization the Master gave was to
be the pattern of organization more perfected than in the past dispensations. There is evidence
of this in the fact that after he had left the people here following his resurrection, he went to
the Nephites, and there again he chose twelve disciples
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/12/1#1">3 Ne. 12:1</a>), whom he set up to govern his Church
and that part of the kingdom here on this continent among the Nephites.
</p><p>
We might then ask, what is the kingdom of God? And again we are not left without an
answer, for the Lord replied, "The keys of the kingdom of God are committed unto man on
the earth...." Where there are the keys to the kingdom, there is the Church of Jesus Christ,
and it is the stone which was cut out of the mountain without hands, as told in Daniel's
interpretation of the dream, which was to roll forth and smite the image and break it in pieces
and to roll on until it should fill the whole earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/65/2#2">D&amp;C 65:2</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith makes this definition of the kingdom of God: 
</p><p>
Some say that the kingdom of God was not set up upon the earth until the day of Pentecost,
and that John did not preach the baptism of repentance for the remission of sins, but I say to
you in the name of the Lord that the kingdom of God was set up upon the earth in the days
of Adam to the present time. Whenever there has been a righteous man on the earth unto
whom God revealed His word and gave power and authority to administer in His name, and
where there is a priest of God . . . to administer in the ordinances of the gospel, and officiate
in the priesthood of God, there is the kingdom of God . . . Where there is a prophet, a priest, or
a righteous man unto whom God gives His oracles, there is the kingdom of God; and where
the oracles of God are not, there the kingdom of God is not.
(<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, pp. 271-272.)
</p><p>
This is but another way of saying what the picture in Huntsville declared as related by
President McKay, "Where the kingdom of God is not there is nothing."
</p><p>
Just as the Master said in his day, the kingdom of God cometh not by observation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/20#20">Luke 17:20</a>), meaning
that there would be no outward signs or no political changes, so today, it is now among us, as
it has been in every dispensation of the gospel since the days of Adam.
</p><p>
Another statement was made by the prophets of the New Testament which to me has some
significance. They are quoted as having said that ". . . the kingdom of God is within you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/21#21">Luke 17:21</a>).
A more correct translation probably would have said, "The kingdom of God is
among you or in your midst," but as I thought of that other statement, "The kingdom of God
is within you," I recalled an experience that we had with a group of students from Brigham
Young University, who were gracious enough to come under the leadership of President
Wilkinson to a little group over in the Lion House, and there sixteen, representing sixteen
foreign countries, were asked to stand and tell how they came to know about the gospel and
accept it, why they were at Brigham Young University, and to bear their testimonies. It was a
most intensely interesting evening. We heard from young men and women from Mexico,
Argentina, Brazil, the Scandinavian countries, France, and England. The story was the same.
When they began to relate how they came to find the gospel, it was this: They were
yearning for truth. They were seeking for it. They were not satisfied, and in the
midst of their search, someone came to them with the truths of the gospel. They prayed about
it and sought the Lord intensely, intently, with all their hearts, and came to receive a divine
testimony by which they knew that this the gospel of Jesus Christ. One woman said, "I had
been studying the gospel, and this night I came to a meeting and I heard them sing, "Joseph
Smith's First Prayer," which gave in song the story of the first vision, and before they had
finished that song, into my heart the Spirit bore testimony that this is the Church and kingdom
of God. So within the heart of everyone, every honest seeker after truth, if he has the desire
to know, and studies with real intent and faith in the Lord Jesus Christ, the kingdom of God
may be within him, or in other words, the power to receive it is his.
</p><p>
I bear you my humble witness that this is the Church and kingdom of God in the earth. This
is the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times. Except for the fact that it is but a continuation of
the same gospel, the same fundamental principles, the same authority which has existed from
the beginning of time, we would have to say with Napoleon I,
</p><p>
Except you can prove to me that this religion has been from the beginning, I will not believe.
</p><p>
God help us to take this message out to the world and convince them of the power of the
gospel and the power which is within them to receive the kingdom of God while it is yet day,
I pray humbly in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
