<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 74-78</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Clark, President McKay, my other beloved brethren of the General Authorities, and
my dear brethren of the priesthood, truly this is nearly breathtaking, and I feel very humble in
standing here tonight. I am sure we didn't expect this tonight, and I will be grateful if I can
have an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
Yes, this is very much a humbling experience. I wish all of you could have the experience I
am now having of looking over this vast audience. I have prayed to the Lord that when I
should be called to occupy this position that he should not leave me. I have prayed to him
first because I believe in prayer and, second, because I know I need the blessings of the Lord.
I confess to you that without those blessings and his sustaining help and influence that I am
nothing.
</p><p>
PROPHETS OF GOD
</p><p>
Surely one's testimony is strengthened as he comes here and listens to the brethren, listens to
the words of the Lord given to us by his servants, yes, by prophets, seers, and revelators of
God, our Eternal Father. We often hear them referred to as prophets, but I am wondering,
members of the Church and particularly holders of the priesthood, if we give serious thought
to the full meaning of that term. I recognize them as prophets of God, I know you do but
there are times, perhaps, when we pass that thought by lightly. Do you feel toward these
brethren, prophets of the Lord, as you would had you known the prophets of old? I want to
bear my testimony to you that I know they are prophets of the living God, I know they are
inspired of our Father in Heaven in their calling. I hope you will have the same feeling
burning in your hearts and accept their teachings, because they are inspired of our Father in
Heaven. If as members of the Church and particularly the Priesthood, we could only have the
faith and the assurance and the conviction that these brethren are prophets, seers, and
revelators, I believe we would pay more attention to what they tell us. Yes, spirituality is as
essential to a man's soul as vitamins are to his body.
</p><p>
ADULT MEMBERS OF AARONIC PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
As I look into this great congregation tonight, I have been thinking of the adult members of
the Aaronic Priesthood, many of them who have never been inside this building. If we could
move this body of men from this building on out to the north and then fill it again and again
with adult members of the Aaronic Priesthood in the Church, we could fill this building just
as full as it is now, seven or eight times. You know, I'm one of those who believes the Lord
loves these men. I believe their wives love them just as much as our wives love us, and their
children love them as much as our children love us. If you had a wayward son, would you
love him? Well, I only have one son, and I love him very much, and if he were a wayward
son, I believe I would love him just the same. What makes you think that the Lord doesn't
love his wayward sons?
</p><p>
NEED FOR GUIDANCE
</p><p>
Many of these men haven't the strength to get back into activity in the Church on their own
power. Therefore, they do need your guidance, your encouragement and your patience; yes,
I'd say they need you. They need someone to call on them, someone to come and see them,
someone to encourage them and help them forsake those things that are keeping them out of
the Church. The Lord has asked us to repent, he has asked all of us to repent, and then he
said; If you truly repent and come unto me, and forsake those things that you're doing, or that
you have done that you shouldn't have done, I will forgive you and remember them no more.
But he wants us to truly repent. I believe these men would love that privilege. Well, you may
say, they have the privilege. Why don't they take it? Well, they haven't the strength yet, until
they can absorb some of the teachings of the Church and of the gospel of Jesus Christ, which
they haven't had for a long time. They have perhaps become spiritually weak, because of
habits that have kept them from church activity or for other reasons. They're not strong
enough yet to put those things aside. And then you must remember that many of these boys
and men have not been taught in their homes. As Bishop Wirthlin told us, they were not
taught their many duties when they were young. I believe there are many fathers in the
Church today, although I think they're not justified, that are leaving the teachings of their
sons to you brethren entirely. If you fail, where are they going to get those teachings? Many
adult members of the Aaronic Priesthood, after they come back into activity, are so delighted
and so anxious that they put a great deal of enthusiasm in their work.
</p><p>
I talked to a brother, who is now a bishop but who was an adult member of the Aaronic
Priesthood five or six years ago. I couldn't help but recognize the joy and the happiness that
has come into that man's soul. I talked to his wife. She didn't have the ability nor the words
to tell me how grateful they were. Yes, sometimes I think they're perhaps more grateful than
some of the rest of us, after the spirit has touched their souls and they've accepted it.
</p><p>
WORKERS NEEDED
</p><p>
Someone has said, "He who knows books knows much, he who knows nature knows more,
but he who knows God has reached the goal of human wisdom." Many of these men are
brilliant men, in their own right, successful men in their own business, and they do know
books, but they have perhaps neglected their knowledge of God. As leaders, I hope that you
make yourselves acquainted with these thousands of adult members. It's too big a load for
just two or three in each ward, or a dozen or so in each stake. There are many stakes in the
Church that have four or five or six hundred, and some stakes with even seven or eight
hundred adult members of the Aaronic Priesthood. Do you know how many men could be
called to work with a group like that, a group of five or six hundred men? You can't preach
to these men in Sacrament meetings, because they're not there. You don't get them into your
priesthood quorum meetings because they don't come out. Therefore we must put the shotgun
method away. We must now have individual contact and use the rifle method where we can
go in and teach those men the principles of the gospel, the teachings that you and I were
fortunate and blessed enough to have in our lives, but which many of them, not of their own
fault, have been denied.
</p><p>
Oh, I hope that you'll somehow or other organize yourselves that you'll be able to touch at
least one man. The Lord has said to us, "And if it so be that you should labor all your days in
crying repentance unto this people, and bring, save it be one soul unto me, how great shall be
your joy with him in the kingdom of my Father! And now, if your joy will be great with one
soul that you have brought unto me into the kingdom of my Father, how great will be your
joy if you should bring many souls unto me!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15-16#15">D&amp;C 18:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
FATHERS AND SONS
</p><p>
Now fathers, how close are you staying to your own sons, so that the group of adult members
will not be increased? Do you fathers have close relationship with your own sons? Can your
sons come to you and tell you all about their problems? Oh, I feel sorry for a boy that can't
go to his dad and tell him all about his mistakes, all about his sorrows, and all about his
problems. I think that that kind of relationship, in not being able to become close to a father,
can only tend to bring that boy, perhaps, more delinquent than ever. I know boys will make
mistakes, but oh, I feel that if they can go to their dads and talk over those mistakes with
them, that those boys will be stronger and will not repeat their mistakes too many times, if
they can come to their dads. Do you dare to go to bed at nights and not know where your
sons are? Do you know whom they're with, or where they are, or do you know when they're
coming home?
</p><p>
Awhile ago I was at a dinner party one night, and about eleven or eleven-thirty, the telephone
rang and one of the men was called to the phone. We couldn't hear the conversation on both
sides, but we could hear what he had to say. When he took his seat his wife said to him,
"who was that calling?" He said, "Well that was our son John. He just called to tell us that he
wouldn't be home at twelve o'clock." He told his father he was going to a waffle dinner after
the show or the dance, I don't recall which it was, but he called to tell his father that he
wouldn't be home until twelve-thirty or one o'clock. I turned to that man and said, "How old
is your boy?" I thought he was a youngster calling up. He said, "He's twenty-three years old."
I thought, what a marvelous relationship, what a marvelous thing that this boy would take the
time and make the effort to call his father at a party to tell him that he would be a little later
than usual.
</p><p>
Only that father said, "We can go home now tonight, and we don't need to worry about our
children. They're going to be home at a certain time, or they're going to call us." Well, there
isn't anything wrong in that kind of discipline. It isn't because it's strict discipline, it's
because there is an understanding between father and son.
</p><p>
CLOSE RELATIONSHIP
</p><p>
And then, fathers, do your boys, at night, when they do come home, come into your bedroom
and kiss you goodnight? Sometimes we have encouraged our daughters to do that with our
wives, their mothers, but we fathers perhaps have not practiced that with our own sons.
What's wrong with a son coming into his dad's bedroom at night and sitting on the side of
his bed and telling him how he liked his girl, or how the party was, or how they got along
tonight. Don't you think if a boy will do that, don't you think he'll go into his own bedroom
and kneel down and say his prayer after he has said goodnight to his dad? Don't you think if
he is that close to his dad, that he can pour his heart out to you after he sometimes stubs his
toe or makes a mistake? I don't like to see any boy or for that matter any man, live with his
mistakes, because I think it eats the best out of him that is in him. Oh, I hope he can go to
his father and tell his father about his problems, and about his mistakes and about his sorrows.
There is no reason, fathers, why we can't be that close to our sons. Does your boy kiss you
goodnight? Does your boy kiss you when you leave in the day, or when you leave for a trip?
Or have we left that to our wives and our daughters? I'll confess that I was guilty of that for
years, but I'm happy, so happy somehow or other that I've changed that in my own life. I'm
glad that I can kiss my boy when he comes around me. I'm glad I can kiss him when I leave:
I'm glad I can kiss him when I return. I don't want to be denied that beautiful blessing. I
recommend to you fathers that you start living a little closer to your sons, that you love them,
that you are not so strict with them that they can't come to you with anything.
</p><p>
Well, brothers, I didn't intend to say those things to you.  May the Lord bless you that you
may try and stay close to your sons, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
