<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Love One Another</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 30-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I am so grateful to be able to use this salutation and know that we
are brothers and sisters in the kingdom of Jesus Christ. A story I read recently is appropriate
here.
</p><p>
A preacher in a small community decided to do some remodeling and renovating of his
church. To begin with he requested a new chandelier. After three or four weeks had elapsed
and it hadn't arrived, he approached one of the deacons on the board and inquired why. He
was informed there were three reasons: "First, it hadn't been ordered because there was no
one on the board who could spell 'chandelier.' Second, we were afraid there wouldn't be
anyone to play it when it came. And third, what we really need in this church is more light."
</p><p>
I recognize we have light today which comes through our prophet and mouthpiece. We also
have the light from the teachings of the Master almost two thousand years ago, and I should
like to speak at this time on what I believe is a crying need in the world today, on the basic
principle of the gospel of Jesus Christ which is love.
</p><p>
The scriptures teach: "For God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that
whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>). This
indicates the depth of this great principle. It was exemplified by the Savior when he lived
upon the earth. On one occasion, he was queried by one of the scribes: "What is the great
commandment in the law?" In reply, Jesus taught an eternal truth. "Thou shalt love the Lord
thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and with all thy
strength: this is the first commandment.
</p><p>
"And the second is like, namely, this. Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/12/30-31#30">Mark 12:30-31</a>).
"On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/40#40">Matt. 22:40</a>).
</p><p>
There was none other commandment greater than these, so said Jesus
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/40#40">Matt. 22:40</a>).
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul spoke on this great principle many times in plain, understandable language.
</p><p>
Even though changing conditions exist in the world today, and many people are confused, the
application of this one principle in our everyday lives will bring happiness, contentment, and
peace.
</p><p>
Surely, if I love my fellow man, I will not cheat him, lie about him, or commit any manner
of evil against him. So again, loving all my fellow men, I will truly find happiness,
contentment, and a peace that passeth understanding.
</p><p>
Paul was inspired to reveal the virtues, or may we call them ingredients, of
which love is composed. Addressing the Corinthian Saints who had membership in the Church
of Jesus Christ, Paul said: "Love suffereth long and is kind" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/4#4">1 Cor. 13:4</a>). We sing a
great hymn, maybe not often enough, "Let Us Oft Speak Kind Words to Each Other." So
much more is accomplished by speaking in kind words and soft tones.
</p><p>
"Love envieth not." We look at others and think the grass is greener on their side. We
sometimes might wonder why ours seems not as green, but love envieth not. "Love vaunteth
not itself, is not puffed up" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/4#4">1 Cor. 13:4</a>).
In other words, love teaches true humility. Jesus
taught it in one parable [parable of Pharisee and Publican], "Whosoever shall exalt himself
shall be abased; and he that shall humble himself shall be exalted"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/12#12">Matt. 23:12</a>).
</p><p>
Daniel Webster had a great thought when asked, "What is the highest thought that has ever
entered your mind?" He answered, "My accountability to Almighty God."
</p><p>
We who have a testimony of the gospel should recognize our accountability to God regardless
of what our achievements might be in business, in church, in school, in civic affairs.
</p><p>
Paul further said: "Love doth not behave itself unseemly" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/5#5">1 Cor. 13:5</a>).
</p><p>
President McKay said it in a few words some time ago: "We are here in mortality to develop
the power of self-mastery." Every single day we have opportunity to practice this art of
self-mastery.
</p><p>
Again Paul said, "Love seeketh not her own" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/5#5">1 Cor. 13:5</a>). The Savior taught by his own
example, to lose ourselves in the service of others. Our beloved prophet said on his ninetieth
birthday: "You may travel the world over but you will not find happiness or contentment until
you lose yourself in the service of mankind." This, of course, would mean sacrifice to God
and our neighbor.
</p><p>
Continuing, Paul said: "Love is not easily provoked. Love thinketh no evil. Love rejoiceth not
in iniquity, but in the truth" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/5-6#5">1 Cor. 13:5-6</a>).
Paul, we see, had a depth of understanding
regarding this great principle of love and the blessings to be attained by those who would
honor and recognize and put into effect in their lives these two commandments, for he said:
"Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things
which God hath prepared for them that love him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/9#9">1 Cor. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
As I tour missions or come into your stakes each week, I have a great hope for the future
because of the many just plain, good people who are applying all the principles of love in
their lives. I say to you, God bless you.
</p><p>
The English statesman, William Gladstone, said: "We look forward to the time when the
power of love will replace the love of power; then will our world know the blessing of
peace." What a difference the placing of words makes. The love of power or the power of
love&mdash;worlds apart!
</p><p>
It is essential to love God, love his Son Jesus Christ and love our neighbor as ourselves.
</p><p>
We are living in a world of automation. Machines seem to be taking over all our jobs. Edwin
Markham, an American poet, had a great idea that is worth repeating: "The way things are
going, we had better learn to do things machines can't do. Love each other, for instance."
</p><p>
Throughout his ministry, the Master kept repeating the importance of love on many occasions.
He said: "A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another; as I have loved
you, that ye also love one another.
</p><p>
"By this shall all men know that are my disciples, if ye have love one to another"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/34-35#34">John 13:34-35</a>).
</p><p>
Do you think a teacher who drove some twenty miles in a battered old car whenever there
was a meeting to pick up just one little girl who lived in a remote area of the stake had a love
of God for her fellow men? I doubt that anyone really knew what she was doing. I just
happened to hear about it.
</p><p>
Oh, may God give us the faith and the desire to put this commandment of
the Lord into effect. ". . . love one another; as I have loved you, that ye shall also love one
another" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/24#24">John 13:24</a>).
Then the world may know that we are true disciples of the Lord Jesus
Christ. God give us the faith, the courage, the determination to make application of these two
great commandments in our lives each day, I humbly  pray in the name of the Lord Jesus
Christ, our Savior. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
