<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Anniversaries in Scandinavia</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1950, pp. 34-38</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I confess, my brethren and sisters, that the call to occupy this position this afternoon is
somewhat unexpected. I am to give the Church of the Air sermon next Sunday morning. It
was intimated that because of that appointment I would not be asked to speak from this stand.
So I have no special message in my heart. I suppose I'll have to depend upon the Lord. That
is good practice for Latter-day Saints
</p><p>
I am always happy to bear my testimony to my brethren and sisters that this is the gospel of
the Lord Jesus Christ. I rejoice in it; I know it to be true. The truth of it has lightened my life
and has given happiness to me and to my family. That I can say always to my brethren and
my sisters.
</p><p>
YEAR OF ANNIVERSARIES
</p><p>
This has been a year of anniversaries. A short time ago, within the last few weeks, the
President of the Church went to Hawaii to celebrate the coming of the gospel to those islands
one hundred years ago. You have read of what happened there. He mentioned it briefly
himself this morning in his address.
</p><p>
It is also a hundred years ago since the gospel was brought to the foreign-speaking lands of
Europe. Up to that time we had only once attempted to preach the gospel in foreign tongues,
namely in the South Sea Islands. But a hundred years ago the missionaries sent out by the
First Presidency of that day entered the Scandinavian and other countries of Europe and bore
witness of the restoration of the gospel of our Lord, Jesus Christ. They made notable progress
at that time, a progress which has resulted in a large influx of men and women, faithful men
and women, to the valleys of the mountains here.
</p><p>
SCANDINAVIAN CELEBRATION
</p><p>
It was my privilege to be sent to Scandinavia a few months ago to take part in the celebration
which the Saints of those countries were holding and enjoying, because of the great
anniversary. I visited the three Scandinavian countries. I was given the privilege primarily, I
suppose, because I am able to speak a little of the tongues of those countries. I visited
Denmark, Sweden, and Norway, in addition to stopping briefly in England. I came back
feeling thrilled with the manner in which the gospel had developed and spread from the
humble beginnings of a hundred years ago in those countries. You know, of course, that here
in these valleys, among the stakes and wards of Zion, the blood of those countries through
intermarriage has spread until a large proportion of our people here carry some of that blood.
</p><p>
The brethren and sisters of the Scandinavian countries had planned large celebrations. I was
able to attend fully the ones in Stockholm, Sweden, and in Oslo, Norway. They were
carefully laid out after the pattern that had been planned for our celebration here at home and
were splendidly rendered, fully as well as the celebration here at home. I missed the
beginning of the celebration in Denmark because of my hurried call and trip, but later on I
met with the Danes and enjoyed their company and partook of their spirit and learned of the
excellence of their celebration.
</p><p>
GOSPEL CHANGES MEN
</p><p>
It was interesting to me to note how the gospel changes the very nature of men and women,
and how faithful and devoted men and women may become to the cause of truth once it sinks
into their hearts.
</p><p>
Norway is a long country, nearly a thousand miles long. Up in the icy north, we have two or
three branches, one very recently established, and I was pleased to find in Oslo, which is
nearly at the south end of the country, people who had come from the far north to celebrate
and to thank the Lord for the coming of the gospel to their land. The same happened in
Sweden: also in Denmark, which is a small country. All had a very large representation of
their Church members in attendance at the celebrations. There was a spirit of
faith and devotion like that we have here today.  Many people had traveled hundreds of miles
to sit by one another in meetings like this and to listen to discourses on the simple principles
of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
It was interesting to note, also, how men grow and develop under the influence of the gospel
spirit. Let a very humble man be touched by the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, and he
becomes transformed. He is no more the same man, no longer the same person. He has
changed completely. I am reminded of the statement of the Prophet Joseph Smith at one time,
when talking about the children of Abraham; he said that any person who accepts the gospel
of Jesus Christ becomes of the seed of Abraham. A subtle change occurs in the very physical
system of the man, which makes him indeed one who belongs to the family of Abraham, the
family of the faithful. This notable change I observed a good many times this trip to
Scandinavia this summer, that men are transformed for the better, their powers multiplied,
their vision increased, their understanding and comprehension brought out in new forms so
much more vigorous because of the gospel which they have received, because of the truths of
the gospel. I am happy to bear this record to my brethren and sisters at this conference.
</p><p>
GREETINGS FROM EUROPEAN SAINTS
</p><p>
I am very happy also to bring you the greetings of the people, our brethren and sisters of the
covenant, of the faraway missions in Europe. They send their greetings to; you and their
blessings also, and their blessings are quite worth while for they come from common sources.
They love you, they watch you; they follow you: they try to emulate and to imitate that which
you do here.
</p><p>
MEETING IN OSLO
</p><p>
Some years ago, I have forgotten just how many, I had the privilege to go to Oslo, the capital
of Norway, with President David O. McKay and Elder Reed Smoot. The three of us came
into the city rather late in the afternoon. I think two of us at least were unannounced. Perhaps
Brother McKay was announced, the president then of the European Mission, I am not sure
about that. But we made our way at once to the meeting place of the Latter day Saints. I shall
never forget that meeting. We were not expected by the members present. The meeting as
composed of the people, the men and women, who had been called to labor as missionaries in
the city of Oslo. It was a report meeting. One after another the people, young and old, got up
and gave a report of what they had done. I recall one elderly lady who said that she hesitated
to make her report; for it was such a poor report. She had only had time during the last
month to bring the gospel to two hundred different homes. I thrilled as I
thought of the faith of that woman, the strength of her faith; and how many of us fail to
appreciate what we have received as she did appreciate it. Many go by day after day, having
received the great gift of the eternal gospel, the greatest of all gifts, but forgetting to pay back
to the Lord as he would like us to do a part of our time and strength and power to assist in
the advancement of the great kingdom of God here upon this earth. I am sure that good sister
received the gift of joy from her labors.
</p><p>
There is much I might tell you even after a brief trip to Scandinavia this summer about the
conditions of the people. They are faithful Latter-day Saints, second to none in the wards of
Zion. I just touched old London for a few days and found it the same wonderful old London,
in the same condition as of the past. The people there, our people, are reported to be faithful
and true to their covenants with the Lord, through their baptism into the Church.
</p><p>
WORLDWIDE MESSAGE
</p><p>
I would like to say, before I close this brief report, that I was greatly thrilled this morning as
I heard Brother Cowley give his report, and added to that we have heard from Brother
Kirkham a few moments ago. The message of the Church is not to the valleys of the
mountains alone. It is not to be confined in these valleys surrounded by these everlasting hills.
We have a worldwide message. Our army of missionaries, five thousand eight hundred strong
as was reported this morning, implies our belief in the spread of the gospel over the whole
earth. The Lord has said himself that every ear shall hear the gospel in these latter days
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/2#2">D&amp;C 1:2</a>). That
means not only the ears of the people who are here in this beautiful, blessed land of America,
but far beyond over the seas, on the islands, everywhere, the gospel has been preached and
must continue to be taught. And we're doing this sacred work to the best of our ability. As
we do that and continue to do it, the Lord will bless us and magnify us and make us powerful
and strong, acceptable to him. Let us never forget the worldwide nature of our obligations
before the' Lord. Our missionary system must be cherished and be kept alive constantly and
forever, until that last great day comes and the Lord says that the work is done.
</p><p>
WE HAVE THE TRUTH
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, I bear you again my testimony that I know this to be the gospel of
Jesus Christ. It is the truth. As Brigham Young used to say, "Men ask me what the gospel of
Jesus Christ is, what name does it bear? And I say to you, its name might well be truth." We
and the Church, if we are faithful, as we have been taught this morning by the President, the
prophet of the Lord, shall conquer. We cannot fail. Truth is never defeated. It blesses all who
possess it. We have the truth. If we will keep the truth and if we cherish it
and practice it in our lives, then victory over error will be ours from the smallest household in
Zion to the farthest outpost of Zion, wherever that may be. Thus through the restoration of
the gospel in our day, the whole world shall be blessed.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us and fill us with an understanding of this mighty work laid out for us in
these latter days and make us able to do the Lord's work, which we can do if we are faithful,
I pray in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
