<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Lowliness of Jesus Christ</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 38-40</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters: It is with deep humility that I rise this morning to say something to
you.  As always, I trust that you will add your prayers to mine that what I say may be of
some value to us.  Without the help of the Lord we stand but weak mortals, not able to do
too much to the advancement of his cause.
</p><p>
I would like to begin by expressing my gratitude to our Heavenly Father for the devotion, the
loyalty, and the great service of thousands of our Latter-day Saints.  There is no sacrifice
which they will not make.  They stand as ready to do the bidding of the spirit as manifested
through the Presiding Authorities of the Church as did the early Saints even in the time of the
Savior and thereafter, and the early Saints in the beginning and the opening of this the Last
Dispensation of the Fulness of Times.  I am grateful to you for that. I appreciate that without
that loyalty and that devotion the work of the Lord would drag, and we should not do the
things that he desires that we should do.  Thank you for your devotion, your loyalty, your
service.
</p><p>
It is a trite expression that we live in an age of materialism, a materialism which has
enthroned worldly things and in a materialism that has cast a shadow even over our
spirituality.  As I see it, one of the great reasons for this is the shadow which we have cast
over Jesus as the Christ.  Even some of our great sectarian churches, like ourselves sons of
our Heavenly Father, are forsaking him. They are making of Christ, as I have often said, a
great teacher, a great philosopher, a great character, where they do not question that, but they
deny to him that he was and is the Christ.
</p><p>
Of all of the innumerable testimonies regarding his personality, I should like to call your
attention only to two or three. The first is the great prayer which he offered on the night
before his crucifixion, after they had left the chamber and gone out to the Mount of Olives,
that great prayer: "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and
Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
And the testimony of Peter before the
Sanhedrin, when challenged as to the name by which he had performed the miracle at the
Gate Beautiful of the temple, he replied: ". . . the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth . . . for
there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/10,12#10">Acts 4:10,12</a>).
</p><p>
And that testimony embodied in that great declaration of the Father himself
to Moses, because it is the epitome, the summary of the gospel of Jesus Christ:  "For behold
this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
There has been an apostasy from that knowledge of the Christ.  You know, the more I
contemplate the life of the Savior, the more I am impressed, the more I come to value his
lowliness, born in the home of a lowly carpenter, not in the halls of the great, not in the
palaces of national rulers, but with royal blood in his mortal veins.  I am impressed with the
observation which he made to a man who came seeking to follow him, to go with him, and
he said to the man, "The foxes have holes, and the birds of the air have nests; but the Son of
man hath not where to lay his head"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/8/20#20">Matt. 8:20</a>).
</p><p>
He was indifferent, so indifferent to the worldly things.  His mind was fixed quite otherwise. 
The very temptation that came to him from Satan, when Satan offered him all the kingdoms of
the world if he would merely bow down and worship him, offered him all the power that
could be bestowed through human hands; but he cast that aside
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/8-10#8">Matt. 4:8-10</a>).
</p><p>
I recall how after he fed the multitude of five thousand, they would have taken him and made
him king (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/6/15#15">John 6:15</a>),
but he thrust that aside also.  Worldly power had no allurement. Worldly power
was not for him.
</p><p>
I recall that as he stood before Pilate, Pilate's first question was political. "Art thou the King
of the Jews?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/27/11#11">Matt. 27:11</a>).
And finally he said to Pilate, who six times tried to get the
Jews to release Jesus&mdash;he finally said to Pilate, "My kingdom is not of this world," and that his
mission was to establish truth, and then that poor, perplexed Pilate queried, "What is truth?"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/36-38#36">John 18:36-38</a>).
</p><p>
I have in mind the things which He did, the miracles which he performed. There were only
three occasions, I believe, when he undertook specifically to provide food for the multitude or
for anyone.  The first was the feeding of the five thousand on the mount
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/15-21#15">Matt. 14:15-21</a>),
the second was the feeding of the four thousand on the plain
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/32-38#32">Matt. 15:32-38</a>),
and the third was that beautiful incident on the
Lake of Galilee after he was resurrected when, as the fishermen, the Apostles who had turned
again to fishing, drew near the shore with their nets empty, he, the Resurrected Christ, stood
on the shore with coals of fire and fish and bread prepared for eating
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/9#9">John 21:9</a>).
</p><p>
I recall but one instance where in fact he furnished money, and I am not sure of another
incident somewhat similar to it. I refer to the time when he lacked money for taxes, and he
sent Peter down to secure it from the mouth of a fish
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/24-27#24">Matt. 17:24-27</a>).
He was not providing money to those
with whom he worked.  The other incident where money was involved directly for him, was
when he was asked if taxes should be paid to Caesar, and he, taking a coin and showing the
image thereon, said, "Render therefore unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's; and unto
God the things that are God's"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/21#21">Matt. 22:21</a>).
</p><p>
As to wealth: You will remember how the rich young ruler came to him and asked what he
should do.  The Savior told him to obey the commandments. He said, "Master, all these have
I observed from my youth." Then said the Master, "Sell that thou hast, and give to the poor .
. . and follow me." And the rich young man turned away (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/16-22#16">Matt. 19:16-22</a>). He wanted all
of the spiritual blessings which God could bestow, but at the same time he wanted to retain
his wealth.
</p><p>
John's disciples came questioning.
</p><p>
"Now when John had heard in the prison the works of Christ, he sent two of his disciples,<br />
"And said unto him, Art thou he that should come, or do we look for another?<br />
"Jesus answered and said unto them, Go and shew John again those things which ye do hear
and see:<br />
"The blind receive their sight, and the lame walk, the lepers are cleansed, and the deaf hear,
the dead are raised up, and the poor have the gospel preached to them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/2-5#2">Matt. 11:2-5</a>).
</p><p>
That is the work of the Savior.
</p><p>
On another occasion, he said unto another, "Follow me," but the other said, "Lord, suffer me
first to go and bury my father. Jesus said unto him, Let the dead bury their dead: but go
thou and preach the kingdom of God" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/59-60#59">Luke 9:59-60</a>).
</p><p>
"And another also said, Lord, I will follow thee; but let me first go bid them farewell, which
are at home at my house.
</p><p>
"And Jesus said unto him, No man, having put his hand to the plough, and looking back, is fit
for the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/61-62#61">Luke 9:61-62</a>).
</p><p>
Much more along this line might be said, but I want to call your attention to his formula, the
principle which guided him, and how beautiful it is, and how it lets all of us who are poor
come to him, and how it promises to us his spirit.  He said in the closing of the incident that
was connected with the coming of the disciples, "Come unto me, all ye that labour and are
heavy laden, and I will give you rest"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/28#28">Matt. 11:28</a>).
</p><p>
I thank the Relief Society for their song.
</p><p>
"Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall
find rest unto your souls.<br />
"For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/29-30#29">Matt. 11:29-30</a>).
</p><p>
His gospel can be lived, can be enjoyed by the poorest of us; the poorest of us may enjoy the
blessings of the gospel, the blessings of the priesthood which accompany it. We need neither
worldly position nor wealth in order to enjoy all that he has to give.  His is the salvation and
exaltation if we follow him, of all of us. There is nothing requiring more than a broken heart
and a contrite spirit, and all that flows therefrom.
</p><p>
May the Lord give us the power so to live that we may have the blessings which he has
promised; may he give us, to each of us, the broken heart and the contrite spirit
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/20#20">3 Ne. 9:20</a>); may we turn
to Jesus the Christ, the Author of our salvation, our Elder Brother; may we worship him in
spirit and in truth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/23#23">John 4:23</a>);
may we approach our Heavenly Father through him, that his blessings may
be ours, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
