<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">With Faith for the Future</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1950, pp. 138-142</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am sure that no one knows as well as I know how much I need help as I face this
congregation here and those who may be listening and looking on the air, and I earnestly
hope that I may have it.
</p><p>
I have jotted down from time to time mentally or actually, these past three days, things that I
think it might have been well for me to have said at this conference, and I have repeatedly
scratched them out as others have said them. They make a rather long list.
</p><p>
I heard some weeks ago a set of figures presented by Brother A. Z. Richards, which I felt
deserved wider circulation as a point of historical perspective. I should like to extract a few of
these figures from a longer list: 
</p><p>
FIGURES QUOTED
</p><p>
When Joseph Smith was born, the population of the United States was about one-half the
present population of California
</p><p>
In 1820, the population of the entire United States was about the population of New York
City today.
</p><p>
In 1830, when the Church was organized, New York City was about one-third larger than
Salt Lake City is today.
</p><p>
In 1837, when our missionaries first went to Great Britain, New York City was smaller than
Denver is today.
</p><p>
In 1847, there were only two United States cities larger than Salt Lake City today; they were
New York and Manhattan, both of which are now part of the present greater New York.
</p><p>
When Martin Harris went to New York with the Book of Mormon characters, New York City
was only slightly larger than Salt Lake City is today.
</p><p>
Before Nauvoo was abandoned by our people, Washington, D. C., was about the same size as
Nauvoo, but Nauvoo had been only three or four years in the making while Washington, D.
C. had been designated as the seat of national government more than a half-century before
that time.
</p><p>
I think these latter figures, and others which might be presented here, bring to us with some
considerable force the kind of people that our pioneer forefathers were&mdash;people of great
courage and conviction. I think we can see from these figures, too, something of the basis of
the concern of some of their neighbors&mdash;with all of the social, religious, political, and
economic implications inherent in growth of this people, and the vigor and purpose they
displayed in rising repeatedly from their poverty.
</p><p>
Two more figures I think may be of interest to you: In 1850 the population of Utah has been
recorded in official records as being about 11,380. Three years later our people started
building the magnificent temple which now stands to the east of us.
</p><p>
MEN OF COURAGE AND FAITH
</p><p>
In 1860, the population of this state has been recorded as being about 40,273. Three years
later than that they began to build the Tabernacle in which we meet today, which, when it
was projected, probably would have seated about one out of every five people in the entire
state. If we were to do likewise today, proportionately, we should have to project ourselves to
the building of an auditorium that would seat considerably more than a hundred thousand
people.
</p><p>
Men of courage, men of faith in the future in spite of all the uncertainties and the drivings
and the depredations that they experienced, they began again and again, and rose from their
poverty again and again, to produce what we see before us and what we are the beneficiaries
of. These walls and these buildings on Temple Square are part of the evidence of their
purpose and their faith, and I hope and earnestly believe that something of their spirit still
lingers here.
</p><p>
UNCERTAINTIES TODAY
</p><p>
Now times have changed, but human nature hasn't changed very much. We face other
uncertainties today, and sympathy and appeals for faith and prayers and for encouragement to
our young people who face the uncertainties of our generation have been expressed repeatedly
in this conference. I should like to add my appeal for faith, for prayers, and for understanding
for these young people who live in confusion and suspense, and who wonder when they are
going to be relieved of all this uncertainty, when they can settle down, what they can count
on for the future, whether to pursue their education and their preparations for professions or
to give it all up.
</p><p>
What can they count on? Well, I think it was Heber C. Kimball or one of his associates who
said that he had started all over again seven different times and left his home and all behind
him. I hope this generation will not be faced with any such extremities, but I do know that we
must have faith in the future, and when we see what our forefathers did with what they had,
and the conditions under which they did it, I feel sure that we can surmise
something of what might be expected of us, and of what might be accomplished by us, in
faith, in that unity of which President Clark so often speaks, and in righteous purpose. There
is much expected of us with what we have, compared with what our pioneer fathers did with
what was theirs.
</p><p>
YEAR OF ANNIVERSARIES
</p><p>
They did some other things also: It has been mentioned that this is a year of anniversaries.
For one thing, it is the centennial of the University of Deseret, now the University of Utah.
The second act of the territorial legislature, as I recall, was the founding of this educational
institution. This month we also observe the seventy-fifth anniversary of the founding of
Brigham Young University. Did the founders of these institutions have their eyes on the
future? They believed in seeking knowledge out of the best books. They believed that "the
glory of God is intelligence" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>),
and "that whatever principle of intelligence we attain to in this
life, it will rise with us in the resurrection"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/18#18">D&amp;C 130:18</a>). And they established
institutions of learning wherever they went. The pursuit of learning was an important part of
their lives.
</p><p>
ACCEPTANCE OF TRUTH
</p><p>
I am aware today, not only of those who are facing uncertainties in the armed forces, to
whom our hearts and prayers go out, but of those who are pursuing knowledge in institutions
of learning, who sometimes run into areas of confusion and seeming conflict in their pursuits.
I am grateful to belong to a Church that has committed itself to the acceptance of all truth,
that encourages its people to pursue truth and to push farther and farther the frontiers of
human knowledge. And I am grateful also (and I have said this before) that the things I don't
understand don't destroy my faith in the things that I do understand.
</p><p>
There is so much that men don't know that we can afford to wait for all the answers where
there seem to be areas of conflict and confusion in the pursuit of knowledge.
</p><p>
OBSERVATIONS AT MT. PALOMAR
</p><p>
I was reading recently an article on the new telescopes lately put into service on Mount
Palomar, California&mdash;the Schmidt telescope, a smaller one of rather radical design with
forty-eight-inch lens and the much larger one with a 200-inch lens. Since early 1949 so says
the writer, the smaller of these two telescopes has provided new clues on the creation of the
universe," "has already revealed hundreds of thousands of island universes and millions of
stars . . . which had never been seen before," and can see and photograph
"clear, undistorted distances of three hundred million light years away or about two thousand
billion-billion miles!" And the larger telescope penetrates about a billion light years away!
"What is man that thou art mindful of him!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/4#4">Ps. 8:4</a>).
</p><p>
And shall we say that these millions of stars that have just been "seen" within recent months
did not exist before we could see them with the aid of these more acute instruments? I think
we should ask ourselves some of the questions that were asked of Job by the Voice out of the
whirlwind, and see how many we can answer when we run into some of these areas of
seeming conflict. If we were to sit down and list those things which have been discovered
even in our own generation, which were not before known, and then think of infinity and of
all that is not yet known by man, we should be humble indeed in our small knowledge, even
the most learned among us.
</p><p>
CLING TO ETERNAL VERITIES
</p><p>
I should like to say to our young people: Keep your lives well-balanced. Pursuing any narrow
field of knowledge or activity to the exclusion of all others will reach a point of diminishing
returns. Give some of your time to the things of the spirit, and always reserve some of your
means to the purposes of your Father in heaven. Look broadly as well as intently, and keep
your lives well-balanced in your pursuits.
</p><p>
I would say today to those who are in the classroom, to farmers in the field, to the laborers in
factories, to men pursuing professions, to young men in military service, to all of us in life,
whatever the discouragements, whatever the seeming areas of conflict and confusion, whatever
the infinite area of things we don't understand, cling to these eternal verities always: that God
lives, that men were made in his image, that life is purposeful, that men are immortal. Cling
to the commandments and give observance to them and to the knowledge that it is our
Father's plan and purpose to bring immortality and eternal life to man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>). If we will cling to
these eternal verities in simplicity and truth and keep our lives well balanced in all our
pursuits, we shall reach a glorious end, with ever-growing knowledge. By all means seek
knowledge out of the best books (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>),
in all fields of thought and learning that are constructive,
and, if possible, it would be wonderful to push the frontiers of knowledge beyond where they
are now. But always keep lives well balanced and reserve some time for the things of the
spirit.
</p><p>
PURSUE PURPOSES OF LIFE
</p><p>
Now as to this discouragement and confusion: I think the enemy of men's souls wouldn't care
too much what means he used to render our lives ineffective, just so long as he did render
them ineffective. I don't think he would care too much whether it was by
indolence or indifference or by withholding willing work, or by doubt, or by discouragement,
or by uncertainty&mdash;so long as he could render us ineffective, it would please him. And it
must be our purpose to see that we pursue our purposes regardless of the things we don&rsquo;t
know which we hope sometime to know. It must be our purpose to pursue with all earnestness
every righteous purpose.
</p><p>
No matter how much we may be discouraged or how often we are set back, we must begin
again and again, if necessary, and earnestly pursue the purposes of life, full of faith for the
future. Enduring to the end is exceedingly important. Pursuing the opportunities and the duties
of every day is exceedingly important, and repenting while there is still time to repent is also
exceedingly important.
</p><p>
PRAYER FOR YOUTH
</p><p>
I hope that we may set our lives in order, and that our Father will bless these young people of
ours, whether they be called to the service of their country or whatever in righteousness they
may be called upon to do, and give them strength and faith, and let them be of good courage,
and help them to keep their lives well-balanced and always to keep their feet firmly on solid
rock. May he bless all of us with all our problems, with our families, with our professions
with our work, and with all that is ours to undertake in life.
</p><p>
I wish to express to you the conviction in my soul as to the reality of those things which have
been spoken of here in this conference, that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, that the gospel
has been restored, that it has within it the answers to the problems that beset this generation,
and the only answers to permanent peace. May we pursue it in unity and with righteous
purpose, ever keeping the commandments and bringing our young people with us, full of
faith, understanding, and courage. I pray in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
