<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">To Help Every Member Be a Missionary</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bernard P. Brockbank</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bernard p. Brockbank, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 88-91</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren in the priesthood: Isn't it marvelous to hear the great vision of a great Prophet? My,
how he sees the great scope of the work to be done on this earth by the priesthood holders!
Brethren, I hope you sense deeply in your hearts the power and the responsibility that you
have.
</p><p>
As President McKay opened the conference yesterday, he made this statement: "A proper
conception [of the sacredness of the individual] would change the attitude of the world to the
benefit and happiness of all human beings." "A proper conception of the sacredness of the
individual"&mdash;in the image and likeness of Deity.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul tells us of the holiness and sacredness of the individual when he said,
"Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
</p><p>
"If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy,
which temple ye are" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Paul also said to the Corinthian Saints, ". . . know ye not that your body is the temple of the
Holy Ghost which is in you, which ye have of God, and ye are not your own?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/6/19#19">1 Cor. 6:19</a>).
</p><p>
We were created by God in his likeness and image (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26#26">Gen. 1:26</a>), and we should not stand alone, but we
should stay close with even the loyalty and love of a child to our Creator and Heavenly
Father. The creator is not without obligation to that which he created, and we who hold the
priesthood of God have a great, important responsibility to our Lord and to his children. Only
through priesthood holders, such as you, can God's children receive baptism by water and the
gift of the Holy Ghost. Both are essential, according to Jesus Christ, for entrance back into
the kingdom of heaven. And, of course, we know that many other great blessings are attached
to the priesthood.
</p><p>
We are called to help build the Church and kingdom of God on this earth. We who hold the
priesthood literally need to be our brother's keeper (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/9#9">Gen. 4:9</a>). The day in which we live is the
dispensation of the fullness of times. "The dispensations of the fulness of times is made up of
all the dispensations that ever have been given since the world began, until this time." (Letter
by David W. Patten, <i>Documentary History of the Church</i>, Vol. 6, p. 220.)
</p><p>
<b>Magnitude of the charge</b>
</p><p>
In 1830, near the opening of this dispensation, there were approximately a billion people on
the earth; 137 years later, today, over three and a half billion; by 1970, four billion; and it is
predicted, by men who know what they are talking about, that by the turn of the century,
2000 A.D., there will be seven billion of God's children upon this earth.
</p><p>
It is a great and glorious period of time for the righteous and an era when the unrighteous
will also prosper.
</p><p>
The President also declared in his opening message at this conference that this "is a glorious
age in which to live, but no thinking man will doubt that this age is fraught with limitless
perils, as well as with untold possibilities."
</p><p>
<b>To "teach all nations"</b>
</p><p>
After the death and resurrection of Jesus Christ, prior to his departure from this earth and his
return to the kingdom of heaven, he gave important instructions to all those who would
represent him and participate in building his Church and kingdom on this earth. And this was
repeated twice by the Prophet in the message just delivered by his son Robert. According to
the Gospel of Matthew, the closing words of the Savior just prior to his ascension to his
Father were: "Go ye therefore, and teach all nations . . .
</p><p>
"Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you: and, lo, I am with
you alway, even unto the end of the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>). That includes us; it includes the
priesthood holders here assembled. We are to teach the gospel and commandments of Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
Similar statements were made by the Savior according to the Gospel of Mark and the Gospel
of Luke.
</p><p>
The Apostle John in giving the closing words of the Savior showed a rather interesting and
beautiful scene of the Savior and Peter, the man he was to leave in charge of his Church. He
asked Peter, "Lovest thou me?" three times. And the great answer from the great Teacher the
Lord and Savior, was: "Feed my lambs; feed my sheep" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/15-17#15">John 21:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Men who hold the priesthood are the teachers</b>
</p><p>
Priesthood holders, do you love the Lord? Do you have any hungry lambs and sheep in your
area&mdash;friends and neighbors hungry for God's righteousness and the gospel plan of
salvation&mdash;good, honest people waiting for the voice of a righteous teacher who speaks as one having
authority (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/29#29">Matt. 7:29</a>), one with the priesthood and authority from God?
</p><p>
Jesus said, "My sheep hear my voice" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/27#27">John 10:27</a>). The voice to mortal man must come
from an authorized teacher and servant of the Lord.
</p><p>
Our assignment, brethren, with all the Latter-day Saints, is to teach the doctrines, ordinances,
and commandments of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I repeat what Jesus said, "Teaching . . . whatsoever I have commanded you: and, lo, I am
with you alway, even unto the end of the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/20#20">Matt. 28:20</a>).
</p><p>
We are to teach every nation, kindred, tongue, and people. The Lord said to the Prophet
Joseph Smith, when there were only one billion of his children on this earth, that the field was
white and ready to harvest (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/4#4">D&amp;C 4:4</a>).
</p><p>
Today, with over three and a half billion people on this earth, the task and responsibility of
harvesting is great and challenging. The field today is still white and ready to harvest.
Millions of honest in heart are waiting to be taught.
</p><p>
Brethren, have we taught the gospel of Jesus Christ to two percent of God's children living on
this earth today? Two percent would be more than seventy million people. When and how are
we going to teach every nation, kindred, tongue, and people?
</p><p>
<b>"Every member a missionary"</b>
</p><p>
The answer has been given by a Prophet of God. Every member of The Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints should be a missionary. Each member should bring one or more of
his neighbors and friends into the Church each year. Each member must increase his faith and
turn up his divine luster and candle power and let his light so shine before men that they may
see his good works, and glorify their Father which is in heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Unity of all missionaries</b>
</p><p>
We will need greater unity between full-time missionaries, stake missionaries, and the Saints
in order to reach and teach additional millions. We need to supply the helps necessary so that
over a million Saints can help the missionary work.
</p><p>
The Lord said, ". . . by their fruits ye shall know them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/20#20">Matt. 7:20</a>). The fruits of the
Church, of the gospel, and of the lives of the Saints need to be seen by the world.
</p><p>
<b>The New York World's Fair</b>
</p><p>
We have learned a great many things from the success of the Mormon Pavilion at the New
York World's Fair. We have learned that with finely created religious art, oil paintings, and
sculptured pieces, movies and backlighted transparencies, we can arrest the interest and excite
the imagination of nonmembers of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>The power of personal testimony</b>
</p><p>
But we have also learned something even more important: that the most valuable tool we have
in delivering the message of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ is the testimony of the
priesthood and the missionary. We have discovered that when one of our missionaries stands
in front of a religious painting and bears his testimony to the validity of its spiritual message,
that same oil painting suddenly becomes a powerful visual evidence for truth that is deeply
etched on the minds of the investigators. They go away remembering both what they heard
and what they saw, and the honest in heart have had a spiritual experience.
</p><p>
<b>Blending of testimony and message</b>
</p><p>
So it is that we now stand at this point of bright discovery. We must blend the testimony of
the missionary with vital and powerful visual messages; we must accelerate our effectiveness
in giving outsiders something they can both see and hear.
</p><p>
Today we must find ways to reach and teach millions and even billions by having them come
to centers where the teachings and fruits of the gospel of salvation and God's plan of life are
on exhibit and where the teacher filled with faith, love, and the Holy Ghost can touch their
hearts. Millions of the Saints can participate.
</p><p>
Under the direction of the First Presidency and the Council of the Twelve, we are creating
and setting up visitors' centers with visual aids and missionaries to teach and reach millions.
</p><p>
<b>Center at Temple Square</b>
</p><p>
The new visitors' center right here on Temple Square, just to the north of this building, will
be completed some time early next year. It will hold some of the great messages of the
latter-day restoration. These will be in the form of specially created artifacts. The great
Thorvaldsen statue that was also shown in the Mormon Pavilion at the New York World's
Fair now stands on the second floor and has as a background a 12,000 square-foot mural of
the firmament with the celestial bodies painted. There is also a 150-foot painted mural
showing outstanding scenes on the life and teachings and examples of Christ. There are other
great paintings of Christ ordaining the Twelve Apostles and Joseph Smith receiving the
Melchizedek Priesthood from Peter, James, and John.
</p><p>
There will also be a First Vision diorama, a replica of the Sacred Grove. The trees will be
duplicated facsimiles made from plaster molds taken right in the grove. Also displayed is a
figure of the 14-year-old Joseph Smith as he kneels in this grove and looks into a light
overhead which is "above the brightness of the sun" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/16#16">JS&mdash;H 1:16</a>), depicting his first
great vision and the first ray of light to this world after a period of darkness, showing that
God lived and that man was literally in his image and likeness.
</p><p>
We'll have a series of paintings, now being created, illustrating the great dispensations of the
Bible, showing Adam and Eve, Noah, Abraham, Moses, and others. Some of these scenes will
depict the great prophecies of the Old Testament, prophecies concerning the birth of Christ;
concerning the apostasy and the restoration of the gospel; concerning the temple of the Lord
being established in the "tops of the mountains" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/2#2">Isa. 2:2</a>).
</p><p>
We'll have a series of rooms that will deal in fine detail with such significant subjects as "the
plan of salvation," the scriptures, the contributions of the Prophet Joseph Smith, Brigham
Young, and the pioneers, the apostasy and reformation, and, certainly, the restoration and all
its great fulfillment of prophecy throughout the ages of man.
</p><p>
And the vision of the Church has swept beyond these works on Temple Square. We have now
completed a great display at the Prophet's birthplace in Sharon, Vermont. Another has just
been installed in Liberty, Missouri.
</p><p>
<b>Centers at other places</b>
</p><p>
We are now working on the possibility of a visitors' center at each of the temples throughout
the Church.
</p><p>
We are working to establish these visitors' centers with visual aids similar to those used at the
New York World's Fair and on Temple Square in Salt Lake City but with the exhibits fitting
in with the particular area.
</p><p>
We've had over 75 requests from various church groups for help in preparing displays this
fall. Hundreds of fairs, both county and state, have asked for visual aids so that the local
members of the Church can deliver the gospel message and bring people to an understanding
of the beautiful doctrines of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>Aids to missionary efforts</b>
</p><p>
In conjunction with the missionary committee, the church information committee is now
printing a series of large-sized posters that will tell in sequence the message of the teachings
and doctrines of Christ, the falling away, and the restoration of the gospel. The posters will be
available soon. They will be a great help in many areas.
</p><p>
New paintings are being painted by talented artists, depicting a wealth of scenes portraying
with spirituality and inspiration the story of the gospel and attempting to relate to individuals
their needs to repent of their sins and come unto Christ.
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon is "to the convincing of the Jew and Gentile that Jesus is the Christ, the
Eternal God, manifesting himself unto all nations" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>), and displays
of the Book of Mormon are being set up to bring this book and record closer to the people. It
would be wise for every priesthood holder to have several copies of the Book of Mormon for
missionary use with his friends and neighbors.
</p><p>
When the visitors' centers and posters are ready, the members with the missionaries can bring
their friends and neighbors to see the exhibits. Other exhibits will be set up in homes and
churches and in many areas for the use of the members. New motion pictures will be made.
Millions have seen the motion picture, <i>Man's Search for Happiness</i>, and it has touched the
hearts of many that had little or no concept of preexistence and life after death.
</p><p>
The members are anxious, we discover throughout the world, to follow the Prophet's counsel
to do missionary work among their friends and neighbors, but they need the help of the great
Christian teaching exhibits.
</p><p>
This, brethren, is the greatest of all dispensations in which to do missionary work. Many
millions are looking for the gospel of Jesus Christ as given in the God-inspired scriptures and
by the Savior. Millions today would like to know, hear, and follow a prophet of God, and to
know that there are twelve living, ordained apostles of the Lord on this earth.
</p><p>
May we do the will of the Lord and his prophets, under their inspiration and revelation, I pray
in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
