<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Stephen L Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Stephen L Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 172-178</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It seemed to me that I could feel the strength of your testimonies in that glorious song, and
that helps to fortify me for my attempt to fill this, my first assignment in my present capacity,
to address the General Priesthood meeting of the Conference.
</p><p>
I feel deeply humble in this undertaking, and I sincerely ask for the Spirit of the Lord to
attend me and for your cooperation and faith and prayers.
</p><p>
I understand that it is appropriate and desirable at this meeting to bring before the Priesthood,
which includes our presiding officers in stakes and wards and missions, some items which
need attention. So with your indulgence and President McKay's permission, I will bring
before you a few items first affecting our missionary service, in the hope that their mention
here may be helpful to the carrying forward of our missionary procedure.
</p><p>
These items are not necessarily related.
</p><p>
INTERRUPTIONS TO MISSIONARY WORK
</p><p>
We would appreciate it, and we speak for the mission presidents, if you would discourage
parents, other relatives and friends, visiting missionaries in the missions. We have had a large
number of instances brought to our attention where serious interruption has come to the
missionary work by reason of these visits, some of which have been very protracted. If you
can use your influence and give the information to discourage these visits and ask the parents
and their other friends to let these missionaries pursue the courses which have been arranged
for them, they will contribute very greatly to our work.
</p><p>
We have had numbers of requests for leaves of absence for missionaries to come home to the
funerals of their kinspeople. We appreciate the fact that their hearts are touched on these sad
occasions, but we have learned that very frequently the visit home only serves as an
interruption to the mission, that no considerable good is accomplished, and that the missionary
himself is often disappointed to think that he left the mission field, his companion, and his
assigned work to go home for such funerals.
</p><p>
I am very grateful to note that it has been the disposition of most of our missionaries in the
field to desire to stay with their labors, and they themselves, have, in a number of instances,
discouraged their kinspeople from requesting their return. If you can bring this matter, as
occasion requires, to the attention of the families, it will serve a good purpose in the
continuity of our missionary work.
</p><p>
CALLING OF SEVENTIES
</p><p>
Now we are confronted with some new questions in missionary work on responses to the call
of the seventy to go into the mission field. May I first express for the First Presidency
appreciation and gratitude for the generous response coming to this call. We have on file at
the present time responses from many stakes of the Church, indicating that they will fully
comply with the request, and that their quotas will be met. This is encouraging.
</p><p>
IMPORTANCE OF GOOD HEALTH
</p><p>
There are, however, brethren, in the sending of these older men, some safeguards that should
be considered. First, the question of health. Our mission presidents have advised us that many
of the older men have not been able to endure the rigorous work, the climate in some cases,
and the exactions that are put upon our missionaries. These older missionaries are often asked
to be companions to younger men. You heard this day something of the vigorous work that
they do, the long hours they spend, entailing a good deal of walking and very strenuous
exercise.
</p><p>
It is not possible in many instances to assign older men to the so-called easier jobs. If they are
to make their greatest contribution they must fit into our missionary program, and in order to
do that they must have good health. We have a great sympathy for our mission presidents.
They have many problems, so many, indeed, that a great part of the time their attention must
be given to exceptional cases, so that we ask you brethren as you send these older men to us,
to make careful inquiry into their health. Sometimes our doctors' examinations&mdash;we are
generally grateful for their service&mdash;are not too searching and we find when they get to the
mission field, particularly some of our older brethren, have some weaknesses that deter them,
and sometimes preclude them, from carrying forward their missionary work.
</p><p>
I know that it is difficult to get the older men to come, but we must have them in good
health. There may be a few exceptional cases where older couples with a car can do some
special service in a mission, but generally speaking the seventies must enter into the work
with the same vigor and we hope with full physical equipment to carry forward the mission
program as the younger men.
</p><p>
WELFARE OF FAMILIES
</p><p>
We have discovered, too, in recent months in the coming of these older men, that very
considerable apprehension is feared for the welfare of some of their families. It is reported in
cases that come to us that families are left without adequate support, and we have a few cases
where couples have been recommended with the understanding that they would leave minor
children with relatives or friends and without parental guidance.
</p><p>
President McKay has long taken the position that that is not wisdom to call parents away
from their children, even for this great missionary service, so before both of the parents are
sent, they must always be free from the parental responsibility that goes to minors in the
home. Where the man is sent, care must be exercised to see that his family may have proper
care in his absence. That will entail a discernment on the part of the bishop, and he should
exercise caution and wisdom before recommending a man whose children and family may
suffer too greatly in his absence.
</p><p>
We do not want to take the sacrifice out of missionary work. We know the history of it in the
past, and we know that it does entail, sometimes great deprivations and sacrifices, but we
want to use wisdom in taking men away from their families.
</p><p>
MISSIONARY EXPENSES
</p><p>
Another item&mdash;it is a part of our traditional missionary custom for the family to pay
missionary expense. Exceptions are made. There are friends sometimes who like to contribute.
Sometimes the ward, sometimes the quorum, will contribute. But it is deemed preferable to
have men sent, who, either by themselves, or through their families, can make some
substantial contribution to their missionary labors.
</p><p>
We do not look with favor, because we feel that it lacks in certain material elements in our
missionary work, upon having support come wholly either from the quorum or from the ward,
or from outside sources. It is true that there are many generous people who send funds into
the Church itself, to be helpful to missionaries who need help, and I assure you that it is a
great satisfaction to have at our disposal some limited funds which can help out a missionary
who hasn't quite been able to finish, whose parents have perhaps reached the end of their
financial resources. But in the main it is preferable to send missionaries who can contribute
substantially to their own support.
</p><p>
THE LANGUAGE OF PRAYER
</p><p>
We have discovered in the mission field in particular, and in other places, also a lack of
proper teaching with reference to prayer. I know that I myself have been shocked out in the
mission field as I have heard missionaries called on for prayer who seem to have had no
experience or training whatever in the use of the language of prayer.
</p><p>
I do not know that it is a matter of vital importance, but I think, my brethren, that in the
quorums and in the classes, you would do well, as in the homes also, to teach the language of
prayer&mdash;"Thee and Thou," rather than "you." It always seems disappointing to me to have our
Father in Heaven, our Lord, addressed as "you." It is surprising how much we see of this in
the mission field among the young men who come to serve there. I think you might make
note of it, and avail yourselves of any opportunities that may come in order to teach the
sacred and reverential language of prayer.
</p><p>
SUPPORT FOR DESERET NEWS
</p><p>
That is all that I had for you, my brethren, with reference to the missionary items. I would
like to take a few moments to mention a few other items of general import, and also with
reference to our Priesthood work. I am not going to preach about it, but I know that Brother
Petersen will not object if I say to you that I think that the loyalty of this Priesthood can well
be shown in supporting the official organ of this Church, the Deseret News. I don't think that
we ought to have to appeal for your support in that respect.
</p><p>
We need an organ for the Church, of course we do, and a good one. We have one. Why
should Latter-day Saints forsake that paper and give help to competition? I believe we can
seriously think over that matter. Personally, I love the paper. My grandfather was its first
editor. I am proud of it, and proud of its history. I appeal for your support for it.
</p><p>
APPEAL TO ELDERS
</p><p>
Now, brethren, I have taken occasion on times before, and there isn't time now, to elaborate
much, to make as earnest an appeal as I know how to make to the elders of this Church who
have been neglectful and careless, and who have set themselves in process of losing that
Priesthood of which President Clark has so impressively spoken.
</p><p>
I do not suppose that I can appeal to too many of them here tonight. They are probably not
here. They are in your quorums. Their presidencies are here, at least in large measure.
Brethren, will you obey the injunction given by President Clark to go out for these lost sheep
and bring them in, and succor them, encourage them, and if necessary, rebuke them in order
to bring them to a realization of what they are losing.
</p><p>
Some years ago I took the liberty of sounding a little slogan to our brethren, as I went around
the Church, in the care of these people. It was a very simple thing. I do not know whether
you will agree with it or not. "If they don't come to us, we will go to them." I put that
forward once, and a young elders' quorum president said, "I don't believe it." He said, "We
provide the quorum facilities for them. If they don't come it is their own fault."
</p><p>
Of course it was not long before he changed his mind when we reminded him that that was
not the missionary spirit. I think we can't go to any who need our help more than to these
brethren who have been careless and neglectful about their Priesthood.
</p><p>
I sincerely hope that in the administration of the quorums you are emphasizing the fraternal
aspects of these great institutions. I have long been persuaded that these quorums ought to be
our clubs. They ought to be the places where we find our dearest associations and we need
not look far beyond them for that fraternity which we all crave. The fraternity of the
Priesthood in our own quorums!
</p><p>
NEED FOR EFFECTIVE VISITING
</p><p>
In your visits to these people, I am sure that you need to exercise great discretion and
judgment. I wish all of the Melchizedek Priesthood&mdash;perhaps many of them did last
night&mdash;might have seen the demonstration in the bishops' meeting which was held on this stand last
evening. There were some very excellent constructive suggestions which were given.
</p><p>
I believe, my brethren, that you will make far more progress in frankness than in attempting
to beat about the bush with these men. I believe if you have the proper spirit you can go to
them and talk about their condition, and their needs without spending time in visits talking
about the weather and politics and current affairs.
</p><p>
One of the most successful missionaries that I ever knew, when I asked him what the
elements of his success were, said, among other things, that he always told people on whom
he called that he never had time to talk anything else but the Gospel, and be begged them to
excuse him from any other discussion.
</p><p>
I am persuaded that if we went to our members and talked to them about their faith, and the
things they were losing, and the things the quorum and the Church hold out for them, that we
would make more progress in their reformation. It requires some courage, it requires some
tact, and most of all it requires love. They say love is, in the end, the only irresistible force in
the world, and if we have love sufficient, and friendship, and these brethren know our love
for them, I think we can approach them and speak frankly to them, and thus help them. I
sincerely trust that we may.
</p><p>
Nearly all of these men are good at heart, but careless. There are a few that are mean.
Perhaps they deserve rebuke, and rebuke might be the best means of bringing them to an
understanding of their position, but remember how that rebuke has to be made, "reproving
betimes with sharpness, when moved upon by the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/43#43">D&amp;C 121:43</a>). That is the only rebuke that is
permissible under the constitution of the Priesthood.
</p><p>
PRIESTHOOD DIVINE
</p><p>
Now, my brethren. I love this Holy Priesthood. I know that it is genuine. Every interpretive
sense that the Lord has given me testifies to me that it is divine. I have felt its influence as I
have administered in the ordinances of the Gospel. I have felt its stimulation. I have felt an
essence pass from me in administering to the Saints that I know was of divine origin. I have
seen its results. I know that it is divine. I know that it is authentic. Its source is not far
removed from us&mdash;into the area of dim antiquity. We do not have to debate about its origin.
Why, it is proximate to us.
</p><p>
A man today said that I ordained him a High Priest some time ago, and asked if I had a card
to give him the derivation of my Priesthood. I said, "No, I don't have a card for you, but I
think you can remember it&mdash;four steps. I was ordained by President Joseph F. Smith. He was
ordained by President Brigham Young. Brigham Young was ordained by the three witnesses,
one of whom was Oliver Cowdery, who with Joseph was ordained by angelic ministers."
</p><p>
That is how close it is to us. There is no debate about it. There is no question about the
authenticity of this great power. We are fortunate indeed not to have to search the records of
ancient days in order to establish this divine authority, upon which the Church and Kingdom
of God is founded.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR ASSOCIATIONS
</p><p>
I express my gratitude for it, and I express my gratitude for my association with my brethren
of the Priesthood. I have had a most impressive experience in the last six months. I had
thought I had always been close to my brethren, but I found that I had never been into the
full confidence of this wonderful relation until I came to be associated with my beloved
President, and President Clark&mdash;without any reservations, without a necessity of concealing
private feelings, but with a freedom of thought and expression welcomed by all, that to my
thinking, is the badge of true friendship, brotherhood and understanding.
</p><p>
I thank the Lord that somehow, in his providence, I have been brought to that great blessing,
and I ask the Lord to help me that I may be in a measure worthy of it. And I ask the Lord to
bless every one of you, my brethren, that each may magnify the sacred calling that the Lord
has vouchsafed to him.
</p><p>
I do so humbly in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
