<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...If Ye Believe Not that I Am He, Ye Shall Die in Your Sins"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 9-12</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren and sisters: I ask you to join your faith and prayers with mine, that what I say will
be in harmony with what has already been said. What I have been thinking about is, I believe,
in harmony with President Clark's great message. I pray that I may have the Spirit of the
Lord as I speak.
</p><p>
To suggest what I have in mind to say, I quote these words which Jesus spake to the
unbelieving Jews: ". . . if ye believe not that I am he, ye shall die in your sins"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/24#24">John 8:24</a>).
</p><p>
I should like to direct my remarks particularly to this great group of singers here in the choir
from Brigham Young University, and to all other students&mdash;students who are challenged by
the wonders of the universe, and who want to learn more about them, and at the same time
prove faithful and true to the faith of their parents.
</p><p>
Such a student returning from a celebrated eastern university recently said in substance:
"Some of my fellow students are apparently as well off as we are. They seemingly observe
our standards with respect to chastity, Word of Wisdom, clean speech, and have lofty ideals.
What do we have which they do not have? If there is a difference between us just what is it?"
</p><p>
A little reflection, I believe, will suggest a number of differences, but the one I wish to
emphasize this morning is our beliefs and faith in Jesus Christ&mdash;not our belief that there is a
God, but rather our peculiar concept about his nature and identity, and our relationship to
him. It is when we descend to particulars that the differences show up. As a matter of fact, it
seems that belief in the existence of a God is almost universal. Thinking people everywhere,
particularly scientists, are accepting the hypothesis that there is a God who created and is now
controlling the universe. The materialistic concept which denies God altogether is being
replaced with the theory set forth by the late French scientist, Dr. Pierre Lecomte du Nouy, in
his great book <i>Human Destiny</i>. His thesis is that there is "an idea, a transcendent will, a
supreme intelligence," an "anti-chance" sustaining the universe. This supreme intelligence he
calls God.
</p><p>
Aroused by what he terms "the universal demoralization" and loss of faith which has resulted
from "paralyzing skepticism and destructive materialism," he examines "critically the scientific
capital accumulated by man": and derives "therefrom logical and rational consequences" which
to him and many other eminent scientists "lead inevitably to the idea of God." The existence
of such a Being is, he concludes, a scientific fact. It is his hope that the acceptance of his
thesis will supply men with a basis, and give them a motive which will sustain faith in God
and in the high destiny of man&mdash;a faith which will keep men struggling to reach the moral
and spiritual plane exemplified by Jesus. "Men must be made to understand," he says, "that
the important thing is to develop what is within them, to purify themselves, to better
themselves, to come closer to the perfect ideal which is Christ."
</p><p>
Now, of course, we believe with him that there is a God who is the Creator and ruler of the
universe. His statement that God's purpose is to bring men "closer to the perfect ideal which
is Christ" is, when interpreted in the light of our belief in Jesus, in harmony with the Lord's
declaration that ". . . this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the
immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
However, we do not see eye to eye with
him as to the nature of that perfection, nor as to the process by which it may be attained. Our
differences on these matters arise from our incompatible beliefs about the nature and the
identity of God and Jesus, and our relationship to them. A comparison of these beliefs will
point up the differences. As to his beliefs, we will let him speak for himself. First, as to God: 
</p><p>
"Any effort to visualize God," he says, "reveals a surprising childishness. We can no more
conceive Him than we can conceive an electron." And again ". . . the idea of God is a pure
idea like the idea of force, or of energy, and does not need to be visualized: nor can it be . . ."
And finally: "When we were led to call on an external action so as to account for the birth of
life and the development of evolution, we admitted that the only possible, logical
interpretation coincided with that which recognized the existence of God. And . . . we were
driven, in order to explain the universe and evolution, to accept the idea . . . However, we were
careful not to define the attributes of this force, which evidently corresponds to the admitted
idea of God. We, therefore used the consecrated name, but avoided as much as possible any
anthropomorphic idea."
</p><p>
Now of course this is not our concept of God. But I think we should respect this scientist's
desire to establish a scientific basis for faith in God. He did the best he could with the light
under which he worked. We will not be disturbed nor disappointed by his conclusion if we
keep in mind the fact that the truth about Deity does not lie within the range of scientific
research nor philosophical interpretation, but rather in the field of direct revelation.
</p><p>
As to his concept of Jesus he says: ". . . let us not forget that the perfect man is not a myth;
he has existed, in the person of Jesus," who he says "can be assimilated," [that is, likened or
compared] "to one of the intermediary . . . forms, perhaps a million years in advance of
evolution."
</p><p>
Because they are familiar to most of us I shall not here review in detail our beliefs about
Jesus. President Clark set them forth with much clarity this morning. But I do submit to you
that these postulated concepts of God and Jesus omit every essential aspect of the divine
Redeemer whom we worship. They rule out his and our pre-existence, his divine Sonship, the
fall of Adam, and Christ's atonement, Christ's and our resurrection, his past, present, and
future role in the courts on high, and our eternal progress and destiny in the world to come.
</p><p>
I repeat that in our peculiar beliefs and faith in Jesus Christ, comprising the foregoing and
other revealed truths concerning him, we greatly differ from other people of the earth.
</p><p>
But does it make any difference which beliefs men accept? Remembering that Jesus said a
tree may be known by its fruit (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/6/44#44">Luke 6:44</a>),
let us look at this question for just a moment. One of the
fruits of the foregoing conceptions of Jesus is that the good life which he projected may be
attained by accepting and applying his so-called "ethical and moral teachings" such as those
expressed in the Sermon on the Mount, while at the same time denying his divinity and
ridiculing the fundamental doctrines of his gospel. Here is a quotation from one of the most
ardent proponents of this theory.
</p><p>
"What was Jesus' ancestry? Was He a descendant of Joseph and Mary, or of God and Mary?
He was a descendant of Joseph and Mary. He was the most perfect human being who ever
lived, but He was not the Son of God." And further, "belief in . . . the Virgin Mary, the
atonement, trinity, etc., will not help to make a better world, but belief in the fundamentals of
Jesus' democracy and the social values named in the Sermon on the Mount will"
(<i>The Good Society</i>, by Willis, p. 58).
</p><p>
Now I submit to you that all history, including the present state of world affairs, testifies that
the fruits of the teachings of Jesus Christ cannot be had by accepting some of his teachings,
rejecting the rest, and denying his divinity. Of all the world's ills, none is more tragic than
the denial of Jesus Christ, the Son of God, by so many people who profess to believe in him.
</p><p>
Another fruit of the supreme intelligence theory is that God set a goal for man, but "did not
prescribe the means" by which that goal may be attained. This was left, so the theory runs, for
man to discover by trial and error. Such a doctrine is the antithesis of our knowledge that
Jesus Christ prescribed the exact course by which men may come to the perfection he
enjoined.
</p><p> 
"He marked the path and led the way,<br />
And ev'ry point defines,<br />
To light and life and endless day,<br />
Where God's full presence shines."
</p><p>
          (Eliza R. Snow)
</p><p>
Now to come directly to the point of these remarks, let us consider the fruits of believing
Jesus to be what he claimed to be&mdash;the literal Son of God in the spirit and in the flesh, the
revelation of God to man, the Redeemer, our advocate with the Father. What does such a
belief do for one?
</p><p>
Speaking generally, it becomes the motivating force in one's life. Specifically, it induces one
to render obedience to the initiatory principles and ordinances of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
That is, to have faith in Jesus, to repent, to be baptized by immersion for the remission of
sins, and to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of hands. Wholehearted
obedience to these purifying and sanctifying principles and ordinances works in the life of the
true believer a far-reaching miracle. For one thing, it confers upon him membership in the
literal kingdom of God, identifying him as a sheep of the true Shepherd.
</p><p>
Through obedience to these principles and ordinances there is introduced into one's life a new
light, a light which conveys to his mind, and opens his understanding to, ". . . pure knowledge
which shall greatly enlarge the soul" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/42#42">D&amp;C 121:42</a>).
Such an one is in a real sense
readmitted into the presence of God. The direct line of communication from God to him is
reopened. By this he is sustained in his belief in Jesus Christ with an assurance beyond the
understanding of the uninitiated.
</p><p>
This great source of pure knowledge, wisdom, light, and intelligence is, of course, the Holy
Ghost who the Savior said would lead men into all truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13#13">John 16:13</a>). To understand and appreciate this
great gift it must be experienced. But I bear you witness that it is real and will work a miracle
in your understanding. You will remember that without it Peter denied Jesus on the night of
his great trial (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/70-75#70">Matt. 26:70-75</a>).
Possessing it, Peter and John defied their captors, (although those captors had
the power to put them to death and in a sense had the disposition to do so) with this
declaration: ". . . whether it be right in the sight of God to hearken unto you more than unto
God, judge ye.
</p><p>
"For we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/19-20#19">Acts 4:19-20</a>). While
one enjoys this gift his belief in Jesus Christ is secure.
</p><p>
Now, the third effect of complying with these principles of the gospel is forgiveness of sins.
This is in itself a mighty miracle. Sin is wickedness and ". . . wickedness never was
happiness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/41/10#10">Alma 41:10</a>).
</p><p>
Most of the suffering and distress endured by people of this earth is the result of unrepented
and unremitted sin. Paul spoke two universal truths when he said to the Romans, ". . . the
wages of sin is death; but the gift of God is eternal life through Jesus Christ our Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/6/23#23">Rom. 6:23</a>).
Just as suffering and sorrow attend sin, so happiness and joy attend
forgiveness of sins.
</p><p>
Alma said of his suffering for sin ". . . there could be nothing so exquisite and so bitter as
were my pains," and then, speaking of the joy which came to him when, through repentance,
he had received forgiveness, he said, "Yea, and again I say unto you, . . . that on the other
hand, there can be nothing so exquisite and sweet as was my joy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/36/21#21">Alma 36:21</a>).
</p><p>
Forgiveness of sins is prerequisite to a full fellowship in the Church of Jesus Christ. It is a
prerequisite to enjoying the gift of the Holy Ghost. As a matter of fact every blessing of the
gospel of Jesus Christ is predicated upon receiving forgiveness of sins; for, as Jesus said, ". . .
no unclean thing can enter into his [God's] kingdom; therefore, nothing entereth into his rest
save it be those who have washed their garments in my blood, because of
their faith, and the repentance of all their sins, and their faithfulness unto the end"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/19#19">3 Ne. 27:19</a>).
Then he added: "Now this is the commandment: Repent, all ye ends of the earth, and
come unto me [that is, believe on me] and be baptized in my name, that ye may be sanctified
by the reception of the Holy Ghost, that ye may stand spotless before me at the last day"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/20#20">3 Ne. 27:20</a>).
</p><p>
In this statement Jesus Christ gave the only prescription there is for obtaining forgiveness of
sins, and, therefore, the only way to happiness, the only way to a pure knowledge of God our
Eternal Father and his Son Jesus Christ, our Redeemer. The following of this prescription
depends wholly upon one's belief in Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I sincerely pray that should the question arise as to, "What do we have which others do not
have?" we will remember and try to understand the eternal truths implied in Jesus' statement
to the unbelieving Jews, ". . . if ye believe not that I am he ye shall die in your sins"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/24#24">John 8:24</a>).
</p><p>
God grant that each of us may escape such a death by believing with Peter that Jesus is "the
Christ, the Son of the Living God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16#16">Matt. 16:16</a>), I humbly pray in his name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
