<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">This Pearl Beyond Price</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 11-16</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brothers and sisters, we are tremendously blessed by the presence of our beloved President
David O. McKay and his dear wife, who is also here with him. President McKay always
brings light and spirit into any assembly where he is present. An evidence of this is the
masterful sermon he gave us this morning. We should ponder it in our hearts because the
instruction and counsel are good. I humbly pray that the remarks I make will not detract from
his splendid message.
</p><p>
<b>He Taught by Parables</b>
</p><p>
During the earthly mission of Jesus Christ, he often employed the parable method of teaching
his disciples and others who sought after him. Parables were used by Christ to convey a moral
or spiritual truth. His parables were based upon real scenes or events such as occur in nature
and human life. They are fundamental stories, true to life situations, employing given
circumstances or facts of one's experience and have a vigorous moral and religious
application. The parables of Jesus were provokingly adapted to challenge the understanding of
his hearers.
</p><p>
Let us consider the following parable: 
</p><p>
"Again, the kingdom of heaven is like unto a merchant man, seeking goodly pearls: 
</p><p>
"Who, when he had found one pearl of great price, went and sold all that he had, and bought
it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/45-46#45">Matt. 13:45-46</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Parable of the Pearl of Great Price</b>
</p><p>
This parable is most significant and meaningful; to appreciate its purpose is to understand the
message. The desire of the merchantman dealing in pearls is to find the most priceless one of
all. Therefore, he earnestly seeks and may travel extensively to world markets before he
discovers the fabulous jewel which measures up to his expectations in standards of quality,
value, and iridescent beauty. Having found the pearl of great price, his joy and happiness is
not complete until the gem becomes his personal property. To satisfy that desire, according to
the parable, the merchant was willing to sacrifice all he had for ownership of the goodly
pearl.
</p><p>
Allegorically the Savior likens the kingdom of heaven unto the merchantman seeking goodly
pearls, signifying that the true pearl of great price is God's kingdom which, for man to be
happy and exalted, he must diligently seek.
</p><p>
This parable accords with the Savior's teaching upon the Mount when he admonished: 
</p><p>
". . . seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be
added unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
When we relate the parable of the goodly pearls and the challenge of our Lord to seek first
the kingdom of God, we receive a more comprehensive understanding of the parable dealing
with the pearl of great price. Pearls have always held a high place among gems, and
merchants have been active and diligent in seeking the largest and richest to be had. Unlike
the man in the parable of the hidden treasure
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/44#44">Matt. 13:44</a>),
who, with little or no effort on his part, found
concealed in a field a precious treasure of great worth, the merchant devoted his whole energy
to the quest for goodly pearls; to find and secure the best was his greatest ambition and
business.
</p><p>
When finally he beheld the pearl that excelled all others, he gladly sold all his other gems.
Indeed, he sacrificed all that he had in gems and other possessions and purchased the pearl of
great price. Seekers after truth may acquire much that is good and desirable but not find the
greatest truth of all, the truth that shall save them and bring about their eternal exaltation and
glory. Yet, if they seek persistently and with right intent and are really in quest of pearls of
truth and righteousness and not imitations or substitutes, they shall find, for the Holy Ghost,
which is the Spirit of truth, shall guide them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13#13">John 16:13</a>,
see also James E. Talmage, <i>Jesus the Christ</i>, pp. 293-294).
</p><p>
Saul of Tarsus, while on his way to Damascus to persecute the Saints, found en route the
pearl of great price by the revelation of Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/3-6#3">Acts 9:3-6</a>). Few are favored as Saul&mdash;who later
became Paul the Apostle&mdash;with a heavenly manifestation to change their ways from evil
purpose to the ways of righteousness.
</p><p>
Every soul earnestly and honestly seeking the pearl of great price is entitled to the Holy Ghost
to aid him or her in that quest.
</p><p>
<b>Gifts of the Holy Ghost</b>
</p><p>
Two significant gifts of the Holy Ghost are the spirit of inspiration and revelation; and also a
function of the Holy Ghost is to bear witness of the Father and the Son. By the gift of that
power, the honest investigator can learn and know the eternal truths of the kingdom of God
with certainty of soul conviction. If an individual fails to yield to the enlightenment of the
Holy Ghost, then the Spirit departs from him, and he is left to his own resources to struggle
alone with his problems.
</p><p>
Men who by search and research discover the truths of the kingdom of heaven may have to
abandon many of their cherished traditions and even their theories of imperfect philosophy
and science if they would possess the pearl of great price, God's kingdom, which, with its
standards, principles, ideals, and holy ordinances is the gospel plan of life, salvation,
exaltation, and glory.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul as Saul of Tarsus, steeped as he was in the traditions of his people and the
Sanhedrin, had this same choice to make. Importantly and wisely he chose to follow Christ,
which he did with a dedication to duty that earned for him the title of the great Apostle to the
Gentiles (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/11/13#13">Rom. 11:13</a>). He was esteemed and honored by his associates and the Saints. The Apostle Paul is
a worthy example to all who find the pearl of great price. As he completely changed his life,
so others must have the courage to change their way of life to the new life, the true gospel
that Christ offers.
</p><p>
We understand that in this parable of the merchantman and the goodly pearls, as in that of the
hidden treasure (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/44#44">Matt. 13:44</a>),
the price of possession is one's all. No individual can become a citizen of the
kingdom of God by partial surrender of his earlier allegiances. He must renounce everything
foreign to the kingdom, or he can never be numbered therein.
</p><p>
If he willingly sacrifices all that he has, he shall find that he has enough. The cost of the
hidden treasure and of the goodly pearl is not a fixed amount alike for all; it is all one has,
and the poorest may come into enduring possession. His all is a sufficient purchase price. (See
Talmage, op. cit., p. 294.)
</p><p>
It is clearly seen that the key to finding the pearl of great price is to earnestly seek for light
and truth as found in the gospel of Christ. The Lord has said: "Draw near unto me and I will
draw near unto you; seek me diligently and ye shall find me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/63#63">D&amp;C 88:63</a>).
</p><p>
In Christ's Sermon on the Mount he taught: "Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye
shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>).
</p><p>
Moroni, an ancient American prophet, bidding farewell to his brethren and to the gentiles,
bore his witness to having seen Jesus and of talking with him face to face
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/39#39">Ether 12:39</a>), and then
admonished:
</p><p>
"And now, I would commend you to seek this Jesus of whom the prophets and apostles have
written, that the grace of God the Father, and also the Lord Jesus Christ, and the Holy Ghost,
which beareth record of them may be and abide in you forever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/41#41">Ether 12:41</a>).
</p><p>
Lehi, an early American prophet, counseled: 
</p><p>
"For he that diligently seeketh shall find, and the mysteries of God shall be unfolded unto
them, by the power of the Holy Ghost, as well in these times as in times of old, and as well
in times of old as in times to come; wherefore, the course of the Lord is one eternal round"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/10/19#19">1 Ne. 10:19</a>).
</p><p>
It behooves many people to change their place of residence and maybe travel far to find the
pearl of great price, and yet others may find it in their communities or nearby. Men and
women must sincerely put their heart and soul into seeking the true gospel found in God's
earthly kingdom. They can so live as to tune in on the spiritual channel activated by the Holy
Ghost and obtain by prayer its companionship to guide them into all truth from God.
</p><p>
<b>Principles, Standards, Ordinances, Covenants</b>
</p><p>
What should men and women look for to distinguish the kingdom of heaven, the goodly
pearl, from all other churches? There are many facets to this goodly pearl. These facets are
principles, standards, ordinances, and covenants. The scriptures also provide colorful facets of
the goodly pearl. Limited time prevents a full discussion of these items. The following few
comments must suffice.
</p><p>
<b>Principles</b>
</p><p>
Under principles we can include the following: (1) free agency, as mentioned by President
David O. McKay, (2) faith in God and his Beloved Son Jesus Christ, (3) sincere and
sorrowing repentance for sins committed and refraining from being guilty of them again, (4)
the Word of Wisdom, the Lord's law of health, which he gave as a principle with promise
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/3#3">D&amp;C 89:3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Standards</b>
</p><p>
Under standards are: (1) chastity, virtue, and moral cleanliness, (2) integrity which includes
honesty, sincerity of purpose, truthfulness, and uprightness; (3) to further emphasize standards,
I quote in part the thirteenth article of our faith: 
</p><p>
"We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men
. . . If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these
things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Ordinances</b>
</p><p>
Under the heading of ordinances we include: (1) baptism by immersion for the remission of
sins, (2) the laying on of hands for both confirmation and bestowing the gift of the Holy
Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/4#4">A of F 1:4</a>), (3) the bestowal of the Holy Priesthood of God by the laying on of hands, (4)
ordinances in the temple of God, which include the endowment and eternal marriage
ceremonies and vicarious work for the dead.
</p><p>
<b>Covenants</b>
</p><p>
Under covenants: (1) The gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ is a covenant between God and his
people. (2) When baptized by an authorized servant of God, we covenant to do God's will
and to obey his commandments. (3) By partaking of the Sacrament we renew all covenants
entered into with the Lord and pledge ourselves to take upon us the name of his Son, to
always remember him and keep his commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/77#77">D&amp;C 20:77</a>).
(4) There is an oath and covenant which
belongs to the priesthood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/39#39">D&amp;C 84:39</a>)
wherein men receiving this holy power pledge themselves faithfully
to keep all the commandments of God and to magnify their callings in the priesthood, which
is God's gift of his power and authority unto them. (5) In connection with all ordinances
pertaining to the temples of our God, men and women accept covenants and obligations which
relate to the endowment and to the eternity of the marriage and family relationship. All these
doctrines and more are necessary and vital to the salvation, exaltation and eternal happiness of
God's children.
</p><p>
<b>Standard Works of the Church</b>
</p><p>
The final facet of the pearl of great price for consideration is the scriptures referred to by the
Latter-day Saints as "the four standard works," which include the Bible, the Book of Mormon,
the Doctrine and Covenants, and the Pearl of Great Price. If all the books in the world were
destroyed except the four standard works of the Church, man would have the foundation of
principles and moral and spiritual values to reestablish his civilization and rise again to lofty
achievements and happiness.
</p><p>
The Bible is listed first among the four standard works of the Church and is accepted by all
Christian peoples.
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon records that Lehi, the first prophet of the Nephite nation, was
counseled by the Lord that before his family and others departed the land of Jerusalem to the
Americas, they must obtain a copy of the book of the Lord, so that, said he, ". . . we may
preserve unto our children the language of our fathers; 
</p><p>
"And also that we may preserve unto them the words which have been spoken by the mouth
of all the holy prophets, which have been delivered unto them by the Spirit and power of
God, since the world began, even down unto this present time"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/19-20#19">1 Ne. 3:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
With this record in their possession they were able to establish an enlightened and a
prosperous civilization in the early Americas.
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon is largely a record of a branch of the house of Israel, the covenant
people of the Lord, who came to the Americas about six hundred years before Christ. It is a
companion book to the Bible to convince both Jew and gentile that Jesus is the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>).
</p><p>
The Doctrine and Covenants contains revelations given by the Lord mainly to the Prophet
Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
The Pearl of Great Price&mdash;the title of the fourth named standard work&mdash;is taken from
Christ's parable we are considering. The book contains the writings of the great prophets
Moses and Abraham, also the twenty-fourth chapter of Matthew as revealed to the Prophet
Joseph Smith. These writings are the word of God representing the goodly pearl so precious
for mankind to study prayerfully and to know. The book also has the Joseph Smith testimony
and the Articles of Faith.
</p><p>
Jesus counseled: "Search the scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are
they which testify of me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/39#39">John 5:39</a>).
</p><p>
Moroni, the last Nephite prophet, in his farewell message gave a marvelous testimony to the
truth of the Book of Mormon to all who read it with a sincere desire to know the truth: 
</p><p>
"And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the
Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a
sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you,
by the power of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
"And by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4-5#4">Moro. 10:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord through the Prophet Joseph Smith challenged those reading the Doctrine and
Covenants to: 
</p><p>
"Search these commandments, for they are true and faithful, and the prophecies and promises
which are in them shall all be fulfilled"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/37#37">D&amp;C 1:37</a>).
</p><p>
All things pertaining to the kingdom of God are important for us to know. Our eternal
happiness depends upon abiding the Lord's gospel plan. It is man's obligation to seek and to
find this pearl of great price and then have the courage of faith and conviction to accept and
to obey the gospel of the kingdom.
</p><p>
<b>Comments of World Fair Visitors</b>
</p><p>
Tens of thousands of people in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints have met this
challenge unflinchingly because they sought and found the truth and had the courage of their
convictions to accept it in full faithfulness. That many men and women today are truly
searching for the pearl of great price is evidenced by the large attendance of people to the
religious exhibits at the New York World's Fair. I should like to share with you a few
statements of people visiting the church pavilion at the World's Fair. These few favorable
comments can be multiplied many, manyfold and are from people of different faiths who are
earnestly and honestly searching for the pearl of great price: 
</p><p>
It was quite an eye opener. I was completely unaware of this faith. I would like to learn
more.
</p><p>
I am very interested in your religion since going through the exhibit.
</p><p>
Found it extremely interesting, have seen nothing equal to it as far as religion is concerned.
</p><p>
Mormon literalism is perhaps the closest thing to original Christianity on earth today.
</p><p>
I think I have found the answer to my questions. Thank you.
</p><p>
I love the way you stay with the teachings of Christ.
</p><p>
It was a highly enlightening experience. I would like to know more about it to make a
decision.
</p><p>
Words seem too inadequate to express the depth and beauty I see in your religion.
</p><p>
It was truly wonderful and I am very impressed. I am considering looking into this religion
more.
</p><p>
This is the word of the Lord and his prophet.
</p><p>
I have strong feelings that this is true&mdash;what has been said here, I seem to remember I lived
before.
</p><p>
I was soul searching when I first saw the pavilion. I have since become a member of this
Mormon Church.
</p><p>
I know this is the word of the Lord. I am grateful to you for this pavilion which meant my
conversion to the Church.
</p><p>
<b>The World's Need for the Kingdom of God</b>
</p><p>
These comments are interesting and challenging to both church members and nonmembers
alike. It should give all of us a real pride of belonging to the Church we testify to the world
in all sincerity and solemnity as being the only true Church of Christ on earth today.
Although church members have in the gospel the pearl of great price, yet complacency,
inactivity, failure to keep the commandments will never save them. We must be doers of the
word and not hearers only (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/22#22">James 1:22</a>).
Where much is given, much is expected
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/12/48#48">Luke 12:48</a>).
If we are true to the faith
of our Lord, God will prosper his work and kingdom. The kingdom of God is the only hope
of the world for understanding and peace. The menacing conflicts and threat of more and
greater conflicts but presages the holocausts to follow. Man's ways are failing. Perhaps it is
time for God's ways to take over now that all else seemingly is falling apart. The world needs
the pearl of great price, which is God's kingdom, and it needs it today as never before.
</p><p>
Now brothers and sisters, may God bless and enlighten the earnest seekers for truth with faith
to believe and with courage to accept when the truth is presented to them. We are the
custodians of these great principles and truths. We have a tremendous responsibility of sharing
what the Lord has revealed to us with our fellowmen. May we be true to this trust, I humbly
pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
