<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Be Thou an Example of the Believers"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 12-13</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters, it is a great source of inspiration to be present this morning.
Week after week as I visit the stakes in the Church, I always feel I am with my brethren and
sisters. That is the way I feel this morning. I know you as my brethren and sisters, but I also
know of our older brother, Jesus Christ, the Son of God. In all of our endeavors, we must
give consideration to him.
</p><p>
This morning, as President McKay was giving us information about the Aaronic Priesthood
and its achievements, I thought of another young man. His name was Timothy. Timothy
became a wonderful missionary in his work with the Apostle Paul. Paul said to him, "Let no
man despise thy youth, but be thou an example of the believers, in word, in conversation, in
charity, in spirit, in faith, in purity"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/4/12#12">1 Tim. 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
Paul's words, "Let no man despise thy youth . . ." can be directed to the thousands of our
young missionaries who are out in the world preaching the gospel to those not of our faith.
Any young man who holds the Melchizedek Priesthood of the Lord Jesus Christ and is
endeavoring to build up the kingdom may come in contact with people who say, "Well, after
all, young man, what do you know about the gospel?" Then, they can remember, if they will,
what Paul said, "Let no man despise thy youth."
</p><p>
Paul also said to Timothy, which is most important, when he mentioned "the believers." That
would indicate that all these young men should understand the gospel and believe it and teach
it to the extent that they can bear testimony that they are representing the true Church.
</p><p>
Paul said to Timothy, "in word," by which he should learn the gospel and all the information
that was essential to teach it to those not of the true faith. Paul not only declared to Timothy,
"in word," but also, "in conversation," which means to preach and teach the gospel of the
Lord Jesus Christ to those who came in contact with him. He also said, "in charity," which
would be kindness and helpfulness in all of his teachings. He then said, "in spirit." The spirit
comes through prayer, being close to the Lord where individual problems can be solved&mdash;the
spirit of loyalty and devotion to the Lord and his Son Jesus Christ, and also with this comes
the gift of the Holy Ghost. I am sure, my brethren and sisters, that no individual can render
the right service in preaching the gospel to those not of our faith unless he has the Holy
Ghost. It is so important in our homes that we instruct our sons and daughters about the Holy
Ghost. Paul also said to Timothy, "in faith." Faith indicates activity. The youth of the Church
and these young missionaries who go out into the world have faith so strong in their souls
that they will be successful in their assignments. He also mentioned "in purity" to the young
missionary, Timothy; purity of mind and body and soul.
</p><p>
The Apostle Matthew recorded these words of the Christ: "And this gospel of the kingdom
shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
President McKay said in the meeting of the General Authorities in the temple two weeks ago
that Satan has more power over the world than ever before in history. I accept this without a
question. Therefore, it is very important for all of us to give thought that sooner or later the
end is going to come&mdash;the end of all of this difficulty that we have at the present time and
that we will prepare the world for the second coming of Christ.
</p><p>
The Apostle John said in Revelation 14:6-7: 
</p><p>
"And I saw another angel fly in the midst of heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach
unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people,
</p><p>
"Saying with a loud voice, Fear God, and give glory to him; for the hour of his judgment is
come: and worship him that made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and the fountains of
waters" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6-7#6">Rev. 14:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
When the Church was upon the earth two thousand years ago, and thereafter was
disorganized, the apostles and all who had labored in building up the kingdom at that time
were gone. There were individuals who desired to organize churches of their own. During that
period of time of darkness in the world when the sons and daughters of our Heavenly Father
were not receiving the divine guidance they had received during the time of the apostles and
those who followed them, the power of Satan was dominant. There were wars, wars that came
about because of the differences in religion and the true gospel itself which was lost. The
priesthood was gone. The people were in darkness.
</p><p>
Proverbs 6:16-19 states: 
</p><p>
"These six things doth the Lord hate: yea, seven are an abomination unto him: 
</p><p>
"A proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood,
</p><p>
"An heart that deviseth wicked imaginations, feet that be swift in running to mischief,"
</p><p>
"A false witness that speaketh lies, and he that soweth discord among brethren"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/6/16-19#16">Prov. 6:16-19</a>).
</p><p>
This statement applies to us today as well as it did to the people almost three thousand years
ago.
</p><p>
A great event was to take place, as I have already indicated to you, when that marvelous
apostle made it very clear that in the last days as he said, "And I saw another angel fly in the
midst of heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach unto them that dwell on the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>).
</p><p>
A young man who was desirous to find the true Church made it a matter of prayer, and there
appeared to him the Father and the Son. The Father said to Joseph, "This is My Beloved Son.
Hear Him!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
Thereafter, the Prophet Joseph received the direction and the authority to organize
the Church. Yes, he received the priesthood when John the Baptist appeared to him. He also
received the Melchizedek Priesthood from Peter, James, and John, the apostles at the time of
Christ. The golden plates were given to him, which gave the history of America, and most
important, they contained the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ in its fulness. The Lord intended
his Church should be organized again. On April 6, 1830, the Church was organized. Since that
time, many other important events have taken place. There was the erection of the temple in
Kirtland, Ohio, and many other temples since then. With these wonderful events, you can
come to but one conclusion, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints was again made
available for all of the sons and daughters of our Heavenly Father who now live upon the
earth and those who come after us.
</p><p>
There are now eight thousand young men preaching the gospel as Timothy taught it, that
those who are seeking the truth can find it through these young missionaries who give them
the inspiration and the knowledge that the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ is again on the
earth.
</p><p>
Our American Prophet Joseph Smith made a statement in the Thirteenth Article of Faith quite
comparable to what Paul said to Timothy: 
</p><p>
"We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men;
indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all things, we hope all
things, we have endured many things, and hope to be able to endure all things. If there is
anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
And as the Apostle Paul said to Timothy, "Let no man despise thy youth; but be thou an
example of the believers, in word, in conversation, in charity, in spirit, in faith, in purity"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/4/12#12">1 Tim. 4:12</a>),
which I pray will be a guide to all the sons and daughters of our Heavenly Father.
This I ask in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
