<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">America Needs You</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas S. Monson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas S. Monson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 140-142</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
</p>
The opportunity to speak to you today brings with it a sense
of responsibility which humbles me. I pray for the
inspiration of the Lord.
</p><p>
Recently I was a passenger on a flight which took me from
the Pacific across the continent to the Atlantic Ocean. At
many points along the way, serenely seen through white,
billowy clouds were the fertile patchwork fields and
majestic mountains of this great land. The words of
Katherine Lee Bates, author of "America the Beautiful,"
coursed through my mind and found lodgment within my soul.
</p><p>
"Oh beautiful for spacious skies,<br />
For amber waves of grain,<br />
For purple mountain majesties<br />
Above the fruited plain!<br />
America! America!<br />
God shed his grace on thee<br />
And crown thy good with brotherhood<br />
From sea to shining sea."
</p><p>
The Lord Himself gave a divine promise to the ancient
inhabitants of this favored country. He said:
</p><p>
"Behold, this is a choice land, and whatsoever nation shall
possess it shall
be free from bondage, and from captivity, and from all
other nations under heaven, if they will but serve the God
of the land, who is Jesus Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>).
</p><p>
Are we today serving the God of the land, even the Lord
Jesus Christ? Do our lives conform with His teachings? Are
we entitled to His divine blessings?
</p><p>
Headlines from America's leading newspapers depicting the
events of the past year pass silently in review that you and
I may judge.
</p><p>
"President Kennedy Assassinated."<br />
"Alleged Assassin Murdered While In Custody of the Law."<br />
"Serious Crime Registers 10% Increase In Past Year."<br />
"Violence Rocks South."<br />
"Racial Strife Hits East."
</p><p>
Murder, rape, arson, burglary, assault, narcotics violations
are all on the increase in the America of today. These are
the headlines of our newspapers.
</p><p>
One cannot help but compare the situation of today with
conditions at the time of Belshazzar the King of the Chaldeans.
</p><p>
The prophet Daniel rebuked Belshazzar: "And thou . . . O Belshazzar,
hast not humbled thine heart . . . But hast lifted up thyself
against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the
vessels of his house before thee, and thou, and thy lords,
thy wives, and thy concubines, have drunk wine in them; and
thou hast praised the gods of silver, and gold, of brass,
iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know:
and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose are all
thy ways, hast thou not glorified"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/5/22-23#22">Dan. 5:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
He then interpreted the writing on the wall. ". . . God hath
numbered thy kingdom, and finished it . . . Thou art weighed
in the balances, and art found wanting"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/5/26-27#26">Dan. 5:26-27</a>).
</p><p>
Too many Americans have been screaming ever louder for more
and more of the things we cannot take with us and paying
less and less attention to the real sources of the very
happiness we seek. We have been measuring our fellowmen more
by balance sheets and less by moral standards. We have
developed frightening physical power and fallen into pathetic
spiritual weakness. We have become so concerned over the
growth of our earning capacity that we have neglected the
growth of our character.
</p><p>
As we view the disillusionment that engulfs countless
thousands today, we are learning the hard way what an
ancient prophet wrote out for us 3,000 years ago. "He that
loveth silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor he
that loveth abundance with increase"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eccl/5/10#10">Eccl. 5:10</a>).
</p><p>
The revered Abraham Lincoln accurately described our
plight. "We have been the recipients of the choicest
bounties of heaven; we have been preserved these many years in
peace and prosperity. We have grown in numbers, wealth, and
power as no other nation has ever grown; but we have
forgotten God. We have forgotten the gracious hand which
preserved us in peace and multiplied and enriched and
strengthened us. We have vainly imagined, in the
deceitfulness of our hearts that all these blessings were
produced by some superior wisdom and virtue of our own.
Intoxicated with unbroken succession, we have become too
self-sufficient to feel the necessity of preserving and
redeeming grace, too proud to pray to God that made us."
</p><p>
Can we extricate ourselves from this frightful condition? Is
there a way out? If so, what is the way? We can solve this
perplexing dilemma by adopting the counsel given by Jesus to
the inquiring lawyer who asked, "Master, which is the great
commandment in the law? Jesus said unto him, Thou shalt love
the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul,
and with all thy mind. This is the first and great
commandment. And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love
thy neighbor as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36-39#36">Matt. 22:36-39</a>).
</p><p>
First, then I would suggest that each American love the
Lord, our God, and with our families serve Him in righteousness.
</p><p>
The road back to God is not nearly so steep nor is it so
difficult as some would have us believe. The gentle
invitation of Jesus yet beckons, ". . . Come unto me." Paul
advised that, ". . . he that cometh to God must believe that
he is, and that he is a rewarder of them that diligently
seek him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/6#6">Heb. 11:6</a>).
</p><p>
The channel by which we seek Him and find Him is personal
and family prayer. The recognition of a power higher than
man himself does not in any sense debase him, rather it
exalts him. Divine favor will attend those who humbly seek
it. If we will but realize that we have been created in the
image of God, we will not find Him difficult to approach.
God did create ". . . man in his own image, in the image of
God created he him; male and female created he them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>).
You cannot sincerely hold this conviction
without experiencing a profound new sense of strength.
</p><p>
By seeking God in personal and family prayer we and our
loved ones will acquire what the great English statesman,
William H. Gladstone, described as the world's greatest
need&mdash;"A living faith in a personal God."
</p><p>
Who can evaluate the real worth of such a blessing? This
faith will light the pathway for any honest seeker of divine
truth. Wives will draw closer to their husbands and husbands
will the more appreciate their wives and children will be
happy children as children are meant to be. Children in the
homes
blessed by prayer will not find themselves in that dreaded
never never land. Never the object of concern, never the
recipient of proper parental guidance. Our children will be
taught integrity which is primarily a matter of early
training. To teach the young to love the truth above
personal convenience is the basis of it. They will be taught
true courage which becomes a living and attractive virtue
when it is regarded not as a willingness to die manfully but
as the determination to live decently. They will be taught
honesty by habit and as a matter of course. Our children
will be taught this way of living by parents who will not
ask the child, "What will people think," but rather, "What
will you think of yourself." Our children will grow
physically from childhood to adulthood, and mentally from
ignorance to knowledge, emotionally from insecurity to
stability and spirituality to an abiding faith in God. Such
is the power gained from loving the Lord, our God, and
serving Him in righteousness.
</p><p>
Second, I would suggest that each American love his neighbor
as himself. Before we can really love our neighbor we must
get the proper perspective of him.
</p><p>
One man said, "I looked at my brother with the microscope of
criticism and I said, 'How coarse my brother is.' I looked
at my brother with the telescope of scorn and I said, 'How
small my brother is.' Then I looked into the mirror of truth
and I said, 'How like me my brother is.'"
</p><p>
Paul counseled us, "Bear ye one another's burdens, and so
fulfil the law of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/2#2">Gal. 6:2</a>). No burden is
heavier to bear than is sin. When we show our brother, our
neighbor, the way back to God through applying the divine
principle of repentance, we help him to build a new and
better life.
</p><p>
If we are not careful, our thoughts and plans to aid others
in making this a better world in which to live will remain
just that&mdash;thoughts and plans. As humans we cannot really see
very far ahead and need, therefore, to take each step with
all the wisdom we can muster. While sensing what lies dimly
ahead, we must do confidently what lies clearly at hand.
Decision is of little account
unless it is followed by action. If we procrastinate our
lofty ambitions too long, we well might suffer the lament
spoken by Jacob Marley's ghost in Dickens' immortal "A
Christmas Carol." Speaking of Ebenezer Scrooge he said, "Not
to know that any Christian Spirit working kindly in its
little sphere, whatever it may be will find its life too
short for its vast means of usefulness. Not to know that no
space of regret can make amends for one life's opportunities
misused. Such was I, oh such was I."
</p><p>
One of the finest examples I know of helping one's neighbors
is that of a prominent businessman who at the height of his
success, generously gave his prosperous business to his
faithful employees and determined to devote the balance of
his life in charitable service. He withdrew from the world
of gold and silver and each day can now be found at a large
welfare distribution center doing his part to relieve the
suffering and need of human souls and make America a better
place in which to live. He is fulfilling the responsibility
to ". . . succor the weak, lift up the hands which hang
down, and strengthen the feeble knees"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/81/5#5">D&amp;C 81:5</a>). He humbly
declares: "This is the happiest period of my life."
</p><p>
The rich satisfactions which come from loving our neighbor
as ourselves are not ushered in at any age to the sound of
drums and trumpets but rather the satisfaction grows upon us
year by year, little by little, until at last we realize
that we have it.
</p><p>
One of the most famous enlistment posters of World War II
was one depicting Uncle Sam pointing his long finger and
directing his piercing eyes at the viewer. The words read,
"America Needs You." America truly does need you and me to
lead out in a mighty crusade of righteousness. We can help
when we love the Lord, our God, and with our families serve
him, and when we love our neighbors as ourselves.
</p><p>
The frightening trend toward crime, lawlessness, and
violence will then be arrested. God will continue to shed
His grace on thee, America, and crown thy good with
brotherhood from sea to shining sea. I pray for this needed
blessing in the name of Jesus Christ, the God of this
choice land of liberty, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
