<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The World Needs Healing</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 40-41</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
There should be no doubt in the minds of any of us that the world is not well. It is not dying
yet, but it is sick. It does not have an incurable disease, for we have a good physician. The
world just needs healing.
</p><p>
<b>World problems not new</b>
</p><p>
This is not new in the world. There have been problems and crises off and on from the very
beginning of mortality. The scriptures are replete with references concerning similar
conditions. The Lord has, from the very beginning, given man warnings and promises. Should
the scriptures fall open at almost any place, they would very likely reveal the remedy for all
problems, even present-day conditions.
</p><p>
Adam and Eve were admonished to repent and be obedient to God's command (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/5-8#5">Moses 5:5-8</a>). Yet, by the
time of Noah the world was so sick, God had to destroy all except Noah and those with him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/20#20">1 Pet. 3:20</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Promise of Moses</b>
</p><p>
Then in the latter part of Israel's wanderings in the wilderness, Moses, having been told he
was not to see the promised land, declared to all Israel the following warning and promise.
</p><p>
"But if from thence thou shalt seek the Lord thy God, thou shalt find him, if thou seek him
with all thy heart and with all thy soul.
</p><p>
"When thou art in tribulation, and all these things are come upon thee, even in the latter days"&mdash;Are 
these not the latter days? Are we not Israel? Then he is talking to us; yes, to us here in
1968&mdash;"if thou turn to the Lord thy God, and shall be obedient unto his voice;"&mdash;Does not
the voice of the Lord come to us from his Prophet?
</p><p>
"(For the Lord thy God is a merciful God;) he will not forsake thee, neither destroy thee, nor
forget the covenant of thy fathers which he sware unto them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/4/29-31#29">Deut. 4:29-31</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Lord's word to Solomon</b>
</p><p>
Open the scriptures to another historical occasion: the dedicatory services of Solomon's
temple.
</p><p>
This was a great sacrificial ordinance. Solomon offered a sacrifice of 2,000 oxen and 120,000
sheep. This was a seven-day dedicatory service. Then the Lord answered Solomon's prayer.
Note here the application to our time: 
</p><p>
The Lord said to Solomon: 
</p><p>
"If my people, which are called by my name [Are these not the members of the Church of
Jesus Christ?], shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their
wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heal their
land" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/7/14#14">2 Chr. 7:14</a>).
</p><p>
Is there any doubt that our land needs healing? Christ in Jerusalem, seeing the iniquity,
declared: 
</p><p>
"O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them which are sent unto
thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her
chickens under her wings, and ye would not!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/37#37">Matt. 23:37</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Book of Mormon record</b>
</p><p>
Turn to the Book of Mormon. This is a record of continual ups and downs of the people.
With righteousness, there was peace and prosperity. When they became wicked and sinful,
there was war, destruction, famine.
</p><p>
Following the great destruction of the more wicked on this hemisphere at the time of the
crucifixion of Christ, the voice of the Lord was heard to declare: 
</p><p>
Yea, verily I say unto you, if ye will come unto me ye shall have eternal life. Behold, mine
arm of mercy is extended towards you, and whosoever will come, him will I receive; and
blessed are those who come unto me.
</p><p>
"Behold, I have come unto the world to bring redemption unto the world, to save the world
from sin.
</p><p>
"Therefore, whoso repenteth and cometh unto me as a little child, him will I receive, for of
such is the kingdom of God. Behold, for such I have laid down my life, and have taken it up
again; therefore repent, and come unto me ye ends of the earth, and be saved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/14,21-22#14">3 Ne. 9:14,21-22</a>).
</p><p>
". . . how oft will I gather you as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, if ye will
repent and return unto me with full purpose of heart" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/10/6#6">3 Ne. 10:6</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Promise of eternal life</b>
</p><p>
Here the Lord says, "Ye ends of the earth." Does that not mean us? This was not just to those
who heard his voice. For this purpose it was recorded and preserved down through the
centuries and brought forth by the instrumentality of God through his servant, the Prophet
Joseph Smith, for us of this day. The promise here is only to those who repent and do his
will&mdash;yes, the promise of eternal life. This means exaltation. He will save the world in that all
will be resurrected, but only those who come unto him and do his will shall receive eternal
life.
</p><p>
Do you believe this? I believe it! I know it, just as I know that God lives, and that Jesus is
the Christ, the Son of the living God. I know that his kingdom has been restored to earth in
these the latter days through the Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
If we will heed the word of the Lord through his servant and Prophet today, President David
O. McKay, the Lord shall heal our land; he shall give us eternal life. I so testify in the name
of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
