<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Responsibility of Membership in the Church</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder James A. Cullimore</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">James A. Cullimore, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 94-96</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters: How wonderful it is to be assembled here with you in this great
worldwide general conference of the Church. As I note the various representatives of stakes
from all over the world, I sense more than ever how completely this is a worldwide church. I am
grateful to be here and to represent you in whatever way I might, and to be of service in this
great church.
</p><p>
<b>The covenants we make</b>
</p><p>
Some of the facts that come to our attention in the line of our duty make me wonder if we take
as seriously as we should the covenants we have made as members of the Church: 
</p><p>
&mdash;The covenants made in baptism&mdash;wherein we "witness before the church that [we] have truly
repented of all . . . sins, and are willing to take upon [us] the name of Jesus Christ, having a
determination to serve him to the end, and truly manifest by [our] works that [we] have received
of the Spirit of Christ unto the remission of . . . sins." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/37#37">D&amp;C 20:37</a>)
</p><p>
&mdash;Promises made to our spouse and unto the Lord as we enter into the marriage covenant.
</p><p>
&mdash;All covenants made in the temple.
</p><p>
&mdash;Promises made to our bishop and stake president, branch president or mission president as we
accept assignments to offices in the Church.
</p><p>
&mdash;The oath and covenant of the priesthood. The obligations we accept as we are ordained to the
priesthood and act in its offices.
</p><p>
The Lord expects us to be obedient to our covenants. Great blessings are promised us as we are
obedient, both temporal and spiritual, the greatest of which is eternal life. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>)
Likewise, condemnation follows disobedience. The Lord expects us to be strong and conquering
as we exercise our agency.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of Church members</b>
</p><p>
President McKay said, in reference to our responsibilities as members of the Church:
"Membership in the Church carries with it the responsibility to overcome temptation, to battle
error, to improve the mind, and to develop one's spirit until it comes to the 'measure of the stature
of the fulness of Christ.' (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/13#13">Eph. 4:13</a>) Habits of intemperance and sensual pleasures should have been buried
in the waters of baptism. What folly to permit them to return when one realizes that not
happiness but misery is allied with indulgence in sin!" (<i>Man May Know for Himself</i> [Deseret
Book Co., 1967], p. 462.)
</p><p>
As we entered the waters of baptism, we covenanted with the Lord to be obedient and keep his
commandments. The Savior set the pattern in this; Nephi told his people the following: ". . . he
[the Savior] showeth unto the children of men that, according to the flesh he humbleth himself
before the Father, and witnesseth unto the Father that he would be
<i>obedient unto him in keeping his commandments</i>.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, after he was baptized with water the Holy Ghost descended upon him in the form of
a dove.
</p><p>
"And again, it showeth unto the children of men the straightness of the path, and the narrowness
of the gate, by which they should enter, he having set the example before them.
</p><p>
"And he said unto the children of men: Follow thou me. Wherefore, my beloved brethren, <i>can we</i>
<i>follow Jesus save we shall be willing to keep the commandments of the Father?"</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/7-10#7">2 Ne. 31:7-10</a> Italics added.)
</p><p>
It is the plan of the Lord that men will have their agency and are free to do as they so desire.
President McKay said on another occasion: "The mission of the Church is to assist mankind to
overcome evil and to cherish the good. It teaches that repentance is an eternal principle of
salvation." (<i>Pathways to Happiness</i> [Bookcraft, 1957], p. 190.)
</p><p>
<b>Stimulate others to serve God</b>
</p><p>
One of our great responsibilities is not only to live the gospel ourselves but also to stimulate in
the lives of every other member of the Church a great desire to serve the Lord. Alma was most
fervent in his approach to this great responsibility when he said: "O that I were an angel, and
could have the wish of mine heart, that I might go forth and speak with the trump of God, with a
voice to shake the earth, and cry repentance unto every people!
</p><p>
"Yea, I would declare unto every soul, as with a voice of thunder, repentance and the plan of
redemption, that they should repent and come unto our God, that there might not be more sorrow
upon all the face of the earth."
</p><p>
And then, as if he realized it would not be the will of the Lord to
be too forceful, as all must have their agency, he said: "But behold, I am a man and do sin in my
wish; for I ought to be content with the things which the Lord hath allotted unto me.
</p><p>
"I ought not to harrow up in my desires, the firm decree of a just God, for I know that he
granteth unto men according to their desire, whether it be unto death or unto life; yea, I know
that he allotteth unto men according to their wills, whether they be unto salvation or unto
destruction." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/1-4#1">Alma 29:1-4</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Righteous, active desires</b>
</p><p>
It is of utmost importance that we stimulate proper desires in our lives, by study, by teaching, by
constant activity. John A. Widtsoe wisely said: "Righteous desire, backed by a ready will and
honest prayer, works wonders in human lives. It reveals truth. It trains the will for righteousness.
It leads to increasing accomplishment. It is protection amidst the temptations and storms of life .
. .
</p><p>
"When such desire is coupled with obedience to law, the gates of heaven are thrown open to our
high eternal destiny. As our desires are, so are we . . .
</p><p>
"A man's desire should be his first concern, for no person can rise above his real desires. Neither
can a nation rise above the assembled desires of the people . . .
</p><p>
"Of course, desires are of value only when they drive us to action. Will must accompany desire.
Then high resolve is born. Desire is the design; will the execution of the design . . . When desire
and will move together, in the right direction, we become strong and conquering."
</p><p>
He said further: "Too many of us spend our hours wishing for heaven, when an active desire for
simple earthly blessings might form rounds in the ladder to celestial glory."
(<i>An Understandable Religion</i> [Deseret Book Co., 1944], pp. 70, 64-66.)
</p><p>
In the selection of the first Quorum of Twelve Apostles in this dispensation the Lord said: ". . .
by their desires and their works you shall know them." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/38#38">D&amp;C 18:38</a>)
</p><p>
Some good counsel was given to Hyrum Smith through revelation that could well be applied in
our own lives as we build faith.
</p><p>
According to your desires, yea, even according to your faith shall it be done unto you.
</p><p>
"Keep my commandments; hold your peace; appeal unto my Spirit; 
</p><p>
"Yea, cleave unto me with all your heart." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/11/17-19#17">D&amp;C 11:17-19</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Means to receive strength</b>
</p><p>
As we strive to keep the commandments, it is wonderful to know that the Lord has provided
means whereby we might receive strength. Through the influence of the Holy Spirit, the
understanding of the Father is conveyed to every creature. It is the means of man's constant
access to the Father. Modern revelation states: ". . . the Spirit giveth light to every man that
cometh into the world; and the Spirit enlighteneth every man through the world, that hearkeneth
to the voice of the Spirit." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/46#46">D&amp;C 84:46</a>)
</p><p>
The Lord has said plainly: "I, the Lord, am merciful and gracious unto those who fear me, and
delight to honor those who serve me in righteousness and in truth unto the end.
</p><p>
"Great shall be their reward and eternal shall be their glory.
</p><p>
"And to them will I reveal all mysteries . . . of my kingdom from days of old, and for ages to
come, will I make known unto them the good pleasures of my will concerning all things
pertaining to my kingdom.
</p><p>
"Yea, even the wonders of eternity shall they know, and things to come will I show them, even
the things of many generations.
</p><p>
"And their wisdom shall be great, and their understanding reach to heaven; and before them the
wisdom of the wise shall perish, and the understanding of the prudent shall come to naught.
</p><p>
"For . . . by my power will I make known unto them the secrets of my will." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/5-10#5">D&amp;C 76:5-10</a>)
</p><p>
The degree to which we receive help from the Lord for the guidance of our lives depends upon
ourselves. We must be in tune with the Spirit to receive and understand its message. We must be
worthy.
</p><p>
The guidance that we seek from our Heavenly Father greatly depends upon our obedience to
every truth known to us. By our good works we demonstrate to the Lord our obedience.
</p><p>
<b>Assurance from doing God's will</b>
</p><p>
The greatest assurance we may receive as to eternal life, and following President McKay's
direction, comes in "doing the will of the Father." The Savior said, "My doctrine is not mine, but
his that sent me.
</p><p>
"If any man will do his will, he will know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I
speak of myself." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/16-17#16">John 7:16-17</a>)
</p><p>
"And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his commandments.
</p><p>
"He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in
him.
</p><p>
"But whoso keepeth his word, in him verily is the love of God perfected; hereby know we that
we are in him." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/2/3-5#3">1 Jn. 2:3-5</a>)
</p><p>
Yes, membership in the Church carries with it the responsibility to live the gospel and overcome
temptations. May we always have a strong desire to serve the Lord, remembering that the surest
way to keep the faith is by being actively engaged in the work of the gospel.
I leave you my witness that this is his work in which we are engaged, and that he will bless us as we keep faithful and live the gospel, in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
