<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Most Vital Principle&mdash;Marriage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1946, pp. 35-39</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters: With the help of the Lord, I hope to present to you one of
the most vital principles connected with the gospel of Jesus Christ. And in order that I may
get it before us properly, I intend to read statements from President Brigham Young and other
Authorities, because their statements will have far greater weight than anything that I might
say. What I am going to talk about is marriage.
</p><p>
PRESIDENT BRIGHAM YOUNG'S COUNSEL ON MARRIAGE
</p><p>
President Brigham Young, in giving a counsel to the members of the Church said:
</p><p>
When a man and woman have received their endowments and sealings, and then had children
born to them afterwards, those children are legal heirs to the kingdom and to all its blessings
and promises, and they are the only ones that are on this earth. There is not a young man in
our community who would not be willing to travel from here to England to be married right,
if he understood things as they are; there is not a young woman in our community, who loves
the gospel and wishes its blessings, that would be married in any other way; they would live
unmarried until they. . . were as old as Sarah before she had Isaac born to her. Many of our
brethren have married off their children without taking this into consideration, and thinking it
a matter of little importance. I wish we all understood this in the light in which heaven
understands it (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, pp. 195-196, 1934 edition).
</p><p>
Again:
</p><p>
Be careful, O ye mothers in Israel, and do not teach your daughters in the future, as many of
them have been taught, to marry out of Israel. Woe to you who do it; you will lose your
crowns as sure as God lives (<i>Ibid.</i>).
</p><p>
Now, I would hardly dare say that. Again:
</p><p>
What was the cause of the first, or one of the first, curses that came upon Israel? I will tell
you. One of the first transgressions of the family called Israel, was their going to other
families or other nations to select partners. This was one of the great mistakes made by the
children of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, for they would go and marry with other families,
although the Lord had forbidden them to do so, and had given them a very strict and stringent
law on the subject. He commanded them not to marry among the Gentiles
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/1/1-6#1">Deut. 1:1-6</a>), but they did and
would do it. Inasmuch as they would not do what he required of them, then he gave them
what I call a portion of the law of carnal commandments. This law told them what they might
and whom they might not marry. It was referred to by the Savior and his
apostles, and it was a grievous yoke to place on the necks of any people; but as the children
of this family would run after Babylon, and after the pride and the vanity and evils of the
world, and seek to introduce them into Israel, the Lord saw fit to place this burden upon
them (<i>Ibid.</i>, pp. 196-197).
</p><p>
Again:
</p><p>
How is it with you, sisters? Do you distinguish between a man of God and a man of the
world? It is one of the strangest things that happens in my existence, to think that any man or
woman can love a being that will not receive the truth of heaven. The love this gospel
produces is far above the love of women; it is the love of God&mdash;the love of eternity&mdash;of eternal
lives (<i>Ibid.</i>).
</p><p>
ADVICE TO MARRY IN THE CHURCH
</p><p>
Now this from President Joseph F. Smith:
</p><p>
I would rather go myself to the grave than to be associated with a wife outside of the bonds
of the new and everlasting covenant. Now, I hold it just so sacred; but some members of the
Church do not so regard the matter. Some people feel that it does not make very much
difference whether a girl marries a man in the Church, full of the faith of the gospel, or an
unbeliever. Some of our young people have married outside of the Church; but very few of
those who have done it have failed to come to grief. I would like to see Latter-day Saint men
marry Latter-day Saint women; and Methodists marry Methodists, Catholics marry Catholics;
and Presbyterians marry Presbyterians, and so on to the limit. Let them keep within the pale
of their own faith and church, and marry and intermarry there, and let the Latter-day Saints
do the same thing in their Church. Then we will see who comes out best in the end.
(<i>Gospel Doctrine</i>, p. 380, 1919 edition).
</p><p>
This from Elder Orson Pratt, which was delivered by appointment and endorsed by President
Brigham Young:
</p><p>
We cannot feel justified in closing this article on the subject of marriage without saying a few
words to unmarried females in this Church.
</p><p>
(May I pause at this point long enough to say that while he is speaking to females, it is just as
true of males, and we could insert that term just as well as to speak of females, so keep that
in mind.)
</p><p>
You will clearly perceive, from the revelation which God has given, that you can never
obtain a fulness of glory, without being married to a righteous man for time and for all
eternity. If you marry a man who receives not the gospel, you lay a foundation for sorrow in
this world, besides losing the privilege of enjoying the society of a husband in eternity. You
forfeit your right to an endless increase of immortal lives. And even the children which you
may be favoured with in this life, will not be entrusted to your charge in eternity, but you
will be left in that world without a husband, without a family, without a kingdom, without
any means of enlarging yourselves, being subject to the principalities and powers who are
counted worthy of families, and kingdoms, and thrones, and the increase of dominions
forever. To them you will be servants and angels&mdash;that is, provided that your conduct should
be such as to secure this measure of glory. Can it be possible that any females, after knowing
these things, will suffer themselves to keep company with persons out of this Church?
</p><p>
It matters not how great the morality of such persons may be, nor how kind they may be to
you, they are not numbered with the people of God; they are not in the way of salvation, they
cannot save themselves nor their families, and after what God has revealed upon this subject,
you cannot be justified, for one moment, in keeping their company. It would be infinitely
better for you to suffer poverty and tribulation with the people of God, than to place
yourselves under the power of those who will not embrace the great truth of heaven. By
marrying an unbeliever, you place yourselves in open disobedience to the command of God
requiring his people to gather together. Do you expect to be saved in direct violation of the
command of heaven? (<i>Millennial Star</i>, XV: 584).
</p><p>
ONLY COVENANTS MADE BY GOD ARE ETERNAL
</p><p>
I have some other quotations on another phase, but I want to refer now to what the Lord has
said in a revelation to the Church.
</p><p>
Will I accept of an offering, saith the Lord, that is not made in my name? Or will I receive at
your hands that which I have not appointed? And will I appoint unto you, saith the Lord,
except it be by law, even as I and my Father ordained unto you, before the world was? I am
the Lord thy God; and I give unto you this commandment&mdash;that no man shall come unto the
Father but by me or by my word, which is my law, saith the Lord. And everything that is in
the world, whether it be ordained of men, by thrones, or principalities, or powers, or things of
name, whatsoever they may be, that are not by me or by my word, saith the Lord, shall be
thrown down, and shall not remain after men are dead, neither in nor after the resurrection,
saith the Lord your God. For whatsoever things remain are by me; and whatsoever things are
not by me shall be shaken and destroyed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/9-14#9">D&amp;C 132:9-14</a>).
</p><p>
Now, I challenge anybody on the face of the earth to disprove this argument. I say it is sound.
It is common sense. It is the gospel of Jesus Christ. It cannot be successfully disputed. That
being true, then the Lord says:
</p><p>
Therefore, if a man marry him a wife in the world, and he marry her not by me nor by my
word, and he covenant with her so long as he is in the world and she with him, their covenant
and marriage are not of force when they are dead, and when they are out of the world;
therefore, they are not bound by any law when they are out of the world. Therefore, when
they are out of the world they neither marry nor are given in marriage; but are appointed
angels in heaven; which angels are ministering servants, to minister for those who are worthy
of a far more, and an exceeding, and an eternal weight of glory
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/15-16#15">D&amp;C 132:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
IMPORTANCE OF ETERNAL MARRIAGE
</p><p>
There is much more here, and you are acquainted with it. I do not need to read it, but I want
to call your attention to the fact that a great many of our beautiful girls and our fine young
men that have been born under the covenant are being married out of the Church and out of
the temple of God. Furthermore, I have discovered by reading the newspapers that the parents
of many of these young people seem to rejoice in it, and so they put big articles and fine
pictures in the papers in regard to the entertainments, the receptions, that are going to be
given, and they seem to be very proud of the fact that their daughters are to
be married or their sons are to be married and they are going to be married by some minister
of some other church, maybe by a bishop of this Church who can only marry them for
time&mdash;he cannot marry them for eternity&mdash;and they seem to be happy about it. I do not know
how they can, in the face of all that the Lord has revealed. For every contract, every bond,
every covenant that is made that is not according to the Lord's will and commandment, and
enforced by his law will of necessity come to an end
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/7#7">D&amp;C 132:7</a>). These young people who seem to be so
happy now, when they rise in the resurrection, and find themselves in the condition in which
they will find themselves, then there will be weeping and wailing and gnashing of teeth,
bitterness of soul, and they have brought it upon themselves because of their lack of faith and
understanding of the gospel, and from, I am sorry to say, the encouragement they have
received many times from their own parents.
</p><p>
I am quite satisfied in my own mind that the parents are not teaching their children in the
home the importance of marriage as the Lord has revealed it. Out in the world they have a
false notion about marriage, because they have not the guidance of the Holy Ghost, and they
cannot understand and properly interpret the scriptures.
</p><p>
The first marriage that was ever performed in this world, that is on this earth, let me say; not
in this world, but on this earth&mdash;was performed before there was any death. What the Lord
said in answering the question of the Jews:
</p><p>
. . . What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/6#6">Matt. 19:6</a>),
</p><p>
means nothing more nor less than this: that where God joins in marriage, man cannot put it
asunder. And the Lord never does anything just for time. Everything is for eternity.
</p><p>
TEMPLE FOR WORTHY MEMBERS
</p><p>
To those who are satisfied with a marriage for time only, I want to raise a warning voice, to
both parents and to the children who have that sort of idea. Of course there are people who
are not worthy to go to the temple, and therefore should not go to the temple. No one should
go to the temple except those who are worthy, as the Lord has said, "who have overcome by
faith," and are cleansed and are just and true
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/53#53">D&amp;C 76:53</a>).
Then they can go to the temple. If they are
unclean, if they lack the faith, they had better stay out until they get the faith and are clean.
</p><p>
I wanted to say those few things.
</p><p>
LORD'S COMMAND TO MULTIPLY
</p><p>
Now, just for a moment or two in regard to another matter closely connected with this. When
young people are married properly, the Lord commands them to multiply
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
Now that is not in accord with the teachings of the world, nor the practice of the world,
especially the practice, and so I want to read one or two other passages now; this from
President Young:
</p><p>
There are multitudes of pure and holy spirits waiting to take tabernacles, now what is our
duty?&mdash;To prepare tabernacles for them; to take a course that will not tend to drive those
spirits into the families of the wicked, where they will be trained in wickedness, debauchery,
and every species of crime. It is the duty of every righteous man and woman to prepare
tabernacles for all the spirits they can.
</p><p>
To check the increase of our race has its advocates among the influential and powerful circles
of society in our nation and in other nations. The same practice existed forty-five years ago,
and various devices were used by married persons to prevent the expenses and responsibilities
of a family of children, which they must have incurred had they suffered nature's laws to rule
pre-eminent. That which was practiced then in fear and against reproving conscience, is now
boldly trumpeted abroad as one of the best means of ameliorating the miseries and sorrows of
humanity. Infanticide is very prevalent in our nation. It is a crime that comes within the
purview of the law, and is therefore not so boldly practiced as is the other equally great
crime, which, no doubt, to a great extent, prevents the necessity of infanticide. The unnatural
style of living, the extensive use of narcotics, the attempt to destroy and dry up the fountains
of life, are fast destroying the American element of the nation; it is passing away before the
increase of the more healthy, robust, honest, and less sinful class of the people which are
pouring into the country daily from the old world (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, p. 197,
1943 edition).
</p><p>
Now I think you bishops, you presidents of stakes, and you presidents of the quorums of the
priesthood, ought to consider these things most carefully, and be prepared to teach the people
that which the Lord would have them taught, and when our teachers go to visit them in their
homes, let them teach the revelations of the Living God and magnify their callings. This I
pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
