<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Faith&mdash;and the Polynesians</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1958, pp. 16-19</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I am indeed grateful for the splendid spirit of this conference session
this morning. I hope what I have to say will not detract from the spirit of the messages given. 
I would like to touch upon a few things connected with the New Zealand Temple dedication
mentioned by Brother Hinckley.
</p><p>
Since the last general conference of the Church Sister Stapley and I have enjoyed the great
privilege and blessing of accompanying our beloved President David O. McKay, Sister
McKay, Elder and Sister Marion G. Romney and others to New Zealand for the dedication of
the new temple in that faraway land.  Brother Gordon Hinckley and his wife had preceded us
there to finalize the preparation for the dedication and opening of the temple for ordinance
work. He mentioned the welcome and reception accorded the official Church party by the
Polynesian Saints. It was a tremendous tribute and demonstration of love and affection for all
of us, but more particularly for their beloved President and Prophet, "Tumuaki" David O.
McKay.
</p><p>
It was a glorious spectacle, so different, colorful and unique that the sweet memory of the
occasion will remain forever. Each Polynesian group, in native costume, entertained with
pageantry, song, and dance for the space of three and a half hours.  I believe it is the only
time in the history of the world that four such widely scattered Polynesian peoples have been
brought together where each featured its individual native entertainment to welcome an
official party.  Such an assembly of mixed talent may never happen again, for it isn't likely
that another similar event of such importance will occur to bring them together.
</p><p>
The majority of the Saints of the South Pacific attending the temple dedication activities did
so, as Brother Hinckley has indicated, at great personal sacrifice.  Ever since the building of a
temple was announced they have been saving in earnest for that important and historic
dedication day.  To them it was the spiritual opportunity of their lives, the fulfillment of their
prayers and dreams.  It would be difficult for the people of the world, not knowing the sacred
value and eternal nature of temple ordinances, to understand why people possess such strong
religious beliefs and faith that would cause them not only to save money, but also to sell their
cars, mortgage furniture and other chattels to raise sufficient funds to visit a temple.  To those
who do understand, no sacrifice is too great to achieve the greatest blessings of their lives&mdash;the
holy temple endowment with the ordinances and sealings that bind husband
and wife and families together in an eternal family relationship and companionship.
</p><p>
In visiting with this mixed group of Saints the evidences of a living and motivating faith were
found on every hand. Tears of happiness flowed freely down the cheeks of these faithful and
worthy people as the significance of these eventful days unfolded more clearly to their
understanding.  Each session of the dedication was a glorious spiritual experience. To watch
the faces of the Saints was a reflection of the joy and happiness they felt.
</p><p>
The simple and trusting faith of the Polynesian Saints was reflected in the answer of Brother
Lafi Toilupi to President McKay's query, "Can you do it?" when he asked Brother Toilupi if
he could translate the dedicatory prayer from English into the Samoan tongue. Brother Toilupi
replied sincerely and humbly, "I can do it if you will bless me." President McKay answered,
"I do bless you," and the translation was accomplished perfectly regardless of the fact the
limited Samoan language does not have equivalent words corresponding in meaning to the
English.
</p><p>
The New Zealand Temple, situated on a prominence overlooking the valley, with its
remarkable floodlighting effects, stands out majestically at night with a brilliance of lighting
intensity which can be seen for miles around, and truly represents "a candle of the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/20/27#27">Prov. 20:27</a>) to
reveal light and truth in the midst of error and spiritual darkness. The favorable publicity of
all happenings there, revealing the purpose of temples, Church beliefs, principles, and
practices, gave to the people of New Zealand and Australia new knowledge and gospel light
which has stimulated a tremendous spiritual upsurge to the work of the Church.
</p><p>
My soul is full of gratitude for the restored gospel of Christ and the blessed power it has to
enrich the lives of people.  I bear humble testimony, my brothers and sisters, that the gospel
taught by the Latter-day Saints is the true gospel of God's kingdom which the Savior testified
"shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end
come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
The missionary system of the Church was established by revelation of the Lord to fulfil this
latter-day obligation. He declared to the Prophet Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
"And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I
have chosen in these last days.<br />
"And they shall go forth and none shall stay them, for I the Lord have commanded them.<br />
"Behold, this is mine authority and the authority of my servants . . . O inhabitants of the
earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4-6#4">D&amp;C 1:4-6</a>).
</p><p>
During the spring and summer Sister Stapley and I visited three Church missions: the two in
Australia, and the Northwestern States Mission.  I personally interviewed over 350 young
missionaries.  I pay sincere and humble tribute to them for their faithful devotion to a great
cause.  I know many families make tremendous financial sacrifices to support their missionary
sons and daughters while away from home in the service of the ministry. The compensations,
however, for faithful and devoted service are rich and rewarding.  Faith is increased;
testimonies are strengthened; principles of righteousness and truth are acquired which build
into the missionary fundamental moral and spiritual values which upgrade his character
attainments for successful and happy living. With few exceptions, the more than 5000
missionaries now serving represent the Church honorably and effectively, and are a great
credit to it.  Thousands of converts each year result from their devoted service.
</p><p>
Recently a mission president reporting his mission made this significant statement: "If the
Church were not true, the 5000 missionaries representing it would have proved it long ago." I
have often thought how true that statement is.  Actuated as they are by the same spirit, the
Holy Ghost, and officiating by the authority of the true priesthood of God, it is not too
difficult to understand the truth of the mission president's statement.
</p><p>
The tempo of the proselyting program has stepped up in Australia, and with
nineteen new lovely buildings to meet and worship in and to carry forward the full Church
program, prospects for increased conversions are constantly improving.  The chapel-building
program alone has set forward the work of the Church many years.  From the beginning of
construction of a beautiful and serviceable chapel in one small branch to the time of
dedication, thirty-three converts were baptized and twenty-five passive members reactivated
who are now in full fellowship.
</p><p>
In two widely separated towns of the Australian Mission where lovely buildings are
completed and in service, the mayors attended the appointed meetings to bid us welcome. 
One, acquainted with the Word of Wisdom, told how he had been prevailed upon to give up
the habit of tobacco and of the personal satisfaction he experienced in doing so.  He
complimented the Church and its people for building such a lovely edifice in which to
worship and to foster cultural activities for the wholesome and broad enrichment of their
lives.  He also pledged to them the full support of his office and the town council he
represented.  It was a beautiful tribute and a marvelous pledge of co-operation.  The second
mayor also gave like praise and commendation and declared that the Church building was
most attractive and inviting, which added spiritual strength and prestige to their progressive
city.  He expressed the hope that the work of the Church would prosper there, and wished the
people every success in their religious program. He promised, in conclusion, to return again.
He made a profound observation by saying that to many people churches were like
elevators&mdash;they could just get on at any time and be taken to heaven without the good life and
good works to their credit.  He firmly believed faith and works go together.
</p><p>
At the dedication of the New Zealand Church College, the Prime Minister of New Zealand
gave an interesting and challenging talk most favorable to the Church and its program to
serve and bless people.  He took exception to the organized unfriendly group opposing the
Church efforts there, who questioned our right to Christian status, and who also were guilty of
maligning the integrity of the Church leaders in Zion.  He called attention to a few of our
brethren who were or are now in high United States government positions, whom he was
privileged to know personally.  Some had befriended and supported him, which permitted the
Prime Minister to become acquainted with their qualities of goodness and sound political
integrity and leadership.  He made particular reference to Elder Ezra Taft Benson, with praise
for his integrity and excellent government service. He indicated favorableness to religious
education in the schools of New Zealand, and praised the character and teachings of Jesus
which he encouraged all to accept and follow.
</p><p>
Such recognition and unsolicited favorable contributions from outstanding leaders not of our
faith are helpful to the work.  Their comments call attention to a letter I received from a
non-member friend of mine while we were yet in New Zealand, who closed by saying, "May
the propagation of the Latter-day Saint faith ever spread over the world." Such is the
encouragement of those who know us best.
</p><p>
The faraway converts of New Zealand and Australia&mdash;and I listened to many&mdash;teach and preach
the same truths, principles, and gospel ordinances as orthodox as we do here. Their
testimonies are fervent, spiritual, and convincing.  To associate with and listen to them, one
would think and feel as if he were in the congregations of the Saints at home. Truly, all who
belong to this Church and yield obedience to its teachings are actuated by the same spirit, the
Holy Ghost, whose function it is to guide into all truth, to bear witness of the Father and the
Son, and to keep the Saints of God united wherever they are. What a blessing it is to be
guided by a power which prevents misunderstandings and divisions among the true followers
of Christ.
</p><p>
I would like to share with you briefly three choice experiences resulting from these mission
tours.  A good woman, called upon by the missionaries while tracting in her neighborhood,
advised them that her niece had joined the Church eight months previously. "Your
Church has done so much for her," she said, and then asked, "Can you do
the same for me?"
</p><p>
A woman investigator, after a few home visits from the missionaries, said to her husband,
"The elders take something with them when they leave our home; when they return that
something is here." They both recognized that "something" present when attending Church
services held by the elders. "What is it?" this good woman asked. The answer came to her and
she exclaimed, "The priesthood of God," to which her husband agreed.
</p><p>
A faithful sister, eighty-nine years of age but young in spirit, related to me this testimony and
experience. As a young woman, her father informed her a new scripture was to come, and the
Church presenting it would be true. She was greatly impressed by this statement and
remembered it.  Her father passed away, and time moved on, but still the new scripture had
not come to her attention.  Some years later two missionaries knocked at her door. When she
received them they introduced to her the Book of Mormon which they advised was a new
scripture revealed by God.  She immediately recalled the words of her father.  She had her
witness. She said to me, "I didn't need the elders to teach me the gospel.  I knew they
represented the true Church." She was quickly converted and baptized by them.  For over fifty
years this good sister has remained a faithful and devoted member.  Her home has been, and
is now, a rallying point for missionary work.  The evening we spent with her was enriched by
her testimony and charm of character.
</p><p>
How wonderful it is, my brothers and sisters, that the true gospel of our Lord can be
understood by the simple, yet is so profound it can challenge the most learned thinker with its
depths of knowledge and wisdom.  The gospel has the power to bring people together in love
and understanding and give purpose and wise direction to life.  Our message to the world is
one of faith in God and his beloved Son, Jesus Christ, our Savior and Redeemer.  It is a
message of brotherhood, hope, peace, and salvation, and is therefore of great importance and
value to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people. We possess the truth, the fulness of the
gospel of Christ with all its glorious principles, high moral standards of conduct, ideals of
noble character, and all saving ordinances for the joy and eternal happiness of mankind.
</p><p>
We cordially invite all people to investigate the restored Church of Christ, and accept its
teachings and way of life as revealed for their salvation and glory.  President Richards made
an excellent appeal in his opening address here this morning. I testify, my brothers and sisters,
that God has established his work for the last time among the children of men, and
preparations are now going forward for the second coming of our Lord and Savior, Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
God help us, my brothers and sisters, to be true to our obligations as members of his
kingdom, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
