<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">One Hundred Percenters</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Carl W. Buehner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Carl W. Buehner, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 31-34</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, it is always an honor to greet you at a general conference of the
Church and to bear you my testimony of the divinity of this great, ever-growing, latter-day
work. What I have read, heard, and observed concerning serious conditions confronting this
world in which we live makes me more appreciative than ever before of the testimony I have
of things eternal.
</p><p>
I am sure we are all interested in security, and would like to say to all people living that if we
are interested in security, we should live close to the teachings of the God of this land, who is
Jesus Christ, for he has said, ". . . and though the heavens and the earth pass
away, my word shall not pass away"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/38#38">D&amp;C 1:38</a>).
I think more people than ever before
are turning their hearts to religion for an answer to some of the perplexing problems we face.
</p><p>
I find great joy in my work in the Church, and I hope it will always be my desire to have the
work of the Church come first. I like people who put "first things" first in the Church.
</p><p>
It is very encouraging to know that progress is being made all along the line. I enjoy my
experiences in the stakes with you people.
</p><p>
Recently, a young man speaking at a stake quarterly conference said: "I am a very important
person in my ward. I hold the office of a priest. I am the only priest in my priests' quorum.
In our quorum, it is either one-hundred percent or nothing." It did not take long for this
young man to prove to us that he was a hundred percenter. I admire the young men and
young women who are achieving to be hundred percenters by the standards with which we
measure them. I am sure we cannot measure all of their activities, but many of them are
making remarkable progress. This is even carrying over to some of our bishops and some of
our other leaders.
</p><p>
I learned not long ago while attending a Fathers' and Sons' banquet in the Summit Stake that
one bishop in a ward&mdash;and I guess he has been the bishop a long time or else it is the
continuous record of two bishops&mdash;said they have not lost a boy to inactivity in their ward
for thirteen years.
</p><p>
In another stake I attended, I heard a bishop make a similar report, but his was for six years,
and still a third bishop in another stake said, "We haven't lost a boy in our ward for five
years." Then I began hoping for the day when we could say to the whole Church, "We have
not lost a boy or a girl in the Church this year, or for five years, or ten years." I think we are
moving forward and accomplishing things that we have never accomplished before.
</p><p>
I was interested in hearing a young Latter-day Saint girl speak on the topic, "When and How
Does a Young Woman Make Preparation for Marriage in the Temple." As she developed her
subject, she said: "I have come to one conclusion. There is a right way to get married, and
there is a wrong way to get married. If some young man does not propose to me who can
take me to the temple, I will convert one who can. I have a desire to be married the Lord's
way, and I am going to insist that the man whom I marry is one who can take me to the
House of the Lord."
</p><p>
I heard another little experience of a man who had recently been asked to supervise a district
in ward teaching. He said, "Bishop, I will accept on one basis, that we do one-hundred
percent ward teaching, and when I am unable to maintain one-hundred percent, I quit." I got a
letter from his bishop the other day, who said, "For forty months, he has had one-hundred
percent, and we see no reason why this will not continue indefinitely."
</p><p>
There come to us many experiences of devoted and dedicated ward teachers to the
ever-expanding ward teaching program. I learned of a pair of ward teachers who travel 180
miles each month to visit three families, and they always get the three families visited. In
another stake&mdash;I think in Florida&mdash;two ward teachers travel 160 miles each month to visit the
families in their district, and they are always doing one-hundred percent teaching. If I
remember right, we had a report some time ago of two teachers in one of the Canadian stakes
who traveled approximately 4,000 miles a year to visit those in their district, and they
faithfully visited every family each month.
</p><p>
I learned of a faithful ward teacher up in the Ogden area who has just completed fifty-six
years as a ward teacher with a perfect record of never missing one month in the fifty-six
years' time that he has been a teacher, even though for the first ten years or more he had
twenty-five families in his district. He underwent a serious operation; he had some other
difficult problems, but his perfect record was maintained in spite of these conditions. He is
held in high esteem by the families in his district.
</p><p>
I learned of two high priests who impressed me very much. One of them is ninety-two years
of age and served as a ward teacher for seventy years. The other at the age of ninety-four had
been a ward teacher for eighty-two years, having started when he was twelve
years of age. This good brother indicated that he had only missed visiting his district four or
five times in this eighty-two year period. In my humble opinion, I think when men, who give
this type of service to the responsibilities that come to them, report to the other side, someone
is going to stand there with outstretched arms, welcoming them into the kingdom of our
Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
The ward teaching program is one of the oldest programs in the Church, having come to the
Prophet Joseph Smith by revelation sometime between the first and sixth day of April 1830,
in what is known as the twentieth section of the Doctrine and Covenants
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/51#51">D&amp;C 20:51</a>). The program is
designed to reach the fireside of every family in the Church with a spiritual message at least
once each month and more often if necessary.
</p><p>
Ward teachers carry a challenging responsibility, that is, to watch over the Church. Residing
within a ward teaching district may be families and individuals whose activities represent a
commendable peak, while there may be some totally indifferent to things spiritual. You may
be interested to know that at the present time there are in excess of 139,000 men and boys
serving as ward teachers in the organized stakes of Zion. During the year 1958, 3,386,000
visits were made to the homes of these families, and this represents eighty percent of the
families visited every month during the year, which is the highest record we have achieved in
the Church.
</p><p>
Ward teachers are expected to promote the spirit of goodwill; be prepared to meet the
criticism of those who find fault. They are always to defend the Church, uphold its doctrine,
and support its leaders; to strengthen those who are offended or weak in the faith; to comfort
those who mourn or have sorrow; to be among the first to offer assistance in cases of
emergency and sickness; and to deliver a message of good cheer to the discouraged, the
unfortunate, the aged, and the homebound. Their message should be gauged to meet the
understanding of both the young and the old in each family.
</p><p>
If ward teachers faithfully perform their duties, each family&mdash;and for that matter, each
member who is willing&mdash;will find themselves enfolded in the arms of the Church. In some
instances faithful ward teachers have been responsible for bringing people into the Church. A
member now residing in Arizona made this report to the stake president in my presence. He
said: "You do not know who I am. A few years ago, I came here from the East, having been
retired because of poor health, and I was told that if I came to Arizona I may have an
opportunity to prolong my life. I had a little money, and I invested in some real estate. The
city grew out my way, and my property became very valuable. I sold it, bought more, and I
have made a lot of money. In short, this is what has happened to me.
</p><p>
"I have recovered my health. I have become a member of your Church, first having been
contacted by the ward teachers, who had the stake missionaries sent to me. I have made a lot
of money. Now I would like to show my appreciation for the goodness of the Lord to me by
having you select a number of young people who might serve as missionaries, but who
haven't the finances to take care of their own expenses. You call them and send me the bill."
I thought that was a nice way to express his appreciation.
</p><p>
I should like to close with another experience I have heard related in which ward teachers
entered a family's home who were rather lukewarm, and even a little bitter, when the ward
teachers came to pay a visit.
</p><p>
In a brusk voice, the head of the family said, "I am a very busy man. You can have fifteen
minutes to get on with your message." This startled the ward teachers, and because their
experience had not been too great, they paused and wondered just how to approach the
subject. They learned about some of the children in the family, and discovered among them, a
little girl who was going to turn eight years of age in just a few days. While they were talking
to the children, the head of the family said, "Five minutes are gone; you have ten minutes
left." They inquired a little further into the family, and after a few more minutes, the
man reminded them again that they had five minutes left. In desperation, the
ward teachers suggested that the family kneel down and have prayer with them before they
left. This they did, and during the prayer, the ward teacher prayed that the Lord would protect
this little girl who was about to become eight years of age, that nothing harmful would
happen to her but that she might be baptized a member of the Church.
</p><p>
The following day, this man was mowing hay in the field behind his home. A number of
children were playing in the yard, among whom was his little daughter. While making one of
the rounds with his tractor, the wheel of the tractor went over a mound. As he quickly looked
around, he observed that his daughter was missing. A sickening feeling overcame him. He
went to the mound, pushing aside the hay, and deep below was his little daughter, who
looking up said, "Daddy, don't tell them where I am. I am hiding from them." The prayer of
the ward teacher had been heard. The little girl's life had been preserved, and needless to say,
the family's reaction to the ward teachers was from this time forward, completely reversed.
</p><p>
May we all have a desire to fulfil our assignments faithfully and well, and if possible, be
hundred percenters. I cannot help but be reminded of the statement that the Savior made: "Be
ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>). To a
great degree, we can accomplish this one-hundred percent perfection.
</p><p>
I leave you my testimony of the divinity of this great work, and my blessing, in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
