<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Greatest of All Blessings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 67-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This is truly an inspiring sight. I have thrilled with the messages that have been given here at
this conference. I am thrilled with the progress of the missionary work and the growth of the
Church throughout its length and breadth. This is truly a blessed people and a choice
generation in which to live.
</p><p>
The gospel of Jesus Christ has been given to people throughout the earth at various times,
even at the time of Adam and the time of Noah and coming down to
the time of Abraham, who was given a very significant promise. Speaking to Abraham, the
Lord said:
</p><p>
"... I give unto thee a promise that this right shall continue in thee, and in thy seed after thee
[that is to say, the literal seed, or the seed of the body] shall all the families of the earth be
blessed, even with the blessings of the Gospel, which are the blessings of salvation, even of
life eternal" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/2/11#11">Abr. 2:11</a>).
</p><p>
This is the time and generation when this blessing is being fulfilled. The blessings of the
gospel are coming to all the peoples of the earth. The Lord is truly touching their hearts and
opening the way for them to receive the gospel.
</p><p>
The Lord is also assisting in other ways which I have mentioned here before, I believe, and I
cannot help continually being grateful for the outpouring of knowledge which has come upon
the earth since the restoration of the gospel, which makes it possible for this, gospel to be
taught to all the people of the earth through the modern facilities that have been developed
and prepared and which continue to grow. I am very thankful and grateful for these facilities.
</p><p>
<i>The Church Section</i> of the News recently mentioned the number of copies of the Book of
Mormon being printed&mdash;nearly 500,000 copies are being printed annually and sent throughout
the world. The facilities that make it possible to send the Book of Mormon to the ends of the
earth, among the various peoples of the earth, as has been indicated here by other speakers,
are peculiar to our Church. Not only the Book of Mormon but also much other Church
literature is being translated into many languages so that not only we of the English speaking
peoples may have the gospel, but also many others throughout the earth.
</p><p>
This is truly a choice generation. I am sure there is no blessing given but what there is an
obligation. Where much is given, much is expected. We have heard from many speakers at
this conference of our obligation to teach the gospel, to warn our neighbors, and above all to
live the gospel ourselves. I would like just briefly to refer to a revelation given by the Lord.
In section 41 of the Doctrine and Covenants, he said:
</p><p>
"Hearken and hear, O ye my people, saith the Lord and your God, ye whom I delight to bless
with the greatest of all blessings, ye that hear me; and ye that hear me not will I curse, that
have professed my name, with the heaviest of all cursings"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/41/1#1">D&amp;C 41:1</a>).
</p><p>
This is a strong warning, but I believe truly that the Lord means what he says. He has given
us the blessings; he continues to pour out his blessings upon us in rich abundance; and then
he gives the warning that we who have accepted the gospel, if we do not live up to these
covenants, he will pour out upon us "the heaviest of all cursings."
</p><p>
I could not help thinking when Brother Hinckley was speaking about Hiroshima, that this
summer I visited again at Oakridge, Tennessee, and found that the process which developed
the atomic bomb which was dropped on Hiroshima is now so obsolete that that process is no
longer in operation. If we think of what might happen to this world if the people of this world
do not keep the commandments of the Lord, we cannot stretch our imagination far enough to
imagine what the Lord might pour out upon this generation when he says, he might pour out
upon us "the heaviest of all cursings." All the blessings and all the scientific developments
which have been given to us, might be turned upon us to our condemnation.
</p><p>
I pray the Lord's blessings upon us that we will heed his teachings, that we will teach our
neighbor and develop righteousness throughout this earth.
</p><p>
The history generally given to us in the Book of Mormon and all this world's history is a
repetition of righteousness with peace and prosperity, and with unrighteousness there is war
and desolation. This shall be repeated throughout the life of this earth, and we are no
exception.
</p><p>
May the Lord's blessings be with us, that we may ever be faithful, keeping the
commandments of the Lord and doing that which he desires of us in teaching the gospel to
our neighbors, our friends, our relatives; and so live the gospel that we will be that kind of
missionary, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
