<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"One Lord, One Faith, One Baptism"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 44-47</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We Latter-day Saints believe the Bible to be the word of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/8#8">A of F 1:8</a>). It is a faithful record of the
Lord's dealing with men down through the ages. It shows that the Lord desires that mankind
should worship him intelligently, not as some incomprehensible being, but as their loving
Father in heaven.
</p><p>
To accomplish this, God revealed himself to men from time to time so that they could see
him and hear him and know him. He revealed himself personally, actually appearing to his
prophets, and he talked with them face to face, even as a man "speaketh to his friend" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/33/11#11">Ex. 33:11</a>).
</p><p>
These appearances of God to man, and by this I mean personal visitations, for that is what the
Bible describes, came periodically through the generations of the past. The Lord was not
content to give one and only one mighty revelation of himself to serve as a foundation for
faith through all time to come. He knew that men are changeable, often drifting into by; and
forbidden paths, and that a constant reminder is necessary to keep them in the right way.
</p><p>
The Bible shows how true that is, for even though the Lord did appear time and again
anciently, the people still drifted toward other religions, at times going into what seemed to be
complete apostasy from the truth, even setting up false gods of their own making.
</p><p>
But the Lord loved his children and desired to save them. He knew they could not be saved in
ignorance nor in the false religions of their contemporaries. Only the truth could save. So to
bring them back into line as they strayed away, he repeatedly gave new revelations of himself,
restoring the true knowledge of the nature of God and pointing to the right way of salvation.
By revealing himself to his living prophets, he showed the people the difference between their
own false gods and the true and Living God.
</p><p>
This became a pattern with him, as is shown so clearly in the scriptures. It is a well-marked
pattern, which is: that as men fell away and lost the truth, God in turn restored his truth to
them again by means of new revelations of himself.
</p><p>
There is only one way to combat error, and that is with the truth. If men lost the truth, they
could only find it by receiving it again from the Lord, and that would entail new revelation
from the heavens.
</p><p>
As such revelation was required in the past, God gave it, and when there was no prophet on
the earth to receive his revelation because of the apostasy of the people, he raised up new
prophets, spoke through them, and appeared personally to them, thus restoring the knowledge
of his true nature so that men could worship him intelligently in spirit and in truth.
</p><p>
Let us point to a few Bible examples of what we say. God walked and talked with Adam and
Eve. They knew what he was like, and they received commandments from him, but many of
their descendants were not true to the faith. By the time of Noah, all mankind was apostate
and as a result was destroyed in the flood, all except Noah and his family. God raised up
Noah as a prophet and talked with both him and his sons, revealing himself to them.
Therefore they knew God and worshiped him as a result of obtaining that knowledge.
</p><p>
Surely, as Jesus said, this is life eternal, "that they might know thee the only true God"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
Noah and his family knew the Lord, but as time went on their descendants went astray until
the days of Abraham when there was much wickedness in the earth. But the Lord followed
his pattern, and as men fell away from the truth he revealed himself to them again, this time to
Abraham, with whom he talked personally, and then to Isaac and to Jacob.
</p><p>
But the believers were few in that day. When Jacob took his family into
Egypt to escape the famine, the whole house of Israel numbered only seventy people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/1/5#5">Ex. 1:5</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/10/22#22">Deut. 10:22</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/14#14">Acts 7:14</a>). In
Egypt the Israelites multiplied and became numerous. Then tragedy came again. They left the
teachings of their fathers, and began worshiping like the Egyptians, who were idolaters. They
became so involved that later on they made a golden calf of their own and worshiped before
it.
</p><p>
The Lord determined to bring his people out of Egypt and restore the truth to them. This
would entail another new revelation, but to whom would he reveal himself? To Pharaoh on
his throne? To the doubting elders of Israel?
</p><p>
He kept to his pattern and raised up an unspoiled man to become his prophet&mdash;a shepherd
whose name was Moses. To him he spoke. To him he appeared. To him he gave power to
lead the children of Israel out of Egypt.
</p><p>
When they reached Sinai, God came down upon the Mount and talked again face to face with
Moses (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/34/10#10">Deut. 34:10</a>).
Seventy of the elders of Israel went into the Mount with Moses, and there they saw
the God of Israel, and "he laid not his hand upon them," the scripture says, but "they saw
God, and did eat and drink" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/24/9-10#9">Ex. 24:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
Those seventy elders with Moses were now qualified to preach to the people and testify of the
true nature of the Deity, for they had seen him themselves and visited with him and heard his
voice.
</p><p>
For a time the people were faithful after this new revelation, but then wickedness came
among them. Doubt returned, many drifted into the forbidden religions of their neighbors, and
apostasy came upon them as a people Do you recall the difficulties of Elijah, the prophet,
with the wicked King Ahab who led his whole nation astray? Do you remember the influence
of Jezebel, and do you recall the problems which faced Elisha and Isaiah?
</p><p>
In the days of Jeremiah the apostasy was so great that this prophet was cast into a dungeon
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/38/6#6">Jer. 38:6</a>).
When John the Baptist ministered among the people, they were so far astray that he referred
to them as a generation of vipers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/7#7">Matt. 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
Then came the ministry of the Savior. He was a manifestation of the true nature of God. He
told the people that he resembled the Father (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/9#9">John 14:9</a>).
Paul said Jesus was in the express image of the Father's person
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/1/3#3">Heb. 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
But he was also in the likeness of other men about him&mdash;his disciples and others. He was so
much like them that the crucifiers could not identify him in a crowd. They had to bribe Judas
to point him out with a betrayer's kiss so that they would not arrest the wrong man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/48#48">Matt. 26:48</a>). That was
the whole point of the betrayal.
</p><p>
But Jesus was also in the express image of God's person, so by his physical ministry among
them the people learned of the nature of his eternal Father in heaven.
</p><p>
Many followed him. At one time there was a multitude of five thousand; at another time, four
thousand. But even in his own day a falling away came, as is recorded in the sixth chapter of
John. When Jesus preached doctrine contrary to the traditional beliefs, many turned away.
</p><p>
John wrote of this, saying: "From that time many of his disciples went back, and walked no
more with him.
</p><p>
"Then said Jesus unto the twelve, Will ye also go away?
</p><p>
"Then Simon Peter answered him, Lord, to whom shall we go? thou hast the words of eternal
life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/6/66-68#66">John 6:66-68</a>).
</p><p>
How unfortunate for those who could not stand true doctrine. They turned away, preferring
their own darkness to the light of Christ.
</p><p>
By the time of his crucifixion his faithful followers were scattered. After his resurrection and
ascension into heaven the Saints gathered to resume their work on the day of Pentecost, but
how many came? Only 120 souls (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/15#15">Acts 1:15</a>).
That is all, according to the scriptures. Indeed there had been a falling away.
</p><p>
But now came another revelation. The Holy Ghost descended upon them in great power. They
resumed their ministry, and thousands joined the Church. But persecution arose in its severest
form. Many died as martyrs. The apostles lost their lives. Error then crept in. Philosophers
from Greece added to the difficulty as they theorized about the previously simple doctrines of
Christ. Disputations developed between the members of the Church.
Differences multiplied. One historian says that a hundred years after Christ there were thirty
different Christian sects.
</p><p>
This has gone on until our own day, when the various denominations of Christendom number
in the hundreds. They have many different creeds and sharply contrasting interpretations and
views pertaining to the nature of God.
</p><p>
But can a misunderstanding of the truth bring salvation? The Savior taught there is but one
straight and narrow way (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/14#14">Matt. 7:14</a>).
One of his great disciples wrote: "One Lord, one faith, one baptism"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/5#5">Eph. 4:5</a>).
Conditions today are much as they were anciently, but in times of old when
they reached this point, God clarified the issues by giving new revelation of himself, even to
the point of raising up new prophets through whom to speak.
</p><p>
Would he do that in modern times? Are modern people as precious in the sight of God as
ancient men and women? Would he make repeated efforts to save his ancient people in their
times of confusion and not do the same for his modern children?
</p><p>
God is the same today as yesterday (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/13/8#8">Heb. 13:8</a>).
He will do as much for modern men as he did for ancient
peoples. But does that mean a modern revelation of himself? Would modern men accept such
a revelation?
</p><p>
Again the Bible points the way. Not only does it emphasize that a falling away would occur,
but it also says that in the latter-days God indeed would reveal himself again, this time to
modern men to restore the truth and to save his people.
</p><p>
But to whom would he appear? To kings or potentates?
</p><p>
As in the days of Moses, so in our day, he would raise up a new prophet not previously
known to man. This modern Prophet was Joseph Smith. As God appeared to Moses, so he
appeared to Joseph Smith and for the same purpose&mdash;to restore the true knowledge of God so
that mankind could worship the Lord intelligently.
</p><p>
And has this come to pass? It has. This is how it happened. In western New York State
religious revivals were being held. One faith said, "Here is Christ." Another, "No, here is
Christ." Confusion spread. In the home of Joseph Smith there was deep concern. The family
desired to know which Church was right that they might join it. Some were inclined toward
one, some to another. The serious-minded boy, Joseph Smith, searched the Bible. In it he
found the writings of James, who said, "If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>).
</p><p>
This he determined to do. Going to a little grove of trees by his father's farm near Palmyra,
New York, he knelt in prayer. In response he received a visitation from the Almighty, even as
did Moses. There appeared to him the Eternal Father of heaven and earth and his Beloved
Son, the Savior of the world, Jesus the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
Think of it! God came to the United States of America, together with his divine Son, and they
appeared personally to that boy whom they had chosen to raise up as an American Prophet,
even as Moses had been raised up in his day. So it was that Joseph Smith learned about the
true nature of God.
</p><p>
But that was not enough. The Lord had determined to restore more than this knowledge
gained in that brief visitation. He sent angels to earth with more light, this in fulfillment of
Bible prophecy. He gave Joseph Smith divine authority for this modern ministry, even as he
had given the divine authority anciently, permitting men to serve as his duly appointed agents.
</p><p>
A church was to be organized, the ancient one to be restored. Baptism was required for
salvation, but who had the power to baptize? The Lord sent the authority to earth. John the
Baptist, who baptized the Savior, came to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery and gave to
them by ordination the divine power to baptize by immersion for the remission of sin.
</p><p>
Then came Peter, James, and John of the ancient twelve, conferring upon these same two men
the Holy Melchizedek Priesthood, including the apostleship which they themselves held. Thus
empowered, Joseph and Oliver were now commanded of the Lord to organize his Church on
the earth with all the gifts and powers of the ancient Church.
</p><p>
This they did. The Lord continued to give them revelation for their guidance, even as he had
given it to the ancient prophets for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the ministry,
for the edifying of the body of Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12#12">Eph. 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
But Jesus came again and yet again. When church headquarters were established in Kirtland,
Ohio, the Saints built a temple there. To it came the Savior of the world. As he appeared to
Joseph and Oliver, they saw his face and his figure, and they heard his voice as he said, "I am
the first and the last; I am he who liveth, I am he who was slain; I am your advocate with the
Father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/4#4">D&amp;C 110:4</a>).
</p><p>
At another time when Joseph was accompanied by Sidney Rigdon, another glorious revelation
of the Savior was experienced. They wrote of it: 
</p><p>
"And now, after the many testimonies which have been given of him, this is the testimony,
last of all, which we give of him: That he lives!
</p><p>
"For we saw him, even on the right hand of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/22-23#22">D&amp;C 76:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
So what is Mormonism, so-called? It is a new revelation of God, given to modern men
through modern prophets for the salvation of all who will hear. We invite all mankind to give
ear to its teachings, for it is the divine truth of God restored in our day. Of this we solemnly
testify in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
