<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Reality of the Resurrection</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder ElRay L. Christiansen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">ElRay L. Christiansen, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 45-46</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, with you I have been thrilled this day since the moment this
conference opened and we heard the outstanding message of our President, David O. McKay.
</p><p>
Now in order to meet the demands of the clock, I beg of you to let me "amputate" the first
part of my remarks. I hope the hemorrhage is not so great that something will not be left.
</p><p>
<b>Resurrection certain and universal</b>
</p><p>
Notwithstanding the precious promises made by the Lord as recorded in the scriptures, I
discover that many people are still in doubt and disbelief and uncertainty as to the reality of
their coming forth in the resurrection.  There is nothing more <i>certain</i> than the resurrection of
the body; there is nothing more <i>universal</i> than the resurrection. I do not pretend to understand
all the complexities of this great event; neither do I know just how the food that I eat is
assimilated and transformed, some into bone, some into muscle, some into blood, some into
digestive juices. I am not so concerned about the process as I am about the fact.
</p><p>
Amulek, the Nephite prophet, speaks of a complete and literal restitution. Said he: "The spirit
and the body shall be reunited again in its perfect form; both limb and joint shall be restored
us to its proper frame, even as we now are at this time" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/43#43">Alma 11:43</a>).
</p><p>
And our beloved President Joseph Fielding Smith has assured us in these words, that "every
fundamental part of every body will be restored to its proper place in the resurrection, no
matter what may become of the body in death. If it be burned by fire, lost at sea, no
matter what. Every fundamental part of it will be restored to its <i>own proper place</i>."
(<i>Answers to Gospel Questions</i>, Vol. 5, p. 103.) What an enlightening and comforting thought that is.
</p><p>
But what of those who die in infancy? The Prophet Joseph Smith taught that the physical
body will develop to its full stature, whether on earth, or in the life hereafter, and he gave
assurance that mothers who have laid their children away in infancy may hold them again in
their arms and they will, in due time, develop to their perfect stature. (Joseph F. Smith,
<i>Gospel Doctrine</i>, pp. 453-455.)
</p><p>
<b>Resurrection from mortality to immortality</b>
</p><p>
One thing we must keep in mind: all persons will, as a gift of the Redeemer, be raised from
mortality to immortality, with perfect bodies, no more subject to aches, or pains, or high
blood pressure, or arthritis, or disease, or any kind of physical deformity. But, in order to
have the fullness of joy and the fullness of opportunity, and that peace which passeth
understanding, and all opportunities in the resurrection&mdash;in order to have these blessings, we
must earn them through obedience to God and through service to others.
</p><p>
When we are resurrected, I doubt that we will be asked, "How many positions did you hold?"
but rather, "How many people did you help?"
</p><p>
<b>Acquired knowledge and intelligence continue</b>
</p><p>
Through the justice of God, each of us will receive exactly what he merits. Each will be
raised to a condition commensurate with that for which he has qualified himself. The gifts and
abilities we have developed here will be restored to us. The knowledge and intelligence we
have acquired will continue with us. Our attitudes, our weaknesses, our virtues, our positive
attributes will be part of us. Indeed, what we are to be, we are now becoming.
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon teaches that we shall in the resurrection "have a perfect knowledge of
all our guilt, and our uncleanness . . . and the righteous shall have a perfect knowledge of
their enjoyment and their righteousness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/14#14">2 Ne. 9:14</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Reap as we sow</b>
</p><p>
In summary, then, God organized our spirits and our bodies and then, in his great wisdom,
permitted us to create or shape our future. We are reaping in this life what we have sown in
the preexistence. We shall reap hereafter what we now sow. It was in harmony with this
principle that the Prophet Joseph Smith taught the divine truth that "whatever principle of
intelligence we attain unto in this life, it will rise with us in the resurrection.
</p><p>
"And if a person
gains more knowledge and intelligence in this life through his diligence and obedience than
another, he will have so much the advantage in the world to come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/18-19#18">D&amp;C 130:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
Therefore, the scriptures assure us that our resurrection shall be according to that glory by
which and to which our bodies are quickened.
</p><p>
"Ye who are quickened by a portion of the celestial glory shall then receive of the same, even
a fulness.
</p><p>
"And they who are quickened by a portion of the terrestrial glory shall then receive of the
same, even a fulness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/29-30#29">D&amp;C 88:29-30</a>).
</p><p>
And so also with the telestial glory: "And they who remain shall also be quickened;
nevertheless, they shall return again to their own place, to enjoy that which they are willing to
receive, because they were not willing to enjoy that which they might have received.
</p><p>
"For what doth it profit a man if a gift is bestowed upon him, and he receive not the gift?
Behold, he rejoices not in that which is given unto him, neither rejoices in him who is the
giver of the gift" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/32-33#32">D&amp;C 88:32-33</a>).
</p><p>
Such, then, is the reality of life after death.
</p><p>
By divine appointment and by his own acceptance, Jesus died that all might live again; and he
provided a plan whereby they who will buy receive, in addition to life hereafter, honor and
joy and satisfaction and happiness in the fullness; where we may, if we will, live in a state of
never-ending happiness with those we love (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/41#41">Mosiah 2:41</a>). To this I testify, bearing also my witness that God
lives, that Jesus is the Christ, that Joseph Smith was the instrument in their hands to restore
this great gospel and Church and kingdom, and that David O. McKay is today the Prophet of
God as surely as any other prophet ever was.
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ, our Master. Amen
</p>
</div>
</div>
