<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 13-16</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This has been truly a spiritual hour. Everyone present has felt the power of his Priesthood.
Everyone has felt the sincerity in the testimonies that have been borne by our Brethren.
</p><p>
Messages that are coming from the assemblies mentioned at the opening of the meeting
indicate that they, too, are partaking of this same spirit. I trust that my duty in answering
some of your questions of a practical nature may not detract in any way, but if possible add
to the spiritual influence thus far manifested.
</p><p>
The question has been asked: Is it proper in the administration of ward affairs, for the bishop
to add to the budget assignment for ward operations, the cost of one or more of the Church
magazines? If so, should he designate the magazine that the members of the ward should
take? The answer: No ward, stake, or mission is under obligation to raise an assigned quota
for any magazine published by the Church and it should not be included in the budget.
</p><p>
Second: Should a member of the bishopric be present always in the Junior Sunday School
when the Sacrament is administered in view of the fact that the Junior Sunday School is
presided over by sisters? This answer should be given by the Superintendency of the Sunday
School, but we will mention this one fact: There should be a member of the Bishopric
present, or one appointed by them holding the Melchizedek Priesthood in the Junior Sunday
School when the Sacrament is administered.
</p><p>
Next, there is a question which indicates the necessity of being more careful about permitting
fathers or other relatives to assist in ordinances of the Fast Meeting. For example, if a father
asks to baptize his son, the bishop of course will know whether the father is worthy, or
whether he holds the Priesthood. But suppose the father of the son lives in another ward, and
appears at the baptismal service and requests the right to baptize. The bishop who has that
baptismal service under his direction, should be sure that this father has the authority, and that
will apply in blessing a child, or in confirming a baptized member. It is suggested, therefore,
that the bishop will explain in announcing a baptismal ceremony or the confirmation, that if
any father belonging to another ward wishes to participate he should apply to the bishop
before the ordinance, and the bishop should request him to bring his recommend from the
ward of which he is a member. We need not particularize to tell you why.
</p><p>
Next: It is reported that recently some members who have been here for only a few years,
indeed a few months, from the mission field, entered the temple and were unable, of course,
to understand the ceremony, they could not understand the English language.  Bishops, under
these conditions, it would be well for you not to be in a hurry to issue recommends to the
temple to those who do not understand the services nor the ordinances. Their going might
prove more injurious to them than helpful.
</p><p>
In order to assist members of the Church better to understand the temple ceremony,
arrangements are being made, and have been made for them to hear that ceremony in their
native tongue. This will apply now already to six, possibly seven, nationalities. The ceremony
has been translated into other languages and as fast as we possibly can, notice will be given
when the ceremony will be presented to particular nationalities. We already have the
ceremony in Spanish, as you know, with good results. We have already had a ceremony in the
temple in the Swedish language. The ceremony is now in German, about completed in
Norwegian, Danish, French, and the Dutch language. Bishops, you may very rightfully and
wisely, ask the members who apply to you for recommends to the temple, a few weeks,
probably months, and first hear the ceremony, impressive as it is, in their native tongue. Then,
afterwards, they may go through and will understand the significance of it.
</p><p>
Indeed, there are of those who speak the English language, some who do not comprehend the
significance of that holy ordinance.
</p><p>
Many of our people write over to vicars for information in foreign countries, particularly in
England. Sometimes they are unable to furnish the records, even if they are willing, the
Church officials in England, and because the law will not permit them to send money out of
England they are therefore unable to return the funds you have sent. Do you get that
condition? You cannot get money back; they cannot furnish you the information. People
seeking genealogical information, therefore, from England, should carry on their
correspondence through the Genealogical Office and not write directly to the Churchmen in
England.
</p><p>
There are one or two other items but the Brethren of the Twelve will present those to you on
their visits.
</p><p>
I would just like to say a few words in conclusion, and I hope not to trespass too much upon
your time. In September 1946, the Board of Directors of the United States Steel held an
official meeting here in this city. At the conclusion of their directors meeting they invited
some of the officials of the Church to a dinner as their guests. There were present in that
group men nationally known throughout business circles, Mr. Irving S. Olds, Chairman of the
Board, Mr. Sewell L. Avery, and others. Mr. Olds was the Master of Ceremonies. At the
conclusion of that dinner, Mr. Olds said, "Now, we have not planned for any speeches, but if
any present would like to make any comments or remarks, now is the time." Mr. Nathan L.
Miller, Director and General Counsel for the United States Steel Corporation, former
Governor of New York State, arose. I remember well his opening sentence: "I am one of
those New Englanders who have harbored all the ill-stories that have been circulated about the
Mormons; but I will confess that this visit has extended my horizons!" He then said, "No one
can walk or drive around this city, observe its cleanliness, its wide, well-kept streets, the
physical accomplishments evident on every hand without being impressed with a feeling that
there is something peculiarly distinctive here&mdash;something different from that felt in any other
city. I don't know," he continued, "whether to call it a spirituality&mdash;yes, that is It!&mdash;there is
evidence of a spirituality, the lack of which is felt in other cities." He said he had been
searching for the source of it; but could not find that source until he heard the tributes paid
the Pioneers during a brief interview in the office of the First Presidency. There was a faith, a
great ideal, a greatness among the founders of this State which the descendants evidently have
succeeded in a degree to hold. "Your very isolation," he continued, "has been a contributing
factor in helping the Pioneers to maintain the high standards that characterized the lives of the
founders of this State."
</p><p>
Mr. Miller has now passed, but I wish he had been here tonight and partaken of the spirit of
these men mentioned, who are devoting their all to the advancement of the work.
</p><p>
Brother Mendenhall left his own affairs and from a business standpoint, they require great
directing, went to New Zealand on his own responsibility and appointed many of those men
who directed those builders of the school, and responded to the second appointment willingly,
and to another appointment. It matters not what it costs. Brother Biesinger, down there,
mentioned by Brother Mendenhall, has left his own business. I asked him down there, "What
has become of your business?" He said, "That is all right, it is gone, but I am here. This is
my mission now." All he has he would like to give to the work.
</p><p>
I met Brother Going down there who is building fifteen of our chapels in Samoa. His
business, too, is not so successful. He said, "I can arrange that. I will be ready to devote all
the time that is necessary."
</p><p>
Brother Matis said nothing other than that he has spent seven years over in the mission field,
but he had a prosperous position, an important position with an important company who said,
"Yes, we will give him a leave of absence." When that leave of absence was up we communicated
with Brother Matis. "No," he said, "this is my mission. Do not worry about that. I will be all
right." And so another year passed and another year, and seven years. You have heard his
testimony tonight how God has blessed him.
</p><p>
This afternoon Brother Moyle brought Brother Leo Ellsworth into the office. He is a
prosperous man of responsibility, governing probably hundreds of thousands of dollars. He
had just built a new home. He and his wife had not even completed their landscaping. The
call came to him to help the Church in a great enterprise. I did not know that until this
afternoon. They left their new house and have spent months now on this other call. He left his
own business. My heart was moved when I heard him say, "When I came back I found my
business even better than when I left it." He bore testimony of how the Lord had blessed
him&mdash;"And this is my work now."
</p><p>
The brother who will offer the benediction tonight, President of the Eastern States Mission,
received word that unless he could get home, give up his mission, he would lose his business.
Well, he had received an honorable release but he said nothing about this threatened loss of
his business unless he would give up his work, and he was going to say nothing about it.
</p><p>
These are but a few practical instances of the faith and devotion of the leaders and members
of the Church of Jesus Christ. I bear you testimony tonight that the power, the spiritual power
of the Gospel of Jesus Christ which comes from a testimony of the truth of the revealed and
Restored Gospel is operative throughout the entire Church, and it is that power that gives the
strength to it. It is the power of God unto salvation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
Put the Lord to the test and you will find
that he will answer and prove to you that he is overruling your affairs as well as the Church
affairs. Financially, you may lose something, but the spiritual gain will far outweigh that
seemingly financial loss.
</p><p>
Even before we came into this meeting tonight, one of the bishops said to me (I happened to
meet him): "Since my appointment, it is marvelous what the Lord has done for us, and how
he has opened up the way."
</p><p>
And so, my beloved brethren, in behalf of all the Church, and particularly in behalf of the
General Authorities, I thank you for your devotion, for your faith in the destiny of God's
Church. "Seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall
be added unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
May the Lord give us power so to do, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
