<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Lamanites</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 15-22</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I humbly ask for an interest in your faith and prayers this morning as I stand before you on
this rare and delightful occasion. It is truly an inspiration to see the priesthood sitting before
us with other members of the Church in this great and historic building.
</p><p>
INDIAN GROUPS VISITED
</p><p>
Since the last conference it has been my privilege to visit many of the tribes of Indians and
spend some time down in Mexico among others of the Lamanites. In Mexico I found many
pureblood Indians who are living the gospel of Jesus Christ. They are in organized branches.
There was the Aztec group down south of Popocatepetl Volcano. I found them dancing the
Gold and Green Ball, though generally they go barefooted. I found them in Mutual activities
of all kinds, singing temple anthems, dancing, dramatizing, and doing many of the things
which we do here at home. And it became my hope that such might be the privilege of all of
the Indians or Lamanites, everywhere in the world, and that the Church blessings might be
brought to them.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY TO PREACH GOSPEL TO LAMANITES
</p><p>
I realize that the responsibility is ours to bring the gospel with all its progress and culture to
the Indian. No other people in the world have the program to give to them, and so it is up to
us to do this. As we realize this, our great responsibility, we remember the
scripture which says,
</p><p>
. . . I will soften the hearts of the Gentiles, that they shall be like unto a father to them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/18#18">2 Ne. 10:18</a>).
</p><p>
One of the very first revelations to the Church in this last dispensation came through the
Prophet Joseph Smith to Oliver Cowdery, and he said:
</p><p>
. . . behold, I say unto you that you shall go unto the Lamanites and preach my
gospel unto them; and inasmuch as they receive thy teachings thou shalt cause my
church to be established among them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/28/8#8">D&amp;C 28:8</a>).
</p><p>
We have now, a stake in Hawaii, the membership of which is largely Lehites. We have
branches of the Church in Spanish-America and in the islands of the sea in great numbers. We
now have an Indian branch in South Carolina. We have Indian wards in the Malad Stake and
in the Maricopa Stake. But our responsibility has not yet been met, for we have some sixty
million people in these Americas who have some of the blood of Israel in their veins and who
must hear the gospel.
</p><p>
DESTINY OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith is quoted by President Wilford Woodruff in referring to this
important matter. May I quote his words. The Prophet was talking to a group of the
priesthood, and he said:
</p><p>
Brethren . . . you know no more concerning the destinies of this church and kingdom than a
babe upon its mother's lap. You don't comprehend it . . .
</p><p>
It is only a handful of priesthood you see here tonight, but this church will fill North and
South America&mdash;it will fill the world.
</p><p>
It will fill the Rocky Mountains. There will be tens of thousands of Latter-day
Saints who will be gathered in the Rocky Mountains, and there they will open the
door for the establishing of the gospel among the Lamanites, who will receive the
gospel and their endowments and the blessings of God
(<i>Discourses of Wilford Woodruff</i>, pp. 38-39).
</p><p>
Then in Second Nephi we have this:
</p><p>
And the gospel of Jesus Christ shall be declared among them; wherefore, they
shall be restored unto the knowledge of their fathers, and also to the knowledge
of Jesus Christ, which was had among their fathers
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/30/5#5">2 Ne. 30:5</a>).
</p><p>
I am sure that the consummation of the work of the kingdom of God in this dispensation
cannot be realized without this important feature of the restitution of all things.
</p><p>
In Third Nephi the Lord has inspired his prophet to say this:
</p><p>
And then shall the work of the Father commence at that day, even when this gospel shall be
preached among the remnant of this people. Verily I say unto you, at that day shall the work
of the Father commence among all the dispersed of my people, yea, even
the tribes which have been lost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/21/26#26">3 Ne. 21:26</a>).
</p><p>
HISTORY OF INDIAN CONVERSIONS
</p><p>
It has been said that the gospel would be preached and that nations would be "born in a day"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/66/8#8">Isa. 66:8</a>).
There was a period back in 1875-1876 when there were great numbers of Indians who came into
the Church. There was Chief Poko-Tel-Lo from the Snake River, who, with his entire band,
was baptized into the Church, and they left Salt Lake City going back to their homes
determined to refrain from all evil practices. The old chief said that the other Indians were
interested, and there would be many who would be baptized. There were fifty from the north
who came down. Chief Alma with twenty-two of his people from the Salmon River country
came down and were baptized into the Church. The chief made the prediction that there
would be hundreds and thousands of the Indians come into the Church. Orson Pratt baptized
fifty-two and blessed nine papooses down at Mount Pleasant in June of that year. In July there
were eighty-five of Kanosh's band who were baptized into the Church, and the following year
there were forty-one men and thirty-nine women, Indians, baptized down at Kanab. It seems
that there were a great many baptisms also up in the Malad country. I quote from The Deseret
News of July 22. 1875:
</p><p>
. . . Yesterday we met with Brother G. W. Hill, who has charge of a colony of
several hundred Indians, mostly of the Shoshone, Bannock, and Pah Ute tribes.
They are Indians who have come forward and demanded to be baptized. The
location is in Malad Valley, Idaho Territory. . . . They declare their intention to
wander about no more, but to lead industrious lives, at peace with all their fellow
creatures, refraining from stealing and from all manner of bad practices, and abide
by the conditions of their baptism, which are that they shall cease every species
of wrongdoing. Elder Hill has baptized about three hundred since last spring.
</p><p>
And then it was stated that these Indians had already shown their good faith. They were all
blessing their food; they were having their family prayers; and they were attending their
regular Sabbath meetings.
</p><p>
MISSIONS SERVING THE LAMANITES
</p><p>
In 1943 the Church organized the Navajo-Zuni Mission to look after the Indians in that area.
This year the mission has been enlarged to include all of the Indians in Arizona and New
Mexico and in the little strip in the southern part of Utah and Colorado. It is a full-time
mission now. We are buying a mission home in Gallup, New Mexico, which will be the
headquarters. And now young missionaries, elders and lady missionaries, are being called to
this mission as the other missions in the Church.
</p><p>
This year the Uruguayan Mission has been opened, and today with that mission and Brazil
and Argentina, we have in South America 169 missionaries working among
the Lamanites. This, of course, is in fulfilment of the dreams of the brethren and particularly
the promise and prayer of Elder Melvin J. Ballard when on the 25th of December in 1925 he
stood on the banks of El Rio de La Plata at Buenos Aires, and under the weeping willow
trees there, blessed South America. He said this, among other things:
</p><p>
 . . . I turn the key, unlock, and open the door for the preaching of the gospel in all these
South American nations, and rebuke, and command to be stayed, every power that would
oppose the preaching of the gospel in these lands. And we do bless and dedicate these nations,
and this land for the preaching of the gospel (The Improvement Era, April, 1926, pp. 575,
576.)
</p><p>
And in the last three months two new fields have been opened. Mexican missionaries from the
Mexican Mission have been sent into Guatemala and Costa Rica, and the work is going
forward with the approval and hearty response, it seems, of the leading authorities of those
nations.
</p><p>
We have the Mexican Mission, the Spanish-American Mission and the Navajo-Zuni Mission
here in the United States and Mexico, in addition to all the program in the isles of the sea.
The work in the stakes is going forward. There are Indians in many of the stakes here in the
West, and the stake presidents are looking after the proselyting of these Indians within their
boundaries, especially in the Blackfoot, Roosevelt, Sevier, Parowan, and other stakes.
</p><p>
We are glad of the work that has been renewed in the missions of the Church, especially here
in North America. In Canada some very splendid work is being done in the Six-Nations
Reservation over near Brantford, Ontario, and in central Canada there are two large
reservations, the "Carry the Kettle" Reservation and the Piapot, where President Ivins recently
visited, and between 175 and 200 Indians came and attended his meetings. Those were the
largest meetings, I understand, in his entire mission visit in western Canada.
</p><p>
We have the Ponca and the Sioux Indians who are showing interest in Nebraska, and the
Shoshones and the Arapahoes in Wyoming. We are doing work in the Rogue River, the Tule
Rivers, and the Rancho Rio reservations in northern California, and the Menominee
Reservation in the Northern States Mission. We have the Iroquois and the Catteraugas in New
York, and it will be remembered that in 1830 when Oliver Cowdery began his missionary
service among the Lamanites, that those were the first Indians to be visited in this
dispensation. Today young elders are on motor bikes going out into the scattered areas and
visiting the Indians, and are receiving a very warm welcome. The Cherokees in the East
Central States Mission are interested. Their chief, Armichain, has indicated a great deal of
helpfulness.
</p><p>
I would like to quote just a paragraph from a letter from one who has indicated intense
interest and been most helpful.
</p><p>
. . . I drove . . . with one of my Indian friends, Charles Crow, to Asheville, and
met the lady missionaries and the elders there . . . he was much impressed by
them . . . We administered to one of the elders who was ill, Charles Crow
witnessing the ordinance . . . He later told me that [that] was taught in the Bible,
and we were the first people he ever knew of that used it. When I had my prayers
that evening I knelt beside him . . . Before I had finished he put his arm on my
shoulder and said, Elder Stokes, pray that I some day may also have such a
testimony and a prayer in my heart.
</p><p>
It was my privilege at Malad Stake recently to see a large number of our Indian members of
the Church. One of the sisters bore a wonderful testimony in the conference, and one of the
old men dismissed the conference. He was one of those original three hundred baptized way
back in 1875 by Brother Hill. He was deaf, but he offered a very fine prayer.
</p><p>
INTEREST IN LAMANITES INCREASING
</p><p>
I believe that the interest generally is spreading and increasing and that we are on the dawn of
a great day for the Lamanite people. Visiting the Mexican Mission in May I found of the
seventy-one missionaries, fifteen of them were Lamanites, and I also found the young
American missionaries were vying with each other to see who could be the companions of
these Mexican and Indian missionaries because they were so efficient.
</p><p>
There have been baptisms by the hundreds. Some of the most recent ones were twenty
baptisms in the Roosevelt Stake within the past few weeks. There were four at Sand Hills,
Arizona. There were forty-one baptized in Mexico City in one day while I was there, and I
witnessed their baptism. And then there were hundreds, many hundreds who have come back
into fellowship in the Church in Mexico through the good graces of President George Albert
Smith, President Arwell L. Pierce, and others who made contributions toward that great
accomplishment.
</p><p>
We have had schools in Mexico, in Hawaii, Tonga, and New Zealand. And so we are looking
forward to a new day in schooling where our Lamanites may receive many of the advantages
that our own children have.
</p><p>
A year ago we established down in Blanding, Utah, a small school, somewhat as an
experiment. It has been very successful. With an outlay of only $1,500 total, we have built
and equipped a two-room schoolhouse there under the direction of Brother Albert R. Lyman,
who has done a glorious work. There have been many donations of all kinds, in materials, in
food, in clothing. For the first year they fed these little Indian children, twenty-seven of them,
a warm midday meal, clothed them, and taught them not only the three R's but the gospel. It
has been very successful, and we are delighted with the prospects that are ahead of us for the
second year now which is beginning. I visited this school last year when it was in session. I
noticed that three of the Indian women came, one of whom had five
children, four in the school and one in the cradle upon her back. She sat at the sewing
machine all day long in one corner of the larger schoolroom, and frequently we would see her
going over to one of the little desks, kneeling down beside it to help her children to learn, and
to impress upon them the importance of taking advantage of this unusual opportunity which
many thousands of little boys and girls should, but do not have.
</p><p>
The 1946 report of the missions discloses the fact, that among the Lamanites there are six
times as many converts for each missionary, as in all the other missions of the world, and
there are twenty times as many converts for each missionary in the Lamanite missions as in
some of the missions in Canada and the United States.
</p><p>
STORY OF POLACCA FAMILY
</p><p>
I had a letter the other day from a Tewa Indian in the Sand Hills of Arizona. His name is
Vinton Polacca. He is the son of one Tom Polacca, who was baptized many years ago by
Jacob Hamblin or his contemporaries. And then it seemed that there were many decades when
there were no missionaries in the area to give them help and courage. But Tom Polacca went
on with his work, and he taught his children the Book of Mormon stories, and promised them
that though it would be slow, the Church would come back again to them. Vinton and his
wife, Fanny, were baptized a few years ago at Snowflake, Arizona. They spoke in the
meetinghouse. They were entertained in the homes of the whites, and they were feted and
banqueted as brothers and sisters. The story of the conversion of this man is most interesting.
</p><p>
He was walking through the little community one day near the store out near the Second
Mesa in that sparsely inhabited area in northern Arizona. He heard a missionary talking to
some Indians near his car. He listened a moment. It sounded like the things his father had told
him those many, many years before, and when the missionary entered his car to go off some
little distance to eat his lunch, this man who had started out to get his horse, and had his
bridle on his arm, climbed on the side of the car, and they went some little distance and
found a place to sit down. Neither the horse was caught nor the lunch eaten because this man
became so involved in his learning of the gospel of Jesus Christ. And so he and his wife were
baptized some little time later.
</p><p>
Let me quote from his letter a few paragraphs of which I believe will interest you. Brother
Vinton is a young man in his forties with a splendid Indian family, part of whom we baptized
recently. We held a testimony meeting with them in their own little home, away out in the
sand hills, and I think it was the first testimony meeting they had attended and the first
sacrament they had ever received. He was a priest, and I helped him to administer to the
sacrament. His letter reads in part as follows:
</p><p>
. . . We are here at Kearns Canyon School now. I am back to work in the bakery again. I sure
like to be with so many little children . . . and I always wonder if all these young souls could
only know the true gospel, it will be a great help to our tribe. Yes. We always talk
about your nice visit to us at Sand Hills. There isn't very much to see up there, but I think
that my father has been led by a great spirit, to find a spring and a good home, and have
more freedom to pray to his true God. I could see him when I shut my eyes, kneeling down
on top of those sand hills and praying to our Great Father in heaven . . . I surely would like
to talk and tell the people all about my father's conversion, how he fine the true gospel . . . 
</p><p>
My father was telling me a story at the sheep camp by a fireplace in the winter as we were
setting by a fireplace, while he was sewing my sheepskin over shoes, he said, "My beloved
Son, you are the youngest son of mine. I'll tell you a story about my life and other people.
You must remember this and try to live up to it. But remember, Son, this is not for yourself.
As I have said before, there are other people who cannot see and hear. If you live right and
pray you might lead them and tell them about it. Give them a drink when they ask for it. Yes,
Son, I have travel a lots of time out in the country. Far off to the other tribe to trade our
goods. Many times I have gone alone out in the wilderness, where there is no roads or where
to fine the spring and food when I need it. Oh my Son you must listen good. Our great spirit
Father in heaven is guiding me. I pray when I am thirsty, I pray when I am lost and when I
need food I pray. All are answer when you believe in him. You don't know yet Son, what I
am talking about. But you must remember and pray for it, you'll fine it. The right one will
come to you and you'll know it, my Son.
</p><p>
"There will be lots of white people. They will all look alike when you see them, all white.
But, my Son, there heart is not alike, so you must be very careful in finding the right one. I
have fine the true gospel so you must try and fine the same one my Son, the Mormons. They
got the true record of our people. But they are coming slow. But they will be here. You'll see
them and hear them when they come. You'll know them by name (Mormon) so my Son, wait
for the Mormons. They got the true gospel of our great spirit Father in heaven. Pray for it so
you'll fine the right one."
</p><p>
At his death bed I was setting beside his bed and he hold out his hands and said, "My Son, I
am leaving you. Remember what I have told you. Wait for the Mormon. Look, Son, there is
the man coming down to take me home. Look. There is the cross above me. Be a good boy,
Son, be brave and be true to our true living God. Goodbye," And he is gone.
</p><p>
Oh yes, he told me that he first meet the missionaries around Tuba City and later on he said
they went up to Salt Lake City to buy a horse with his brother, and thats the time he said he
was been baptized. He did not said where he was been baptized. Only name that I remember
was Jacob.
</p><p>
And then Vinton tells his own little story, briefly:
</p><p>
When I was about eight years old I start to heard sheep, and from that time on I have learned
lots about God's work. I was a lonely boy. My brothers and sisters were big. When my father
died in 1911 I was left alone with my mother, and she also encourage me to remember my
father's last words&mdash;told me to live right and pray morning and evening so I keep it up. But
sometimes I think of myself if I was worth to God, then with a humble heart I look toward
east where Sun rises. I would then think of the day that would come for me to meet the right
true gospel. In 1913 I was able to read and write. I went to Baptizes [Baptist]
Church. I got hold of the Holy Bible and I sure did study it. But still it was not enough of the
story that my father had told me. In my mind (the Mormons) so in 1915 I went to Santa Fe to
school and there I found out about the Catlices [Catholics] I sure want to go to there church
so I did and I have found that it was not the kind that my father had told me about it, so that
Sunday night I ask our God what to do. I though [thought] that I was lost. The next week
Sunday they told me to go to church, but I stand alone there in the hole [whole] crowd. I
don't know which way to go, so I did not go to church for about a month. The school boy
use to call me divil [devil] because I didn't want to go to church . . .
</p><p>
I have waited about 20 years before I have found the true gospel .... Well, brother, I'll try and
tell you . . . all about my father's life . . . and also my own hard traveling and looking for the
true gospel which at last I have fine, and now I am feeling very happy . . 
</p><p>
I wish I would be up there with you during the general conference. Well, we all send our love
to our brothers and sisters. We remain as true to gospel.
</p><p>
From Polacca family<br />
Vinton L. Polacca.
</p><p>
LAMANITES TO BE "WHITE AND DELIGHTSOME"
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, in conclusion may I say that we owe a great debt to these people, which
we can only pay by giving to them the gospel and the many advantages and opportunities
which we enjoy. They are a warmhearted and devoted people. They believe without
skepticism. They have a simple, childlike faith which admits of no cheap rationalization.
</p><p>
The Lamanites must rise in majesty and power. We must look forward to the day when they
will be "white and delightsome"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/5/21#21">2 Ne. 5:21</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/30/6#6">2 Ne. 30:6</a>),
sharing the freedoms and blessings which we enjoy; when
they shall have economic security, culture, refinement, and education; when they shall be
operating farms and businesses and industries and shall be occupied in the professions and in
teaching; when they shall be organized into wards and stakes of Zion, furnishing much of
their own leadership; when they shall build and occupy and fill the temples, and serve in them
as the natives are now serving in the Hawaiian Temple where I found last year the entire
service conducted by them and done perfectly. And in the day when their prophet shall come,
one shall rise
</p><p>
. . . mighty among them . . . being an instrument in the hands of God, with exceeding faith,
to work mighty wonders (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/24#24">2 Ne. 3:24</a>).
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, the florescence of the Lamanites is in our hands. May we not fail them, I
pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
