<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Honor the Priesthood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1962, pp. 87-90</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren, always when charged with the responsibility of appearing before the people
of the Church and especially before the priesthood, I am conscious of my inadequacy, and
ever desirous of securing the guidance of my Heavenly Father as I attempt to serve.
</p><p>
Because of the things that have happened to me in recent months, I have been searching my
heart in an attempt to find justification for the Lord's goodness to me. Certainly we are all
blessed beyond our merits, which fact should keep us humble and grateful.
</p><p>
I recommend to all, not only the young men holding the Aaronic Priesthood, but to those
holding the Melchizedek Priesthood, that when the excellent talks given tonight by the
Presiding Bishopric are published, they read and apply their timely instructions. I certainly
congratulate the Bishopric on their thorough preparation and the inspiration of their addresses.
They have spoken directly, of course, to the Lesser Priesthood, because that is their special
charge.
</p><p>
You men, most of you here, and many listening in, know that the man who stands at the head
of the Melchizedek Priesthood&mdash;in fact of all the Priesthood of the Church&mdash;is the President
of the Church. He presides here tonight, and I conduct under his direction. He is an ideal
model, an exemplar to all of us. He often quotes, and in his life exemplifies, the admonition
of Isaiah: 
</p><p>
". . . be ye clean, that bear the vessels of the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/52/11#11">Isa. 52:11</a>).
</p><p>
I shall not detain you long because I know from whom you wish to hear. I should like,
however, to make a few observations on the responsibility of all whom God has honored by
permitting them to act for him. There is need for courage and constancy in the midst of
perilous and ominous world conditions. As I read of the Prophet Joseph Smith in Liberty Jail,
I am inspired by the courage and faith which enabled him to carry on in spite of persistent
and bitter persecution throughout his lifetime. When in Liberty Jail, where he spent many
months in 1838-39, he felt that he had suffered about all that mortal man could endure. In an
inspired appeal he prayed: 
</p><p>
"O God, where art thou? And where is the pavilion that covereth thy hiding place?
</p><p>
"How long shall thy hand be stayed, and thine eye, yea thy pure eye, behold from the eternal
heavens the wrongs of thy people and of thy servants, and thine ear be penetrated with their
cries?
</p><p>
"Yea, O Lord, how long shall they suffer these wrongs and unlawful
oppressions, before thine heart shall be softened toward them, and thy bowels be moved with
compassion toward them?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/1-3#1">D&amp;C 121:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
And the Lord answered, with the understanding born of experience: 
</p><p>
"My son, peace be unto thy soul; thine adversity and thine afflictions shall be but a small
moment; 
</p><p>
"And then, if thou endure it well, God shall exalt thee on high; thou shalt triumph over all thy
foes" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/7-8#7">D&amp;C 121:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
In the 121st section of the Doctrine and Covenants we have one of the most beautiful of all
revelations: 
</p><p>
"Behold, there are many called, but few are chosen. And why are they not chosen?
</p><p>
"Because their hearts are set so much upon the things of this world, and aspire to the honors
of men, that they do not learn this one lesson&mdash;
</p><p>
"That the rights of the priesthood are inseparably connected with the powers of heaven, and
that the powers of heaven cannot be controlled nor handled only upon the principles of
righteousness.
</p><p>
"That they may be conferred upon us, it is true; but when we undertake to cover our sins, or
to gratify our pride, our vain ambition, or to exercise control or dominion or compulsion upon
the souls of the children of men, in any degree of unrighteousness, behold, the heavens
withdraw themselves; the Spirit of the Lord is grieved, and when it is withdrawn, Amen to
the priesthood or the authority of that man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/34-37#34">D&amp;C 121:34-37</a>).
</p><p>
Brethren of the priesthood, let us never exercise unrighteous dominion. Let us honor the
priesthood in our own homes, in our attitudes toward our wives and children, for there as
elsewhere "when [the Spirit] is withdrawn, Amen to the priesthood or the authority of that
man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/37#37">D&amp;C 121:37</a>).
The Spirit will not always strive with man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/33#33">D&amp;C 1:33</a>), but we should always strive to retain his
Spirit in our homes, in our businesses, in all that we undertake to do.
</p><p>
We must cleanse and purify our bodies and souls, and try to be worthy to be called the sons
of God and to hold the Holy Priesthood. I read on: 
</p><p>
"No power or influence can or ought to be maintained by virtue of the priesthood, only by
persuasion, by long-suffering, by gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned; 
</p><p>
"By kindness, and pure knowledge, which shall greatly enlarge the soul without hypocrisy,
and without guile&mdash;" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41-42#41">D&amp;C 121:41-42</a>).
</p><p>
"Let thy bowels also be full of charity towards all men, and to the household of faith, and let
virtue garnish thy thoughts unceasingly; then shall thy confidence wax strong in the presence
of God; and the doctrine of the priesthood shall distil upon thy soul as the dews from heaven.
</p><p>
"The Holy Ghost shall be thy constant companion, and thy scepter an unchanging scepter of
righteousness and truth; and thy dominion shall be an everlasting dominion, and without
compulsory means it shall flow unto thee forever and ever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/45-46#45">D&amp;C 121:45-46</a>).
</p><p>
I never tire of reading or hearing this scripture, for it is the direct word of the Lord to the
men who hold the priesthood, telling us how to honor it, how to officiate under it warning all
against unrighteous dominion. I should like to say to you fathers tonight that our conduct in
our homes determines in large measure our worthiness to hold and exercise the priesthood,
which is the power of God delegated to man. Almost any man can make a good showing
when on parade before the public, but one's integrity is tested when "off duty." The real man
is seen and known in the comparative solitude of the home. An office or title will not erase a
fault nor guarantee a virtue.
</p><p>
"True worth is in being, not seeming,<br />
          In doing each day that goes by,<br />
          Some little good, not in the dreaming,<br />
          Of great things to do bye and bye.
</p><p>
"Whatever men say in their blindness,<br />
          And in spite of the fancies of youth,<br />
          There's nothing so Kingly as kindness,<br />
          And nothing so Royal as truth."
</p><p>
Let us never, in the words of the 37th verse of this section of the Doctrine and Covenants
". . . undertake to cover our sins, or to gratify our pride, our vain ambition, or to
exercise control or dominion or compulsion upon the souls of the children of men, in any
degree of unrighteousness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/37#37">D&amp;C 121:37</a>).
</p><p>
The late President Joseph F. Smith wrote, "There is no office growing out of this Priesthood
that is or can be greater than the Priesthood itself. It is from the Priesthood that the office
derives its authority and power. No office gives authority to the Priesthood. No office adds to
the power of the Priesthood, but all offices in the Church derive their power, their virtue, their
authority, from the Priesthood. The President of the Church carries on as President by virtue
of his Priesthood."
</p><p>
And now to you brethren who preside in the Church, I should like to say a word&mdash;presidents
of stakes, presidents of missions, bishops of wards, all who preside in any capacity&mdash;we urge
you to recognize and use your counselors. You will notice through all the organization of the
Church our Father in heaven has provided that each presiding officer shall have two
counselors. We regret that occasionally we hear of a stake president, a mission president, a
bishop or some presiding officer, who arrogates to himself the honors which belong to the
office he holds, who presides in a "one man" dictatorial way, forgetting his counselors,
neglecting to counsel with them, and thereby assuming all the honors of the presidency or
bishopric and taking upon himself all the responsibility for decisions in which his counselors
should share. There is wisdom and safety in counsel. Honor those with whom and over whom
you preside. That we honor the priesthood and the offices in it applies not only to our
attitudes toward those who preside over us, but also toward those over whom and with whom
we preside. Let us preside with kindness, consideration, and love.
</p><p>
Now, brethren, we who are assembled tonight here and in 320 other places should form a
great bulwark against communism and its attendant evils. The efficiency of our opposition to
them depends upon the way we honor our priesthood and place ourselves in a position to seek
and obtain God's help in fighting evil. Communism is of the devil. Communism started when
the devil was cast out of heaven because of his rebelling against the will of his Father that
men should have their free agency. Satan and his emissaries would rob men of their priceless
freedom. We do not wish tonight to enter into a long discussion of this evil, but it is well that
all men know that the Church and the leaders of the Church stand squarely against
communism.
</p><p>
To emphasize this I refer to what President Grant, President Clark, and President McKay
wrote sometime ago: 
</p><p>
"The Church does not interfere, and has no intention of trying to interfere with the fullest and
freest exercise of the political franchise of its members, under and within our Constitution . . .
</p><p>
"But Communism is not a political party nor a political plan under the Constitution; it is a
system of government that is the opposite of our Constitutional government, and it would be
necessary to destroy our Government before Communism could be set up in the United
States."
</p><p>
I wish you would read the rest of it yourselves and see what the stand of the First Presidency
was at that time, and I think I can authoritatively say to you that the position of the First
Presidency has not changed since that time.
</p><p>
But, brethren, beware that you do not become extremists on either side. The degree of a
man's aversion to communism may not always be measured by the noise he makes in going
about and calling everyone a communist who disagrees with his personal political bias. There
is no excuse for members of this Church, especially men who hold the priesthood, to be
opposing one another over communism; we are all unalterably opposed to it, but we must be
united in our fight against it. Let us not undermine our government or accuse those who hold
office of being soft on communism. Furthermore, our chapels and meetinghouses should not
be made available to men who seek financial gain or political advantage by destroying faith in
our elected officials under the guise of fighting communism. Let self-appointed protectors of
our freedom finance their own schemes. We call upon the priesthood of the Church to stand
together with a solid front against everything that would rob men of their
God-given freedom.
</p><p>
I leave again my testimony with you that I know that God lives and that Jesus is the Christ.
From the center of my heart I bear witness to that fact and that Joseph the Prophet was
ordained and set apart and called as the leader of this great dispensation. I bear witness to the
fact that our beloved President today holds all the keys and authority given to Joseph Smith
and that he is the mouthpiece of God on earth today. We honor and sustain him.
</p><p>
God help you brethren and all of us to remain true to the end, true to God, true to our
country and its institutions, and true to the truth, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
