<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Where is Peace?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Howard W. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Howard W. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 14-17</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<b>Peace</b>
</p><p>
On the campus of one of our large universities there were recent riots by students carrying
large placards, some of which had the words, "We demand peace." It cannot be denied that
we live in troubled times and that the lives of most people in the world today are affected by
war. Both sides of the controversy have stated their terms for peace, and politicians talk about
an equitable and lasting peace despite the fact that down through history there has been
almost continual warfare and political unrest.
</p><p>
<b>Destroyed by lust</b>
</p><p>
The Apostle James, in writing to Israel, asked this question: "From whence come wars and
fighting among you? come they not hence, even of your lusts that war in your members?
</p><p>
"Ye lust, and have not: ye kill, and desire to have, and cannot obtain: ye fight and war, yet ye
have not, because ye ask not.
</p><p>
"Ye ask, and receive not, because ye ask amiss, that ye may consume it upon your lusts"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/4/1-3#1">James 4:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
At the time of this writing, the Jews were revolting against the Romans in defense of their
religion and fighting to procure the liberty to which they believed themselves entitled. They
had been split in many factions and were having conflicts among themselves. At the same
time they were waging wars against the heathens in Egypt, Syria, and other places, killing
many and being massacred in their turn.
</p><p>
James asks this question: Does not war come from lusts? The Jewish contentions and
predatory wars were generated upon lust. Lust has been the motivating force of the wars that
have afflicted and desolated the world. One nation has coveted another's territory or property
or has attempted to force its will or way of life upon another by resorting to physical violence
as a means to accomplish its purposes. Nations kill, slay, burn, and destroy until one of them
is overcome. History is a repetitious recital of intentional and wanton destruction of life and
property. Today is not different from the yesterdays. The populace prays and cries for peace.
</p><p>
<b>Peace defined</b>
</p><p>
The word <i>peace</i> appears frequently in scripture and has many meanings. In classical Greek the
word refers to cessation, discontinuance, or absence of hostilities between rival forces. This
definition is the antithesis of war and strife. The New Testament, however, has given far
wider range of meaning. This is partly due to the influence of the Hebrew word for peace,
which is far more comprehensive of meaning. It was commonly used as a form of greeting
when persons met or parted: "May peace be with you."
</p><p>
Jesus said, "Daughter, thy faith hath made thee whole; go in peace" 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/5/34#34">Mark 5:34</a>).
On the evening of the day of the resurrection, he came to the place where the disciples were
assembled and said to them, "Peace be unto you.
</p><p>
"And when he had so said, he shewed unto them his hands and his side. Then were the
disciples glad, when they saw the Lord.
</p><p>
"Then said Jesus to them again, Peace be unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/19-21#19">John 20:19-21</a>).
</p><p>
Paul has incorporated this greeting into the opening sentences of his letters, as do the other
writers of the epistles.
</p><p>
The word has also been used in the New Testament in reference to "domestic peace" between
husband and wife (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/7/15#15">1 Cor. 7:15</a>),
to harmonious relationships within the whole family
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/34#34">Matt. 10:34</a>),
and in many instances to happy, personal relationships with others. It has also been
used to mean "peace of mind" or serenity, and the right relationships between God and man.
</p><p>
<b>God prescribes conditions of peace</b>
</p><p>
Because of the difference in definitions, those who seek peace may be searching for unrelated
conditions. The peace for which the world longs is a time of suspended hostilities; but men do
not realize that peace is a state of existence that comes to man only upon the terms and
conditions set by God, and in no other way.
</p><p>
In a psalm in the Book of Isaiah are these words: "Thou wilt keep him in perfect peace,
whose mind is stayed on thee: because he trusteth in thee" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/26/3#3">Isa. 26:3</a>).
This perfect peace mentioned by Isaiah comes to one only through a belief in God. This is not understood by an
unbelieving world.
</p><p>
<b>"My peace I give unto you"</b>
</p><p>
On the last occasion that Jesus had supper with the Twelve, he washed their feet, broke bread
for them, and passed them the cup; then, after Judas had left their midst, the Master spoke to
them at some length. Among other things, he told of his impending death and of the legacy
he left for each of them. He had accumulated no goods, property, nor wealth. The record tells
us of no possessions other than the clothing he wore, and on the next day after the crucifixion
this would be divided by the soldiers, who would cast lots for his coat. His bequest was given
to his disciples in these simple yet profound words: "Peace I leave with you, my peace I give
unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled, neither let
it be afraid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
He used the Jewish form of salutation and benediction: "My peace I give unto you." This
salutation and bequest was not to be taken by them in the usual sense, for he said, ". . . not as
the world giveth, give I unto you." Not empty wishes, not just polite ceremony, as the people
of the world use the words as matters of custom; but as the author and Prince of peace, he
gave it to them. He bestowed it upon them and said, "Let not your heart be troubled, neither
let it be afraid." Within a few hours they would be subjected to trouble, but with his peace
they could overcome fear and stand firm.
</p><p>
<b>"Be not afraid"</b>
</p><p>
His last statement to them before the closing prayer on that memorable evening was this: ". . .
in the world ye shall have tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Promise of peace</b>
</p><p>
There is no promise of peace to those who reject God, to those who will not keep his
commandments, or to those who violate his laws. The Prophet Isaiah spoke of the decadence
and corruption of leaders and then continued in his admonitions by saying: "But the wicked
are like the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and dirt.
</p><p>
"There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/57/20-21#20">Isa. 57:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
The unrighteous and wicked have no peace, and their actions take away the peace of others.
Turmoil in the world has usually been caused by a few individuals or a minority, causing
millions of innocent persons to suffer. Today, as in eras gone by, those who are the innocent
victims of oppressors hopefully look for peace. This cannot come by riots or placards or even
the cessation of hostilities. It can come only in the way the Lord gave his peace to the
Twelve, "not as the world giveth."
</p><p>
One of the great writers has penned: "Peace does not dwell in outward things, but within the
soul; we may preserve it in the midst of the bitterest pain, if our will remains firm and
submissive. Peace in this life springs from acquiescence, not in an exemption from suffering."
(Fenelon.)
</p><p>
<b>Peace, triumph of principles</b>
</p><p>
Emerson wrote: "Nothing can bring you peace but yourself; nothing can bring you peace but
the triumph of principles." (Essay, "Self-Reliance.") These principles are incorporated into the
gospel of Jesus Christ. Indifference to the Savior or failure to keep the commandments of God
brings about insecurity, inner turmoil, and contention. These are the opposite of peace. Peace
can come to an individual only by an unconditional surrender&mdash;surrender to him who is the
Prince of peace (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>),
who has the power to confer peace.
</p><p>
One may live in beautiful and peaceful
surroundings but, because of inner dissension and discord, be in a state of constant turmoil.
On the other hand, one may be in the midst of utter destruction and the bloodshed of war and
yet have the serenity of unspeakable peace. If we look to man and the ways of the world, we
will find turmoil and confusion. If we will but turn to God, we will find peace for the restless
soul. This was made clear by the words of the Savior: "In the world ye shall have tribulation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>);
and in his bequest to the Twelve and to all mankind, he said, "Peace I leave
with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Come unto me, all ye that labor"</b>
</p><p>
We can find this peace now in a world of conflict if we will but accept his great gift and his
further invitation: "Come unto me, all ye that labor and are heavy laden, and I will give you
rest.
</p><p>
"Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall
find rest unto your souls" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/28-29#28">Matt. 11:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
This peace shelters us from the worldly turmoil. The knowledge that God lives, that we are
his children, and that he loves us soothes the troubled heart. The answer to the quest lies in
faith in God and in his Son, Jesus Christ. This will bring peace to us now and in the eternity
to follow.
</p><p>
I witness that Jesus is the Christ, the Savior of the world, and that this is his Church, in his
holy name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
