<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1949, pp. 175-179</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Just as soon as I can get my breath I will start. Brother Ivins tells the story of a deacon who
was called, extemporaneously, to speak in one of our stakes. He stood up a minute and
switched from one foot to the other and said, "Brothers and sisters, I am just stalling for
time." Then he preached a nice sermon on the Word of Wisdom. He then looked at them and
said, "I have surely put myself on the spot, haven't I?"
</p><p>
DOES THE GOSPEL FIT?
</p><p>
Now brethren, I am happy to be here; I am happy in my work in the Church; I love the
brethren, and I love the Saints. I have the privilege of interviewing a good many missionaries
as I travel from stake to stake, and I always ask them how they feel about going on a mission
and how the gospel fits them. I say, "When you go into a store to buy a suit of clothes, it
either fits or it does not fit. Does the gospel fit you? How do you feel when you hear the
Prophet Joseph Smith's story of having gone into the woods to pray, and having seen the
Father and the Son and what transpired there? Can you accept all of that; do you believe it?
Do you believe that John the Baptist came and conferred the Aaronic Priesthood upon Joseph
and Oliver and that Peter, James, and John conferred the Melchizedek Priesthood? And that
Elijah, Elias, and Moses brought the keys of their dispensations; does all that fit?" When they
say it does, then I say: "Then you know that we do not have just another Church&mdash;we have
the only true Church."
</p><p>
I feel that the most important thing in our teaching in this Church is
to try to impress upon our people the truth of the gospel, and I want to tell you from my
experience that I do not think they have to be old men and old women to know the gospel is
true. I have more young people at our conferences tell me they know the gospel is true, than
the older ones, and I believe them.
</p><p>
On the day of Pentecost, Peter called the people to repentance and they were pricked in their
hearts and said, "Men and brethren, what shall we do? Then Peter said unto them, repent and
be baptized, everyone of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of sins, and ye
shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost. For the promise is unto you, and to your children,
and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God shall call"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37-39#37">Acts 2:37-39</a>). And I know the
promise is unto our children, and they can know the truth of the gospel through the gift of the
Holy Ghost. I am not quite so much worried, sometimes, about the children as I am about the
older folk.
</p><p>
EZEKIEL'S CONTRIBUTION
</p><p>
I attended a Sunday School class not very long ago, and they were considering the life and
mission of the prophet, Ezekiel, and the brother in charge of the class proceeded to say that
we did not know very much about Ezekiel. Then he told a little about the condition of the
world at the time Ezekiel lived, but said nothing about his teachings or prophecies. He was
about to close the class. I very seldom say anything in a Sunday School class when I am
there, but I said, "Brother So-and-so, were you going to close right at that point?" He said, "I
thought so, is there anything you would like to add?" I told the class that Ezekiel had made
one contribution to this great Latter-day cause thousands of years ago, that no other prophet
had made, for it was he who gave us the knowledge that there were two records to be kept,
not only one of Judah and his posterity, but one of Joseph and his posterity
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/37/15-20#15">Ezek. 37:15-20</a>), and save for
Ezekiel we would not know that there was to be another volume of scripture, and I said that it
seems to me we ought to capitalize on what Ezekiel left us.
</p><p>
MISSIONARY EXPERIENCES
</p><p>
It reminded me of when I was in the mission field in the Eastern States. Into one home I
went, the man was not a member of the Church, and every time I would leave he would say,
"I believe I have been a Mormon all my life, but did not know it;" but I could not get his
wife to come in and listen to me. She would go into the next room and iron. You know
ironing is a quiet job. I do not need to tell you that I usually take my "loud-speaker" along
with me, just in case, and I made sure she heard all I had to say. The last visit I made there I
said, "Mrs. McDonald, you would surely honor me if you would come in today and listen to
me." She finally consented. I said, "You may never see me again in this world." We had just
started our discussion and in walked her son from Harvard College. She said, "My boy, you
are just in time. You take this book," because I had her take the Bible to follow me, "and you
show us how this man is trying to lead us astray." I took one hour
and a half and I closed my Bible. The discussion that day was on the House of Israel, the new
land the Lord had promised to Joseph, the ultimate final gathering in the latter days, and the
two records to be kept; and I turned to her son from Harvard and said, "You tell your mother
how I am trying to lead you astray, will you please?" He said, "Mother, this man is not trying
to lead you astray, he is teaching you the truth." Before I left she said, "Mr. Richards, even if
I do not believe all you say, there is something about you I cannot help but like. Will you
pray with us before you go?"
</p><p>
In that same city we were holding a street meeting, and the Gospel Hall people were holding
a convention a short distance away. They adjourned their meeting to come and try and break
up ours. I said, "You men would like to be gentlemen, wouldn't you?" As I recall, there were
about sixteen ministers there that night. I said, "You give us twenty minutes to finish our
meeting and then we will stay thirty minutes and listen to you." I said to the crowd, "Won't
we?" There were between two and three hundred there, and they indicated they would. During
their thirty minutes they painted the Prophet Joseph as black as anybody could. "Why," they
said, "if you would let them, the Mormons would bind the Book of Mormon in the same
cover with the Bible and ask us to take it and like it." I did not like to see that meeting close
right at that point, so I stepped up to this minister and said, "You would not mind if I made
an announcement before the meeting closes, would you?" He said, "No, go ahead." So I
turned to the crowd and said, "If you will come back next Tuesday night at 7:30 we will tell
you why we bind the Book of Mormon in the same cover with the Bible and ask you to take
it and like it." And I said, "Bring your Bibles along with you because you will not need them
after next Tuesday night if you are not willing to accept the companion volume of scripture,
Ezekiel said the Lord would bring forth the record of Joseph which He would join to the
record of the Jews and the two should become one in His hand"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/37/15-20#15">Ezek. 37:15-20</a>). When they came that night,
and the crowd was larger than the previous one, I said, "How can any of us stay the hand of
God from bringing forth the record He has promised?" As I remember we sold sixteen copies
of the Book of Mormon that night.
</p><p>
Well, I have had so many experiences that I cannot understand why we cannot plant the truth
in the hearts of our people until no outside thing or movement in the world can have any
influence with them. We have so much more to offer than any other church in the world.
</p><p>
I was out tracting in that city one day and I had been to a particular house several times when
the lady of the house said, "Mr. Richards, what are you trying to do anyway, are you trying to
make Mormons out of all of us?" "Well," I said, "I will tell you one thing,
I will never ask you to join the Mormon Church," and that seemed to
put her mind at ease. Then I said, "If I could show you where you could trade a dollar for
five dollars, I would not have to ask you to do it, would I?" After I had been home a few
months I received a letter from her calling me "Brother Richards." She said, "I decided to
trade the dollar for five dollars. I was baptized a member of the Church last Friday night."
</p><p>
I think that any elder in Israel who cannot make Mormonism look better than five to one had
better get hold of the scriptures and go to work and study the gospel.
</p><p>
I was in The Hague, Holland, and was invited into the home of the owner of a large furniture
store. His associates were all business men. I cannot take the time to tell you how I got there,
but I was there by invitation, and I was there to discuss a certain subject of the gospel&mdash;the
universal salvation of man, including the work for the dead. This happened to be a Bible class
and they spent a night each week studying together. They all had their Bibles and they turned
the class over to me. After having discussed this subject for about an hour and a half, I closed
my Bible and there wasn't anything said for a few minutes. Finally the daughter of the house
turned to her father and said. "Father, I cannot understand; you always have the last word to
say on everything and tonight you have not said a word." He said, "My daughter, there isn't
anything to say. This man is teaching us things we have never heard of before and he is
teaching them to us out of our own Bibles." And he did not have anything to say.
</p><p>
Well, why don't we teach these things to our children until they become like the Rock of
Gibraltar, founded upon a faith that cannot be moved?
</p><p>
ETERNAL MARRIAGE
</p><p>
You take our principle of eternal marriage and the eternal duration of the marriage covenant. I
have had similar experiences in teaching this principle. I spoke on this subject in Quitman,
Georgia, and I took the statement from Brother Rulon Howells' book, "Do Men Believe What
Their Church Prescribes?" and read what other churches prescribe on this subject. There is no
church I have ever heard of that believes the marriage tie or the family unit will endure
beyond the grave. We cannot imagine anybody being satisfied with a religion like that unless
he is like the lady I met back in New Bedford. I tried to teach her this principle and she said,
"I'll tell you, Mr. Richards, if there is any marriage relationship beyond the grave, I'll take
chances on getting something better than I have now." (Laughter.) "If I live with my husband
until I die, I think I will have done pretty well."
</p><p>
As I say, I spoke on this subject in Quitman, Georgia, and at the close of the meeting a
Baptist minister came up and introduced himself and told me who he was. I said, "Did I
misquote you," because I had read of the belief of the Baptist Church on this subject. He said,
"No, Mr. Richards, it is just like you say, we do not all believe all the
things our churches prescribe." I said, "You do not believe it either. Why do you not go home
and teach your people the truth. They will be glad to receive it from you, and they are not yet
ready to accept it from the Mormon elders." That was all I could get out of him. He said, "I
will see you again."
</p><p>
The next time I went to Quitman my picture appeared in the paper, because I was president of
the mission, and when I went up to that little church he was waiting for me. I said, "I would
be glad to know what you thought of my last sermon." He said, "Mr. Richards, I have been
thinking about it ever since and I believe every word you said, only I would like to have
heard the rest of it." You know I never quite get finished on a subject, the clock travels too
fast. This principle is not difficult for even ministers to accept when you explain it to them.
</p><p>
I was at the Manti Temple recently with my father, and President Anderson, who is here
tonight, told of a minister who had visited the temple grounds a few weeks ago. When he
heard our story of our belief in eternal marriage and the eternal duration of the family unit he
said, "You know, I had two of my young people come to me recently, and they wanted me to
marry them for time and all eternity," and he said, "I did it. I thought that was the kind of
marriage we all ought to have, but they do not teach it in their churches."
</p><p>
I spent an hour and a half in the study of one of the most prominent ministers in the United
States. He died a few weeks ago, and at the time of his death he was chaplain of the United
States Senate. While I was in his study we discussed this subject. He said, "Mr. Richards, our
church does not give us any hope that there will be a continuation of the marriage tie or the
family unit beyond this life, but in my heart I find stubborn objections." Then he used this
illustration, and it was better than I could have given him. I have used it since, myself. He
said, "When you take the kitten away from the cat, in a few days the cat has forgotten all
about the kitten, and when you take the calf away from the cow, in a few days the cow has
forgotten about its calf; but when you take the child away from its mother's bosom, though
she lives to be a hundred years old, she never forgets the child of her bosom. I find it difficult
to believe that God created love like that to perish in the grave." But he could not tell his
people that from the pulpit because he could not hold his job and teach them Mormonism.
</p><p>
I want to tell you that we have so much more than any other church that five to one does not
begin to show it. Why do we not get into the hearts of our boys and girls and our men and
women so that no power under heaven will have the power to take them away from this
Church.
</p><p>
God bless you in the great work you are doing, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
