<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Prophet Is Born</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1960, pp. 83-86</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, this has been a great conference. I pray that the Spirit of the
Lord may attend me in what I shall say.
</p><p>
About fifty years ago, Mr. F. M. Bareham wrote the following: 
</p><p>
"A century ago men were following with bated breath the march of Napoleon and waiting
with feverish impatience for news of the wars. And all the while in their homes babies were
being born. But who could think about babies? Everybody was thinking about battles.
</p><p>
"In one year between Trafalgar and Waterloo there stole into the world a host of heroes:
Gladstone was born in Liverpool; Tennyson at the Somersby Rectory, and Oliver Wendell
Holmes in Massachusetts. Abraham Lincoln was born in Kentucky, and music was enriched
by the advent of Felix Mendelssohn in Hamburg."
</p><p>
And we might add, and Joseph Smith was born in Vermont, four years
earlier.
</p><p>
Quoting Bareham further: 
</p><p>
"But nobody thought of babies, everybody was thinking of battles. Yet which of the battles of
1809 mattered more than the babies of 1809? We fancy God can manage his world only with
great battalions, when all the time he is doing it with beautiful babies.
</p><p>
"When a wrong wants righting, or a truth wants preaching, or a continent wants discovering,
God sends a baby into the world to do it."
</p><p>
While most of the thousands of precious infants born every hour will never be known outside
their own neighborhoods, there are great souls being born who will rise above their
surroundings. We see with ". . . Abraham the intelligences that were organized before the
world was; and among all these there were many of the noble and great ones, . . ." and we
hear the Lord saying: 
</p><p>
"These I will make my rulers . . . Abraham, thou art one of them, thou wast chosen before
thou wast born" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/22-23#22">Abr. 3:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
He commanded Adam: "Be fruitful and multiply, and replenish the earth, and subdue it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
</p><p>
And the Psalmist sang: 
</p><p>
"Lo, children are an heritage of the Lord . . . Happy is the man that hath his quiver full of
them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/127/3,5#3">Ps. 127:3,5</a>).
</p><p>
Regarding these "Men of the Hour," Carlyle said: 
</p><p>
"The most precious gift that heaven can give to the earth; a man of genius, as we call it; the
soul of a man actually sent down from the skies with God's message to us."
</p><p>
What mother, looking down with tenderness upon her chubby infant does not envision her
child as the President of the Church or the leader of her nation! As he is nestled in her arms,
she sees him a statesman, a leader, a prophet. Some dreams do come true! One mother gives
us a Shakespeare, another a Michelangelo, and another an Abraham Lincoln, and still another
a Joseph Smith!
</p><p>
When theologians are reeling and stumbling, when lips are pretending and hearts are
wandering, and people are "running to and fro, seeking the word of the Lord and cannot find
it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/8/12#12">Amos 8:12</a>)"&mdash;when
clouds of error need dissipating and spiritual darkness needs penetrating and
heavens need opening, a little infant is born. Just a few scattered neighbors in a hilly region in
the backwoods even know that Lucy is expecting. There is no prenatal care, nor nurses; no
hospital, no ambulance, no delivery room. Babies live and die in this rough environment and
few know of it. Another child for Lucy! No trumpets are sounded; no hourly bulletins posted;
no pictures taken; no notice is given; just a few friendly community folk pass the word along.
It's a boy! Little do the brothers and sister dream that a prophet is born to them; even his
proud parents can little suspect his spectacular destiny. No countryside farmers or loungers at
the country store, nor village gossips even surmise how much they could discuss, did they but
have the power of prophetic vision.
</p><p>
"They are naming him Joseph," it is reported. But not one knows, not even his parents, at this
time, that this infant and his father have been named in the scriptures for 3500 years, named
for and known to their ancestor Joseph, the savior of Egypt and Israel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/15#15">2 Ne. 3:15</a>). Not even his adoring
mother realizes, even in her most ambitious dreaming and her silent musings, that this one of
her children, like his ancestor, will be the chief sheaf of grain to which all others would lean
and the one star to which the sun and moon and the other stars would make obeisance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/37/6-11#6">Gen. 37:6-11</a>).
</p><p>
He will inspire hatred and admiration; he will build an empire and restore a church&mdash;the
Church of Jesus Christ. Millions will follow him; monuments will be built to him; poets will
sing of him; authors will write libraries of books about him.
</p><p>
No living soul can guess that this little pinkish infant will become the peer of Moses in
spiritual power and greater than many prophets before him. He will talk with God, the Eternal
Father, and Jesus Christ, his Son, and angels will be his guest instructors.
</p><p>
His Vermont contemporaries know not that this little one just born will live as few men have
lived, accomplish what few men have accomplished, and die as few have ever died, in his
own sacred blood in a prison at the hands of assassins as a martyr to
everlasting truth!
</p><p>
All expectations are understated. Destiny out-distances all imagination and dreams!
</p><p>
"God moves in a mysterious way<br />
      His wonders to perform; <br />
      He plants his footsteps in the sea<br />
      And rides upon the storm.
</p><p>
"Deep in unfathomable mines<br />
      Of never-failing skill,<br />
      He treasures up his bright designs<br />
      And works his sovereign will."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                  &mdash;William Cowper.
</p><p>
During the unfolding of this Smith-flower; during the brief ripening years of this fruit of the
loins of that other Joseph of Israel, the world is preparing for the greatest event since the
Meridian of Time. The triplet infants, Liberty, Freedom, and Justice, are contending for life; a
small colonial nation is struggling to its feet; the people from many lands, squirming in the
"melting-pot," are firming up, suffering labor pains toward the birth of a divine new program,
"a marvelous work and a wonder" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/14#14">Isa. 29:14</a>),
the restoration of the gospel in all its far-reaching detail.
</p><p>
"We fancy," said Bareham, "God can manage his world only with great battalions, when all
the time he is doing it with beautiful babies."
</p><p>
O foolish men who think to protect the world with armaments, battleships, and space
equipment, when only righteousness is needed!
</p><p>
Having read the pages of history, six thousand years of it, can we not see that God sent his
babies to become the teachers and prophets to warn us of our threatening fate? Cannot we
read the handwriting on the wall? History repeats itself.
</p><p>
O mortal men, deaf and blind! Can we not read the past? For thousands of years, have
plowshares been beaten into swords and pruning hooks into spears, yet war persists. Ever
since Belshazzar saw the finger writing upon the wall of his palace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/5/5-9#5">Dan. 5:5-9</a>), the warning reappears. It
seems to restate with great forcefulness, Daniel's indictment of an unhumble people: 
</p><p>
"God hath numbered thy kingdom, and finished it . . . Thou art weighed in the balances, and
art found wanting. And thou his son, O Belshazzar, hast not humbled thine heart, though thou
knewest all this . . . and thou hast praised the gods of silver, and gold, of brass, iron, wood,
and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know: and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and
whose are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/5/26-27,22-23#26">Dan. 5:26-27,22-23</a>)
. . . Blessed be the name of God . . . he
removeth kings, and setteth up kings" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/20-21#20">Dan. 2:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
The answer to all of our problems&mdash;personal, national, and international&mdash;has been given to
us many times by many prophets, ancient to modern. Why must we grovel in the earth when
we could be climbing toward heaven! The path is not obscure. Perhaps it is too simple for us
to see. We look to foreign programs, summit conferences, land bases. We depend on
fortifications, our gods of stone; upon ships and planes and projectiles, our gods of
iron&mdash;gods which have no ears, no eyes, no hearts
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/5/23#23">Dan. 5:23</a>). We pray to them for deliverance and depend
upon them for protection. Like the gods of Baal, they could be "talking or pursuing or on a
journey or peradventure sleeping" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/18/27#27">1 Kgs. 18:27</a>)
when they are needed most. And like Elijah, we might cry out to our world: 
</p><p>
"How long halt ye between two opinions? if the Lord be God, follow him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/18/21#21">1 Kgs. 18:21</a>).
</p><p>
My testimony to you is, the Lord is God. He has charted the way, but we do not follow. He
personally visited Joseph Smith in our world in our century. He outlined the way of peace in
this world and eternal worlds. That path is righteousness. The Prophet Joseph with all his
successor prophets proclaiming the ripening of this world in iniquity and the solution of all
vexing problems. The Book of Mormon which he brought into existence relates the story of
two hundred years of peace in the old days, which was the greatest era of happiness of which
we have any complete record.
</p><p>
God lives as does his Son, Jesus Christ and they will not indefinitely be mocked. May we
hearken and repent "for the day of the Lord is near in the valley of decision . . . the Lord
will be the hope of his people" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/joel/3/14,16#14">Joel 3:14,16</a>).
</p><p>
Joseph Smith is a true prophet of the Living God and his successors likewise. The mantle of
authority and prophecy and revelation and power lies in his choice servant
who now leads us, President David O. McKay, and he is God's prophet not only to Latter-day
Saints, but to every living soul in all the world. This is my testimony to you, in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
