<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 72-74</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, no one can arise on an occasion like this, before an audience so large
and so eager, without feeling a sense of deep responsibility. I rejoice with you in the growth
and progress made by the Church. I have been greatly uplifted by the proceedings of this
conference.
</p><p>
THE LIGHT OF THE WORLD
</p><p>
The other day, before a large audience of Relief Society workers, in this tabernacle, Dr.
Howard R. Driggs made a remark that has been sounding in my ears since I heard it. "The
word <i>light</i>," he said, "appears frequently in the scriptures." It is the responsibility of the
Church to spread this light among men. Jesus is the light of the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>). His gospel is the
beacon light to direct you and me in our journey through life. Jesus also said on one occasion:
</p><p>
. . . this is the condemnation, that light has come into the world, and men loved darkness
rather than light, because their deeds are evil
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/19#19">John 3:19</a>).
</p><p>
He also admonished:
</p><p>
Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your
Father which is in heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
I feel that this Church, in carrying forward the great program entrusted to it, is actually and
truly spreading light throughout the world.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith in a revelation has said this:
</p><p>
For thus shall my church be called in the last days, even The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints. Verily, I say unto you all: Arise and shine forth, that thy light may be a
standard for the nations (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/4-5#4">D&amp;C 115:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
I wonder if you catch the boldness and the audacity of that statement, made in the early days
when the Church was not so well established nor so well organized as it is today; and yet the
Lord said then through his servant,
</p><p>
Arise and shine forth, that thy light may be a standard for the nations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/5#5">D&amp;C 115:5</a>).
</p><p>
FAITH GIVES PURPOSE IN LIFE
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, great things have been accomplished by the Church, but as we view the
situation now, with its many problems, there is still much to be done. All of us can
contemplate the history of the Church with supreme satisfaction. As I think of these things I
feel that the Latter-day Saints will never surrender their heritage of faith. That faith has given
purpose and significance to their lives. It has opened the Holy Bible to their understanding. It
has sustained them in adversity and trial. It has offered them every inducement to right living.
It has been their refuge and their strength in sorrows and disappointments, and it has
established their belief in moral and spiritual values, a most important belief. Faith in God is
always the pathway to power and achievement; it is the motive power of progress and
advancement.
</p><p>
On one occasion I discussed with a minister of another church some of our religious views.
Finally, he said to me. "I cannot believe that Joseph Smith was divinely called, but I do
believe," he said, "in the principle of tithing taught by your Church." "Why then," I asked, "is
it not practiced by your church?" He hesitated for what seemed to me a long time, and then
replied, "Because we do not have the faith and the conviction among our members which is
characteristic of the Latter-day Saints."
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, I have always regarded that as a great compliment coming as it did from
an outside source and certainly a worthy tribute to the faith and integrity of the Latter-day
Saints.
</p><p>
TEMPLE WORK PART OF GOSPEL PLAN
</p><p>
Two weeks ago we dedicated a beautiful temple at Idaho Falls. Why do we build temples?
Because we believe in temple work; we believe in salvation for the dead as well as for the
living. It is a part of the gospel plan. We believe, too, in the eternity of the marriage covenant
as solemnized in the holy temples. That doctrine is sound, reasonable, consistent, and in
harmony with Paul's teachings when he said:
</p><p>
. . . neither is the man without the woman, neither the woman without the man, in the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/11/11#11">1 Cor. 11:11</a>).
</p><p>
SUCCESS OF MISSIONARY WORK IN HAWAII
</p><p>
A year ago today I was traveling on a steamer headed for the Hawaiian Islands. On Sunday
morning a beautiful service was conducted by a protestant minister. At the conclusion of the
service the minister approached me. After asking some questions about our faith, he turned to
me with this remark, "The greatest missionary enterprise in modern times," he said, "was
launched by the Mormons on the Islands when they began to preach to the natives." As soon
as I reached the Islands I began to inquire. I was told that three or four missionaries in the
early days were laboring in Honolulu with little or no success. Finally, one of them suggested
that they give up their missionary labors on the Islands and return to the mainland. George Q.
Cannon, then a young man of vigor and faith, said to his associates, "No, we cannot return
home; we will continue our labors on these Islands, not among the white population as we
have done, but among the natives." The response to that missionary endeavor was great, and
these people on the Islands in whom the spirit and blood of Israel were strong, joined the
Church by the hundreds, and many of them have remained true and faithful to the covenant so
that today branches, wards, and a stake are organized and functioning among them.
</p><p>
May God bless us in our responsibilities. May he give us faith, wisdom and determination to
carry forward his great work in these, the last days, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
