<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Same Today, Yesterday, and Forever</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 133-135</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"How Firm a Foundation, Ye Saints of the Lord"&mdash;
</p><p>
I am sure I gained strength from the last verse of that song. I have prayed for each one who
has occupied this position during the last three days, and in return I know I shall receive of
their faith and prayers in my behalf as I stand here for a few moments this afternoon. This
was manifest when my associate, Elder Christiansen, placed his hand on my arm a few
moments ago and said, "Hold on, we're with you."
</p><p>
I, too, am happy to sustain Brother Bennion who was chosen here this morning as an Apostle
of the Lord Jesus Christ. I recall along with Sister Longden, how about twenty-four years ago
he brought into our hearts and our souls the words of the Savior to help comfort us. We were
called to undergo a serious tragedy in having our three-year-old daughter, our first-born child,
taken beyond the veil. His words at that time have rung true through the years. I know he will
contribute much with his talents and his leadership to stir the membership of this Church as
he visits throughout the stakes.
</p><p>
As I returned to this building just a while ago with President Ivins and his good wife, it was
beginning to rain. I heard the strains from the organ playing "God Moves in a Mysterious
Way His Wonders to Perform." The words to one of the verses come to me: 
</p><p>
"Ye fearful Saints, fresh courage take; 
The clouds ye so much dread are big with mercy
And shall break in blessing on your head."
</p><p>
I realize that we have had great blessings here in the past three days in the sessions of this
conference; one in particular&mdash;that we have been brought out of the darkness of the world
and into the light of the glories of the gospel of Jesus Christ. I cannot help reflecting upon the
words of Peter, that great Apostle, when he said in his day to that generation,
</p><p>
Ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people;
that ye should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of
darkness into his marvelous light
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
Yes we have been made partakers of the glorious light of the gospel of Jesus Christ. We have
had great manifestations of the inspiration of our Heavenly Father in these sessions of the
conference. I have been reflecting as I have listened to the speakers that there has been no
improvement in the Ten Commandments, and it is reported that they are some thirty-five
hundred years old. There has been no greater wisdom given than that which was given by our
Lord and Savior Jesus Christ in his great Sermon on the Mount, almost twenty centuries ago.
And there has been no greater teaching than that which was given by the Prophet Joseph
Smith when he was asked over a hundred years ago what were the tenets of our faith. He
gave what we now know as the Articles of Faith. They teach the world that we believe in
God and in his son Jesus Christ, and in the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>), and they also confirm those
principles which were taught by the Savior as to how we might gain exaltation and eternal
life. These truths are contained in the gospel which has been restored for us today. Those
Articles of Faith state that men should have authority to perform the ordinances which pertain
to the salvation and the exaltation of our Heavenly Father's children
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/5#5">A of F 1:5</a>). Also, we believe in the
same organization that existed in the primitive church
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/6#6">A of F 1:6</a>). I am grateful that in those Articles of
Faith it teaches us that we believe the Bible to be the word of God as far as it is translated
correctly (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/8#8">A of F 1:8</a>). I am further grateful that I belong to a Church which enables and encourages me to
have a Bible in my home and to peruse it and study it and understand its teachings.
</p><p>
And then the thirteenth article of our faith,
</p><p>
We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, and in doing good to all men, indeed we
may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all things, we hope all things, we
have endured many things, and hope to be able to endure all things. If there is anything
virtuous, lovely or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
Obedience to the Ten Commandments, the Sermon on the Mount, and our own Articles of
Faith revealed in this day will bring the glorious light of the gospel of Jesus Christ into our
lives. We have partaken of a real spiritual feast these past three days. We have exercised some
of our God-given senses. We have come, and those of the listening audience on radio, and the
viewing audience on TV, have also seen and heard. I hope we will take these things into our
hearts that they might register deep into our souls, that we might carry these messages back
into our wards and our stakes, that there might be truly an upsurge of spirituality.
</p><p>
There has been reference made here to the powers which are manifest in the earth: the power
of Jesus Christ on the one hand, and on the other, the power of the adversary. Everything that
is contrary to the teachings which we have heard in this conference is promulgated and taught
by the evil one, and I testify to you that Satan is real. He is not a myth; he is not a
superstition; but he is real, endeavoring to thwart the work of our Heavenly Father. But how
thankful I am for the precious light of the gospel which shines upon us and gives us the
strength to hold on to the truth. Power will be given us to overcome evil if we live close to
the teachings of this conference. We have no greater example than that given by the Savior
himself as he had been tempted and tested, if you please, for forty days and forty nights. He
was able to subdue Satan in several instances as recorded in the fourth chapter of Luke
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/1-13#1">Luke 4:1-13</a>). You
will find there it states that Satan departed <i>for a season</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/13#13">Luke 4:13</a>), giving evidence to me and to all of us
that there is never a time when we won't be subject to the temptations of the adversary as
long as we live in the mortal flesh. I call your attention to the other scripture
which says that the Savior returned to Galilee in the power of the Spirit
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/14#14">Luke 4:14</a>).
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, I'm sure we have been filled with the Spirit of the Lord Jesus Christ
by the truths and light which have been given to us in this conference. May we go back to
our homes in the power of that Spirit, for I bear witness to you that these things are true, that
God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, and that we have a prophet, seer, and revelator, a
mouthpiece of our Heavenly Father directing the affairs of this Church in the earth today, and
these men whom we have sustained as Apostles are literally the true servants and special
witnesses of the Master. This testimony I bear to you in all humility and sincerity and in the
name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
