<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Feed My Sheep"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bernard P. Brockbank</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bernard P. Brockbank, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 65-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brothers and sisters, it is always a joyful and honored occasion to look in the faces of so
many priesthood bearers, to be in the presence of our prophet, twelve apostles, and so many
fine people desiring to enjoy and know the spiritual things of life.
</p><p>
I would like to just mention that in the passing of President Henry D. Moyle, working so
close with him in the mission field, I learned to appreciate his great strength and his power
and his interest in taking the gospel to every soul. He knew no limit, and he always had an
open door to everyone. He always had time for the right things. I have never experienced an
individual like President Moyle, a man of leadership, capacity, and strength, and with so
many varied interests.
</p><p>
Also working in the mission field with President Tanner, I used to marvel at how he could
make so many interviews. I am sure that he tired the same as the rest of us, but it never
seemed to show. Courage and strength&mdash;he has only one real desire and interest and that is to
further the work of the Lord. It was good to share missionary blessings and to have friendship
with these two great missionaries.
</p><p>
I enjoy reading the scriptures. You know, they seem to have quite a human touch. You
remember Peter saying after the Savior's resurrection, and in his absence, "I go a fishing"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/3#3">John 21:3</a>).
That is just about as brief as you can put it. The Savior appeared while Peter and
the disciples were fishing. After the Savior had shown them how to catch fish by casting their
nets under his direction (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/6#6">John 21:6</a>)&mdash;casting
the net under his counsel and his guidance&mdash;that is the way
to fish. He taught them how to be fishers of men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/19#19">Matt. 4:19</a>), to cast their nets under the direction of the
Savior. I would like to take the next part of this great message that the Savior left with Peter
on how to be an effective missionary. This was now the third time that Jesus showed himself
to his disciples after that he was risen from the dead. Jesus saith to Simon Peter, "Simon, son
of Jonas, lovest thou me?"
</p><p>
These scriptures are well known to all. This is a very important question for
each one of us. May I ask each of you, "Do you love the Lord?" The answer almost without
exception would be, "Yes." Let us place ourselves in the position of Peter.
</p><p>
". . . Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? . . . He saith unto him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest
that I love thee. He saith unto him, <i>Feed my lambs</i>." The Lord can tell if we love him.
</p><p>
"He saith to him again the second time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? He saith unto
him, Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. He saith unto him, <i>Feed my sheep</i>.
</p><p>
"He saith unto him the third time, Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me? Peter was grieved
because he saith unto him the third time, Lovest thou me? And he said unto him, Lord, thou
knowest all things; thou knowest that I love thee. Jesus saith unto him, <i>Feed my sheep</i>."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/15-17#15">John 21:15-17</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
Can you picture this great scene of that powerful Peter being asked these simple questions?
And the Lord had a way of knowing how deep the love was within Peter and how to teach
him the way to show his love for Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
We show and prove our love by <i>feeding the lambs and the sheep</i>. There are over three billion
people on the earth today, and at the present rate of teaching, over two and a half billion of
God's children will never be taught the gospel of Jesus Christ. What if you were to live on
this earth and never had a chance to hear and be taught the true way of life?
</p><p>
Our task is great. Teachers are needed. Every member of this Church that has a testimony and
is converted is urgently needed. The lambs and the sheep are hungry for the bread of life, for
the gospel of Jesus Christ. We can show our love by following the prophet of God, "by every
member being a missionary" to bring one or more souls into the Church each year. It is great
to have a prophet. Have you followed the prophet?
</p><p>
I find people occasionally worried and concerned about whether someone else's convert is
fully converted. They are more concerned sometimes about this than about feeding and
teaching their own friends and neighbors the gospel. I learned a lesson about this point in the
mission field.
</p><p>
The missionaries baptized a little Scottish boy, very shabbily dressed, from a very poor home,
family conditions almost as bad as you could find. I asked the missionary, "Why did you
baptize this boy?" "Well, he is a good boy." The boy brought his entire family into the
Church. His father was an alcoholic. He failed to bring his money home. Well, the story has a
beautiful ending. Today the boy's father is the bishop. I learned not to judge the conversion
of someone else. The Lord will hold the person that improperly brings someone into this
Church, and him alone.
</p><p>
Now what have we to teach the people? You know, the Savior gives us this great message.
We don't have to guess at what to teach. The Savior said, ". . . Go ye into all the world, and
preach the gospel to every creature.
</p><p>
"He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-16#15">Mark 16:15-16</a>). And then he gives us
the key. Jesus said: "Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/20#20">Matt. 28:20</a>).
</p><p>
Our job is to teach the people to observe all things whatsoever Jesus Christ has commanded.
We are to teach every nation, kindred, tongue, and people the commandments given by
Christ.
</p><p>
The Prophet Ether in the Book of Mormon is an excellent example of a good effective
missionary. ". . . he could not be restrained because of the Spirit of the Lord which was in
him.
</p><p>
"For he did cry from the morning, even until the going down of the sun, exhorting the people
to believe in God unto repentance lest they should be destroyed, saying unto them that by
faith all things are fulfilled" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/2-3#2">Ether 12:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
Here are some of the things that Jesus commanded:
</p><p>
"Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your
Father which is in heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
Teach them to search the scriptures; they contain the program that God has
provided for his children.
</p><p>
Teach your fellow man to have faith in the Living Personal God as found in the scriptures.
</p><p>
Teach your neighbors and friends that they were created in the image and likeness of God,
their Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
Teach them to have faith in Jesus Christ, the Son of God and the Savior and Redeemer of the
world.
</p><p>
Teach them to repent from sin and evil and to seek first the kingdom of God and his
righteousness.
</p><p>
Teach them baptism&mdash;the same baptism that Jesus exemplified as he went down into the
water at the river Jordan under the hands of God's authorized servant, John the Baptist.
</p><p>
Teach them that they must be born of the spirit and receive the Holy Ghost. Jesus said, ". . .
Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
Teach them to love God and neighbor.
</p><p>
Teach them to pray from their hearts to a Living God and a Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
Teach them that revelation from God to man has never ceased if man desires to know and
receive the heavenly blessings and witnesses.
</p><p>
Teach the people to pray to God and ask for his blessings through the Savior Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Teach them to be kingdom builders. Remember the Lord's Prayer&mdash;". . . When ye pray," the
Lord said, "After this manner therefore pray ye . . .
</p><p>
"Thy kingdom come." Anyone praying after the manner of Jesus Christ prays to be a kingdom
builder. "Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/7,9-10#7">Matt. 6:7,9-10</a>).
</p><p>
Teach them to have joy and happiness; long suffering, goodness, meekness, temperance, love,
peace, and faith; these are the fruits of the Spirit.
</p><p>
Teach them the value and power of the priesthood of God, and that it has been restored to the
earth.
</p><p>
When you teach, follow the Savior's counsel and "let your light shine"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>). Pray always before
you teach for faith, wisdom, and the inspiration of the Holy Ghost. What a marvelous
experience to teach the gospel under the inspiration of the Holy Spirit! What great joy comes
from <i>feeding the lambs and the sheep</i>.
</p><p>
I would like to just mention in closing a little about the World's Fair as a great missionary
venture. I would like to mention that the Church of Jesus Christ's pavilion and exhibit at the
New York World's Fair will help to show the world that we are Christians after the order of
Jesus Christ's program and teachings, that we literally accept the living personal God of the
Holy Bible, that we accept the living personal Jesus Christ as the Son of God and as the
Redeemer and our Savior.
</p><p>
The church pavilion and exhibits will have the beauty and atmosphere of sacred Christian love
and peace. The building, I am sure the architect was inspired by God. It has an atmosphere of
peace and sacredness, the way the golden light enters the building, the way the extension of
the building is designed. It is worth a trip to the fair just to see this marvelous building and
the exhibits.
</p><p>
The church pavilion and exhibits will have the beauty and atmosphere of Christianity. The
theme is "Man's Search for Happiness." We hope to show that happiness comes from
Christian righteousness. We hope to show many of the fruits of the Church. Jesus said, "by
their fruits ye shall know them" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16#16">Matt. 7:16</a>). We will show the restoration of the gospel
of Jesus Christ back to the earth again, the same as it was when Jesus lived upon this earth.
</p><p>
The fair will be for two years, 1964 and 1965. It is estimated that over seventy million people
will attend. In my estimation it will be the finest World's Fair ever held because of the
two-year period.
</p><p>
Our task is great as members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, but with two
million full-time missionaries and Saints, we can teach the people, our neighbors, as Jesus
said, "to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/20#20">Matt. 28:20</a>).
</p><p>
May we all follow our prophet and be missionaries and show our love for
God by <i>feeding the lambs and the sheep</i>, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
