<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Resurrected Christ Appears</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 5-7</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, here in the building and on the air, all children of our Heavenly
Father, I stand before you in humility, in need of help from our Heavenly Father. I have
asked him to help me. I would appreciate an equal prayer from you to the same end.
</p><p>
This is Easter time. The celebration of the resurrection has just passed, and sometimes there is
a tendency to think that thereafter the Lord ascended, and we have nothing more to do about
it. I have had particularly in mind two or three passages that I shall try to recall.
</p><p>
In the Passover chamber, the Lord said, ". . . I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man
cometh unto the Father, but by me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).
At various times in his mission, he added
the word "light," so that in its complete form it stands, "I am the way, the truth, the life, and
the light."
</p><p>
I remember that at the time of the raising of Lazarus, the Lord said, in response to a
statement from Martha:
</p><p>
". . . I am the resurrection, and the life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet
shall he live:<br />
"And whosoever liveth and believeth in me shall never die. Believest thou this?<br />
"She saith unto him, Yea, Lord: I believe that thou art the Christ, the Son of God, which
should come into the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25-27#25">John 11:25-27</a>)
</p><p>
Peter, speaking to the Sanhedrin, in response to their question, ". . . By what power, or by
what name, have ye done this?" replied, ". . . by the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, whom
ye crucified, . . . for there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we
must be saved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/7-10,12#7">Acts 4:7-10,12</a>)
</p><p>
As I have read the record, I have been persuaded that not so fully did the apostles themselves,
up until after the resurrection, understand who the Savior was or might be, as did the learned
men of Israel, who saw, who partially understood, and who feared.
</p><p>
The Savior, the Book tells us in Acts, remained on the earth after his resurrection for forty
days (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/3#3">Acts 1:3</a>),
during which time he worked and preached and, I would assume, assisted in setting in
order his Church.
</p><p>
But I thought that I might run over, so far as my memory serves me, a few of the visual
demonstrations that were given in those early days of the Resurrected Christ. You remember
that an earthquake came before the break of day and rolled back the stone from the sepulchre.
We are not given an account as to how the Savior came from the sepulchre except that we
read that the burial clothes were left in the sepulchre itself.
</p><p>
You remember that Mary Magdalene was the first, even before the dawn broke, to go to the
sepulchre. Seeing it open, she rushed to tell Peter and John. They not realizing, not
understanding, not knowing what to look for, rushed to the sepulchre and found it empty
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/1-9#1">John 20:1-9</a>).
</p><p>
Shortly after that the women came with spices because there had been no time on the
previous Friday night properly to prepare the Christ for his burial. They did not understand
that he was to be resurrected on the morning of the third day, for they came
on that morning properly to dress and prepare the body for burial. Mary Magdalene was with
them and Mary the mother (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/1-2#1">Mark 16:1-2</a>).
You recall that while he forbade Mary, to whom he had already
shown himself, to touch him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/17#17">John 20:17</a>),
he permitted the women to hold his feet.
</p><p>
They saw him. They heard his voice. They knew he was resurrected.
</p><p>
A little later on that day, two of the disciples were on their way to Emmaus. The Savior
joined them. He seemed to be uninformed about what had happened in Jerusalem which
seemed to have been common talk in Jerusalem by that time, and they talked a bit about that.
The Savior did not appear apparently to them as he had appeared before his resurrection. So
he went along with them and began to tell them all about it, who he was, and began to repeat
the scriptures to them. Coming to an inn they invited him in with them. They went in, sat
down, preparing to eat. He broke bread and offered it to them. Then they recognized for the
first time who he was, and he vanished (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/13-32#13">Luke 24:13-32</a>).
</p><p>
That night the ten&mdash;there were only eleven altogether now because Iscariot had committed
suicide; were sitting in a room together and suddenly the Savior stood among them. They
were frightened. They thought he was a spirit. He said, ". . . Why are ye troubled? . . .
Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself: handle me, and see; for a spirit hath not
flesh and bones, as ye see me have"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/38-39#38">Luke 24:38-39</a>).
They had thought he might be a spirit.
</p><p>
And then he asked them&mdash;and this has always been interesting to me&mdash;he asked them for
food&mdash;they were at dinner&mdash;and they gave him broiled fish and honeycomb, and he ate&mdash;a
resurrected being ate of these earthly foods
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/41-42#41">Luke 24:41-42</a>).
</p><p>
Thomas was not there, and Thomas said that he would not believe if he could not touch the
Savior to be sure. Eight days following, the apostles were all together again, this time Thomas
with them, and the doors being shut, so the record says, the Savior suddenly appeared in their
midst and addressing himself to Thomas, with his unbelief, invited an examination of his
body. "Reach hither thy hand," said he, "and thrust it into my side: . . ." Whether Thomas did
as he was bid or not, is not clear, but at the end of it, Thomas said, "My Lord and my God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/26-28#26">John 20:26-28</a>).
</p><p>
Thereafter, or on that same day, he had shown himself to Peter as was disclosed in the report
which was made by these disciples who had seen him on their way to Emmaus
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/33-34#33">Luke 24:33-34</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/5#5">1 Cor. 15:5</a>).
</p><p>
Thereafter, he appeared several times; among others he appeared to five hundred at one time,
and the writer of Acts declared that some were then living of that five hundred when he
wrote (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/6#6">1 Cor. 15:6</a>).
</p><p>
He appeared to the disciples and talked with them thereafter, particularly on the occasion
when Peter and six others of the apostles, apparently, decided that they would go fishing, that
everything was over. So they went fishing. You will all remember, I am very sure, the
incidents of that fishing trip. The apostles had fished all night and caught nothing. As they
neared the shore of the Sea of Galilee they saw a figure on the shore by a fire. The figure
asked them if they had caught any fish. They answered no. Then said he, "Cast the net on the
right side of the ship" which they did, and it was filled with fish. Then John perceived that
this was the Lord and so told the group.
</p><p>
Peter, the impetuous Peter, who sometimes apparently talked before he thought, cast himself
over the side of the boat, having first wrapped himself with his coat, for he was naked and
did not want to appear before the Christ in that kind of condition&mdash;which carries its lesson, I
think, as to chastity and morality and modesty&mdash;and he hurried to the shore. They all went to
the shore. They found there the Lord whom they then recognized. He had already prepared
something to eat and invited them to partake of it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/1-14#1">John 21:1-14</a>).
</p><p>
It is not clear to me whether or not the Lord ate at that time, though the inference might be
that he did.
</p><p>
That was the time when he questioned Peter a bit, "Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more
than these?" referring, I assume, to the fish and the food. "Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I
love thee."<br />
"Feed my lambs" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/15-16#15">John 21:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
The second inquiry came and the same answer, except that at this time the
Lord said, "Feed my sheep." And even a third time did this question come, and the third time
Peter, with what quite evidently was something of irritation, said, "Lord, thou knowest all
things; thou knowest that I love thee."
</p><p>
"Feed my sheep" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/17#17">John 21:17</a>).
</p><p>
A great lesson in three words of the mission and duty of the Church then under organization
and which has been the obligation and the duty from that day until now of those who possess
the priesthood of God, as we do.
</p><p>
Finally, he called them together again on a mount in Galilee, the disciples, and at that time he
gave them the great commission, "Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to every
creature.<br />
"He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved; but he that believeth not shall be damned"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-16#15">Mark 16:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
Those are the words of the Christ. Then he told them of the signs which should follow them
that believed.
</p><p>
We, brethren and sisters, are the recipients of the great blessings that attach to the work of the
last dispensation. We are also the
obligees of the great responsibilities which have been placed upon those whom God has called
to lead this last dispensation. I personally try to think more frequently of the obligations I
have than of the blessings that I have enjoyed, and yet as I cast my mind back over a long
life, I think of no one in my acquaintance who has received greater blessings of health and
strength than have I myself, for which I am grateful.
</p><p>
I am grateful, as we all are, for the prayers of the Saints in our behalf. We know we have
them, we know they are efficacious. We pray that you will overlook our weaknesses and
failings, for each and all of us are human; make us humble but never let us forget our
gratitude for the blessings which we enjoy.
</p><p>
The Lord is good to us. He is giving us direction if we will take it. I urge you to bring your
thoughts back, as I did last night, from space, about which we know nothing in comparison
with what there is to know&mdash;and fix our minds upon the great powers and authorities which
we have as members of the priesthood, representing our Heavenly Father, endowed with a
portion of his authority to work out his purposes, not ours.
</p><p>
I bear my testimony to the truthfulness of the gospel, that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ,
that the Prophet Joseph was a prophet raised up under his direction, who with his authorities
through the revelations of our Heavenly Father, founded the Church. I bear my testimony that
the same Spirit and the same power and the same authority with which he, the Prophet
Joseph, was invested, now exists in the Church and has since its foundation, that President
David O. McKay is the recipient of that power and that authority today.
</p><p>
I urge upon you with all the fervor that I can express, that we follow the leadership of the
Church, know that President McKay is the prophet, seer, and revelator of the Church, that we
bring our lives into complete harmony with the commandments of the Lord, all to the end
that having fulfilled our obligations to the dead and to the living, we may be finally saved and
exalted in his presence, which I ask in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
