<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Repent and Turn to God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Patriarch Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 77-79</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Since the dawn of history, civilizations have fallen or been destroyed when the people became
ripened in iniquity. It seems that when we, as mortals, follow the path of least resistance, our
moral standards fall rather than rise.
</p><p>
<b>Wickedness in history</b>
</p><p>
Genesis tells us of the conditions which preceded the flood. The book of Moses gives more
detail. Noah preached to the people, calling them to repentance, but they mocked him and
refused to listen. The Lord sent the flood in his anger against the wickedness of the people.
Only Noah, his wife, and his three sons and their wives were saved&mdash;and that because of
their righteousness.
</p><p>
Time and again throughout Bible and Book of Mormon history the wicked multitudes have
been destroyed and only those who were the more righteous remained. Does this mean that
God does not strive to help his people and to teach them? No! His prophets are preaching the
word of God. Enoch preached to the wicked people with such success that they became
righteous&mdash;so righteous, in fact, that the entire city of Zion "was not, for God received it up
into his own bosom" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/69#69">Moses 7:69</a>).
</p><p>
It is said that history repeats itself. If this is true, and I believe it is, then the Book of
Mormon should be one of the most valuable records we have. It gives us a record of a people
from their small beginning, through many generations, through growth and decay.
</p><p>
Here, then, we should find the answer to all the national problems of peace and war. What do
we find? Look at the over-all story and we find a continual wave of peace with righteousness
on the one hand and wars accompanied by, or the result of, unrighteousness on the other.
</p><p>
<b>Promise to the righteous</b>
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon early in the history records a great promise referring to the people who
should possess this land (the Americas). The Lord made the promise that if they should "serve
him according to the commandments which he hath given, it shall be a land of liberty unto
them; wherefore, they shall never be brought down into captivity; if so, it shall be <i>because</i> of
iniquity; for if iniquity shall abound cursed shall be the land for their sakes but unto the
<i>righteous</i> it shall be blessed <i>forever</i>" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/1/7#7">2 Ne. 1:7</a>, italics added). The word "forever" brings
this promise to us in this day also.
</p><p>
This promise and warning is repeated often in the Book of Mormon Yet, all through history
we find wars, and contentions associated with sin and unrighteousness.
</p><p>
<b>Faithfulness and deliverance from adversity</b>
</p><p>
When the people were faithful in keeping his commandments, God blessed them with
prosperity and peace and helped them fight their battles against their enemies. The following
is typical of many such examples: 
</p><p>
". . . the Nephites had all power over their enemies; and thus the Lamanites did attempt to
destroy the Nephites until their chief captains were all slain; yea, and more than a thousand of
the Lamanites were slain; while, on the other hand, there was not a single soul of the
Nephites which was slain" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/49/23#23">Alma 49:23</a>).
</p><p>
The Lamanite leader "was exceedingly wroth, and he did curse God, and also Moroni . . . and
this because Moroni had kept the commandments of God in preparing for the safety of his
people.
</p><p>
"And it came to pass, that on the other hand, the people of Nephi did thank the Lord their
God, because of his matchless power in delivering them from the hands of their enemies"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/49/27-28#27">Alma 49:27-28</a>).
</p><p>
The story of the sons of Helaman is another matchless tale of the blessings of God and the
rewards for keeping his commandments.
</p><p>
These promises refer as much to us today as they did to the time in which they were given.
You cannot deny that God has guided our destiny, that the settlement of this land, the
declaration against tyranny, the war that followed, the framing of a constitution&mdash;all have
been guided by the hand of God. How else could his gospel have been brought forth, were it
not for the blessed freedom provided in this "land of promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>)?
</p><p>
And now here we are today, the recipients of the greatest blessings of all time. What are we
doing with them?
</p><p>
<b>The cycle of righteousness</b>
</p><p>
Where are we now in this cycle of life&mdash;this cycle of righteousness with peace and prosperity
or unrighteousness and wickedness, accompanied by wars and destruction? This is what an
editorial from the <i>San Francisco Examiner</i> has to say: 
</p><p>
<b>The deluge of woe</b>
</p><p>
"What has happened to our national morals?
</p><p>
"An educator speaks out in favor of free love.
</p><p>
"A man of God condones sexual excursions by unmarried adults.
</p><p>
"Movies sell sex as a commercial commodity.
</p><p>
"Bookstores and cigar stands peddle pornography.
</p><p>
"A high court labels yesterday's smut as today's literature.
</p><p>
"Record shops feature albums displaying nudes and near nudes.
</p><p>
"Night clubs stage shows that would have shocked a smoker audience a generation ago.
</p><p>
"TV shows and TV commercials pour out a flood of sick, sadistic and suggestive sex
situations.
</p><p>
"A campaign is launched to bring acceptance to homosexuality.
</p><p>
"Radio broadcasts present discussions for and against promiscuity.
</p><p>
"Magazines and newspapers publish pictures and articles that flagrantly violate the bounds of
good taste.
</p><p>
"Birth control counsel is urged for high school girls.
</p><p>
"Look around you. These things are happening in <i>your</i> America. In the two decades since the
end of World War II we have seen our national standards of morality lowered again and
again.
</p><p>
"We have seen a steady erosion of past principles of decency and good taste.
</p><p>
"And&mdash;we have harvested a whirlwind. As our standards have lowered our crime levels and
social problems have increased.
</p><p>
"Today, we have a higher percentage of our youth in jail . . . in reformatories . . . on
probation and in trouble than ever before.
</p><p>
"Study the statistics on illegitimate births . . . on broken marriages . . . on juvenile crimes . . .
on school drop outs . . . on sex deviation . . . on dope addiction . . . on high school marriages
. . . on crimes of passion.
</p><p>
"The figures are higher than ever. And going higher."
</p><p>
How do we stand today?
</p><p>
With this level of corruption at home, how can we expect to have peace or victory on the
battlefield? Satan knows that time is short, and he's waging an all-out effort to win. He's
stopping at nothing.
</p><p>
The enemy in Viet Nam is the same enemy at home. It is the same force of evil that is the
cause of riots and destruction all over our country. The same force that is causing all the
conditions referred to in the <i>San Francisco Examiner</i> is prevalent all over our land.
</p><p>
With conditions at home as here described, is it any wonder that we are at war in Viet Nam?
The answer for peace is not military might alone. We must turn to God and keep his
commandments. We must seek him in prayer, and be sincere in our prayers.
</p><p>
We must cleanse ourselves from all iniquity. We must humble ourselves must again make the
home sacred, and we must honor virtue!
</p><p>
<b>Repent and return to God</b>
</p><p>
There is only one answer: Repent and turn to God.
</p><p>
Will you who are within the sound my voice strive with your whole souls to live the kind of
life Christ would have you lead? to "love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy
soul, and with all thy mind . . . And . . . love thy neighbor as thyself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37,39#37">Matt. 22:37,39</a>)?
</p><p>
"Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glorify your
Father which is in heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
President McKay has said: "Peace is the exemption from individual troubles, from family
brawls, from national difficulties. Peace does not come to the transgressor of law. Peace
comes by obedience to law, peace to the individual that he may be at peace with God at peace
in the home, and in the neighborhood. Peace can come to the world only through obedience
to the gospel of Jesus Christ."
</p><p>
I pray that we may all keep the commandments of the Lord, that we may have the blessings
promised that this "shall be a land of liberty" and "never be brought down into captivity," that
this land shall be "blessed forever" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/1/7#7">2 Ne. 1:7</a>).
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
