<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Follow Counsel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop John H. Vandenberg</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Vandenberg, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 39-42</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"The backslider in heart shall be filled with his own ways"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/14/14#14">Prov. 14:14</a>) is a proverb
credited to the ancient King Solomon, who the Bible records was ". . . wiser than all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/4/31#31">1 Kgs. 4:31</a>).
It is assumed that Solomon in this proverb referred to those who had
retrogressed in their allegiance to God by failing to give heed to his counsel. Frequently God
has sent his prophets to counsel his children in an attempt to arrest them from their
wrongdoing, their backsliding, and to point the way to happiness and salvation. The task of
persuading man from his carnal ways has always been an arduous struggle, as evidenced by
history. The inhabitants of the earth seem eager to be filled with their own ways. Because of
this the prophets have, from time to time, suffered much tribulation.
</p><p>
<b>Counsel of the Prophets</b>
</p><p>
Jeremiah was such a prophet. In his day he faced almost continuous opposition and insult as
he tried to stem the tide of idolatry and immorality among the people. During his lifetime he
tried to teach the multitude that true worship of Jehovah required more than devotion to
external forms of worship. His message was: One must live and dedicate oneself to keeping
all of God's commandments. At last, many, too blind to see that they were heading for
destruction and captivity and no longer of a mind to listen to Jeremiah, were the cause of his
being stoned to death. His tragic death, however, did not nullify or stay his decreed counsel,
for soon the people passed through all of the adversity that he foretold would transpire if they
did not repent of their evil ways.
</p><p>
In contrast, in this same period we learn of a refreshing episode wherein the Lord told the
Prophet Jeremiah to go into the house of certain men called Rechabites and to invite them
into the house of the Lord and give them wine to drink. When wine was placed before them,
however, they refused to drink because their father had counseled them never to drink wine
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/35/1-7#1">Jer. 35:1-7</a>).
"Thus have we obeyed the voice of . . . our father in all that he hath charged us"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/35/8#8">Jer. 35:8</a>),
they said. After these young men had reaffirmed their steadfastness in following the
counsel of their father, the Lord through his prophet pronounced upon them a special blessing.
He decreed that members of this family and their seed would always be numbered among the
righteous (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/35/18-19#18">Jer. 35:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
The determination to follow good counsel, to obey divine law, is paramount for true success
and happiness in life. In the era in which we live, as anciently, the Lord has sent us his
prophets and has reaffirmed the need to adhere to his precepts. The Prophet Joseph Smith, on
April 2, 1843, said, "There is a law, irrevocably decreed in heaven before the foundations of
this world, upon which all blessings are predicated&mdash;
</p><p>
"And when we obtain any blessing from God, it is by obedience to that law upon which it is
predicated" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/20-21#20">D&amp;C 130:20-21</a>).
Paralleling this revealed truth is the admonition:
</p><p>
". . . let every man learn his duty, and to act in the office in which he is appointed, in all
diligence.
</p><p>
"He that is slothful shall not be counted worthy to stand, and he that learns not his duty . . .
shows himself not approved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100#99">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>).
</p><p>
<b>To Ignore Counsel is to Invite Failure</b>
</p><p>
It seems that one of the great weaknesses in man's character is the tendency to shun good
counsel and instruction. Men do, in fact, set up barriers for themselves, for they seem to want
to become laws unto themselves. Jacob understood this when he warned, ". . . O the vainness,
and the frailties, and the foolishness of men! When they are learned they think they are wise,
and they hearken not unto the counsel of God, for they set it aside, supposing they know of
themselves, wherefore, their wisdom is foolishness and it profiteth them not . . .
</p><p>
"But to be learned is good if they hearken unto the counsels of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/28-29#28">2 Ne. 9:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
Some years ago the MIA theme was, ". . . seek not to counsel the Lord, but
to take counsel from his hand. For behold, ye yourselves know that he counseleth in wisdom,
and in justice, and in great mercy, over all his works"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/4/10#10">Jacob 4:10</a>).
</p><p>
There have been some noble men who unwittingly sought to counsel the Lord. One such man
was Hezekiah, king of Judah, who began to reign when he was twenty-five years old. The
scriptures tell us that during his reign ". . . he did that which was right in the sight of the
Lord . . .
</p><p>
"He removed the high places, and brake the images, and cut down the groves, and
brake in pieces the brasen serpent . . . for . . . the children of Israel did burn incense to it . . .
</p><p>
"He trusted in the Lord God of Israel; so that after him was none like him among all the
kings of Judah, nor any that were before him.
</p><p>
"For he clave to the Lord, and departed not from following him, but kept his commandments,
which the Lord commanded Moses" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/18/3-6#3">2 Kgs. 18:3-6</a>).
</p><p>
It is recorded that in about the fifteenth year of Hezekiah's reign, ". . . Hezekiah [was] sick
unto death. And the prophet Isaiah . . . came to him, and said unto him, Thus saith the Lord,
Set thine house in order; for thou shalt die, and not live.
</p><p>
"Then he turned his face to the wall, and prayed unto the Lord, saying,
</p><p>
"I beseech thee, O Lord, remember now how I have walked before thee in truth and with a
perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy sight"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/20/1-3#1">2 Kgs. 20:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord then spoke to Isaiah the Prophet and said to him, ". . . tell Hezekiah . . . Thus saith
the Lord . . . I have heard thy prayer, I have seen thy tears: behold, I will heal thee . . .
</p><p>
"And I will add unto thy days fifteen years" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/20/5-6#5">2 Kgs. 20:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
Thus the Lord granted Hezekiah's request to extend his life. This, no doubt, was enjoyed by
Hezekiah, for during these additional years he did many things. But there was one unforeseen
occurrence that destroyed much of the good he had accomplished. Hezekiah sired a son who
was twelve years of age when his father passed away. This son, whose name was Manasseh,
became king and ". . . did that which was evil in the sight of the Lord, after the abominations
of the heathen . . .
</p><p>
". . . he reared up altars for Baal . . .
</p><p>
". . . used enchantments, and dealt with familiar spirits and wizards: he wrought much
wickedness in the sight of the Lord, to provoke him to anger.
</p><p>
". . . Moreover Manasseh shed innocent blood very much . . . [and] filled Jerusalem . . . in
doing that which was evil in the sight of the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/21/2-3,6,16#2">2 Kgs. 21:2-3,6,16</a>).
</p><p>
As one reviews this account, one wonders, would it not have been better for Hezekiah to have
submissively accepted the Lord's first decree, ". . . Set thine house in order; for thou shalt
die" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/20/1#1">2 Kgs. 20:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Father Adam Accepted Counsel</b>
</p><p>
Father Adam set us a splendid example of following counsel. After Adam and Eve were
driven out from the Garden of Eden, the Lord ". . . gave unto them commandments, that they
should worship the Lord their God, and should offer the firstlings of their flocks, for an
offering unto the Lord. And Adam was obedient unto the commandments of the Lord.
</p><p>
"And after many days an angel of the Lord appeared unto Adam, saying: Why dost thou offer
sacrifices unto the Lord? And Adam said unto him: I know not, save the Lord commanded
me.
</p><p>
"And then the angel spake, saying: This thing is a similitude of the sacrifice of the Only
Begotten of the Father, which is full of grace and truth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/5-7#5">Moses 5:5-7</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Be Submissive to God</b>
</p><p>
Our attitude should be one of submissiveness to all of God's commandments. We need not
indulge in self-sophisticated reasoning to justify our compliance with God's counsel. Our
motivation should be based upon a desire to serve.
</p><p>
The late President Joseph F. Smith said if the President of the Church ". . . or somebody else
gives counsel to some of our brethren, if it does not suit them exactly, they will begin to
whine about it, and shed great crocodile tears, perhaps. I have heard of men shedding tears
because they had received counsel from their brethren! And what is more,
the men that shed tears and mourn over having received a little counsel, are the kind that do
not carry it out; or, if they do, they tell why they did it&mdash;making somebody else responsible
for their acts" (<i>Conference Report</i>, April 1899, p. 70).
</p><p>
I believe that God wants his children to be happy and has charted the course through prophets
for its attainment. I believe that true happiness will only come in this life by following his
counsel. As someone has said, "Doing the will of God leaves no time for disputing about his
plan."
</p><p>
<b>An Example from the Old Testament</b>
</p><p>
We can learn another lesson from an incident in the Old Testament concerning a captain in
the Syrian army whose name was Naaman. Syria's armies had attacked ancient Israel, and
Naaman had brought as a captive an Israelite maid who waited on his wife.
</p><p>
Naaman was a great soldier, but he was afflicted with leprosy. The little Israelite girl told her
mistress about the Prophet Elisha who could heal her husband. So Naaman went to the
Prophet Elisha, expecting a ceremonious reception. He was bitterly disappointed. Elisha didn't
even go to the door to greet him; instead, he sent a servant with a message saying: ". . . Go
and wash in Jordan seven times, and thy flesh shall come again to thee, and thou shalt be
clean" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/5/10#10">2 Kgs. 5:10</a>)
</p><p>
This made Naaman very angry. He was disappointed; he expected Elisha to satisfy his vanity
with some ritual in calling upon the Lord. He then questioned indignantly: Why the river
Jordan? Are not there other rivers that are better? He turned to go away sullenly. Whereupon
his servant spoke to him and said, ". . . if the prophet had bid thee to do some great thing,
wouldest thou not have done it?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/5/13#13">2 Kgs. 5:13</a>).
This question cleared Naaman's thinking, and he resolved to
follow the prophet's advice, and he went down and dipped himself seven times in the river
Jordan. His flesh came again like unto a little child, and he was clean. Naaman went back to
the Prophet Elisha, filled with gratitude, and offered to pay him for making him whole. But
Elisha knew it was by the power of God that Naaman was made well and declined the gift
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/5/1-16#1">2 Kgs. 5:1-16</a>).
</p><p>
You can imagine the joy that Naaman and his family experienced as a result of following the
counsel and direction of the prophet.
</p><p>
<b>A Modern Example</b>
</p><p>
A few years ago, a bishop from a small agricultural town visited my office to arrange for the
dedication of the meetinghouse in his ward. During our conversation he told me that when he
was advised by the brethren to build a meetinghouse, he had many doubts, since it was a
small community with modest resources. He said, "I didn't have the slightest idea where the
money was coming from, but following counsel, we started, and the funds came and now we
are ready to dedicate, having all bills paid." Then he added, "And do you know, the tithing
paid by those good Saints has increased over 600% during the three-year period!" I have
never seen a person filled with more joy and satisfaction than this good bishop, who simply
followed counsel.
</p><p>
Recently a member of the church building committee told me about a visit he had made to a
new building project. This particular project had been completed with such efficiency and
order that everyone viewed the achievement as an unbelievable feat. I was told that they did
nothing dramatic to bring about the accomplishment; they simply followed the counsel given
through the program. He said further that "on this project, as on many others, the Lord's hand
has been plainly manifested in procuring materials and performing the work. These fine
people can testify that the building program is inspired of God. The workmanship is excellent,
the people have grown spiritually, and there is a unity and oneness in the group, resulting
from the united desire to follow direction."
</p><p>
Likewise, all of us should be eager to adopt and follow the suggested programs of the Church,
for in this respect we demonstrate our willingness to heed counsel.
</p><p>
I pray that we will continue to cultivate a firm resolve, as demonstrated by
Nephi when he declared, ". . . I will go and do the things which the Lord hath commanded,
for I know that the Lord giveth no commandments unto the children of men, save he shall
prepare a way for them that they may accomplish the thing which he commandeth them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/7#7">1 Ne. 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
