<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Testimony&mdash;A Motivating Force</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Theodore M. Burton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Theodore M. Burton, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 65-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, it is a great pleasure again to be with you, and to participate in
that which has taken place this day. I pledge anew my loyalty to the First Presidency and to
the Quorum of the Twelve, and tell you that I know in my heart these men are called of God
as prophets, seers, and revelators. I am grateful for their leadership, and I am grateful for my
associates among the General Authorities. These are wonderful men, and I am very, very
grateful for the privilege I have of working together with them.
</p><p>
Last Sunday I talked by telephone with all the mission presidents in the European Mission
and received their reports. I am happy to tell you that the missionaries are well- they are
happy; they are enjoying their work; and we are having great success in the European
Mission.
</p><p>
Usually in summer we have quite a drop in converts during the time the Europeans take their
summer holidays, for they take them very seriously. This year, just as the holidays were
beginning, we had a wonderful visit from President [Henry D.] Moyle and from Elder
[Gordon] Hinckley. These two wonderful men, devoting themselves to the work of the Lord,
came over to help us. I just can't express to you our gratitude for the help they gave us. As a
result of their visit our August conversions were twenty-eight percent above our conversions
for July. Our September conversions were thirty-seven percent above our August conversions.
</p><p>
These new converts are good people. They are excellent people. We were instructed to
emphasize group instruction, and we were told&mdash;in fact, these brethren insisted&mdash;that we
strive for true conversions. We are only interested in those people whose hearts had been
broken and whose spirits are contrite. These are the people who have come into the Church.
We have some wonderful, strong, new converts.
</p><p>
These are dedicated converts, willing to sacrifice and willing to work. There was nothing new
in what these brethren told us. We can summarize it in just about four simple statements, but
they are fundamental principles; for instance, there is happiness in work, and
we all know that. There is joy in dedication, and that we know, too. There is success in
spirituality, and achievement comes only through sacrifice. By using these magical keys we
have had our present success, and things look very wonderful for the future.
</p><p>
This success is represented by a recent meeting held in the city of Berlin. When President
ElRay L. Christiansen came to visit the temples, President Percy K. Fetzer wanted to hold a
special group meeting in Berlin and take full advantage of that wonderful man and his ability
to sway and move people. So a special evening conference session for investigators was
called. Usually people are pretty tired after they have been in meetings since eight o'clock in
the morning. However an evening meeting was called, and the people who came exceeded
their wildest expectations. There were 687 people in that investigator meeting to hear the
testimonies that were given, and to hear the wonderful address that Elder Christiansen gave.
</p><p>
From that meeting we had 460 good referrals that the elders in Berlin are working on. Is it
any wonder that the month just past established a new record in the number of conversions in
the Berlin Mission? They are looking forward to the future with great enthusiasm. The
missionaries are on fire, so is the mission president, and I am walking up in the clouds, too.
</p><p>
You know, there is no blessing with out sacrifice, but it isn't a sacrifice unless it hurts. I like
President Tanner's definition of sacrifice. "Sacrifice means going without or giving up
something which is good for something which is better." Now, our missionaries are willing to
make such sacrifice, and truly they give up many good things. They sacrifice from two to two
and a half years of their lives. They put aside schooling, employment, cars and sports,
vacations, and dancing, swimming and friends, families and sweethearts for a time, to work
harder than most of them have ever worked before in their whole lives.
</p><p>
Why do they do it? As we were coming home, we talked to a sweet little girl on the plane, a
stewardess of Norwegian birth. We talked to her about our religion and asked her the Golden
Questions of course. She said that she was very satisfied with her present religion. She said
that she was a member of the state church, and so I congratulated her on her activity. I said,
"It pleases us to know that people believe what they profess." She said, "Oh yes, I am very
active in our church. We attend church regularly."
</p><p>
I said, "That is wonderful. I am happy to hear that."
</p><p>
"Yes," she said, "we go every Christmas and every Easter."
</p><p>
"I am happy to know that," I answered, and she went on to say, "My father thinks we can
worship God in free nature."
</p><p>
I said, "Indeed we can, too, but is that what Jesus Christ told us to do?"
</p><p>
"Well," she said, "I don't know." Then I told her about the sacrifices that were made by our
people who believed from the bottom of their hearts that the work they were doing is true,
and I said to her, "Would you give up your present job as a stewardess, paying your own way
on a mission for two or two and a half years to proclaim the divinity of the faith that you
profess?"
</p><p>
She shook her head. I said, "Would you make such sacrifices as our people make?" And then
I told her some of the things done in our Church by our people. I said, "Would you willingly
pay ten percent of your income to back up your belief? Would you fast monthly and give a
fast offering the way we do in our Church as a demonstration of your belief?"
</p><p>
"No," she said. "I am amazed at the faithfulness and the devotion of your people." I said to
her, "Then why do we do it?" I ask you that question, and I ask people all over the world
why such things are done in this Church. Well, they are done simply because people are
convinced in their hearts that these things are true, and that is the only reason, just as Paul
said: 
</p><p>
"For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation to
every one that believeth; to the Jew first, and also to the Greek"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
Furthermore, Christ said, beginning at the sixteenth chapter and
twenty-fourth verse of Matthew: ". . . If any man will come after me, let him deny himself, and take
up his cross, and follow me.
</p><p>
"For whosoever will save his life shall lose it: and whosoever will lose his life for my sake
shall find it.
</p><p>
"For what is a man profited if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul? or what
shall a man give in exchange for his soul?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/24-26#24">Matt. 16:24-26</a>).
</p><p>
Truly, these young Mormon missionaries are obtaining the greatest thing in this whole life, a
testimony of the divinity of Jesus Christ. Do you wonder, then, that when they come back
home at the close of their missions they are strong and stalwart, courageous and unafraid, and
that they fit well into life again to take up their positions rightfully as leaders? We have had
timid young girls come to us in the mission field so frightened when they first came, that they
would cry when you would look at them. When they get through with their missions, they are
not afraid of anything. They are full of courage and determination, willing to sacrifice because
of the testimony which is within their hearts.
</p><p>
There is another missionary endeavor which I would like to mention just briefly. It is not well
understood in the Church, for it is too new. To me it represents something which proves
definitely that this Church is led by a prophet. I am referring to a new revolutionary concept
which we call our labor-missionary or better, our building missionary program. It began very
quietly in the far reaches of the Pacific Ocean but has now spread to all parts of the world,
where skilled and successful men like many of you sitting right here today have responded to
a missionary call to serve without salary, and have taken their families into foreign lands and
foreign places to build beautiful church buildings. We are having so many converts come into
the Church that it is all we can do to provide places for them to worship. Most churches are
having a hard time to get congregations. We are having a hard time to provide meetinghouses
for our congregations to meet in.
</p><p>
Think of the sacrifice that this requires, taking a family with you into foreign lands, where the
children have their schooling partially interrupted, living under difficult conditions, leaving
business connections, devoting themselves to the faith. Yet I have never heard one of them
complain, nor express any regret for the course they have taken. They are converted, and they
are accomplishing a great work.
</p><p>
Young people can come into the Church now and almost immediately respond to a call to
serve. By sacrificing they become strong, capable people. Let me just give you a couple of
quick illustrations.
</p><p>
One young man in southern Germany came into the Church. He had only been in the Church
a very short while. He was a printer by trade. Some of the missionaries talked to him about
their farewells, since he was being called as a building missionary. So, being a printer, he
designed and printed his own mission program just the way our young people have their
programs printed here. He went to his father, who was not a member of the Church, and
asked him if he would speak on his farewell program. His father said, "Why, no, I am not
going to have anything to do with those Mormons." The boy said, "Father, you can't shame
me before my people. They expect that my father will come to my farewell program and say
something kind about me."
</p><p>
Well, the father was put in a delicate situation, and so he said, "Well I'll do it." He went to
the farewell very unwillingly, but when he came to the meeting hall and saw the love of those
people for his son, when he saw how they respected him, when he saw what his son was
actually going to do, he understood the program for the first time. When he was called upon
to speak, he stood up in the meeting and talked himself right into the Church.
</p><p>
We had a little widow sister in Berlin whose son was called on a building mission. At first
the brethren were unwilling to call him because they said it would mean too great a sacrifice.
When his mother heard about it, she said, "I want my son to go on that mission," and he
went. She has taken a job to support him while he is on his labor mission.
</p><p>
Our young people, even our new converts, will sacrifice, because of the strong testimony they
have of the truthfulness of this work. Miracles are happening, therefore, right in front of our
eyes, for this is God's work. Like the builders of Solomon's temple, these young men and
women are erecting buildings and houses for the children of God to honor and worship the
Father. They are building holy houses of prayer and worship, beautiful beyond anything we
used to dream of.
</p><p>
And what does this do to the people? Well, you see, under this wonderful new program we
are not just building buildings. We are building men and women, and when they return they
are going to be instructed in the Church, its principles, and in righteousness and be able to fill
any position we ask them to. I will venture to say that in years to come, as we begin to
establish more and more stakes and wards in foreign areas, that those building missionaries
will be some of those who will show the necessary leadership to fill such positions as bishops
and high councilmen and stake presidents of those foreign stakes.
</p><p>
This is a wonderful work. I am grateful to be part of it. I am grateful for prophets to lead us,
for faith to accomplish these modern miracles, but all this is only possible because of the
knowledge in the hearts of the people that Jesus is indeed the Living Christ. The hearts of our
people are placed upon the altar, a living testimony to the divinity of this work. This
testimony I also leave with you, for I know that this work is true, and I say it in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
