<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Value of the Individual</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Merrill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Merrill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 111-115</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren, we are alone this evening, the microphone having been switched off from the
powerful KSL broadcasting station. We, therefore, become a priesthood leadership meeting of
the same type as we are now holding as a part of stake quarterly conferences. So it will be in
order for me, I hope, to talk about matters that primarily concern priesthood officers.
</p><p>
EFFECTS OF HARSHNESS AND KINDNESS
</p><p>
In the bishops' meeting last evening in this hall, Bishop M. O. Ashton told two stories that
deeply impressed me. Each story was about a bishop and some boys. In the first one, a group
of boys engaged in some Halloween pranks of a rather serious, provocative nature. The bishop
secured the names of the boys and charged them to come to the sacrament meeting and
publicly ask forgiveness for engaging in the pranks committed, on pain of excommunication
for failure to do so. In consequence there are in that community today a number of families
that grew up outside of the Church.
</p><p>
In the second case a group of boys and a bishop were involved. A wedding party was held at
the bishop's home. A big freezer of ice cream waited on the back porch for the refreshment
hour. When the cream was to be served, it was observed that the freezer was empty.
Pondering over the matter the bishop decided to invite the guilty boys to an ice cream festival
and provided two freezers of ice cream for the occasion. All the boys accepted the invitation.
When the lads were seated at the feast, it was noticed that tears began to run down one boy's
face. Soon all the other boys were in tears also. From among that group have come some of
the finest leaders in their community.
</p><p>
Those were the factual stories told by Bishop Ashton. Hearing them I was reminded of
section 121:39-41, D&amp;C, which reads as follows:
</p><p>
We have learned by sad experience that it is the nature and disposition of almost all men, as
soon as they get a little authority, as they suppose, they will immediately begin to exercise
unrighteous dominion. Hence many are called, but few are chosen. No power or influence can
or ought to be maintained by virtue of the priesthood, only by persuasion, by long-suffering,
by gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/39-41#39">D&amp;C 121:39-41</a>).
</p><p>
The two bishops of the story were undoubtedly actuated by the best of motives. Not for a
moment would I question that. But one bishop was wise and the other unwise. The thought in
the mind of one was to use persuasion, long-suffering, gentleness, meekness, and love, so
beautifully stated in the revelation quoted. In the case of the other bishop he seems to have
acted impulsively, yielding to the influence of the evil power. He forgot the
scriptural injunction found in the D&amp;C 64:9-10:
</p><p>
Wherefore, I say unto you, that ye ought to forgive one another; for he that forgiveth not his
brother his trespasses standeth condemned before the Lord; for there remaineth in him the
greater sin. I, the Lord, will forgive whom I will forgive, but of you it is required to forgive
all men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/9-10#9">D&amp;C 64:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
I do not find in the teachings of the Master the word "must" used in the sense of force. But
we do find the message of the foregoing quoted scripture printed in a beautiful hymn, found
in the L.D.S. <i>Hymn Book</i>, 24th edition, 1905, the first two stanzas being as follows:
</p><p>
Know this, that ev'ry soul is free<br />
To choose his life and what he'll be; <br />
For this eternal truth is given,<br />
That God will force no man to heaven
</p><p>
He'll call, persuade, direct aright,<br />
And bless with wisdom, love, and light; <br />
In nameless ways be good and kind, <br />
But never force the human mind.
</p><p>
FREE AGENCY A GOD-GIVEN PRINCIPLE
</p><p>
We all remember, according to the scriptures, both ancient and modern, in that great council
held in heaven when a plan was being considered to offer the Father's children when they
came to earth, that Lucifer, the son of the morning, was there. He wanted to be sent to earth
to have charge, promising the Father that all his children would be returned to him&mdash;none to
be lost&mdash;provided the Lord would give Lucifer his glory (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1-4#1">Moses 4:1-4</a>). Satan proposed
to accomplish his purpose by the use of force by denying men their free agency, taking from
them their inalienable right that the Father gave to all his children in the spirit world as well
as in the world of mortality. Free agency and accountability go hand in hand they complement
each other.
</p><p>
But I have digressed; let me return. There is no indication in the stories Bishop Ashton told
that either bishop wanted to take free agency from the boys, but they certainly wanted to
reform the boys. One succeeded, and the other failed, due to the methods employed. And this
suggests the need for care, study, and prayer not only in dealing with boys but in dealing with
all other people as well. Perhaps no two individuals are exactly alike. What is good for one
may be bad for another. What succeeds with one may utterly fail with another. I have heard
physicians say that this is one reason that makes the practice of medicine interesting&mdash;the fact
that the doctor continually faces a challenge; for what is one man's meat may be another
man's poison.
</p><p>
BISHOP'S DUTIES
</p><p>
In large measure, a bishop deals with individuals rather than with people en masse. If it were
not so, there would often be insufficient reasons for dividing a large ward, for large wards
have some advantages not usually possessed by smaller ones. But the need of individual
treatment requires of the bishop wisdom, discernment, tact, sympathy, love, in order that he
may succeed, without giving offense, in best serving his people. Among other duties, he is
required to administer programs designed to help the boys and girls of his ward. As I see it
these duties, in general, are second in importance to no others. If we can save the youth of the
Church, we will save the Church. I would not have anyone think, however, that the individual
exists for the Church. The reverse is true&mdash;the Church exists for its members. Because this is
true, the Church is perhaps the finest example of a large democratic organization found in all
the world. No individual can grow up in it, taking advantage of the opportunities offered him
therein, without experiencing large personal growth and development in personality, attributes,
talents, powers, and other leadership qualities.
</p><p>
ETERNAL PROGRESSION
</p><p>
Yes, the Church teaches the fact that each of us is a child of God, both in the spirit and in the
flesh. Since in the realm of life, like begets like, we normally must possess, even though in
ultra-microscopic quantities, the attributes of God our Father. And a characteristic teaching of
the Church is that "as God now is man may become"&mdash;a statement in poetic language of our
magnificent doctrine of eternal progression. Man is in very deed the acme of creation. In the
language of the Psalmist we too can ask:
</p><p>
What is man, that thou are mindful of him? and the son of man, that thou visitest him? For
thou hast made him a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and
honour (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/4-5#4">Ps. 8:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
So in the plan of eternal progression life here on earth is an essential link, and in this link the
most important thing is man&mdash;the individual. This is evident from the plan which, if
successfully followed, will lead the participants back to the Father's presence. The Lord
revealed to Moses that:
</p><p>
. . . This is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
To accomplish his purposes the Lord has set up his highly organized Church as an agency to
serve his children. Hence the Church exists for us and for all who will accept its service.
</p><p>
SERVICE BRINGS OPPORTUNITY AND RESPONSIBILITY
</p><p>
And we who are here this evening, and many thousands of others besides, have been honored
by being called into the service of the Church and thus given opportunity to serve our fellow
men. If we serve well, we will be blessed. I am reminded at this point of the words
Shakespeare put in the mouth of one of his characters:
</p><p>
. . . it [mercy] is twice blessed; It blesses him that gives and him that takes.
</p><p>
And of the two, the giver is usually the greater blessed&mdash;always so if he blesses with a sincere,
unselfish motive.
</p><p>
Now let us, too, remember that to accept a proffered opportunity to serve is to accept a
responsibility as well. We then in very fact become to an extent our brother's keeper. And in
a larger or a smaller measure the welfare of a brother, a child of God, is in our keeping. From
this point of view how fit for divine condemnation is he who having accepted responsibility
fails in his duty to his brethren. Should not this thought act as a spur to the discharge of duty?
Should it not help to send us reverently to our knees to seek earnestly and sincerely for the
Lord's aid, suited to our needs? Without his help, brethren, none of us can fully succeed in
his work. But succeeding, how great the joy and satisfaction that fills our breasts&mdash;a delightful
feeling that all the money of a millionaire could not buy for us. This type of feeling is a
reward from our God for service in his cause. It is an evidence of his acceptance of our
efforts.
</p><p>
SATAN'S POWER BEING EXERCISED
</p><p>
Another point and I am done. Let us not forget that Satan, a spirit brother of ours, is here on
earth with a myriad of other spirit brothers. They are among us for a purpose&mdash;they are doing
all in their power to destroy us and handicap the work of the Lord. Satan knows us
</p><p>
-our desires, our weaknesses, our secrets. He tempts us in a multitude of ways. He attacks us
where we are weak, not where we are strong. He stirs us up to doubt, to question, to criticize,
to hate, to be slothful, discouraged, sinful, and wicked. He is at the bottom of dissension
among the Saints. He is ever near at hand to make attempts to overcome and lead us away. I
have in mind not only us in this meeting but people generally. Undoubtedly Satan's influence
and power in the world today is greater than ever before.
</p><p>
We here and many others in the Church are called to be watch-men upon the towers of Zion
where duty calls us to be faithful in teaching the Lord's way of life by example as well as by
precept. Then we shall be effective missionaries. And upon the Church is divinely placed the
heavy responsibility of carrying on missionary work, a labor to which all baptized members
are called, be they living at home or abroad. No one can escape the
all-seeing eye of God our Father, who keeps us constantly wherever we are under scrutiny.
Let us remember that finally the books will be opened and we will be judged by the things
therein written&mdash;the deeds done in the body
(<a href="http://scriptures.byu.edu/getscrip.php?ID=3004#10">2 Cor. 5:10 (JST)</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/20/12#12">Rev. 20:12</a>).
</p><p>
Through his wiles Satan is leading some of our people away. Describing conditions in the last
days, Jesus, speaking to his disciples, said:
</p><p>
For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall shew great signs and wonders;
insomuch that, if it were possible, they shall deceive the very elect
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/24#24">Matt. 24:24</a>).
</p><p>
Brethren, there is but one way of safety&mdash;live honestly, sincerely, and whole-heartedly near to
the Lord and be wholly loyal to the leadership of the First Presidency of the Church.
</p><p>
I pray that every one of us with the help of the Lord will have the desire, courage, and
strength thus to live, and do it in the name of our Redeemer. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
