<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Today's Great Need Is Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1952, pp. 71-73</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters, I stand before you with a good deal of timidity and
trepidation. Although I have been doing this for a good many years now, I never get quite
used to the feeling. I hope that you will help me with your faith and prayers, that there may
be in what I say something that may be helpful to some of us, to give us renewed courage
and faith. My sole purpose is to be of help.
</p><p>
When Dr. Widtsoe was talking the other day of his experiences and how he was called in as
an expert on irrigation problems, I got to thinking about the similarity there is between that
and life. I once read from a Spanish writer this statement: "There are more uncultivated souls
in the world than lands."
</p><p>
Now the purpose of irrigation, of course, is to bring under cultivation lands that otherwise are
not so useful and not productive, and the accomplishment of it represents some of the
fundamental principles of our lives and our faith.
</p><p>
To begin with, the waters that we bring on to our land, when they are uncontrolled, may be
the source of tremendous danger and damage to us. Sister Ivins and I stood on the banks of
the river in Elmira, New York, and watched houses go by under the bridge, watched the water
come into the city and fill all the basements of the town, and read in the newspaper of people
who were drowned in the flood. And why? Because the waters of that river were beyond
control.
</p><p>
Now, when we can bring water under control, and through our faith and works bring it onto
the arid lands, those lands become productive. But to do so, there must be a fundamental
application of the principle of faith. Without it we would never make the effort. Then there
must be such structures erected as will keep the water which we bring onto the lands under
absolute control; furthermore, to make efficient use of it, it must have direction, wise and
adequate direction.
</p><p>
When we can apply all those things to it we reap a harvest, a rich harvest. But if at any time,
during that process, we become lax and lose control, the hope of a season, and sometimes of
the future, may vanish in an hour.
</p><p>
That is a good deal like life. The purpose of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is
to redeem and cultivate the souls of the people. The purpose, even, is to build up and
strengthen and make better the lives of the people who have come already to recognize the
power of God, his restored priesthood in the earth, and become members of the Church, for
none of us is perfect.
</p><p>
The development of those souls is the greatest responsibility of life. There is, of course, the
time when that control must be exercised by others, just as we exercise control over the
life-giving elements we lead on to the soil. Custody of a soul begins when a man is born&mdash;a
puny, powerless, helpless child. There is, however, implanted in him by God a power which
can develop, and if controlled, would redound to the benefit and blessing of mankind. It is the
duty of the parents of that child to see that its early years are properly guided and its activities
properly directed, that the selfish, jealous, evil things which carnal man is subject to, may be
taught out of the nature of that child, that it may be taught the virtues, the higher virtues of
life, so that in its formative period it may be safeguarded from the evils that surround us in
such great number.
</p><p>
Sometimes, as fathers and mothers, we do not realize that responsibility. We take children
more or less as a matter of fact; we do not realize that they are the sons and daughters of
God, and that in their care and custody, we are the representatives of God, our Heavenly
Father. If we could sense that fully, I am sure that we would be more serious in the care and
direction which we give to the life of our children.
</p><p>
Now there comes a time, of course, when the father and the mother may have done all that
was within their power, and they send their sons and their daughters out into the world to
struggle with its changing conditions. Then these young people have this direction within their
own power; they have to direct their course; they have to direct their efforts; Father and
Mother are no longer in control.
</p><p>
Now in that process the principal element of success, it seems to me, is faith, for without faith
in God we are not likely to seek his aid, and without his aid we would lack inspiration, and
without inspiration we may be subject to the baser tendencies of the body.
</p><p>
This writer says, "uncultivated souls"; and the Prophet said, "The spirit and the body is the
soul of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/15#15">D&amp;C 88:15</a>).
Consequently, if we are going to cultivate the soul well, we
must pay attention to the spiritual development, and likewise to the physical development of
the body. Without a proper relationship of the two we may not succeed.
</p><p>
Now, faith in God then becomes the fundamental principle of life. The great principle of the
gospel is love. But how can you love God without having faith in his power, and his interest
in you, and his ultimate direction of the affairs of this world of ours? To love him, you must
have faith in him. With that faith there will come a love of God, and an effort to do his will,
to keep his commandments, to develop ourselves, that we may be ultimately valiant and
useful servants unto God in developing his program in the earth.
</p><p>
Without faith, there can be no love between a man and a wife. Without faith there can be no
love between a son and a father. Faith must go in both directions, it seems to me. But if that
faith can be developed, we will strive to meet the full requirements of our lives; to develop
ourselves to our utmost and ultimate capacity. It requires a struggle, constantly, to drive
jealousy out of our hearts; it requires a constant struggle to prevent hatred from coming into
our feelings and our attitudes; it requires a constant struggle to develop the higher facilities of
the body and the mind, but it must come from faith&mdash;faith in God, faith in each other as
well. But in the beginning is faith in God, because from that develops love, the fundamental
principle of the gospel, and from love develops the fidelity that should exist in all family
relationships.
</p><p>
We have been told what a wonderful thing it is that we can enjoy our companions here, with
the expectation that if our lives are proper, we will have that association throughout eternity
culminating in the grandest blessing of the gospel of Jesus Christ; But if we do not have the
faith that prompts us to love and respect each other, to honor the pledges that we make in
marriage, we will fall far short of the realization of that great and wonderful privilege.
</p><p>
I have come to believe, in this great struggle, that the greatest victory a man can make is the
victory of self-control. It did Alexander the Great no good to conquer the world and die a
drunken, debauched person, in early manhood. Because he had no self-control, he lost all the
advantage that he had gained by his unholy conquests.
</p><p>
So I repeat, it matters not what your conquests are here in other directions, if you fail to gain
absolute self-control, you have failed in the greatest victory of life. It is the greatest battle,
too, because man, abandoned by the spirit of God, we have been told already, is carnal, and
that carnal man is an enemy of God. Without that struggle, without the Spirit of God, we are
going to surrender ourselves to our baser and more ignoble tendencies. We must not do it,
brothers and sisters. Man or woman, we must have faith in God in order to serve him
properly, and make this tremendous struggle that is necessary to overcome these baser
faculties.
</p><p>
We must never so mistreat our bodies that we surrender the controls that we have gained over
these propensities to the unsettling influences of narcotics or things of that sort. We must live,
brothers and sisters, through the faith we develop in God, true to all the commandments that
have been given us, and to all of the pledges that we have made.
</p><p>
Now, when we lead the water out over the soil, we may have planted a crop which is the
result of months and months of labor, and then, because in an unguarded moment, we relax
our control and our watchfulness over it the whole work may be carried away.
</p><p>
And I have known men, and women, too, who apparently have made this successful struggle
until well along in years, and then either feeling secure or indifferent, I do not know which
they relax these controls; they succumb to temptation; and in an unguarded moment, they
destroy their hopes for the future.
</p><p>
I have seen men disorganize marriages that should have carried over into eternity because in
an unguarded moment they failed to exercise their faith in God and the controls that come
from it.
</p><p>
I believe, brethren and sisters, the greatest need we have today is the development of faith in
God and the controls over ourselves which come from that faith; and if we can do so, our
future is secure. If we can do so as individual families, the security of our children should be
secure. If we can impress those basic principles upon them so that they will adhere to them
for the rest of their lives, the generation that they bring into the world should be secure; the
whole future, brothers and sisters, depends upon our faith in God, and the exercise of these
controls that come through that faith, and the inspiration of God which we get through it.
</p><p>
Now, may we realize these things, brothers and sisters, and may we live true to them, for the
pledges we make in the waters of baptism and in the temples of God are serious. There are
wonderful promises held out to us. The breaking of these pledges is a serious thing, and has
most, what shall I say, most unwanted results, terrible, destructive results in our lives. Have
you ever seen persons who forget these things, lose their standing in their communities, sink
to oblivion and die, unmourned? I believe you have. Why? Simply because we allow
ourselves to forget God, and in the forgetting of him, we lose faith in him because faith is
maintained by the exercise of our faculties in the service of God. And when we stop
exercising those faculties, that faith may decrease, and with its decrease, our controls may
likewise decrease; we may wake up one sad day to find that the blessings which should have
been ours are impossible to us.
</p><p>
God grant that we may understand our relationship to him, that we may learn to love him,
and have the faith which will guide us, and help us to direct our efforts to the greatest
development of ourselves and those dependent upon us, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
