<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Closing Address</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President George Albert Smith</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Albert Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1946, pp. 147-153</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This has been a wonderful conference. The Lord has said that if two or three shall meet
together in his name, he will be there to bless them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/20#20">Matt. 18:20</a>), and this house has been filled to
overflowing seven times during the last week by the sons and daughters of the Living God.
</p><p>
ALL ARE CHILDREN OF GOD
</p><p>
I esteem it a great privilege to be here with you, my brethren and sisters, and when I say
"brethren and sisters," I am reminded of the fact that every man is a son of God, every
woman, a daughter of our Heavenly Father. Wherever they may be, all that have been born
upon the earth are the children of the Lord, and our Master taught that to love our neighbors
as ourselves is the second great commandment
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>).
If we would follow the advice of Brother
George F. Richards to love our neighbors, it would go a long way towards bringing happiness
into the world.
</p><p>
I trust that during the few moments I occupy I may be blessed of the Lord to say the things
that he would have me say. I trust that we who are here may be inspired of our Heavenly
Father to rejoice in the blessings that are ours, and that we may be here today as brothers and
sisters in the sense in which he desires that we should be.
</p><p>
This is only a small congregation compared to the multitude of our Father's children scattered
over the earth, but it is a very choice congregation, because so many of those who are here
have devoted most of their lives to going about doing good. That, in a measure, is the sum of
the meaning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, to go about doing good
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/38#38">Acts 10:38</a>). While there are in this
congregation men and women who are not members of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, I hope that you will feel that you are welcome in this great congregation,
and then realize that wherever you may go and find members of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints who are worthy of the name, you will be welcome, and they will be glad to
do you good.
</p><p>
Last night over ten thousand men assembled in this house and the adjoining building, all
listening to the same voice at the same time. It was probably the largest group of men that
have ever been assembled together in a priesthood meeting since the world began. The fact
that so many of you brethren have the priesthood, of course, is one principle that many people
do not understand.
</p><p>
THE PROBLEM OF SAFETY
</p><p>
In this fast-moving age, the problem of safety is of great importance. We pick up the papers
day by day to find that this man has been run over by an automobile, or that
automobile has overturned and been wrecked, and those riding in it have been killed. We hear
of collisions between railroad trains and automobiles. Nearly every day the headlines of our
papers tell how many people have lost their lives by accident, and I may say to you that in
almost every case, if proper precautions had been taken, those lives would not be lost. So,
today, safety campaigns are being carried forward in an attempt to preserve the lives of
people that are being wastefully destroyed. I hope that the membership of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints will be among those most anxious and most willing to lend their
efforts to preserve life. It is very precious. We have only one life, and if we keep the
commandments of God and live as we should, it will be an eternal life of happiness. That is
the blessing which comes to us from the gospel.
</p><p>
On our highways, some turn over high-powered cars to children, as soon as they can handle
the wheel, and they do not always wait until they are entitled to drive by procuring that
privilege from the state in which they live. They do not measure the danger and the result is
that many accidents occur. Many accidents result because some men, and some women, I am
sorry to say, presume to sit down at the wheel of an automobile and drive off into traffic
when they themselves ought to be in bed under the care of a physician, and some of them
ought to be in jail sobering up.
</p><p>
Now, what can we do? Let us join with the nation. Let this group of men and women here
exercise their influence in encouraging our sons and our daughters and our neighbors, while
we are setting the example ourselves, to safeguard the lives of every one of these, our
Father's children. They are his, and he will not be pleased with us if by our carelessness, or
our wickedness, we destroy their lives.
</p><p>
A number of years ago we did not drive so fast. I remember when the governor of this state
drove a car at a time the limit was thirty miles an hour. Of course that was flying in those
days, it was so much faster than a horse. I was riding with the governor and noticed that he
drove very carefully. As we rode along the highway, I said: "You are a pretty safe driver,
aren't you?" 
</p><p>
He said: "I want to be."
</p><p>
I said, "This is a lovely car you are driving."
</p><p>
"Yes," he said. "The state furnishes me this car, and just as soon as I got it, my boys and girls
wanted to drive it. I couldn't very well keep them from doing it, and so we had this
agreement, that whenever we were in the car it would be law-abiding. So," he said, "this is
one car in the state that observes the law."
</p><p>
I have thought of that a good many times. If we teach our children to be law-abiding and
reasonable, perhaps we will be the means of preserving lives that are very precious to our
Heavenly Father. In this day when we are talking about safety everywhere, let us do
something about it. Let each of us do our part.
</p><p>
There are so many things that crowd my mind, I do not know what to talk
about. I hope you will not be in the position of the little fellow who sat through a long
meeting. When the last speaker got up and said: "I just don't know what to talk about," the
little fellow helped him by saying, "Talk about a minute."
</p><p>
DISOBEDIENCE BRINGS DISTRESS
</p><p>
What a blessed thing it is to know that we are living eternal lives. What a wonderful thing it
would be if all the people in the world knew that they are living eternal lives. How blessed it
would be if all men knew that our Heavenly Father was the Creator of the heavens and the
earth, and that he is our Father, the Father of our spirits. What a happy world it would be if
men everywhere recognized their fellowmen as brothers and sisters, and then followed that up
by loving their neighbors as themselves. Think of the sorrow and the distress that have been
in this world for the last few years, due to the great war. Of what benefit has it been?
Millions of lives have been sacrificed; millions in treasure have been wasted; and beautiful
cities have been wrecked and destroyed. Many people tonight will be sleeping, either on the
ground or in wrecked homes because of the great war. There are widows who have been left,
and orphans who will have to go through life without father and mother. Why? Because men
have refused to keep the commandments of God.
</p><p>
One of the great commandments that was given at Sinai was: "Thou shalt not kill"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/13#13">Ex. 20:13</a>).
</p><p>
I wonder if we realize how easy it is to violate a commandment of God? Think of the Ten
Commandments that were given to ancient Israel when they were in the wilderness, spoken by
the Lord and written by his finger upon tablets of stone. If the people, during the hundreds of
years that have elapsed since that time, had honored those Ten Commandments, this earth
would have been heaven, most of the time, and the men and women who have lived upon it
would have attained great blessings that we have not known yet.
</p><p>
It was a simple thing for the prophet of God, Moses, to bring those Ten Commandments
among the people, but it seems to have been most difficult for the men and women who have
lived upon the earth to observe them. I fear that the time is coming, unless we can find some
way not only to prevent the destruction of human life by careless accidents, but also unless
we can call the people of this world to repent of their sins and turn from the error of their
ways, that the great war that has just passed will be an insignificant thing, as far as calamity
is concerned, compared to that which is before us. And we can avoid it if we will; if we will
each do our part, it can be prevented.
</p><p>
EARLY SCENES IN SALT LAKE CITY
</p><p>
I am standing here today not more than about three hundred yards from the very spot where
I first breathed the breath of life. It was just across the street in a little humble home, a little
adobe house with four or five rooms, surrounded by a little garden and
orchard. That is where I began. Salt Lake City at that time was a village. We did not have
any water pipes. All our water was picked up in buckets and barrels at the side of the ditches
that ran down our streets, and then it was carried to the house in smaller receptacles. We did
not have any electric lights in those days. We had tallow candles, or kerosene oil lamps, but
no electric lights. The gas did come a little later while I was a child.
</p><p>
At that early day we did not have a foot of pavement in the city, either on the roads or on the
sidewalks. I can remember this great wide road just at the west of us here. There used to be
about six inches of dust upon it in the summer time, the finest dust that you could ever put
your feet into. That is the way we used to play, bare-footed, running up and down the street
playing ball. We did not have to dodge automobiles. Nobody had ever dreamed of an
automobile at that time, I think; at any rate it was a long time after that before the first one
came here, and then it was a curiosity. I am thinking of what has happened since. This house
was built at the time I was a child. The temple was begun before that time, and when it was
completed I still lived across the street.
</p><p>
During the time that has elapsed since my birth I have traveled in many parts of the world
and met many of our Fathers other children, men and women of various creeds and
nationalities; and what occasion I have this day to be grateful for the kindness they have
extended to me! It is not difficult for me to love my fellow men because I have known so
much kindness from them, wherever I have been. Of course I have found, occasionally,
individuals who had not grown up. They had bitterness and jealousy, and suspicion, and
hatred in their hearts for their fellows, but that was not the kind of training that I had.
</p><p>
MOTHER'S TEACHINGS
</p><p>
I was trained at the knee of a Latter-day Saint mother. One of the first things I remember was
when she took me by the hand and led me upstairs. In the room there were two beds, the bed
in which my parents slept, and a little trundle bed over on the other side. I can remember it as
if it were yesterday. When we got upstairs, she sat down by my little trundle bed. She had me
kneel in front of her. She folded my hands and took them in hers, and taught me my first
prayer. I will never forget it. I do not want to forget it. It is one of the loveliest memories
that I have in life, an angelic mother sitting down by my bedside and teaching me to pray.
</p><p>
It was such a simple prayer but I can repeat it today.
</p><p>
Now I lay me down to sleep. I pray the Lord my soul to keep. If I should die before I wake,
I pray the Lord my soul to take.
</p><p>
That was my first prayer. That prayer opened for me the windows of heaven. That prayer
extended to me the hand of my Father in heaven, for she had explained to
me what it all meant as far as a little child could understand. From that day until now, while I
have covered approximately a million miles in the world among our Father's other children,
every day and every night, wherever I have been, when I have gone to my bed or arisen from
it, I have felt I was close to my Heavenly Father. He is not far away.
</p><p>
My mother gave birth to eleven husky children, three of them girls. It was the gospel of Jesus
Christ that prompted her to bring us into the world, notwithstanding the anxiety we gave her.
She wanted to do what God had commanded our first parents to do, to multiply and replenish
the earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
As long as she lived upon the earth, I was taught to love my Heavenly Father. I had
an angel mother, for she was an angel, as we understand angels these days to be. And as I
stand here today, after the experiences of a long life I realize that she was only one of the
daughters of my Heavenly Father, and he loves them all.
</p><p>
Just a few days ago the national Relief Society of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints filled this building with women, many of them wives and mothers and grandmothers.
They, just like the men who were here in this building last night, had the training given to
them when they were children that we believe in God the Eternal Father, and in his Son Jesus
Christ, and in the Holy Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>).
That is the training of the children of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints, and of course of many other churches. But I am thinking of what
your privileges have been, of how the Lord called you out from the world, that call which
was heard by one of old:
</p><p>
. . . Come out of her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her sins, and that ye receive not
of her plagues (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/18/4#4">Rev. 18:4</a>).
</p><p>
BLESSINGS OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
Many of you who are in this house came from foreign lands, from sections of the world
where there were not the blessings you enjoy here. You have come to the tops of these
everlasting hills, to the headquarters of the Church, and what has been the result? When you
started, you found that the Lord had promised this:
</p><p>
. . . seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be
added unto you (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
That is what brought your parents and mine, your grandparents and mine, from other lands,
and from other parts of this country. They came because they felt that they held their Father's
hand. Many of them had a hard time when they came. There was not very much food, not
much clothing, and housing accommodations were poor, but they held their Heavenly Father's
hand. Morning and evening they bowed in thanksgiving and prayer to him who is the giver of
all. They taught us who were born later to adjust ourselves so that we could be happy by
being filled with the love of God and the love of our fellows in the world.
</p><p>
THE TABERNACLE CHOIR
</p><p>
I am thinking of how the Lord's promise has been fulfilled. Here you are today, listening to
this great choir. This choir has been singing not only to the United States, but during the war
the broadcast has also been carried to our boys and women in the armed services in different
parts of the world. Year after year, the faithful men and women in this choir have given their
time, without compensation, because they wanted to sing the sacred things of our Heavenly
Father to his children.
</p><p>
EVAN STEPHENS
</p><p>
We used to have here a number of years ago a young man who came from Wales. He did not
have the opportunity of a college education, but he was a Welshman, full of Welsh music.
When he came here, he became the leader of this great choir. He it was who had joy, along
with those who preceded him and those who followed, in building a choir not just to sing but
to sing praises to our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
I want to tell you a little incident about Evan Stephens. Some very prominent people were
coming here. In that day we did not have so many visitors of prominence. We were too far
out in the wilderness. One of our good bishops came to Even Stephens and said: "Brother
Stephens, I have some company coming next Sunday to the religious meeting"&mdash;(we used to
have a meeting here at two o'clock every Sunday)&mdash;"and I hope you are going to have some
good music."
</p><p>
Brother Stephens said: "All right, Bishop, we will have good music."
</p><p>
The bishop did not think that was enough assurance so he pressed it a little. He said: "These
people are not ordinary people. They are men of affairs and wealth. Their families are
wealthy, and I would like them to see just what a fine choir we have. Now, won't you give us
something just a little extra?"
</p><p>
Brother Stephens said: "Bishop, we have already had our practice. The music has all been
prepared. I don't see how we can make a change. I think it will be good enough for your
friends."
</p><p>
Then the bishop pressed him a little harder, and then Brother Stephens' Welsh got up, and he
said: "Now look here, Bishop, we have prepared the music for next Sunday to sing to the
Lord, and I suppose if it is good enough for the Lord, it is good enough for your company."
</p><p>
That is the spirit that has always been here. This house was dedicated to the worship of God,
by the spoken word and by music, by song and by story. I stand in a pulpit here that has been
sanctified by the righteous men and women who have stood here and have testified of their
knowledge of God and have encouraged others to keep his commandments,
that they might be happy. I feel very grateful for my blessings.
</p><p>
WARNING AND TESTIMONY
</p><p>
In conclusion let me say: We are not out of the woods. This world is in for a housecleaning
unless the sons and daughters of our Heavenly Father repent of their sins and turn to him.
And that means the Latter-day Saints, or the members of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, along with all the rest, but we, first of all, ought to be setting the example.
We have sent over seventy thousand of our sons and daughters into the world, paying their
own expenses, to divide the gospel of Jesus Christ with his other children. Why? Because we
know it is the only plan God has given to the children of men to earn a place in the celestial
kingdom. That is why it is so important. In this great building that has been so sacred to all,
after listening to the splendid choir and the organ, listening to the prayers that have been
offered here, listening to the testimonies that have been borne, I want to leave my testimony
with you and say to you: I know that God lives. I know that Jesus is the Christ. I know that
Joseph Smith was a Prophet of the Living God, and had restored to him the true gospel of
Jesus Christ in these latter days.
</p><p>
That might sound like boasting if it were not so serious. It is serious, and I know that I will
have to answer for that testimony as I leave it with you today. It will not be long until this
man who is talking will have finished his work and passed to the other side, and when I go, I
want to be worthy to join my grandparents and my parents, my brothers and sisters who have
passed on. I know they have earned a place that is worthwhile. I want to go where they have
gone, and I know that if I were not to tell you the truth in regard to this matter, I might lose
that opportunity.
</p><p>
So, realizing the seriousness of a testimony like that, realizing what it means, and with love
unfeigned and a desire to be a blessing to all our Father's children, I leave this witness with
you that this is the gospel of Jesus Christ, the only power of God unto salvation in
preparation for the celestial kingdom (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>),
into which kingdom we may all go if we will, but it
will be on his terms, and I bear you that witness this day, in the name of Jesus Christ, our
Lord. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
