<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Spirit of Conversion</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 43-47</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am sure, my brethren and sisters, that we all appreciate the opportunity to lift our hand to
sustain President David O. McKay as President of the Church, and in so doing we have in our
hearts a feeling of deep gratitude for the privilege that is thus afforded us as members of the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
It is glorious to be a member. It is glorious to have any office or calling in the Church, no
matter how relatively humble the title may sound. I am impressed constantly with the fact
that, regardless of our calling, we are all encouraged, we are all dedicated, and we are all
working in the service of the Master. I am sure that we do not permit our closeness to the
work, we do not permit the fact that we have such ready access to our Father in heaven
through prayer to take our membership in the Church lightly or to take our callings in the
Church lightly. We are always conscious of his nearness to us and the blessings which we
receive in answer to our prayers.
</p><p>
I am sure it would be more pleasing to our Father in heaven to have us
resign our positions&mdash;and that is not a practice which we commend in the Church&mdash;but
nonetheless it seems preferable to neglecting our duties in the least detail. It gives us an
awesome feeling to realize that we are dedicated to the work of the Lord, and having thus
committed ourselves, it is not our privilege or our prerogative to violate his commandments,
even the slightest of them. The Lord expects, and we expect it of ourselves, each one of us, to
live out our lives here upon this earth in as complete conformity to the laws of God as we are
capable. No means of rationalizing, no means of conjuring up excuses as to why we should
do this or should not do the other, contrary to the will of our Heavenly Father, has any place
in our lives.
</p><p>
I am grateful this morning that throughout the world the work of the Lord is progressing most
satisfactorily, indeed so satisfactorily that sometimes we feel that we are hardly capable of
keeping up with the progress of the Church.
</p><p>
In the mission field the Lord has blessed us. I just want to give you two figures. In the first
nine months of 1959 in the foreign or full-time missions of the Church, we had over 23,000
what we call convert baptisms, and in the first eight months of 1961 we have had over
54,000. We are constantly asked why it is that this great increase in converts should come
about at this particular time.
</p><p>
My first answer to that question would be that the faithfulness and the devotion of the Saints,
their efforts to live lives of righteousness, to dedicate their lives to the principles of truth and
right, is of primary importance. We know without any question of a doubt that the blessings
which descend upon us as a people are directly commensurate with our faithfulness, with our
nearness to our Heavenly Father. As we keep the channel of communication between us and
our Father in heaven open, we can expect to be blessed more abundantly all the time.
</p><p>
In the second place, we cannot be close to this missionary work without being conscious of
and without acknowledging the fact that the Lord has touched the hearts of men all over the
world and has made them responsive to the humble testimonies of the elders as they go forth
in the performance of their duties as missionaries of the Church of Jesus Christ in preaching
the gospel throughout the world.
</p><p>
Our approach, our initial contact with our friends throughout the world, is the simplest
approach we know how to make. Our lessons and their presentation are also direct and to the
point. This simplicity of our approach and presentation of the gospel belies the existence of
any design or device or scheme or contrivance or intrigue of any kind by which unsuspecting
investigators might be brought in as members of the Church without their really knowing
what they are doing or without their having exercised an absolute free agency of which
President McKay spoke so beautifully yesterday.
</p><p>
Let us stop and think for a moment what a young missionary has to accomplish before he
leads the convert down into the waters of baptism. He must first teach him the Word of
Wisdom, and that means teach him in practically all cases to give up practices which have
been lifelong and confirmed and live virtually a new life and to have the investigator commit
himself to the keeping of this commandment of the Lord from the time of his baptism until
the Lord calls him home.
</p><p>
We ask him to reform his life with reference to Sunday observance. We teach him that
Sunday&mdash;the Sabbath&mdash;is a holy day. The Lord has prescribed for his children what should
and what should not be done on the Sabbath day. And here again the convert is required to
give up in many instances that weekly activity toward which he has always looked
previously&mdash;a holiday, rather than a day of worship.
</p><p>
We teach him the law of tithing as revealed in these latter days by the Lord to his children,
something he has been unaccustomed to in the past, and here again it is obligatory upon the
missionary to commit his candidate for baptism to a strict observance of the law of tithing,
accounting to the Lord for the rest of his life for a tenth of his income, his
increase.
</p><p>
Converts are taught to live worthy to hold the priesthood of God. They are taught from the
beginning that after their baptism they will be introduced into the priesthood. They will have
the Aaronic Priesthood conferred upon them, and later the Higher or the Melchizedek
Priesthood. In order to be worthy of this progress and advancement in the Church, they must
be as strict as possible in keeping the laws and commandments of God.
</p><p>
Then too, they are taught and told and have impressed upon their minds the fact that when
they are once members of the Church, they then have an obligation to assist in promulgating
the gospel to their friends and neighbors. In short, to be prepared to answer each and every
call of the priesthood made of them, just as these fine men and women who today have been
called into service have willingly responded. Those who are being released and given other
positions accept the changes with the same kind of loyalty and devotion which they have
previously extended to the work.
</p><p>
When you take into consideration these and many other unmentioned facts, you have to stop
and ask yourself the question, "How can this nineteen-year-old boy of mine or of yours go out
into a strange world, many of them to a strange country, where a strange language is spoken,
and find almost of a sudden that they are touching the lives of total strangers in a manner
which is almost beyond comprehension and certainly beyond the power of man?"
</p><p>
Take these great reformers, these great evangelists, who are able to draw, through their
publicity and otherwise, great bodies of men and women. What is their ultimate
accomplishment? They do not seek to change a man's way of life. They are happy when they
can get the man or the woman to confess that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the Living God,
and when they have made that confession, that is it. No organizations, no requirements, no
obligations of any kind! These are learned men&mdash;men, I presume, as brilliant as any men in
the world. They are mature, and I ask you to sit down and stop and think occasionally when
you have this missionary work on your mind as to the difference between the results wrought
in the lives of converts to the Church and converts to these great popular movements, no
matter how fine, how elegant, how praiseworthy they may be.
</p><p>
You know, to me it is nothing short of a miracle to have men and women mature, much older
than the missionaries, submit themselves to these young men to be baptized by them. That
involves a serious matter. The average normal citizen, friend, would only do that upon one
foundation or one basis and that is that they have received in their hearts a testimony from
God that this young elder has the priesthood of God conferred upon him by those who have
that authority to preach the gospel and administer in its ordinances. Otherwise, what they do
would be a mockery. It is not to be presumed that 54,000 people this year in all of the
countries of the world in which we have missionaries would have permitted themselves to go
through this formality to no good purpose. It takes some effort, it takes a great deal of
humility. Unless they were convinced and converted to the fact that there in this young
missionary they had found the power of God vested to administer in the sacred ordinances of
the gospel, they would not do so.
</p><p>
It has interested me because in more than one country this year the following question has
been raised more or less officially. Can a nineteen-year-old boy be a minister of the gospel?
Are we justified as a government to confer upon him the benefits that inhere in the status of a
minister of the gospel? And they say no. A nineteen-year-old boy could not possibly be a
minister of the gospel. He has not studied. He has not gone through school. He is not mature.
</p><p>
Now, what does that mean? He is not learned in the ways of man. If they stop, as these
54,000 converts have stopped, and reflected and prayed and received an answer to their
prayers, they would know that the Lord is capable of conferring blessings upon his children
here on the earth through a nineteen-year-old boy as well as through an older
man, that one of the conditions is not that he be steeped in the learning of man, but that he is
in tune with the Spirit of our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
I must not take too much time, but I cannot sit down without giving you one or two examples
of what is going on in the world today to indicate this thought of mine that we are converting
by the Spirit, and the only virtue in the plan which we have in use now throughout the world
is that it is the simplest possible presentation of the gospel that these great mission presidents
of ours have been able to work out in the mission field, the least likely to affect the minds or
the reason of men&mdash;so simple, in fact, that it cannot have any effect upon men of the world
unless there is a higher power that touches their hearts and brings conversion to their souls.
</p><p>
I have become more and more convinced in my association with missionary work that most
people are touched by the Spirit of the Lord upon the occasion of the missionary's first
contact. Otherwise, they would not invite the missionary back time after time to be taught the
principles of the gospel and to be brought closer and closer and ultimately into the waters of
baptism.
</p><p>
Brother Brossard tells us the story of twenty-five conversions in France. Certainly there was
no scheme that brought these conversions about. There was an army officer, a soldier, in
Algeria, and while he was there in the service of his country, his wife had a baby, and it died.
It was not baptized in the church of its parents, they believing in infant baptism, and therefore
the church denied to that family a church funeral service for the child. I will not go into the
details, but we had a friend of Brother Brossard and the missionaries, (and I guess they are
friends to all of us) who called the attention of this distraught mother to the missionaries, and
they went in at the request of the family and held the services, and these twenty-five baptisms
came as a result of it, all from a single group. I was looking for this figure because I do not
want to go beyond the facts, but this group is much larger than the twenty-five, and the
missionaries are now in the process of teaching the gospel to the rest of them, and President
Brossard assures us that the twenty-five is just a small beginning to what will come about out
of this single instance.
</p><p>
Then we have the story of a missionary who ran a red light, and by so doing got the name
and address of the traffic officer and an invitation to visit him in his home. The officer's
penalty after the missionary got through with him was&mdash;what does the Good Book say?&mdash;"Go
thy way and sin no more"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/11#11">John 8:11</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/24/2#2">D&amp;C 24:2</a>).
</p><p>
We have the story of two missionaries coming from Zollingen in Germany who went to the
mayor to give him a Book of Mormon, made friends with him, and on a rainy day, seeing
them from his limousine, the mayor called to them to come over and get in the car. He
wanted to drive them to the City Council and introduce them officially to that august body.
</p><p>
And two missionaries in Hamburg, Germany, went to the chief of police to make themselves
known and to tell their story, and as a result he gave them his card and said, "I want you
elders to feel free to call upon me at any time in case you have any difficulty, or there is any
service we can render you, and I will have my car to you within five minutes."
</p><p>
These were all nineteen-year-old boys, and I could go on and tell you of many others. There
was not anything those boys could do or say of their own that would bring about such
miraculous results, but the first contact was enough to open the door for future contacts. That
is the way the work of the Lord goes on. Isn't it wonderful to realize that the prophecies of
old are being fulfilled? How true it is that a stone has been cut out of a mountain without
hands and is rolling forth and will fill the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/35,45#35">Dan. 2:35,45</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/65/2#2">D&amp;C 65:2</a>).
Almost every prophecy we have in the Old
and the New Testaments concerning the latter days fits into our program and furnishes us the
exact, the proper answer to this inquiry as to the marvelous results accompanying the work of
our missionaries. They work by and through the Spirit, and let me say this to you mothers
and fathers, we love you, and we appreciate your loyalty, and we appreciate
your sons' and your daughters' service. Have no concern about your sons and daughters in the
mission field. It makes no difference who their mission president is. As long as they are in the
line of their duty, encouraged by their parents so to be, they are in the hands of the Lord, and
he has promised to take care of them and is bound by those promises. I can conceive of
nothing more wonderful in all the world than to have the absolute assurance that the Spirit of
God is with your sons and daughters in the mission field to preserve them, to protect them, to
inspire them, to perform a service that no one upon this earth can perform unless he has the
delegated power from God to do so.
</p><p>
"And any man that shall go and preach this gospel of the kingdom, and fail not to continue
faithful in all things, shall not be weary in mind, neither darkened, neither in body, limb, nor
joint; and a hair of his head shall not fall to the ground unnoticed. And they shall not go
hungry, neither athirst.
</p><p>
"And whoso receiveth you, there I will be also, for I will go before your face. I will be on
your right hand and on your left, and my Spirit shall be in your hearts, and mine angels round
about you, to bear you up" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/80,88#80">D&amp;C 84:80,88</a>).
</p><p>
God bless us all and bless the missionaries. They are looking to us today for guidance and
direction and encouragement. Let us give it to them, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
