<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"If Ye Love Me, Keep My Commandments"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President N. Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 46-51</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
At the call of our leader, President David O. McKay, I am privileged this morning to address
you who are assembled here in this historic Tabernacle, and also the vast radio and television
audience. I do so in all humility and with a prayer in my heart that what I might say will be
in harmony with the teachings of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
We who will occupy this position during this conference have the responsibility to do as Paul
charged Timothy: 
</p><p>
"Preach the word; be instant in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort with all
long-suffering and doctrine.
</p><p>
"For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts
shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears; 
</p><p>
"And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/2-4#2">2 Tim. 4:2-4</a>).
</p><p>
"This know also, that in the last days perilous times shall come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/1#1">2 Tim. 3:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Men refuse sound doctrine</b>
</p><p>
The last days are here and now, and Paul's prophecy is being fulfilled before our very eyes.
Men are refusing sound doctrine, and after their own lusts they are turning their ears from the
truth and are listening to those who preach to their own liking. As a result, we are suffering
many tribulations throughout the world. We have reached a time in our history which I
believe is the most crucial mankind has ever had to face.
</p><p>
Thinking, serious-minded people in all fields of endeavor agree that present circumstances
cannot continue very much longer without precipitating one of the most serious crises man
has ever known.
</p><p>
<b>Reason for turmoil</b>
</p><p>
As we consider these disturbing conditions in a world of turmoil, I am sure we are asking the
simple questions: Why is there so much strife and hate in the world between nations, within
nations, within states, in universities, and even in groups of local communities, and with this
unrest, distrust, and strife extending even into the home? Why is it so universal? What can
and should be done to correct these conditions with which none of us are content or happy?
</p><p>
As I was contemplating these matters, I continued to search the scriptures for an answer. As
we all know, the Holy Writ is replete with exhortations, warnings, and prophecies pertaining
to the welfare of mankind and conditions in the latter days, or the days in which we now live.
</p><p>
We find the world divided into two great opposing camps. One is made up of individuals and
nations whose philosophy of life is fully materialistic, who not only reject, but aggressively
repudiate, the true Christian way of life.
</p><p>
In the other camp are those who still retain a nominal recognition of spiritual and moral
values. These comprise what we call our Christian civilization. One of the greatest tragedies
of this generation, however, is that so much of our so-called Christian civilization does no
more than profess Christianity, and, in fact, many today do not even profess.
</p><p>
<b>Solution to problems</b>
</p><p>
The only clear and sure solution to our problems is to make our professed Christianity real, to
make it personal, apply it in our lives, accept Jesus Christ as the Son of God, and as the real
living Savior of mankind, "for there is none other name under heaven given among men,
whereby we must be saved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus Christ not only gave his life for us, but he has also given us clearly the plan of life and
of salvation, and he has assured us that to gain eternal life we must live by sound doctrine,
which is the word of the Lord, spoken either by God or Jesus Christ or by the prophets of
God. This doctrine answers clearly and definitely such vital questions as: 
</p><p>
Who are we?
</p><p>
Where did we come from?
</p><p>
Why are we here?
</p><p>
Is there life after death?
</p><p>
Is there a living, personal God?
</p><p>
What is our relationship to God, the Eternal Father?
</p><p>
Is Jesus Christ, the Savior of the world, the Son of God?
</p><p>
What must we do to gain exaltation and enjoy eternal life?
</p><p>
<b>Answers to questions</b>
</p><p>
For answers to these questions, let us turn to and consider the words of the Lord and of the
prophets, both ancient and modern.
</p><p>
While we were all in the spirit world with God the Father, his Only Begotten Son, then with
him in the spirit, said: 
</p><p>
"We will go down . . . and we will make an earth whereon these may dwell; 
</p><p>
"And we will prove them herewith, to see if they will do all things whatsoever the Lord their
God shall command them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/24-25#24">Abr. 3:24-25</a>).
</p><p>
"So God created man in his own image, in the image of God created he him; male and female
created he them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>).
</p><p>
How uplifting and dignifying it is to know that we are truly the spirit children of God, made
in his image; that he and Jesus Christ are personal gods, that they are interested in us, and
that "God so loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in
him should not perish, but have everlasting life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Teachings of Jesus Christ</b>
</p><p>
Jesus Christ is the Son of God, as stated in ancient and modern scripture. On different
occasions God introduced him to men on the earth in these words: <i>"This is my Beloved Son.
Hear Him!"</i> (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>; <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/7#7">3 Ne. 11:7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus taught that as the spirit children of the Father, with that spark of divinity in us, we can
become like him by keeping his commandments. He also said: "Search the scriptures . . .
which testify of me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/39#39">John 5:39</a>). And Paul told the Romans: "For whatsoever things were
written aforetime were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the
scriptures might have hope" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/15/4#4">Rom. 15:4</a>).
</p><p>
Then again we have the words of Jesus: "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee
the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
In answer to the question, "If I die shall I live again?" Christ said: "I am the resurrection, and
the life: he that believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live: 
</p><p>
"And whosoever liveth and believeth in me shall never die" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25-26#25">John 11:25-26</a>). He gave his life
and was resurrected that man might not remain forever in the grave.
</p><p>
He also assured the multitude: "In my Father's house are many mansions: if it were not so, I
would have told you. I go to prepare a place for you.
</p><p>
"And if I go and prepare a place for you, I will come again, and receive you unto myself; that
where I am, there ye may be also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/2-3#2">John 14:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Resurrection an important step</b>
</p><p>
Regarding his resurrection, we have also the testimony of Paul, who was once a persecutor of
the Saints, and denier of Christ, that the apostles and he himself and hundreds of others had
seen Christ after he rose (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/5-8#5">1 Cor. 15:5-8</a>),
"the third day according to the scriptures" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/4#4">1 Cor. 15:4</a>).
</p><p>
How fortunate is the person who looks forward to the resurrection as an important step in
eternal progression and prepares now to meet God!
</p><p>
As I attended the funeral of our loyal and devoted colleague and faithful servant of the Lord,
William J. Critchlow, Jr., I was greatly impressed by the serenity of his wife, his children,
and even his grandchildren. They had been taught and they believed in a literal resurrection,
and they knew they would be reunited as a family. I tried to compare their feelings with those
who do not have such faith, who will not accept sound doctrine, but who search in vain for
hope. I humbly prayed to my Heavenly Father that I would be able to touch the hearts of
some and help them to appreciate and understand what great joy and satisfaction and
assurance faith in the resurrection gives.
</p><p>
<b>Difficulties in acceptance</b>
</p><p>
With all the irrefutable testimonies of the prophets regarding the gospel truths, why is it so
difficult for man to accept and endure sound doctrine, which is so important to all of us?
Some of the reasons are evident.
</p><p>
First, Satan's influence on mankind. In the spirit world, even before the world was, Satan
rebelled because his plan was rejected, and God said: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, because that Satan rebelled against me, and sought to destroy the agency of man,
which I, the Lord God, had given him . . . I caused that he should be cast down; 
</p><p>
"And he became Satan, yea, even the devil, the father of all lies, to deceive and to blind men,
and to lead them captive at his will, even as many as would not hearken unto my voice"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/3-4#3">Moses 4:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
Satan then determined to do all in his power to defeat the work of righteousness, and thus he
goes up and down, to and fro, in the earth, seeking to destroy the souls of men (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/27#27">D&amp;C 10:27</a>).
He does so by deceit and flattery, and by his emissaries who teach false doctrine to all who will listen;
and it seems that they are meeting with great success.
</p><p>
<b>Teachers of false doctrine</b>
</p><p>
Communists, anti-Christs, and the promoters of the God-is-dead theory, as well as the skeptics
and some who style themselves as religious leaders, are actively engaged in teaching false
doctrine and in using every hostile means to break down and destroy a belief in God and in
the scriptures, thereby fulfilling the prophecy of Jesus Christ when he said: 
</p><p>
"For there shall arise false Christs, and false prophets, and shall shew great signs and
wonders; insomuch that, if it were possible, they shall deceive the very elect"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/24#24">Matt. 24:24</a>).
</p><p>
Also, many, as they become learned in the worldly things such as science and philosophy,
become self-sufficient and are prepared to lean unto their own understanding, even to the
point where they think they are independent of God; and because of their worldly learning
they feel that if they cannot prove physically, mathematically, or scientifically that God lives,
they can and should feel free to question and even to deny God and Jesus Christ. Then many
of our professors begin to teach perverse things, to lead away disciples after them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/20/30#30">Acts 20:30</a>);
and our youth whom we send to them for learning accept them as authority, and many are caused to
lose their faith in God.
</p><p>
A graduate student who had just received his doctor of philosophy degree was telling me of
some of the attacks that are made on Christianity, or a belief in God, and how difficult it is to
stand up against them, particularly for those who have not been taught the gospel in their
homes and who have not gained a testimony of its truthfulness. He said that one professor
taunted him with this statement: "Surely you don't believe in that archaic stuff you find in the
Bible and in your Book of Mormon," and then spent some time with him trying to turn him
away from the truth.
</p><p>
<b>Need for faith in God</b>
</p><p>
I cannot understand a scientist or pseudo-intellectual, or anyone who should be searching for
the truth, having the temerity to place himself as authority in religion to the point that he
would challenge, let alone deny, the teachings of God the Eternal Father, the Creator of the
world, and of his Son Jesus Christ because he cannot prove it scientifically.
</p><p>
How much wiser and better it is for man to accept the simple truths of the gospel and to
accept as authority God, the Creator of the world, and his Son Jesus Christ, and to accept by
faith those things which he cannot disprove and for which he cannot give a better explanation.
He must be prepared to acknowledge that there are certain things&mdash;many, many things&mdash;that
he cannot understand.
</p><p>
How can we deny or even disbelieve God when we cannot understand even the simplest
things around us&mdash;how the leaf functions, what electricity is, what our emotions are, when
the spirit enters the body, and what happens to it when it leaves? How can we say that
because we do not understand the resurrection, there is not or cannot be a resurrection?
</p><p>
We are admonished to "trust in the Lord with all thine heart; and lean not unto thine own
understanding" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/3/5#5">Prov. 3:5</a>). And we are warned: "Woe unto them that are wise in their own
eyes, and prudent in their own sight!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/5/21#21">Isa. 5:21</a>).
</p><p>
How can man believe and know that he can travel in man-made space ships around the earth
at thousands and thousands of miles an hour, communicate with man here upon the earth, and
be directed in his course, with the knowledge that if he keeps in tune with home base he will
be guided back to a safe landing; and that mere man can also construct implements such as
the <i>Surveyor</i>, which he has sent to the moon, with which he has communicated in directing its
activities, and from which he has received reports&mdash;and still say that it is impossible for and,
the Creator of the world, to communicate with man, his own creation, who is traveling
through space on a space ship created by God and known as the earth, and that by keeping in
touch with home base he can be assured of a safe return when he has completed his tour here
upon the earth?
</p><p>
<b>Application of Christ's teachings</b>
</p><p>
In order to return to our Father in heaven, it is most important that we and our children know
and understand and apply the teachings of Jesus Christ in our lives. In order to understand, we
must be taught. The question is: Where and how are we to be taught? The gospel or the
spiritual side of life is not permitted to be taught in the schools. In fact, in so many of our
schools, and particularly in the universities, as pointed out before, a belief in God and the
teachings of Jesus Christ are derided.
</p><p>
It is the general attitude of people that the teaching of the gospel should be left to the
churches, but only a small percentage of either the parents or the children attend church,
where they could be taught. And to even that small minority who do attend, many of the
churches are failing to teach sound, unadulterated doctrine as given to us by the Savior and
the prophets through whom the Lord speaks.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of parents</b>
</p><p>
How many churches today teach that God is a personage? And that we were made in his
image, as he said we were? Do we realize how difficult it is to have faith in and love a God
who has neither body, parts, nor passions, as so many of the sects are teaching today? In any
event, as the Lord has said, the truths of the gospel, which are the most important things in
our lives, need to be taught in our homes. These are his words: 
</p><p>
"And again, inasmuch as parents have children in Zion . . . that teach them not to understand
the doctrine of repentance, faith in Christ the Son of the living God, and of baptism and the
gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the hands . . . the sin be upon the heads of the
parents.
</p><p>
"And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25,28#25">D&amp;C 68:25,28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Word of Wisdom</b>
</p><p>
To assist the parents in their duty, the Lord speaks through his prophets. Even in these latter
days the revelation known as the Word of Wisdom has been given to the world through the
Prophet Joseph Smith. It advises, among other things, against the use of tobacco and strong
drink, and with it is given a promise (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/5-8#5">D&amp;C 89:5-8</a>).
</p><p>
If we would just remember to keep this Word of Wisdom, there would be no drunken drivers
causing thousands and thousands of accidents and deaths on the highways; there would be
much less poverty, fewer broken homes, no alcoholics, and no crimes committed because of
the influence of alcohol. No one would be suffering from or dying with lung cancer and other
diseases caused by the use of tobacco. In this revelation we also have this promise: 
</p><p>
"And all saints who remember to keep and do these sayings, walking in obedience to the
commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones; 
</p><p>
"And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures; 
</p><p>
"And shall run and not be weary, and shall walk and not faint.
</p><p>
"And I, the Lord, give unto them a promise, that the destroying angel shall pass by them, as
the children of Israel, and not slay them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-21#18">D&amp;C 89:18-21</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Teach doctrines of salvation</b>
</p><p>
Parents, we must not become so engrossed with worldly matters that we fail to teach our
children the doctrines of salvation, both by example and by precept. We must teach them a
belief in God, that his Son Jesus Christ is the Savior of the world, who gave his life that we
might be resurrected.
</p><p>
How many families today meet in family prayer, or teach their children to pray privately to a
personal God who will hear and answer their prayers, or teach them the importance of loving
their fellowmen?
</p><p>
What a great world this would be to live in if all parents would hold a weekly family home
evening and would teach their children the word of the Lord.
</p><p>
Just accepting and living what he called the "great commandment in the law" would create a
heaven on earth wherein all could dwell in peace and happiness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36#36">Matt. 22:36</a>). He said:
</p><p>
"Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy
mind.
</p><p>
"This is the first and great commandment.
</p><p>
"And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.
</p><p>
"On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37-40#37">Matt. 22:37-40</a>).
</p><p>
Then he said: "If ye love me, keep my commandments" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/15#15">John 14:15</a>).
</p><p>
If we loved our fellowmen, we would not steal, we would not kill, we would not commit
adultery, we would not bear false witness or do any of those things which would be
detrimental to our neighbor (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/13-17#13">Ex. 20:13-17</a>).
</p><p>
Blessed is the person who can truthfully say that he believes in God the Eternal Father, and in
his Son Jesus Christ, and in the Holy Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>); that through the atonement of Christ all mankind
may be saved, by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the gospel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>);
and that he is prepared
to repent and be baptized for the remission of his sins and then accept and live the teachings
of Jesus Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38#38">Acts 2:38</a>).
</p><p>
I bear testimony that these things are true, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
