<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Questions for the Iconoclast</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 125-129</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The Seventy are traditionally minutemen. I have just been multiplied. Under the stimulation of
the great song we have sung together, I should like to put into the record a story and a
statement which I think President McKay probably does not know of, but which I think
should be known to him and to all of us.
</p><p>
In the last few years it has been my occasional blessing to take distinguished visitors to our
city, who have come to Temple Square, into the offices of the President of the Church to
greet him, to be greeted by him, and to feel the strength and stimulation and love which
always emanates from him.
</p><p>
A few months ago Brother Evans and I with some others were privileged to attend a
conference in the office of President McKay with one of the leading labor leaders in America,
possibly as influential and important a man as there is in his field. He was accompanied by
his wife and two little daughters, and the experience was a beautiful and impressive one.
There was no posturing, no pretense or effort to impress by President McKay&mdash;only genuine
friendliness, interest, and love. The part of the story I would want remembered and on the
record was what occurred when we had left the office. We stood in the halls of the Church
Office Building, and this man, who in his employment and administration influences the lives
of many millions of men, said to those of us who stood with him, and he said it with a moist
eye, "I have lived in many lands. I have been in the presence of kings and presidents and
rulers, and I want to say to you men that I do not think our generation will produce another
character like that."
</p><p>
This has happened not once, but many times. And for no other purpose than to express my
own faith and convictions about President McKay and the office and calling which he holds, I
repeat to you who may not have enjoyed such privilege my observation that many men who
are good and stalwart and powerful in their own right recognize in him who leads us a great
man and an authorized representative of our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
There have been many things in this conference which have inspired sincere gratitude in me.
With no desire to be lengthy I would like to express my appreciation for the return to the
measure of health which they enjoy of our two good Brethren in the Council of the Seventy.
We have learned to love and respect Brother Kirkham and Brother Hunter and feel for them
the esteem and brotherhood which this wonderful service opportunity should engender in us.
</p><p>
I would like humbly to express another feeling of gratitude. There sits in this building today a
man who was among the very first to whom I bore testimony of the gospel on these grounds
when I came out of the service eleven years ago. He is here today as a bishop of a ward in
one of the great new stakes in the Church. Having been touched with the spirit of the gospel
on Temple Square, he, through his own earnest efforts, through the effective teaching of good
missionaries and the living of the gospel by the members of the Church in his home town,
soon came to a knowledge of the truth and accepted it.
</p><p>
It is a privilege also to express gratitude for the magnificent music which we have enjoyed
here. The Tabernacle Choir is known to the whole Church as a great missionary organization,
and yet perhaps we who work on these grounds are more aware, through our opportunities, of
their effectiveness than others could be. I honor them. During this conference we have heard
two other groups&mdash;a wonderful choir of young singers from Brigham Young University, and a
great, and to me thrilling, group of young people from the Institute of Religion at the
University of Utah.
</p><p>
I have great love for these young people, and I desire to express publicly my appreciation for
the privilege of having been a teacher of some of them. I would like to say how proud I was
of the group from the Institute of Religion. They have not had the privilege of singing here
before and of being thus excellently represented before the Church.
Anything fine that can be said of other young men and women in the Church can properly be
said of them, for they are intelligent and loyal and steadfast. Not all of you would understand
the pressures that are upon them in their daily learning. I want to express my gratitude and
faith and confidence in the good men who teach them, some of whom also taught me, and I
express my own appreciation for the great contribution in faith and good lives that has come
out of that institute and others like it.
</p><p>
There are a few simple suggestions I would like to make today to these who are young.
</p><p>
Some weeks ago it was my privilege to go into one of the great subterranean caverns in the
southwestern part of our land. Thousands upon thousands of people visit it annually. The day
I went into it, far below the surface of the earth, I was in the company of a large group, but
no one whom I knew personally. The path on which we walked through this great cavern over
a period of more than an hour was quite a narrow one, permitting two to walk abreast, if a bit
crowded. The trail was lighted in sections as we went and was very clearly marked with white
stones at the edges and with signs all along the way. We were accompanied by three forest
rangers and met others as we went. I walked near the front and heard some of the comments
of the ranger as we were led into the magnificent scenery of this underground wonderland. 
</p><p>
As we walked, we passed beneath a huge, high dome. Below it, appropriately named, was a
deep hole called "The Bottomless Pit." There was conjecture among the people as to what
might have caused this empty place in the earth. Some thought it might have been an early
fossil deposit, others an area of highly soluble materials, others the result of an earth
movement or some other like occurrence of nature. It was discussed for a time with no
conclusion reached. The ranger informed the party that there is divided opinion on the
question among the experts.
</p><p>
A little farther along the trail we came into an area where there was another vast vaulted
dome, but the debris from that cavity lay below it in a mountainous pile. Again there were
comments along the trail. One said: "My, I'll bet there was a tremendous clap of noise when
that fell!" An army man replied, "Do you really think there was? After all, there was no one
here to hear it!"
</p><p>
They discussed this issue at some length, whether or not in the absence of someone to hear,
noise actually occurs. I listened and said nothing, but thought of Bishop Berkeley, Irish
philosopher, whose theory was that "to be is to be perceived," that is, that so-called material
things exist only in being perceived&mdash;if it is not perceived, it does not exist. It is said that a
group of the bishop's students at Oxford taught him the true nature of reality one very dark
evening when they placed a tree stump on a certain unlighted path where he habitually
walked. His perception of the stump was said to be a realistic shock to George Berkeley.
(Laughter.)
</p><p>
Well, when we left the cavern, the people were still discussing whether or not when things
fall there is a noise in the absence of human ears to hear it.
</p><p>
As I left the cavern, I thought to myself that these may be legitimate fields for inquiry, and it
may be that someday someone will discover the answers, though that seems doubtful. But
would it not be a most foolish thing to abandon the cave because we do not know the
answers? Suppose someone should take it into his mind that all the glory of this
wonder-work, God's handiwork, should be abandoned and never enjoyed more because those
mysterious questions were not answered. Suppose one with ready access to the place and with
personal knowledge of its great beauty should decide that he would never enter more because
there were things he did not fully understand about it&mdash;or go about seeking to dissuade others
from enjoying the majesty of it because it took effort to reach and there were certain (to him,
here and now) hard-to-understand problems.  Would not this be foolish and tragic?
</p><p>
Do you know that some of our wonderful young people of great potential intelligence  and
capacity and contribution are abandoning their faith and their way of
life in the gospel, with all the strength and beauty of it, because they have come to questions
for which they have not learned satisfactory answers?
</p><p>
May I read you a statement from the pen of one of the most learned among us, who left us a
legacy of scientific research and useful knowledge, and of great faith. Dr. Widtsoe, after
encouraging "mature examination," said:
</p><p>
"Wise men do not throw the Church overboard because they have not satisfied themselves
concerning every principle of the gospel. Under the law of progression every principle may in
time find lodgment in the inner consciousness of the seeker."
</p><p>
To abandon the marvelous demonstrable truths of the gospel because there are some questions
one cannot satisfactorily resolve would be foolishness in the extreme. As President Clark said
the other evening, "A foolish man can ask questions that the wisest cannot answer." It is no
reproach to our religion or to us not to be able to answer definitively, categorically, finally,
every question that can be asked. I plead with you, and I talk not theoretically but with some
of your faces in my mind, not to abandon all that is good in your religion because there are
some things you do not understand.
</p><p>
Now, President Clark in his two great sermons in the evening meetings, Brother Evans in his
conference address and in this morning's wonderful short sermon, and President Richards this
morning, have all alluded in some measure to something I would now like to say. I could not
presume to add to what they have said, but I can raise my voice with them and testify as to
my own experience and observation. What I say I say humbly, knowing my own limitations,
and not from any position of personal arrogance or assumed unusual competence. I would
speak to some who influence these young people in causing them to abandon what they
believe.
</p><p>
Along the trail down in the cavern, well-marked and defined as it was, with signs and guides
to make clear that we were to stay on it, some "boy play" occurred between some young
Scouts in uniform who walked the trail just a short distance behind me, supervised by a
scoutmaster and several assistants. The boys were jostling and pushing each other all the way
along, trying to get some adventurous, "progressive" soul to get off the trail and go out and
explore a little. I watched it all and observed the instance I now think of, when a larger boy
who had been tantalizing a younger one, pushed him off the trail and into a dimly lighted,
muddy area. The boy went near the edge of a crevice, and with an outcry that startled us all
and got the rangers quickly to his side, signalized the danger he was in and the possibility that
he might have perished in the darkness.
</p><p>
You see, along this trail at periodic intervals the ranger would stop and bend over and turn a
switch which was hidden from the view of the rest of us, and an area ahead of us would
suddenly become lighted. The ranger at the back, when we were safely through a certain area,
would turn off the light. The youngster had gone into a section of the cave where the light
did not reach.
</p><p>
I thought, as the lights went on and off, how realistic this experience is to life. We talk of
questions, some solvable. We know that the Lord has encouraged us to seek truth, to "knock,"
"ask" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>),
and "search diligently" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/23/1#1">3 Ne. 23:1</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/24#24">D&amp;C 90:24</a>).
Yet there come times when we reach the end of our capacity to
reason and to understand. We must learn to walk by faith. There has been given us enough
light to walk the paths we are here to tread. As the Lord in his wisdom desires that we have
more light, we have the assurance that it will be given. I bear my witness that from the
beginning of the history of the Church the lights have come on when the need arose. It has
always been so; it is so now; it will always be.
</p><p>
When the little boy was brought back on the trail, the ranger was very angry, chastised him
severely, declared him banished from the group, and started to send him away, while the real
culprit in the case stood silent. He was not going to be punished, just the boy. Then the
scoutmaster spoke up and said, "If he goes, this boy ought to go, too." He was a wise man.
The ranger talked to them both for a moment, and on promise of good behavior, allowed both
of them to stay. Though God and wise men may forgive, there is no
happiness to be found in leaving the narrow path of gospel principle to adventure in strange
paths and forbidden ways, in the enticement of dark places, in "looking beyond the mark"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/4/14#14">Jacob 4:14</a>), as
Jacob said.
</p><p>
We left the cavern a while later. My teacher's mind and my interest in youth had brought me
to some renewed conclusions, and I pass them on earnestly to mature persons who are given
to assisting young people off the trail. The dictionary has a word for them: iconoclast. It is
defined as, "One who attacks cherished beliefs as shams." What if the cherished beliefs that
are attacked along the trail are true? What if they are the very beliefs that make these boys
and girls the worthwhile, promising people they are? What if the foundations of their faith are
effectively shaken at this crucial period, and they dangle, with no substantial footings to stand
on? President McKay in his opening address quoted the economist, Babson, from whose
writings I should now like to read a sentence:
</p><p>
"Many of the most important men in America, who are what they are because of what they
learned at their mother's knee, now deny their own and other people's children those same
blessings, in the name of 'liberalism' or 'progressivism' or 'emancipation.'"
</p><p>
Such men, Babson says, deny others the very blessings that made them what they are.
</p><p>
Do you know that when one who has influence with youth, be he teacher, leader, or parent,
seriously weakens the foundations upon which a young person has built, by faith-destroying
challenges the youngster is not yet equipped to meet, he fashions a disciple who has been
effectively cut loose from fundamentals at a time when he needs most to rely on them? The
challenger may himself be a moral, educated, well-meaning person of integrity, doing what he
does in the name of honesty and truth. His own character may have been formed in an
atmosphere of faith and conviction which through his influence he may now help to destroy
in his young follower. "Disenchanted" himself in his mature years, he turns his powers on an
immature mind and leaves it ready prey for nostrums and superstitions and behavior he
himself would disdain.
</p><p>
Let me ask a question or two, as I hurry to a conclusion. To you who influence this boy, to
"emancipate" him, in your way of thinking, may I ask you: Have you really helped him
develop his capacity to contribute to the world's useful knowledge and useful work? In which
particular is he a better person when you get through with him? In what aspect of life has his
ability to serve been strengthened? Does he love God and his fellow men more? Is he a more
moral, clean, virtuous, decent man? Is he a more faithful husband, father, or son? Has he
learned more gratefully to honor his father and mother? Does he merit their increased respect
and esteem as he matures? Is his power for good increased? Has he acquired a greater
influence for motivating others to constructive, participating citizenship? Is he a more worthy,
admirable person to his younger brothers and sisters? Has he experienced increase of
generosity, unselfishness, thoughtfulness for the needs of others through your tutelage? Is he
more kind, considerate, gentle, sensitive? Does he have more sympathy, love, and
understanding for those who are distressed? Does he live life more courageously, manfully?
Will he endure tribulation more patiently and understandingly because of you?
</p><p>
I have answers to these questions. Again I do not talk from theory but with faces and lives in
my mind. My experience is that when you get through with him, as fine a man as you are, as
much respect as I may have for your education and your brilliance and your effectiveness and
your personal integrity, you have not improved him in any of these important ways. He may
be, in fact, he often is, cynical, destructively critical, vain, high-minded, impervious to
instruction. Quite often he has acquired habits and attitudes toward society and moral behavior
which break the hearts of those who love him most and which you yourself would never
stoop to. He sneers at his parents, those whom he once respected, and often at God and holy
things. It is quite a responsibility you have assumed.
</p><p>
May I commend to you what Richard L. Evans said this morning: "A teacher is
responsible for the total effect of his teaching." So is it true of a parent, an official, a leader
of youth. What is the total effect of your influence on the young?
</p><p>
I want to mention one other thought that came in the cavern. As we walked in that
subterranean beauty, I thought what each of you under like circumstances would have thought.
I thought how wonderful it would be if my lovely wife and little girls could be with me; I
wanted to share with them the wonder, the inspiration, the nearness to God I felt then. A
verse of scripture came to mind. It is recorded in First Nephi:
</p><p>
And it came to pass that I did go forth and partake of the fruit thereof; and I
beheld that it was most sweet, above all that I ever before tasted. Yea, and I
beheld that the fruit thereof was white, to exceed all the whiteness that I had ever
seen.<br />
And as I partook of the fruit thereof it filled my soul with exceeding great joy;
wherefore, I began to be desirous that my family should partake of it also . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/11-12#11">1 Ne. 8:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
We should all desire to share the goodness and beauty and, truth of the gospel with others of
God&rsquo;s children.
</p><p>
In the story of Ammon's missionary work among the Lamanites there is one statement the
unusual language of which sometimes evokes mirth in a student when he first hears it, but
which to me is one of the most sacred and provocative verses in all the record. The king has
been stricken and lies as if he were dead. Ammon is summoned by the queen, his loving,
loyal wife. She says:
</p><p>
. . . I would that ye should go in and see my husband, for he has been laid upon his
bed for the space of two days and two nights; and some say that he is not dead,
but others say that he is dead and that he stinketh, and that he ought to be placed
in the sepulchre; but as for myself, to me he doth not stink
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/19/5#5">Alma 19:5</a>).
</p><p>
The love of this faithful wife for her beloved husband seems typical to me of the love which
will obtain in the heavenly kingdom and which should here characterize our relationships with
those dear to us.
</p><p>
I pray that the Spirit of the Lord will guide the young people of the Church as they seek
answers to their questions, for this is encouraged, that they may seek "by study and also by
faith" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>);
that they may with dedication and honest effort seek for useful knowledge, for the
Lord has said that "to be learned is good," if we hearken to the counsels of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/29#29">2 Ne. 9:29</a>).
</p><p>
I caution those who influence young people, and ask you to look at the total effect of your
teaching. I bear my witness as to the truthfulness of the message of the Prophet Joseph in his
testimony of the mission of the Lord Jesus Christ, and of the restoration, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
