<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">That Ye May Be Able to Withstand in the Evil Day</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, p. 64-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My prayer is that what I say in these next few moments may not be out of harmony with
what has seemed to be the theme of this great conference, which has, among other things,
impressed upon us the vital importance of keeping the commandments of God as an effective
hedge against the evils of our day. Many questions are asked today as the disturbed conditions
in the world become more confusing and appalling to our people and to others who are
shocked by the continuance of undeclared wars and by the spectacle of government affairs
and some private and public businesses being dominated, in many instances, by official
mandate rather than by due legislative processes. We see rebellion against the law, which
approaches anarchy when leaders openly incite riots against law and order; we are witnessing
the constant parading of ugly and soul-destroying, lewd, and provocative literature, theatricals,
and radio and television shows. We hear vicious attacks on public officials without the
opportunity being given to them to make a defense or a rebuttal to the evil diatribes and
character assassinations that tend to discourage worthy men from accepting appointments to
public offices. These are but a few of the ills that afflict us in our so-called modern age.
</p><p>
In the midst of all this, we hear our faithful people asking these questions over and over
again: Are we living in the last days? Is there a sure way we can know the false from the
true? Does the Church take any position in these matters? Is the devil on the loose? Has the
Church a defense against these terrifying circumstances?
</p><p>
<b>Sure guides to truth</b>
</p><p>
To all of these questions, the answers are unwavering: Yes, we are living in the last days.
There are sure guides to truth if church members will use them. The Church is a continuing
revolution against any and all norms of society that fall below the gospel standards. Within
the gospel of Jesus Christ may be found the solution to every problem confronting us that will
enable us to find happiness here and eternal life in the world to come. Yes, the devil is
certainly on the loose.
The Church indeed has the most effective possible defense against these ungodly and
terrifying conditions.
</p><p>
<b>The conflict with evil</b>
</p><p>
My text for this brief address sets out in cleanness the eternal contest with the evil forces
among us. The Apostle Paul admonished the Saints of Ephesus: 
</p><p>
"Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil.
</p><p>
"For we wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against principalities, against powers, against
the rulers of the darkness of this world, against spiritual wickedness in high places"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/11-12#11">Eph. 6:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Love and obedience</b>
</p><p>
This profound admonition was preceded by pertinent instructions that impress the very present
needs of today. There must be the love of a husband for his wife and the love of a wife for
her husband (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/5/22-23#22">Eph. 5:22-23</a>),
and children must be obedient to parents (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/1-4#1">Eph. 6:1-4</a>).
The Apostle Paul drew a parallel
between the reverence for and love of parents and children in the home to the love of the
Master for his Church, and then concluded with these words: "Finally, my brethren, be strong
in the Lord, and in the power of his might" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/10#10">Eph. 6:10</a>).
</p><p>
All with righteous desires are opposed to sin. Some years ago I participated in a panel
discussion at the University of Utah with public officials, businessmen, and a district judge, as
well as professional men of the university. The district judge made a profound statement when
he declared that the great need in the fight against lawlessness, against immorality, against
atheism, socialism, Communism, or other related ills is faith in the Lord Jesus Christ. Our city
attorney had accompanied me, I being a city official at the time. To him the comment of the
judge about faith as a weapon against sin was sheer stupidity and a pompous display of
religious bigotry. As I have thought about the statement of the judge, I have recalled a wise
observation by one of my esteemed colleagues: "Beautiful roses," he said, "do not grow unless
the roots of the parent bush are planted in rich, fertile soil&mdash;watered and cultivated and
carefully nurtured by the hand of a master gardener. Likewise, beautiful flowers of virtue,
honesty, integrity, or sobriety do not blossom in a human soul unless his feet are firmly
planted on a testimony of the divine mission of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ." (Charles A.
Callis, formerly of the Council of the Twelve.)
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge of God's word</b>
</p><p>
Despite the sarcasm of my nonmember attorney friend, the judge in the panel discussion was
right. My knowledge of the Lord's word concerning sin and my experience in dealing with
human problems have taught me that the judge was close to the mark. We must know the
truth, for the truth only will make us free from the pitfalls of evil
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>). Knowledge of and love for
the Son of God as a perfected being will bring heaven close when temptations are near.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul closed his sermon to the Ephesians with these meaningful words: "Stand
therefore, having your loins girt about with truth, and having on the breastplate of
righteousness: 
</p><p>
"And your feet shod with the preparation of the gospel of peace;
</p><p>
"Above all, taking the
shield of faith, wherewith ye shall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked.
</p><p>
"And take the helmet of salvation, and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God: 
</p><p>
"Praying always with all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, and watching thereunto with all
perseverance and supplication for all saints" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/14-18#14">Eph. 6:14-18</a>).
</p><p>
To the Corinthians, the Apostle Paul set forth in plainness that his teachings would not be
from his learning in secular fields in which he was a recognized scholar. His pledge to them
as a preacher of righteousness and truth was significant: 
</p><p>
"And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom,
declaring unto you the testimony of God.
</p><p>
"For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified . . .
</p><p>
<b>Faith in the wisdom of God</b>
</p><p>
"That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/1-3,5#1">1 Cor. 2:1-3,5</a>).
I would that all who are called to high places in the Church would determine, as
did the Apostle to the Gentiles, to know and to preach nothing save Jesus Christ and him
crucified (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/2#2">1 Cor. 2:2</a>).
</p><p>
We are told plainly in the revelations that the fruits of the true gospel of Jesus Christ are
unity and harmony. The following from a revelation while the Church was young and the
leaders inexperienced plainly declares that the gospel in its fullness was given to overcome
contention. Listen to his words: 
</p><p>
"Yea, and I will also bring to light my gospel . . . and shall bring to light the true points of
my doctrine, yea, and the only doctrine which is in me.
</p><p>
"And this I do that I may establish my gospel, that there may not be so much contention; yea,
Satan doth stir up the hearts of the people to contention concerning the points of my doctrine;
and in these things they do err, for they do wrest the scriptures and do not understand them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/62-63#62">D&amp;C 10:62-63</a>).
</p><p>
Then the Lord has declared something more, which all of us as leaders and teachers should
heed: 
</p><p>
"Behold, this is my doctrine&mdash;whosoever repenteth and cometh unto me, the same is my
church.
</p><p>
"Whosoever declareth more or less than this, the same is not of me, but is against me;
therefore he is not of my church.
</p><p>
"And now, behold, whosoever is of my church, and endureth of my church to the end, him
will I establish upon my rock, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against them.
</p><p>
"And now, remember the words of him who is the life and light of the world, your Redeemer,
your Lord and your God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/67-70#67">D&amp;C 10:67-70</a>).
</p><p>
"I say unto you, be one; and if ye are not one, ye are not mine" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/27#27">D&amp;C 38:27</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Harmony evidence of oneness</b>
</p><p>
The absolute test of the divinity of the calling of any officer in the Church is this: Is he in
harmony with the brethren of that body to which he belongs? When we are out of harmony,
we should look to ourselves first to find the way to unity. A wise man has given us the key to
his development in his unforgettable statement; here are his wise words: "If there was any
'key' to this process of growing up, it lay in the systematic effort I made to subject myself to
critical self-appraisal. As I came to know myself, I acquired a better understanding of other
people." (Bernard Baruch.)
</p><p>
Martin Harris, you remember, was warned particularly to repent of his sins, for he sought the
praise of the world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/39#39">D&amp;C 58:39</a>). I suppose the love of praise and adulation of the world is
the beginning of the downfall of many men. Alma, a prophet of the Book of Mormon,
seemed to make it clear that the sowing of the seeds of hatred, suspicion, and contention in
any organization is destructive of the purpose of life and unbecoming to the children of God.
</p><p>
This is a part of a great sermon delivered by this ancient prophet: "And he commanded them
that they should teach nothing save it were the things which he had taught, and which had
been spoken by the mouth of the holy prophets.
</p><p>
"Yea, even he commanded them that they should preach nothing save it were repentance and
faith on the Lord, who had redeemed his people.
</p><p>
"And he commanded them that there should be no contention one with another, but that they
should look forward with one eye, having one faith and one baptism, having their hearts knit
together in unity and in love one towards another.
</p><p>
"And thus he commanded them to I preach. And thus they became the children of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/18/19-22#19">Mosiah 18:19-22</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Power of the works of God</b>
</p><p>
A few years ago while touring the missions of South America, I heard President William
Grant Bangerter of the Brazilian Mission make some interesting comments. He reported that
there had been a wave of incidents in which evil spirits were afflicting the missionaries and
the Saints. At every conference the missionaries were relating experiences they were having
with evil spirits. The intensity of their influence was frightening. The mission president
admonished them to cease talking about the works of the devil in the future and instead teach
with power the works of the Lord and bear testimony of his works among them. There was an
almost immediate cessation of the power of the evil spirits when the people confined their
testimonies to the works of the Lord rather than of Satan, the mission president told me.
</p><p>
We should all learn that the fundamentals of gospel teachings are the Lord's weapons against
evil and sins of all kind, whether they be political dangers, immorality, threatened family
disasters, or any other sinister afflictions among us.
</p><p>
One wise teacher, the superintendent of California schools, has said: "You don't train a boy to
refrain from burglary by teaching him how to manipulate the tumblers of a safe in the dark;
neither do you teach him to avoid immorality by teaching him all about sex in the school
room." (Dr. Max Rafferty, in <i>The Salt Lake Tribune</i>, 1964.) By the same token, you don't
teach people to avoid Communism by telling them all about Communism or to avoid
murderous acts of violence by constantly telling horror stories.
</p><p>
<b>Freedom and obedience</b>
</p><p>
President David O. McKay has said it better than I can. "In these days of uncertainty and
unrest, liberty-loving people's greatest responsibility and paramount duty is to preserve and
proclaim the freedom of the individual his relationship to Deity, and the necessity of
obedience to the principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ. <i>Only thus will mankind find peace and happiness</i>"
(President David O. McKay, <i>The Improvement Era</i>, Dec. 1962, p. 903).
</p><p>
I should like to read that again because it is the key to what I am trying to say: "In these days
of uncertainty and unrest, liberty-loving people's greatest responsibility and paramount duty is
to preserve and proclaim the freedom of the individual, his relationship to Deity, and the
necessity of obedience to the principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ. <i>Only thus will mankind find peace and happiness</i>."
</p><p>
<b>Man's relationship to Deity</b>
</p><p>
The conclusions we must reach are inescapable as we ponder these profound declarations. One
who has an abiding conviction concerning God, who has faith in his relationship to Deity and
the necessity of obedience to the principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ who believes in and
has a love for the Son of God, and who has a feeling of certainty as to the immortality of the
soul can successfully combat sin and unrighteousness in any guise.
</p><p>
Ours, then, must be a positive rather than a negative approach, as indicated by these divine
instructions. The Lord has explained this in his preface to his revelations in our day, as he
tells us the value of the scriptures and why the fullness of gospel teachings was given to us
today. He said: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments; 
</p><p>
"And also gave commandments to others, that they should proclaim these things unto the
world; and all this that it might be fulfilled, which was written by the prophets&mdash;
</p><p>
"The weak things of the world shall come forth and break down the mighty and strong ones,
that man should not counsel his fellow man, neither trust in the arm of flesh&mdash;
</p><p>
"But that every man might speak in the name of God the Lord, even the Savior of the world; 
</p><p>
"That faith also might increase in the earth; 
</p><p>
"That mine everlasting covenant might be established; 
</p><p>
"That the fulness of my gospel might be proclaimed by the weak and the simple unto the ends
of the world, and before kings and rulers.
</p><p>
"Behold, I am God and have spoken it; these
commandments are of me, and were given unto my servants in their weakness, after the
manner of their language, that they might come to understanding.
</p><p>
"And inasmuch as they erred it might be made known; 
</p><p>
"And inasmuch as they sought wisdom they might be instructed; 
</p><p>
"And inasmuch as they sinned they might be chastened, that they might repent; 
</p><p>
"And inasmuch as they were humble they might be made strong, and blessed from on high,
and receive knowledge from time to time" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17-28#17">D&amp;C 1:17-28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Beware false leaders</b>
</p><p>
How much clearer can the Lord tell us the value of the gospel in keeping us from following
false leaders up blind alleys?
</p><p>
The Lord has sounded a warning to all of us who hold responsible places in his kingdom in
this day.
</p><p>
Said he: "But there is a possibility that man may fall from grace and depart from the living
God; 
</p><p>
"Therefore let the church take heed and pray always, lest they fall into temptation; 
</p><p>
"Yea, and even let those who are sanctified take heed also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/32-34#32">D&amp;C 20:32-34</a>).
The sanctified, as defined, are those who have a holiness of life and character&mdash;those who may have titles of
high places in the Church.
</p><p>
A President of the Church has told us where we may expect to find false leaders: 
</p><p>
"First," he said, "The hopelessly ignorant, whose lack of intelligence is due to their indolence
and sloth . . .
</p><p>
"Second&mdash;The proud and self-vaunting ones, who read by the lamp of their own conceit; who
interpret by rules of their own contriving; who have become a law unto themselves, and so
pose as the sole judges of their own doings" (President Joseph F. Smith, <i>Gospel Doctrine</i>,
twelfth ed., p. 373).
</p><p>
<b>Allegiance to God</b>
</p><p>
Ours is the great responsibility to become fully involved in the great drive going forward in
the Church today: to impress parents with their responsibility to teach their own families in
their homes and to have a completely correlated course of gospel teachings in church
auxiliaries and priesthood quorums for the children, the youth, and the adults&mdash;all to the end
that we might develop a gospel scholarship in the individual that will withstand in this evil
day the forces that, without this abiding testimony of the gospel, would make us and our
children prey to all the vices and false ideologies in the world.
</p><p>
May the Lord continue to pour out his knowledge upon his Church and give to all who are
members, and indeed to all the honorable of the earth, attentive minds and obedient hearts, that
he may indeed be an ensign to the world as prophesied when "many people shall go and say,
Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the house of the God of Jacob; and
he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/3#3">Isa. 2:3</a>).
</p><p>
For that I pray humbly for all of us as individuals and for the Church collectively.
</p><p>
The Master closed his last recorded sermon prior to his crucifixion with the words: "These
things I have spoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye shall have
tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>).
</p><p>
I humbly bear solemn witness to the life and mission of our Lord and Master, the Prince of
Peace (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>),
in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
