<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Prophets</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 73-74</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I believe in the prophets. "Where the Scriptures speak," said the
Reverend Thomas Campbell, "we speak; where the Scriptures are silent, we are silent." Saint
Augustine, who lived around the year 400 A.D., made a similar statement when he said,
"Nothing is to be accepted save on the authority of the Scriptures."
</p><p>
These declarations, you will readily see, close the doors to continuous revelation from God
and eliminate the holy prophets. Contrary to these expressed views, The Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints declares to all the world: "We believe all that God has revealed, all
that He does now reveal, and we believe that He will yet reveal many great and important
things pertaining to the Kingdom of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"All He has revealed; and will yet reveal"</b>
</p><p>
The world is constantly looking for new knowledge, not only in science but also in religion. It
is the keystone
to progress. Herein lies the apostasy of the Christian Church established by Jesus and the
apostles. In other words, they believed in the prophets dead, and rejected the living oracles.
Spiritual knowledge comes from God through his prophets.
</p><p>
<b>Prophets, revelators</b>
</p><p>
Ancient Israel was a prophet nation. The prophets appeared from time to time as they were
needed. Their messages were vital, for they were the inspired spokesmen of the Lord. They
were not always popular. They were often ridiculed, persecuted, and held in disrepute.
Stephen, the Martyr, in his last and solemn testimony, said to the mob, "Which of the
prophets have not your fathers persecuted? and they have slain them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/52#52">Acts 7:52</a>).
</p><p>
These chosen servants, misunderstood and maligned, devoted themselves wholeheartedly and
constructively to the task assigned them. It was never an easy one. It was a challenge to
strong men who put their service to God above all worldly aspirations. Their aim was always
to rescue and fortify against the forces of evil, of moral and spiritual disintegration. Through
these holy men God has given commandments to his children. But, generally speaking, their
words were ignored and rejected. Had they been respected and accepted, the course of human
history would have changed. They appeared as lighthouses to the generation in which they
lived. When they were ignored and cast aside by unscrupulous leaders, as was often the case,
the light was extinguished and darkness covered the earth. There were no prophets during the
dark ages.
</p><p>
<b>Divine messages come through the prophets</b>
</p><p>
God's message to his children comes through his chosen servants, the prophets. These
servants were chosen before they were born. They had a divine message that was not only
timely but important. They gave evidence of their divine calling wherever and whenever they
appeared. Spirituality is a consciousness of God, an awareness of his place and power in the
universe. To know him is life eternal. When Israel was at its lowest ebb spiritually, Elijah, a
great prophet, came to their rescue and converted a nation to the true worship of Jehovah.
They had been reassured through a manifestation of God's power.
</p><p>
I have often said that the story of Joseph in Egypt gives the world its finest lesson on
morality and clean living. It should be told and repeated frequently to every boy and girl
during their adolescence. The example and teaching of the prophets will never become
outmoded by a righteous people. Every page of scripture contains a directive for you and me
as we move along in the journey of life. Where would we be today if all the idealism and
morality taught by the prophets had been lost in the scramble for earthly and worldly
recognition? International negotiations and all the controversies now going
on, it seems to me, are tinctured with selfish ambitions. May I remind you there is no place
for selfishness in God's kingdom or in the restored gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Someone has said that Moses was the first man in history who fought for human rights. He
freed the Israelites from the Egyptian bondage. He freed them from their own limitations and
taught them the fundamentals of good government. He laid the foundation for law and order.
Moses brought to the world the Ten Commandments. They are very fundamental. They are
basic to every system of law made to govern humanity. To violate them means disaster and
destruction. The road to wickedness begins when one of these mandates from God is broken.
"And there arose not a prophet since in Israel like unto Moses, whom the Lord knew face to
face" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/34/10#10">Deut. 34:10</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Modern prophets bring divine guidance</b>
</p><p>
Like the prophets of old, Joseph Smith, the modern Prophet, saw visions, received revelations,
predicted the future, and interpreted the scriptures. The Church would not have come into
existence without a prophet. There could have been no restoration without these holy men
who spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21#21">2 Pet. 1:21</a>). Their powers and understanding went
beyond the limits of our finite comprehension of things. They looked beyond the veil that
separates the seen from the unseen world. Had Joseph Smith lacked the insight, the power, and
the enlightenment that came to him through his prophetic calling, the Book of Mormon could
not have come forth.
</p><p>
Without the visions of Moses and Elijah, there would have been no gathering of Israel, and
the temple building program characteristic of the Church would have had no beginning. The
existence of these temples in the United States, in Canada, in Europe, and on the islands of
the sea is a solemn testimony of the sincerity, the conviction, and the positive faith of the
Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
I believe in the prophets, modern and ancient. We have listened to their words during this
conference. May we remember them and may we abide in the holy commandments that came
from God to them, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
