<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">America&mdash;A Man and an Event</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 121-125</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, seen and unseen, humbly and gratefully I approach this sacred
responsibility.
</p><p>
First may I endorse with all my heart the masterful keynote discourse of our beloved prophet,
President David O. McKay, delivered Friday, entitled "Man's Free Agency&mdash;an Eternal
Principle of Progress." As he closed his prophetic warning, he said, "Pernicious efforts and
sinister schemes are cunningly and stealthily being fostered to deprive man of his individual
freedom."
</p><p>
Once again the prophet has warned us about our loss of freedom and has left us without
excuse. God grant we may be wise enough to heed his counsel. Let us become alerted and
informed regarding the insidious influence abroad in this and other lands which would rob us
of all we hold dear.
</p><p>
It is good to be home&mdash;to stay, insofar as a member of the Twelve can determine&mdash;after
nearly two years abroad.
</p><p>
I bring you the love and greetings of tens of thousands of faithful members and friends of the
Church in Europe.
</p><p>
<b>Suffering Mankind</b>
</p><p>
I love America&mdash;my country&mdash;and so it is a joy to be home, but I love all of our father's
children everywhere. I have seen them on both sides of the iron curtain, in forty-five nations
in the last few years. Nineteen years ago I saw millions of them in Europe, hungry and cold
as a result of the hell of war. I have been with them in bombed-out buildings, on their little
farms, in their shops, in their homes. They are our Father's children, my brothers and sisters. I
have a deep love for them.
</p><p>
Some of them have lost their freedom and are living in bondage under godless leaders. But
there is a spark of divinity in all of them. Generally speaking they love the Lord. And our
Father in heaven loves them. They want to live in freedom and peace. They want to be good
neighbors. Many are confused, but they love their homes and families. They want to improve
their standard of living. In their hearts they want to do what's right.
</p><p>
<b>America, Heaven-blessed</b>
</p><p>
But with this love of our Father's children, I love America in a special way. The United
States is not just another nation&mdash;not just one of the family of nations. This nation was
intended to be a beacon to liberty-loving people everywhere. This is a choice land, for the
Lord Jesus Christ&mdash;the God of this land (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>)&mdash;has
so declared through his prophets. This is a
land with a prophetic history which was held, as it were, in the hollow of God's hand to
perform its great mission for the blessing of all peoples.
</p><p>
The Lord raised up the Founding Fathers. He it was who established the Constitution of this
land&mdash;the greatest document of freedom ever written. This God-inspired Constitution is not
outmoded. It is not an outdated "agrarian document" as some of our would-be statesmen,
socialists, and fellow travelers of the godless conspiracy would have us believe. It was the
Lord God who established the foundation of this nation; and woe be unto those&mdash;members of
the Supreme Court and others&mdash;who would weaken this foundation.
</p><p>
I am sorry to say that I am saddened and sick at heart at what I see, at what has happened in
the past few years and is happening today in my beloved country. But that is a subject for
another time.
</p><p>
It was the Lord who created an atmosphere of freedom here in America so that his Church
could be restored in its fullness for the blessing of all mankind. Here in these United States
the Lord has established his base of operations in these last days. He selected America. That
is why I love the United States of America in a special manner. Every true Latter-day Saint
should love America.
</p><p>
No, the Lord's base of operations was not established by the General Authorities of the
restored Church. The Lord himself prepared the way through the centuries. He established his
base of operations here in America, and it is the duty of every liberty-loving soul, and
especially every Latter-day Saint, to help protect, safeguard, and strengthen the Lord's base of
operations, because it is from this base that the glorious saving principles of the eternal gospel
are going and will continue to go forth to the world to bless all of our Father's children and
to provide a true basis for peace. There is no other way.
</p><p>
Yes, I love America, but it is about something else, closely related, that I now testify.
</p><p>
Today I desire to bear witness to the inspiration and divine mission of a truly noble character
and the reality of the greatest event of the past nineteen centuries. The setting for both is here
in the United States.
</p><p>
<b>Joseph Smith, American Prophet</b>
</p><p>
Some thirty years ago the well-known Macmillan Company published a most significant book.
On the flyleaf of this 400-page volume appeared a statement essentially as follows: 
</p><p>
"Here is a man who was born in the stark hills of Vermont; who was reared in the backwoods
of New York; who never looked inside a college or high school; who lived in six States, no
one of which would own him during his lifetime . . . who, even when he had his freedom,
was hounded like a fugitive; who was covered once with a coat of tar and feathers, and left
for dead; who, with his following, was driven by irate neighbors from New York to Ohio,
from Ohio to Missouri, and from Missouri to Illinois, and who, at the unripe age of
thirty-eight, was shot to death by a mob with painted faces.
</p><p>
"Yet this man became mayor of the biggest town in Illinois and the state's most prominent
citizen . . . the founder of cities and of a university, and aspired to become President of the
United States.
</p><p>
"He wrote a book which has baffled the literary critics for [more than] a hundred [and thirty]
years and which is today more widely read than any other volume save the Bible. On the
threshold of an organizing age he established the most nearly perfect social mechanism in the
modern world, and developed a religious philosophy that challenges anything of its kind in
history, for completeness and cohesion. And he set up the machinery for an economic system
that would take the brood of Fears out of the heart of man&mdash;the fear of want through
sickness, old age, unemployment, and poverty.
</p><p>
"In [fifty-three] nations are men and women who look upon him as a greater leader than
Moses and a greater prophet than Isaiah; his disciples now number [over two] million; and
already a granite shaft pierces the sky over the place where he was born, and another over the
place where he . . . received the inspiration for his Book." (John Henry Evans.)
</p><p>
This book from which I have quoted is titled <i>Joseph Smith, an American Prophet</i>. I testify to
you that Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of God&mdash;one of the truly great prophets of all
time. This I know and bear witness to all the world.
</p><p>
<b>The Martyr</b>
</p><p>
Joseph Smith the Prophet went willingly to his death. He sealed his testimony with his life&mdash;his
own blood. On that fateful day, 120 years ago in Nauvoo, Illinois, as he looked back upon
his city and people whom he loved, on his way to Carthage Jail and his martyrdom, he
declared: 
</p><p>
"This is the loveliest place and the best people under the heavens; little do they know the
trials that await them." (<i>DHC</i>, 6:554.)
</p><p>
Later the Prophet said feelingly, but calmly and courageously: 
</p><p>
"I am going like a lamb to the slaughter, but I am as calm as a summer's morning. I have a
conscience void of offense toward God and toward all men. If they take my life I shall die an
innocent man, and my blood shall cry from the ground for vengeance, and it shall be said of
me, 'He was murdered in cold blood!'" (<i>DHC</i>, 6:555; see also
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4#4">D&amp;C 135:4</a>).
</p><p>
Following his martyrdom his saddened and devoted followers who revered him as a prophet
of God issued to the world a statement which appears in a sacred volume of scripture, the
Doctrine and Covenants, and which reads in part as follows: 
</p><p>
"To seal the testimony of this book and the Book of Mormon, we announce the martyrdom of
Joseph Smith the Prophet, and Hyrum Smith the Patriarch. They were shot in Carthage jail,
on the 27th of June, 1844, about five o'clock p.m., by an armed mob&mdash;painted black&mdash;of
from 150 to 200 persons. Hyrum was shot first and fell calmly, exclaiming: <i>I am a dead man!</i>
Joseph leaped from the window, and was shot dead in the attempt, exclaiming: <i>O Lord my God!</i>
They were both shot after they were dead, in a brutal manner, and both received four
balls . . .
</p><p>
<b>The Prophet of Salvation</b>
</p><p>
"Joseph Smith, the Prophet and Seer of the Lord, has done more, save Jesus only, for the
salvation of men in this world, than any . . . man that ever lived in it. In the short space of
twenty years, he has brought forth the Book of Mormon, which he translated by the gift and
power of God, and has been the means of publishing it on two continents; has sent the fulness
of the everlasting gospel, which it contained, to the four quarters of the earth; has brought
forth the revelations and commandments which compose this book of Doctrine and Covenants,
and many other wise documents and instructions for the benefit of the children of men;
gathered many thousands of the Latter-day Saints, founded a great city, and left a fame and
name that cannot be slain. He lived great, and he died great in the eyes of God and his
people; and like most of the Lord's anointed in ancient times, has sealed his mission and his
works with his own blood; and so has his brother Hyrum. In life they were not divided, and
in death they were not separated!
</p><p>
". . . their <i>innocent blood</i> on the floor of Carthage jail is a broad seal affixed to 'Mormonism'
that cannot be rejected by any court on earth, and their <i>innocent blood</i> . . . is a witness to the
truth of the everlasting gospel that all the world cannot impeach; and . . . is an ambassador
for the religion of Jesus Christ, that will touch the hearts of honest men among all nations"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/1,3,7#1">D&amp;C 135:1,3,7</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, Joseph Smith, the latter-day Prophet, was an instrument in the hands of the Lord in
opening a new gospel dispensation&mdash;the last and greatest of all gospel dispensations.
</p><p>
He witnessed and participated in the greatest event that has transpired in this world since the
resurrection of the Master.
</p><p>
Here is a partial description, in his own words, of that great and all-important event: 
</p><p>
"After I had retired to the place where I had previously designed to go, having looked around
me, and finding myself alone, I kneeled down and began to offer up the desire of my heart to
God. I had scarcely done so, when immediately I was seized upon by some power which
entirely overcame me, and had such an astonishing influence over me as to bind my tongue so
that I could not speak. Thick darkness gathered around me, and it seemed to me for a time as
if I were doomed to sudden destruction.
</p><p>
"But, exerting all my powers to call upon God to deliver me out of the power of this enemy
which had seized upon me, and at the very moment when I was ready to sink into despair and
abandon myself to destruction . . . just at this moment of great alarm, I saw a pillar of light
exactly over my head, above the brightness of the sun, which descended gradually until it fell
upon me.
</p><p>
"It no sooner appeared than I found myself delivered from the enemy which held me bound.
When the light rested upon me I saw two Personages, whose brightness and glory defy all
description, standing above me in the air. One of them spake unto me, calling me by name
and said, pointing to the other&mdash;<i>This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/15-17#15">JS&mdash;H 1:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
This glorious vision of God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ, in broad daylight, in the
spring of 1820, is the greatest event that has transpired in this world since the resurrection of
our Lord.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith, who witnessed it, was and is a prophet of God. Today some 12,000
missionaries and more than two million members of the Church throughout the free world are
bearing witness of this important fact.
</p><p>
Mormonism has been before the world for 135 years. It has met mob violence, persecution,
drivings, and deception by wicked men, and prejudice and misunderstandings by many people
throughout the world. Yet, in spite of widespread opposition, ambassadors of truth have
carried from the very beginning and are today carrying to the world the all-important message
of the restored Church.
</p><p>
Paraphrasing the words of Apostle Paul: This thing has not been done in a corner
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/26#26">Acts 26:26</a>).
</p><p>
The world has generally revered the ancient prophets dead and rejected the living ones. It was
so with Joseph Smith. Truth is often on the scaffold&mdash;error on the throne. But time is on the
side of truth, for truth is eternal.
</p><p>
<b>The Restored Gospel for the Modern World</b>
</p><p>
The message of Mormonism is a world message. It is the truth. The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints is a world organization.
</p><p>
In the early days of the restored Church, the Lord, in a revelation to Joseph Smith, addressing
all of his children, both in and out of the restored Church, said this: 
</p><p>
"Hearken, O ye people of my church, saith the voice of him who dwells on high, and whose
eyes are upon all men, yea, verily I say: Hearken ye people from afar; and ye that are upon
the islands of the sea, listen together.
</p><p>
"For verily the voice of the Lord is unto all men, and there is none to escape, and there is no
eye that shall not see, neither ear that shall not hear, neither heart that shall not be
penetrated . . .
</p><p>
"And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I
have chosen in these last days.
</p><p>
"And they shall go forth and none shall stay them, for I the Lord have commanded them.
</p><p>
"Behold this is mine authority, and the authority of my servants, and my preface unto the
book of my commandments, which I have given them to publish unto you, O inhabitants of
the earth . . .
</p><p>
"Wherefore the voice of the Lord is unto the ends of the earth, that all that will hear may
hear . . .
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing, the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments . . .
</p><p>
"And also those to whom these commandments were given. might have power to lay the
foundation of this church, and to bring it forth out of obscurity and out of darkness, the only
true and living church upon the face of the whole earth, with which I, the Lord, am well
pleased, speaking unto the church collectively and not individually&mdash;"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1-2,4-6,11,17,30#1">D&amp;C 1:1-2,4-6,11,17,30</a>).
</p><p>
These are the words of Jesus Christ to his prophet and all the world.
</p><p>
The message of Joseph Smith&mdash;the message of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints&mdash;the message of Mormonism&mdash;is the most important world message.
</p><p>
The Church is a world organization&mdash;the true Church of Jesus Christ restored to the earth in
its fullness&mdash;and is intended to bless all of our Father's children.
</p><p>
These things I know and bear witness in humility and gratitude.
</p><p>
God lives, Jesus is the Christ, the Redeemer of the world, with his latter-day base of
operations here in America, and Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of the living God, as is
our beloved present-day leader, David O. McKay.
</p><p>
This is my witness and testimony to all the world in humility and gratitude, in the name of
the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
