<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Sermon on the Mount</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 55-56</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, the good and fervent prayer offered at the beginning of this session
by President Lewis has been answered in blessings upon our heads. I hope the good Spirit
will continue with us throughout this service.
</p><p>
I am very happy, and I was delighted to hear that President Hunter had been called to fill the
vacancy in the Quorum of the Twelve. President Hunter has been for many years a leader in
Zion. He has been proved, and I say that a Church is very fortunate indeed that can call upon
men of his caliber to serve freely and pleasantly in the great position which he now occupies.
</p><p>
I was also very happy this morning for the vigor and the strength demonstrated by President
Clark in his sermon to us. The Lord has blessed him, and I am sure you join with me in
expressing gratitude for his recovery, that his leadership may continue amongst us.
</p><p>
Yesterday, I was thrilled and greatly by that masterful sermon delivered by President McKay
on the character, the teachings, and the life of Jesus Christ, the Lord. I was also pleased with
his references to the Sermon on the Mount delivered by the Savior before a small group of
people gathered on the mountainside. That sermon has lived for centuries. It has survived the
Dark Ages. It has survived the Renaissance. It has survived modern speculations and the
conflicts and the contention among nations.
</p><p>
That sermon will live forever. There is nothing more fundamental in God's word than the
sermon which the Savior gave and which is called the Sermon on the Mount.
</p><p>
A few years ago I attended a Sacrament meeting in the South London Branch in London. The
occasion was a Christmas program. On that program appeared a Jewish musician. He played a
selection on the cello. It was very good. The presiding officer tried to get him to play another
selection, but he refused. He said, however, "I will sing a solo, if that will be acceptable." He
stepped forward, and he sang the song we all love, "The Lord's Prayer," after which he took
his seat in the audience.
</p><p>
When the meeting was over, he walked up to me and said, and these are his words, "You will
have to get something more practical than the Sermon on the Mount if you expect to convert
the Jews."
</p><p>
I said to him, "Have you ever read the Sermon on the Mount?"
</p><p>
He said, "I must have read it."
</p><p>
"I hope you have," I suggested, "before you criticize it." And then I said to him, "You sang a
wonderful song tonight, 'The Lord's Prayer.' Did it ever occur to you that that prayer was a
part of the Sermon on the Mount?" He did not seem to realize it.
</p><p>
"Now," I said, "Will you tell me one single teaching in that sermon which is not practical.
Name one thing in it that cannot be practiced and introduced into your daily life." He was
silent.
</p><p>
Then I began to repeat for him that wonderful prayer offered by Jesus as an example to his
disciples. "'Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven'
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/9-13#9">Matt. 6:9-13</a>).
Isn't that a practical aspiration to have?" I said.
</p><p>
He made no reply.
</p><p>
Then I repeated this: "'Give us this day our daily bread.' Surely, that is practical to a man
like you."
</p><p>
And he said, "Oh it is very practical."
</p><p>
I continued, "'And forgive us our debts, as we forgive our debtors.' We are having a lot of
trouble with debts these days, individual and national. Don't you think we
ought to pray about it once in a while?" I asked.
</p><p>
"It wouldn't be amiss," he replied.
</p><p>
And then I gave him this statement: "'. . . deliver us from evil.' Is that not a prayerful hope
that all of us should have? It refers to the evil that appears in our pathways, evil that
frustrates and stultifies us as we go forth in our daily affairs. 'Deliver us from evil,' is a plea
for strength to resist temptation.
</p><p>
I called his attention to two or three other statements in the sermon: "Judge not, that ye be not
judged.
</p><p>
"For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged: and with what measure ye mete, it
shall be measured to you again" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/1-2#1">Matt. 7:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
At last he was impressed. He said, "Oh, if you Christians would honor that last
commandment, 'As you measure out to others, it shall be measured back to you.'"
</p><p>
I said, "Not only the Christians, but the Jews as well."
</p><p>
Then he began to explain if that commandment were believed today we would be living in a
different world. Fancy someone believing a teaching which declares, as we measure out to
others, it will be measured back to us. There would then be no dishonesty in the world. There
would be no persecution. There would be no war. There would be no bloodshed. There would
be no contentions in our civilized society because the world stands on one of the great laws
taught by the Lord Jesus.
</p><p>
I quoted again from the sermon: 
</p><p>
"'Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto
you' (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>).
Can't you see the practical thing in that teaching, my brother? If we desire something,
something that is precious, something we need, certainly it will require effort on our part."
</p><p>
My friend left me. He said, "I will go home and read the Sermon on the Mount."
</p><p>
I asked, "You have a New Testament?"
</p><p>
He said, "I believe I have, but it must be covered with dust."
</p><p>
And now it occurs to me that when Joseph Smith penned his thirteen Articles of Faith, he
stated in the fourth one that the first principle of the gospel is faith in the Lord Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/4#4">A of F 1:4</a>).
There may be other kinds of faith, but the faith that will lead us on to eternal happiness and
salvation is faith in the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
May we be true to that sermon, and may we acquit ourselves in such a way that we may be
worthy of an exaltation in God's kingdom, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
