<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"My Church Shall Be Called in My Name"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 116-120</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brothers and sisters, and I include all of you, both you in this building and you
who are listening in on radio and television. I consider you all my brothers and sisters, for I
know, as you do, that we are all the sons and daughters of our Father in heaven. I sincerely
trust that you will join with me in a prayer that while I speak I may enjoy the Spirit and that
you may enjoy the Spirit, for I am convinced with Nephi that ". . . when a man speaketh by
the power of the Holy Ghost the power of the Holy Ghost carrieth it unto the hearts of the
children of men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/33/1#1">2 Ne. 33:1</a>).
</p><p>
I have a prepared talk in my pocket, which took me five months to prepare, titled "The Book
of Mormon&mdash;The Keystone of Our Religion." You, of course know what Brother McConkie
did to it. (laughter) He has made me feel towards it as the player on a boys' baseball team
felt towards left field. This player was taken out of a game to give Jimmy from the second
string a chance to play. As luck would have it, Jimmy dropped the first two balls hit into left
field. He was therefore taken out, and the left fielder put back in. The next two balls hit also
went to left field, and the regular player dropped them. When he came off the field at the end
of the inning, the coach said, "I wasn't surprised when Jimmy fumbled the ball, but I was
surprised at you." "Well, Coach," said the player, "I'll tell you, Jimmy messed up left field so
badly that no one can play it."
</p><p>
However, I do want to say one or two things about the Book of Mormon before I get to the
point that I have in mind to comment on.
</p><p>
As you know, the Book of Mormon is the current study course for
Melchizedek Priesthood quorums. I urge everyone to read it during 1961, particularly
Melchizedek Priesthood bearers. This I do because I think we need&mdash;as we increase in
Church membership under the impetus of our great missionary program&mdash;to keep pace in the
perfecting of our own lives. This we can do by putting on the "whole armour of God," as
Paul says, (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/11#11">Eph. 6:11</a>)
or, as Peter puts it, by more rapidly becoming "partakers of the divine
nature" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/4#4">2 Pet. 1:4</a>).
I do not know any more effective way to do this than to know and live
the teachings of the Book of Mormon. The Prophet knew what he was talking about when he
said that ". . . a man would get nearer to God by abiding by its precepts, than by any other
book" (<i>DHC</i> 4:461).
</p><p>
The Prophet also knew what he was talking about when he said "the Book of Mormon" is
"the keystone of our religion." We may not know all he had in mind when he said this, but
we do know the statement was amply justified because the authenticity of the Book of
Mormon rests upon two facts, acceptance of which is tantamount to acceptance of the whole
of the restored gospel, namely: the fact of modern revelation, by which I mean direct
communication from God to men, and the fact that Joseph Smith was a prophet of God.
</p><p>
Acceptance of the Book of Mormon requires acceptance of these two facts, because they are
inseparably connected with its coming forth. If one accepts them and the Book of Mormon,
he cannot deny the restored gospel, for it rests upon the same two facts. The person who
knows the Book of Mormon is true has passed the point of no return, so far as conversion is
concerned. He has come out of darkness into the glorious light of truth. He has, in effect,
accepted the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I would now like to say a few words about the significance of this conference. I have been
thinking about this as I have sat here on this stand during these conference sessions and
considered what was going on. I do not think I have the language to convey to you its full
significance, but I can say that it represents the most effective force in the world for the good
of humanity.
</p><p>
We have great gatherings, of course, in the United Nations. Representatives from the
governments of the world convene to deliberate, to reason, to argue, to compromise, to try in
every way devisable by the human mind to resolve differences. I suppose most of them come
with honest hearts to try to bring peace to the world.
</p><p>
We have come to this conference from many nations of the world&mdash;not, however, as
representatives of the governments of these nations. We are here representing the leadership of
the kingdom of God. This Church is the literal kingdom of God in the earth. We did not
come to argue, to jockey for position, to compromise differences and establish policies. We
came here to hear and learn the word of God as he has and does now reveal it through his
appointed servants, and to take it back and teach it to our people. We know that the gospel of
Jesus Christ, of which this Church is the repository, is the one and only way of peace. We
know that to everyone who accepts and lives it there comes peace&mdash;peace in his heart&mdash;even
in the midst of turmoil in the world. We know that if the people of the world would accept it
and live it, we would have peace in all the world. We are in very deed representatives of
Jesus Christ our Redeemer and his Father, God our Eternal Father. Our authority comes from
them.
</p><p>
This is the Church of Jesus Christ. It is the Church of Christ by his own statement as to what
his Church had to be. I am going to take the time to read to you what he said his Church had
to be. Brother [Milton R.] Hunter told about the visit of Jesus to the Nephites after he had
completed his post-resurrection ministry among the Saints at Jerusalem. When he appeared to
the Nephites, they saw him as he was&mdash;a glorified man of flesh and bone and spirit. He
walked with them, and he talked with them. He organized his Church among them. He clearly
pointed out to them two distinguishing characteristics of his Church. He chose, as you
remember, twelve disciples who were to serve among the Nephites as the
Twelve Apostles served the people in the land of Jerusalem.
</p><p>
"And it came to pass that as the disciples of Jesus were journeying and were preaching the
things which they had both heard and seen, and were baptizing in the name of Jesus, it came
to pass that the disciples were gathered together and were united in mighty prayer and fasting.
</p><p>
"And Jesus again showed himself unto them, for they were praying unto the Father in his
name; and Jesus came and stood in the midst of them, and said unto them: What will ye that I
shall give unto you?
</p><p>
"And they said unto him: Lord, we will that thou wouldst tell us the name whereby we shall
call this church; for there are disputations among the people concerning this matter.
</p><p>
"And the Lord said unto them: Verily, verily, I say unto you, why is it that the people should
murmur and dispute because of this thing?
</p><p>
"Have they not read the scriptures which say ye must take upon you the name of Christ,
which is my name? For by this name shall ye be called at the last day&mdash;[That great day when
we shall be called to stand before him to be judged]; 
</p><p>
"And whoso taketh upon him my name, and endureth to the end, the same shall be saved at
the last day.
</p><p>
"Therefore, whatsoever ye shall do, ye shall do it in my name; therefore ye shall call the
church in my name; and ye shall call upon the Father in my name that he will bless the
church for my sake.
</p><p>
"And how be it my church save it be called in my name? For if a church be called in Moses'
name then it be Moses' church; or if it be called in the name of a man then it be the church
of a man; but if it be called in my name then it is my church, if it so be that they are built
upon my gospel" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/1-8#1">3 Ne. 27:1-8</a>).
</p><p>
How about the name of this Church? What is it? It is "The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints." How did it get the name? Did Joseph Smith select it? No. The Lord Jesus
Christ himself told Joseph Smith to name this Church "The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints." I will not take time to read the instruction. You will find it in the 115th
section of the Doctrine and Covenants. In that revelation Jesus refers to "all the elders and
people of my Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints scattered abroad in all the world;
For thus shall my church be called in the last days, even the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/3-4#3">D&amp;C 115:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
Now what about the other point? It is my church "if it be called in my name . . . if it so be
that they are built upon my gospel." Now what is the gospel of Jesus Christ? I would like to
read to you out of this same chapter, the 27th chapter of 3rd Nephi, the gospel of Jesus
Christ, as defined by the Master himself&mdash;not by Joseph Smith, not by men, but by Christ
himself as he stood among the Nephites, as a resurrected being. To me it is marvelous: 
</p><p>
"Behold I have given unto you my gospel [he said], and this is the gospel which I have given
unto you&mdash;that I came into the world to do the will of my Father, because my Father sent
me.
</p><p>
"And my Father sent me that I might be lifted up upon the cross; and after that I had been
lifted up upon the cross, that I might draw all men unto me, that as I have been lifted up by
men even so should men be lifted up by the Father to stand before me, to be judged of their
works, whether they be good or whether they be evil&mdash;
</p><p>
"And for this cause have I been lifted up; therefore, according to the power of the Father I
will draw all men unto me, [in the universal resurrection], that they may be judged according
to their works.
</p><p>
"And it shall come to pass, that whoso repenteth and is baptized in my name shall be filled;
and if he endureth to the end, behold, him will I hold guiltless before my Father at that day
when I shall stand to judge the world.
</p><p>
"And he that endureth not unto the end [this is the Redeemer speaking], the same is he that is
also hewn down and cast into the fire, from whence they can no more return, because of the
justice of the Father.
</p><p>
"And this is the word which he hath given unto the children of men. And for
this cause he fulfilleth the words which he hath given, and he lieth not, but fulfilleth all his
words.
</p><p>
"And no unclean thing can enter into his kingdom; therefore nothing entereth into his rest
save it be those who have washed their garments in my blood, because of their faith, and the
repentance of all their sins, and their faithfulness unto the end.
</p><p>
"Now this is the commandment [said the Redeemer]: Repent, all ye ends of the earth and
come unto me and be baptized in my name, that ye may be sanctified by the reception of the
Holy Ghost, that ye may stand spotless before me at the last day.
</p><p>
"Verily, verily, I say unto you, this is my gospel"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/13-21#13">3 Ne. 27:13-21</a>).
</p><p>
Then he adds that "if ye do these things blessed are ye, for ye shall be lifted up at the last
day" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/22#22">3 Ne. 27:22</a>).
</p><p>
Now this Church is the Church of Jesus Christ. Of course, no one can know this fact with
certainty unless he has received a witness from the Holy Ghost. Everyone who will look can
see, however, that the Church meets the requirement laid down by the Redeemer. It was
named by him, it is called after him, and it is built upon the gospel as he defined it.
</p><p>
This Church is the standard which Isaiah said the Lord would set up for the people in the
latter days. This Church was given to be a light to the world and to be a standard for God's
people and for the Gentiles to seek to
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/9#9">D&amp;C 45:9</a>). This Church is the ensign on the mountain spoken of
by the Old Testament prophets
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/18/3#3">Isa. 18:3</a>). It is the way, the truth, and the life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).
</p><p>
I know these things are true. I know them by the witness of the Spirit to my soul, and I bear
you that witness. I know Jesus Christ lives. When I think of him, my Redeemer, I am always
moved. In my mind's eye, I see him in that great council before the world was
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/2#2">Moses 4:2</a>), when he said
in effect to his Father, "I will go. Mine be the willing sacrifice, the endless glory thine."
</p><p>
I view him as the Creator of this world and of the starry heavens. In this respect it is difficult
for us to realize the greatness of Jesus. Enoch was amazed when the Lord showed him his
creations. He referred to the number of them in this language: ". . . were it possible that man
could number the particles of the earth, yea, millions of earths like this, it would not be a
beginning to the number of thy creations"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/30#30">Moses 7:30</a>).
</p><p>
I think of this man&mdash;this Son of God, Jesus&mdash;as he stood on Mount Shelem before the
brother of Jared in his full-length spirit body and said: 
</p><p>
"Behold, I am he who was prepared from the foundation of the world to redeem my people.
Behold, I am Jesus Christ. . . .
</p><p>
". . . Seest thou that ye are created after mine own image? Yea, even all men were created in
the beginning after mine own image.
</p><p>
"Behold, this body, which ye now behold, is the body of my spirit; and man have I created
after the body of my spirit; and even as I appear unto thee to be in the spirit will I appear
unto my people in the flesh"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/3/14-16#14">Ether 3:14-16</a>).
</p><p>
That was 2,200 years before he appeared on earth as the infant son of Mary. I think of his
coming into this world, the Son of Mary and God the Eternal Father.
</p><p>
I think of him as he went through his life, teaching and blessing the people.
</p><p>
And, oh, I think of him in Gethsemane, when he suffered the pain of all men, that we might
be forgiven of our sins on conditions of repentance. I think of Luke's statement describing
Christ's suffering in Gethsemane: "... his sweat was as it were great drops of blood falling
down to the ground" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/44#44">Luke 22:44</a>).
 And of Christ's statement to Joseph Smith: ". . . Which
suffering caused myself, even God, the greatest of all, to tremble because of pain, and to
bleed at every pore, and to suffer both body and spirit&mdash;and would that I might not drink the
bitter cup, and shrink&mdash;
</p><p>
"Nevertheless, glory be to the Father, and I partook and finished my preparations unto the
children of men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/18-19#18">D&amp;C 19:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
By his suffering he put into effect the plan of mercy, the merciful gospel
plan of redemption by which all men may be cleansed of their sins.
</p><p>
And then I think of him on the cross. I think of him in the garden, when he spoke to Mary,
following which the light and knowledge broke through upon his disciples that he in reality
had won the victory over death, bringing about not only his own, but the resurrection of all
people.
</p><p>
I think of him with the Father in the grove with the Prophet Joseph. I know he lives.
</p><p>
I know my Redeemer lives. "Hear, O ye heavens, and give ear, O earth, and rejoice ye
inhabitants thereof, for the Lord is God, and beside him there is no Savior"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/1#1">D&amp;C 76:1</a>).
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony that this statement is true, and this witness which I bear will be
binding upon you; for I, like my brethren of the presiding councils of the Church, am a called
and ordained personal witness of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
This Church is the Church of God. We do have the gospel of Jesus Christ. If we will live it,
we will gain the promised blessings. That this may so be, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
