<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Responsibility for the Guidance of Youth</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 63-66</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Richards, President Clark, my beloved brothers and sisters: 
</p><p>
I always need the blessings of the Lord when I am called to this position. I could hardly
proceed without the assurance of those blessings. I shall be grateful for your prayers, your
patience and your understanding. After much fasting and much praying, I trust that the Lord
will sustain me. We do believe in praying, and we believe in fasting, and I testify to you that
therefrom comes great strength to us.
</p><p>
I am sure we were deeply touched this morning by this wonderful choir both at the broadcast
and at this session. They are a great credit to us, a great credit to themselves and to the
Church. Truly, they are regarded as wonderful servants, and they are not alone wonderful
singers, but they are wonderful people.
Regarding the divinely appointed responsibility of parents, the sobering counsel is given to us
that ". . . they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
These and many other scriptures make it crystal-clear the
heaven-imposed responsibilities of teaching our children properly. If we fail in our duty
toward them, we are weakening the foundation of our own influence.
</p><p>
Marriage is the gateway through which a man or woman obtains personal experience in
human relationships. Parenthood is the opportunity for putting that experience to heavenly and
practical use. It is a God-given right for parents to have children so that they can give them
intelligent, mental, moral and spiritual training. Parent love is beautiful, but parent love
combined with intelligent discipline is the force that turns children into great characters.
Misdirected and misguided offspring result in one of civilization's appalling wastes and
present-day problems. Good citizens are necessary to civilization but good parents are
obligatory if civilization is to continue.
</p><p>
We hear very little nowadays about the strength of character that our forefathers drilled into
their children. In those days, a boy grew up with the understanding that he could get
somewhere in this world through hard work, rather than looking for short-cuts. Promotion was
considered on performance, results, ability, and talent. Parents implanted in their children a
desire for sound knowledge and a yearning for excellence and a willingness for hard work.
The sense of personal responsibility was as basic as love itself.
</p><p>
Somewhere in our recent past, many of us have adopted the idea that a father's firm influence
is not essential in the raising of children. All too often father's role in family discipline has
been dismissed to, "You ask your mother." This may be all right with daughters, but with a
son, it is an invitation to disaster. A boy who grows up unable to look to his father for
guidance and decision and help will not have much respect for authority whatever its source.
</p><p>
Ninety percent of the youngsters who have had troubles are the products of homes where the
father's influence was lacking. As unattractive as the task may seem, a father is the guiding
director of the family, and when he fails in his job, there can be only chaos and trouble.
Should a father surrender to his wife his own position as head of the household, then the
results may be the same.
</p><p>
Faithful parents are entitled to the inspiration of the Lord. What would we do as parents
without that inspiration? But sometimes parents do not have the courage to follow that
inspiration, and they yield, when they should stand firm.
</p><p>
There should be well-established rules of behavior for growing boys and girls. The word "no"
is now practically obsolete. Is it wrong for youngsters to have to toe the line? Discipline&mdash;why,
we all need discipline! Someone has said that respect is no longer a part of the everyday
living. The lack of discipline will bring a lack of respect. Are parents smart to give in? Would
we not be better parents if we put our "foot down"? Youngsters are still youngsters, perhaps
immature. They need so much help and so much counsel. They have a lot to learn but as
parents we should not be afraid to teach them.
</p><p>
Perhaps we should let our youngsters know that they are supposed to achieve&mdash;they will be
required to work, and that celebration comes only after victory, accomplishment, and
achievement. A sensible youngster does not necessarily want his freedom. All he wants and
needs is love, and he knows deep down in his heart that the people who love him the most
are the ones who will have the courage to say "no." Discipline&mdash;yes, it is necessary to save
our youngsters from themselves!
</p><p>
There is no strength comparable to the strength of a nation whose people know the meaning
of sacrifice. Some parents say, "We do not want our youngsters to sacrifice." Young people
should be taught the meaning and the law of sacrifice. They will have to pay a price for
success. The price of success is high, but it is not nearly so high as the price of failure!
</p><p>
There are so many unwholesome outside influences working against us today, that it is a
challenge to all parents to teach their children properly and watch over them carefully.
</p><p>
During the last year, many of us have become increasingly alarmed by the fact that prolonged
exposure to television is having a disastrous effect on our children. Many
times, parents use television as a built-in substitute for parental guidance.
</p><p>
According to Edward R. Murrow, and I quote: 
</p><p>
"As a child's mind and character is shaped by what he sees and hears and as TV trends
continue, the nation faces the danger of mass imbecility."
</p><p>
Television has taken the place of reading, studying, and true family life in many homes. If
this continues for another generation, we may be shocked at the results.
</p><p>
During the past year, the greatest wave of crime and horror shows of all time has deluged this
nation.
</p><p>
Last fall, a prominent magazine stated that networks were devoting twenty-four hours a week
to violence. Of the thirty-one new programs introduced (and that number has now increased),
half are devoted to violence. It also states that one week's television programs showed 160
murders, 500 percent more than five years ago; 60 justifiable homicides; 192 attempted
murders; 83 robberies; 15 kidnappings; 24 conspiracies to commit murder; 21 jail breaks; 7
attempted lynchings, 6 dynamitings; 11 extortions; 2 cases of arson; and 2 cases of torture;
plus an unaccountable number of fights, sluggings, maulings, etc.
</p><p>
I wonder if we realize what effect this is going to have. It seems a shame that children should
be subjected to such atrocities. What we need are more producers and sponsors who are
interested in educational programs and character building.
</p><p>
Judge Frank J. Kronenburg of New York says that "television is an instrument of undue
pressure that convinces the immature mind that violence is an accepted way of life . . . The
results will best be known by posterity . . ."
</p><p>
James V. Bennett, director of the Federal Bureau of Prisons states: "The increasing number of
prisoners young and old whose crime closely parallels what they have seen on television is a
matter of great concern to me. The impressionable maladjusted or emotional young person
sees these crimes and re-enacts them."
</p><p>
Since all of us are so deeply concerned, it is up to us to encourage and suggest to sponsors,
stations, public officials, radio commissioners, newspapers, and magazines, new and different
programs; and patronize good programs. Television is a great modern invention. It can be so
educational, it can be such a help in character building. Many programs are already very
excellent, and we should support them.
</p><p>
The proper use of leisure time is very important, and the proper use of it has been the means
of helping many young men and women to greatness.
</p><p>
I recently heard someone say, talking about television, that it was a good way to kill time.
Then I thought at that time of what Thoreau once said: "As if you could kill time without
injuring eternity."
</p><p>
Of course, we as parents cannot blame all juvenile delinquency on television. We must take
the responsibility in the home. Make no mistake about that. Most parents love their children
and want them to have as much freedom as is necessary, but as Sam Levenson says, "We
don't want the Bill of Rights to turn into the rights of Billy."
</p><p>
"It is a full-time job to be decent"&mdash;to be decent to everybody all the time. To be decent is to
cease bitterness jealousy, and hate, to refrain from gossip, refrain from backbiting, and from
passing on untrue comments and unreliable stories about another, to be considerate,
thoughtful, and sympathetic. After all, everyone that I know of already has a very heavy load
to carry.
</p><p>
Referring to the life of Jesus, there was no hate in him, but only gentleness and patience.
Through him, it was not just a religion that was born. It was man reaching out for something
clean and good, yearning for something decent and dignified. Men had known for centuries
that happiness did not evolve from violence and injustice, not even from power. They knew
cruelty always defeated itself.
</p><p>
Jesus taught that respect and love should be the primary guides of human behavior and human
decency. There is an eternal hope that this can be a good world, that nations can live in
harmony, that people can produce and trade and serve, each for the profit of
the other. It is a beautiful thing that man after all his tragic experience with war, brutality and
despair, can hold to this wonderful belief.
</p><p>
Remember, young people, there is a price for success, but the price of success is not nearly so
high as the price of failure. Remember, young people, that you are holding our hearts and
your future in your hands.
</p><p>
I want to bear my testimony to the Lord for his kindness and mercies to me, for his blessings,
for his help and his guidance. I know that this is the true Church of Jesus Christ. I know that
God lives, that he is our Father. I know that Jesus Christ is the Son of God, our beloved
Savior and Redeemer.
</p><p>
I wonder how near we can get to our Heavenly Father and to our Savior. I know from my
own experience that when I can become humble, it is possible for me to get very close to the
Lord. I know that there is divine inspiration and revelation in the Church today. I know that
our beloved President David O. McKay, a prophet of God, is at the head of the Church. I
know he is inspired of the Lord. I know that the priesthood is in the Church today, and that
inspiration and revelation in the Church today is as strong or stronger than we have ever
known it before.
</p><p>
May God bless us that we may live up to the standards of this beautiful gospel, to this Church
which is our life, which makes our life as it is, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
