<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Stephen L Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Stephen L Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 10-13</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren:  With the impressive presentation which we have witnessed here in this building
tonight, I wish that, all assembled who are privileged by special wire to hear this service
might have seen it also.
</p><p>
With President Clark's remarks as something of a background and justification, I would like
to say a few words to the priesthood upon a subject which has been weighing upon my mind
for quite a period of time.  I would like to speak briefly on the subject of justice and mercy. 
The Gospel of Jesus Christ is founded on law, salutary, righteous, benevolent
law, established or the salvation and the blessing of humanity.  For every law given, there is a
penalty for its infraction.  I know of no scripture where this is more plainly stated than by the
Prophet Alma: "Now, how could a man repent except he should sin?  How could he sin if
there was no law?  How could there be a law save there was a punishment?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/42/17#17">Alma 42:17</a>).
The Savior himself declared that he came to fulfill the law, not to do away with it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/17#17">Matt. 5:17</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/12/17-19#17">3 Ne. 12:17-19</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/15/2-10#2">3 Ne. 15:2-10</a>), but with
the law he brought the principle of mercy to temper its enforcement, and to bring hope and
encouragement to offenders for forgiveness through repentance.
</p><p>
I presume it has always been a nice question, and a perplexing one, to determine when the
demands of justice are satisfied and the principle of mercy takes over.  To assist in the
determination of this issue, we have available to us again the words of Alma: "For behold,
justice exerciseth all his demands, and also mercy claimeth all which is her own; and thus,
none but the <i>truly penitent</i> are saved.  What, do ye suppose that mercy can rob justice?  I say
unto you, Nay; not one whit.  If so, God would cease to be God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/42/24-25#24">Alma 42:24-25</a>).
</p><p>
Now the Church of Christ is commissioned with the authority to interpret the law and pass
judgment on infractions thereof.  This is a heavy responsibility, one which many officers of
the Church would forego, if they could justify themselves in so doing.  In civil government it
is not uncommon to hear references to the majesty of the law, by which is contemplated, we
may assume, not only its supremacy and binding force, but also the deference and respect
which should be shown for it, and the obligation to sustain its sovereign power.  Certainly this
applies with greater force and extended meaning to the majesty of divine law. It is God's law. 
It must be supported and it must be enforced to win salvation and the respect of those within
the Kingdom and those without.
</p><p>
For the maintenance of the law of the Lord, judges have been set up in his Kingdom,
tribunals established, and guiding principles laid down for the administration of justice. 
Bishops of Wards have been designated common judges in Israel, and they, with their
counselors, have been delegated with authority to deal with cases properly coming under their
jurisdiction. Appellate courts, culminating in the First Presidency of the Church, have likewise
been designated by revelation having both appellate and original jurisdiction.
</p><p>
With this as a premise, I ask first the question, How can the priesthood and ecclesiastical
authority of the Church best discharge the responsibility so committed to it.  Do not "the
judges in Israel" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/17#17">D&amp;C 58:17</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/72,76#72">D&amp;C 107:72,76</a>) have a compelling
obligation to deal with all cases of infraction against the
law, mercifully but justly? What good to the Church, what real benefit to erring members, can
come from ignoring this obligation and, as we sometimes say, winking at and
"white-washing" the offenders?  Can the judges thus help in setting people on the way to
repentance and forgiveness?
</p><p>
What is repentance, and when does it become operative in the attainment of forgiveness?  We
all know the answer.  Repentance consists first in a godly sorrow.  Note the term "godly
sorrow," which the scriptures tell us "worketh repentance to salvation . . . but the sorrow of the
world worketh death" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/7/10#10">2 Cor. 7:10</a>).
This godly sorrow is something more than admission
after being discovered in sin, and the judges in Zion will do well not to confuse the two. 
Next after godly sorrow comes confession, which is prompted by the inward sorrow and the
earnest desire for relief from the suffering entailed by acute realization of wrongdoing of
which we saw an impressive illustration tonight.  To whom should confession be made?  To
the Lord, of course, whose law has been violated.  To the aggrieved person or persons, as an
essential in making due retribution if that is necessary.  And then certainly to
the Lord's representative, his appointed judge in Israel, under whose ecclesiastical jurisdiction
the offender lives and holds membership in the Kingdom.
</p><p>
Is the offender justified in bypassing his immediate Church authority and judge, and going to
those who do not know him so well to make his confession? Almost universally, I think the
answer should be No, for the local tribunals are in position to know the individual, his history
and environs far better than those who have not had close contact with him, and in
consequence the local authorities have a background which will enable them to pass judgment
with more justice, and also mercy, than might be reasonably expected from any other source. 
It follows that it is the order of the Church for confessions to be made to the Bishop, which
entails heavy and exacting responsibilities on the part of the Bishop, the first of which is that
every confession should be received and held in the utmost confidence. A Bishop who
violates such a sacred confidence is himself guilty of an offense before God and the Church. 
Where it becomes necessary to take counselors into his confidence, as it frequently does, and
where it is necessary to organize tribunals, the Bishop should inform the confessor, and if
possible obtain his permission so to do.
</p><p>
Why is confession essential?  First, because the Lord has commanded it, and secondly,
because the offender cannot live and participate in the Kingdom of God, to receive the
blessings therefrom, with a lie in his heart.
</p><p>
Now the confessed offender is not without hope, for he can obtain. forgiveness by following
the course outlined, and by forsaking sins comparable to that committed, as well as all other
sin, and living before the Church and the Lord in such manner as to win approbation of both. 
The offender who has brought stigma and affront to the ward, the stake or the mission should
seek the forgiveness of those he has thus offended.  That may be had at times through the
presiding authorities of the various divisions of the Church.  At other times it may be
appropriate and quite necessary to make amends for public offenses and seek forgiveness
before organizations of the people.  The judges of Israel will determine this matter.  And if
the judges in the missions, the wards and the stakes need counsel in the matter, they know
where to get it.
</p><p>
How may the judges of Israel determine when repentance is adequate? Surely this
determination must rest with the inspired discernment and discretion of the judges.  No
specification of time required can be definitely made, but one caution may be wisely
observed.  That caution is for a sufficient time to elapse to permit a period of probation for
the one seeking forgiveness.  This probation serves a double purpose: First, and perhaps most
important, it enables the offender to determine for himself whether he has been able to so
master himself as to trust himself in the face of ever-recurring temptation; and secondly, to
enable the judges to make a more reliable appraisement of the genuineness of repentance and
worthiness for restored confidence.
</p><p>
Now I well recognize that the most serious aspects of this whole matter relate to personalities
involved.  I think I have never been moved to greater compassion than that arising out of
sympathy for the innocent victims of a sin committed by a son or a daughter, a father or a
mother.  I am sure that the officers of the Church will always be susceptible to feelings of
deep pity for those who have fallen from the path of righteousness and for their families. And
the question will continually arise in the future, as it has done throughout the past, how far
such considerations shall deter the judges of Israel from merciful, kind, but just adjudication
of offenses against the laws of God.  Long ago I have taken the position, with which I think
my brethren accord, that <i>every case of infraction</i> and I speak now of those infractions
violative of the laws of God which involve moral turpitude, every infraction
<i>against the laws of God should be dealt with</i>. I do not say how. I leave that to the inspired
wisdom of the judges.  Knowingly permitting a serious infraction of divine law to pass
unnoticed is no kindness to the offender. He will never gain forgiveness except on the terms
the Lord has prescribed, and which I have tried to outline.
</p><p>
And I ask you as a final question, How can we ever hope to maintain the dignity of the
Church and the majesty of the law of the Lord without exercising disciplinary action through
the tribunals which the Lord has set up. So I think I am justified in calling upon the
Bishoprics, the High Councils, the Stake Presidencies, the Mission Presidencies, and the
officers of quorums to be watchmen on the towers of Zion, to guard and forewarn the people
against the incursion of sin, to teach in plainness and without equivocation the law of the
Lord, to up old the law, and righteously and mercifully enforce it for the blessing of our
membership in the Church and all mankind.
</p><p>
Now I hope, my brethren, that I do not seem too exacting in what I have laid before you.  I
believe that it is but a kindness to our brethren and our sisters throughout the Kingdom of the
Lord to make them understand these principles which he has laid down, and I believe that if
we exercise the great priesthood which has been given to us in the manner in which we
should exercise it, we shall accomplish for those who offend, as well as for the Church, a
great service.  And I ask the Lord to bless us in this great power of the Holy Priesthood, to
which tribute has been paid here tonight.  It is the power of God; it is the direct delegation of
his authority for the administration of his work, and he has selected his servant who stands at
the head of this Kingdom to represent him, and I know that as we follow his direction and
counsel and his example, we will win for ourselves his confidence and we will win the
confidence of the Lord, and the blessings which will make us happy.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless you, my brethren, I humbly ask in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
