<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Divine Call of the Seventies</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 63-66</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: I should like to express my appreciation for this excellent choir that
has been rendering the music of today. The singers are Germans, and we are all interested in
the German people. They have made a contribution to this sacred religious movement that we
represent. I believe with all my heart that the German nation will come back and establish
again the civilization and culture that it once had. They are a great people.
</p><p>
A few days ago, two meetings of all the General Authorities of the Church were held. The
first one was in the temple at Logan, and a few days later the second meeting was held in our
temple here in Salt Lake City. In thinking of them I realize more and more that to love and
know God is the highest blessedness of mankind. Temples built by the Latter-day Saints are
houses of prayer, of fasting, and of faith, houses of glory and order, houses of God. You
recall the words as found in the dedicatory prayer of the Kirtland Temple which were given
by the Prophet Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
. . . seek ye diligently and teach one another words of wisdom; yea, seek ye out of the best
books words of wisdom, seek learning even by study and also by faith; 
</p><p>
Organize yourselves; prepare every needful thing, and establish a house, even a house of
prayer, a house of fasting, a house of faith, a house of learning, a house of glory, a house of
order, a house of God; 
</p><p>
Have mercy, O Lord, upon all the nations of the earth; have mercy upon the rulers of our
land; may those principles which were so honorably and nobly defended, namely, the
Constitution of our land, by our fathers, be established forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/7-8,54#7">D&amp;C 109:7-8,54</a>).
</p><p>
I wonder sometimes if in reading our sacred books we enter into the thoughts of the prophets
of God, and into their hearts. Have we as religious and moral men sought to attain the perfect
life by contemplation and work? So much might be said about our meetings in the
temples. We all felt the goodness and beauty of human life. We felt as we
have never felt before the hunger and labor, love and death, faith and work which operated to
produce these sacred buildings.
</p><p>
When we think of the Constitution of our land, we recall many historical statements that are
sacred and true. First, the words of the French writer, Michelet. He had written about the
terrible days of the French Revolution when he writes these words: 
</p><p>
The world is waiting for a faith, to march forward again to breathe and to live. But never can
faith have a beginning in deceit, cunning, or treaties of falsehood.
</p><p>
It is interesting to note that according to Washington Irving, Columbus when he set foot on
the island of San Salvador, uttered the following prayer, which has been translated from the
Latin: 
</p><p>
O God, our Father, eternal and omnipotent, Creator of heaven and earth and sea, we glorify
Thy holy name, praise Thy majesty, whom we serve in all humility, we give unto Thy holy
protection this new part of the world.
</p><p>
Then we have the prayer of Pastor Robinson as he blessed the Pilgrim fathers when they left
in the <i>Mayflower</i> for the New World.
</p><p>
Brethren, we are now quickly to part from one another, and whether I may ever live to see
your face on earth anymore, the God of Heaven only knows; but whether the Lord hath
appointed that or not, I charge you before God and His blessed angels, that you follow me no
farther than you have seen me follow the Lord Jesus Christ. If God reveal anything to you, by
any other instrument of His, be as ready to receive it, as ever you were to receive truth, by
my ministry; for I am fully persuaded, I am very confident that the Lord has more truth yet to
break forth out of His holy word. For my part, I cannot sufficiently bewail the condition of
the reformed churches, who are come to a period in religion, and will go at present no further
than the instruments of their reformation. The Lutherans cannot be drawn to go beyond what
Luther saw; whatever part of his will our good God has revealed to Calvin, they will rather
die than embrace it and the Calvinists, you see, stick fast where they were left by that great
man of God, who yet saw not all things. This is a misery much to be lamented; for though
they were burning a shining light in their times, yet they penetrated not into the whole
counsel of God; but were they now living, would be as willing to embrace further light as that
which they at first received. I beseech you to remember it as an article in your church
Covenant. "That you be ready to receive whatever truth shall be made known to you from the
written word of God." But I must herewithal exhort you to take heed what you receive as
truth. Examine it, consider it, and compare it with other scriptures of truth, before you receive
it; for it is not possible that the Christian world should come so lately out of thick
anti-Christian darkness and that perfection of knowledge should break forth at once.
</p><p>
To be called to the field as a missionary is an honor and a recognition of a person's real
worth. It is a call to labor with undying zeal to awaken within men a faith in the living God
and to turn to him with a repentant heart. No one can deny the force the beauty of the passion
for extending one's own belief and hopes to others "for imparting to them the comfort of
one's own salvation." What splendor of life is that of Paul the Apostle, who no sooner was
his own life made over, no sooner had the faith and the hope of a new life taken possession
of him, than he was overcome with the desire to disseminate this possession to all the world
and to make Jew and Gentile alike see and glory in the light and splendor of the Christian
truth. In our day, since the restoration of the gospel, we know the hundreds, yea, thousands
who have gone into the remote parts of the world to preach the gospel and to turn men's
thoughts to their God. This was even true long before there were railroads or quick and safe
means of travel by sea. Missionaries left home and friends to go to far-off China and India,
and the South Seas, to say nothing of Europe and South America. They
faced hardships in strange lands, and often misery for the sake of communicating the Gospel
message. Many have given their lives as they bore testimony of the restored word of God.
The splendor of their spirits and the grandeur of their achievements are known. The stories of
their experiences and accomplishments will someday become the most beautiful epics of the
Latter-day Saints, epics that will thrill the world with their truth and beauty. Let me here
relate a story of the long ago: 
</p><p>
In the summer of 1857, my father, Seymour B. Young, Phillip Margetts, and David Wilcken
were called to England on a mission; They were all of the same age, nineteen years.
Constructing a handcart, they made ready to leave. Their first objective was Council Bluffs,
just across the Missouri River from Omaha. From there they would take the train for New
York, where they could embark on a sailing vessel for England. One night, while they were
sitting around a wood fire on the Platte River, singing songs, and talking about the "folks at
home," Brother Margetts began to recite some of the fine lines from the plays of Shakespeare,
among which were the words of <i>Macbeth</i>: 
</p><p>
Tomorrow, and tomorrow, and tomorrow<br />
Creeps in this petty pace from day to day<br />
To the last syllable of recorded time; <br />
And all our yesterdays have lighted fools<br />
The way to dusty death. Out, out, brief candle!<br />
Life's but a walking shadow, a poor player<br />
That struts and frets his hour upon the stage<br />
And then is heard no more.
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; (Wm. Shakespeare, Macbeth, Act V. Sc. 5.)
</p><p>
"We sat deep in thought," said my father, "for we had been listening to a sage of history, a
man who knew Shakespeare. We slept under the stars that night, as we did for over three
months. Every night we studied the words of Holy Writ, every day as we pulled the handcart
over the trail and through the rivers, our hearts were swallowed up in a kind of glow of
God's love coming down as a constant stream of light."
</p><p>
They were missionaries of the Lord.
</p><p>
In the days of Queen Elizabeth of England, there were many able seamen who manned the
large navy which brought England to the height of her power on the seas. Among the noted
commanders of the fleet was Sir Francis Drake, who sailed up the Pacific Coast as far as the
present state of Washington, and then went on around the world. He was the first Englishman
to circumnavigate the earth. Standing on the deck of his ship one day, Drake said to his men: 
</p><p>
Men pass away, but people abide. See that ye hold fast the heritage we leave you, yea, and
teach your children its value, that never in the coming centuries, their hearts may fail them, or
their hands grow weak. Hereto, we have been too much afraid. Henceforth, we will fear only
God.
</p><p>
In this troubled world we need more and more the principle of unity amid all the marring
elements of human life. We must in our work have a definite purpose, and before that
purpose can be well established in our hearts, we must see it related to the very purposes of
God. Every quorum should have an ideal which is well defined and which invites the greatest
effort on the part of every member to help realize that ideal. The ideal is to bring about a
brotherhood within the quorum, a brotherhood so lasting that nothing can break it. Certainly
no outside power can. This brotherhood will be expressed in their thoughts and interest in one
another. The members touch one another by doing good, by kindness, by
philanthropy&mdash;something more than the mere clasp of hands and interchange of idle words. It is the delight
of diffusing something of the spirit of gentility and graciousness. In all such expressions of
good-will and respect, the grace of the act depends as much on the manner of it, as on the act
itself.
</p><p>
One of the essential things with Jesus Christ was the training of his disciples to have faith in
God. ". . . ye believe in God, believe also in me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1#1">John 14:1</a>). His disciples
went into the world to preach the gospel. I have given you an example of missionary zeal.
And now one of ancient times: Paul, the Apostle, had become one of the disciples of the
Lord. He went about preaching the gospel "with inspired eloquence and logic." He went to
Athens. They took him to the Areopagus, saying: ". . . thou bringest certain strange things to
our ears" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/20#20">Acts 17:20</a>).
You read Paul's discourse for yourselves. "It is the shortest important
speech ever made, excepting only Lincoln's undying Gettysburg speech address. In less than
one hundred and fifty words he put the argument for and assertion of the living God of
salvation and the resurrection of the dead. In doing this he even included a quotation from the
Greek poets." He had planted the seed. He had aroused interest.
</p><p>
As missionaries, we should find the good in people. We should judge all people not by their
mistakes but by the abundance of their powers. Our work as teachers is based on love, and if
we have the love of our listeners, we must see to it that their merits are understood, rather
than their faults found out.
</p><p>
Let us keep in mind the beautiful words of the Chinese Confucius, ages before Christ: 
</p><p>
Those who know the truth are not equal to those who love it; and they who love it are not
equal to those who live it.
</p><p>
I pray that we may all come to a deeper understanding of the gospel, that we may live as God
would have us live. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
