<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Facing Another World Crisis</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 63-70</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This group of choice young men and women from Brigham Young University is an
inspiration even aside from the glorious singing. Just to look at them and realize what they
represent, I am sure, fills each heart with thanksgiving. They are here to render service today,
and we appreciate their presence. I was just thinking as I listened to these inspiring opening
songs that every one of these young men and young women has been taught by a mother and
a father to be true to the gospel of Jesus Christ, has been taught that to keep himself or
herself unspotted from the world will bring the greatest joy and happiness in this life and in
the world to come. I am thankful for an institution in the Church which associates with all the
sciences and all the learning given in the institutions of the state the teachings of the
principles of the gospel of Jesus Christ. I know they are true, and so may these young people,
and I pray that they will always hold to that truth.
</p><p>
Some of their mothers are worried. Some of you mothers have called by telephone; some of
you have called in person and expressed deep concern over the conditions in the world. Your
pleas and questions have prompted what I desire to say this morning. I wish all the world
could partake of this peaceful spirit, and the hope and inspiration that we received in the
sessions of the conference that were held yesterday, and the encouragement from the excellent
messages given, and I pray that I may say a word or two that will put you at peace and
increase that spirit of contentment.
</p><p>
A GUIDE TO PEACE
</p><p>
Jesus said on one occasion to his disciples who were somewhat worried and anxious because
Jesus had told them he was going to leave them,
</p><p>
Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1#1">John 14:1</a>).
</p><p>
In that one sentence, Jesus gives both a comforting admonition and a guide to contentment
and peace.
</p><p>
We are living in a troublous age. Many people in the Church, as millions in the world, are
stirred with anxiety; hearts are heavy with feelings of foreboding. For the third time in half a
century lowering war clouds threaten world peace. O foolish man! Will he never profit by the
experiences of the past! The responsibility of choice always rests upon each normal
individual. Never was that responsibility greater than today. A former member of the Deseret
Sunday School Union Board (author of an excellent little work, <i>Out of the Ashes</i>) expresses
the thought succinctly thus:
</p><p>
What the people now think and do, or what they fail to think, or what they fail to do means
which way to this generation, and means what chance to the generation next to come.
</p><p>
THE NEED FOR REPENTANCE
</p><p>
A leading businessman, Mr. W. T. Holliday, president of the Standard Oil Company of Ohio,
in an article captioned, "Our Final Choice," declares that:
</p><p>
. . . whenever a civilization is faced with a new and fundamental challenge, there is only one
thing that can save it from decline and fall&mdash;its men and women must change their habits of
thought to meet the challenge. Either they meet their new world with new thinking, or they go
under.
</p><p>
Though with a different ideal in mind, that is the advice which Peter gave the multitude on
the day of Pentecost, when in perplexity they cried: "Men and brethren, what shall we do?"
His answer was:
</p><p>
. . . Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of
sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37-39#37">Acts 2:37-39</a>).
</p><p>
To repent is to change one's mind or one's heart with regard to past or intended action,
conduct, etc., on account of regret or dissatisfaction.
</p><p>
Individuals, groups, and nations viewing with alarm the many critical national, industrial, and
moral problems are hoping that "some means will be found to turn our misdirected powers
into new channels, leading to the establishment of new and prosperous conditions."
</p><p>
SPIRITUAL READINESS
</p><p>
Radio and press commentators, contributors to magazines, editorial writers and statesmen
suggest various plans and policies as solutions of our difficulties and perplexities. One of the
best is a plan for a world federation, supported by a sufficiently strong armament to enforce
its laws and statutes.
</p><p>
One great objection to its adoption, however, is that "human nature is not spiritually ready"
for such a federation. It is of this "spiritual readiness" I wish to speak.
</p><p>
It is the duty of the members of the Church to hold aloft true spiritual standards. Then we
shall be better prepared for any eventuality brought about by pagan aggression. These
principles have been proclaimed in all ages. They are simple, easily understood, but all too
generally ignored.
</p><p>
WARNING OF MOSES TO ISRAEL
</p><p>
Approximately thirty-five centuries ago Moses, "the human transmitter of the greatest human
conduct code of all time," warned the people of Israel as follows:
</p><p>
Therefore thou shalt keep the commandments of the Lord thy God, to walk in his ways, and
to fear him.
</p><p>
For the Lord thy God bringeth thee into a good land, a land of brooks of water, of fountains
and depths that spring out of valleys and hills;
</p><p>
A land of wheat, and barley, and vines, and fig trees, and pomegranates; a land of oil olive,
and honey;
</p><p>
A land wherein thou shalt eat bread without scarceness, thou shalt not lack any thing in it; a
land whose stones are iron, and out of whose hills thou mayest dig brass.
</p><p>
When thou hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt bless the Lord thy God for the good land
which he hath given thee.
</p><p>
Beware that thou forget not the Lord thy God, in not keeping his commandments, and his
judgments, and his statutes, which I command thee this day:
</p><p>
Lest when thou hast eaten and art full, and hast built goodly houses, and dwelt therein:
</p><p>
And when thy herds and thy flocks multiply, and thy silver and thy gold is multiplied, and all
that thou hast is multiplied;
</p><p>
Then thine heart be lifted up, and thou forget the Lord thy God, which brought thee forth . . .
</p><p>
And thou say in thine heart, My power and the might of mine hand hath gotten me this
wealth.
</p><p>
But thou shalt remember the Lord thy God: for it is he that giveth thee power to get wealth,
that he may establish his covenant . . .
</p><p>
And it shall be, if thou do at all forget the Lord thy God, and walk after other gods, and serve
them, and worship, them, I testify against you this day that ye shall surely perish
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/8/6-14,17-19#6">Deut. 8:6-14,17-19</a>).
</p><p>
All that Moses wrote in praise of the richness and productivity of the Promised Land, and
more than he wrote can be applied to this great land of America&mdash;a land of corn, wheat,
barley, and all other kinds of grain&mdash;a land of milk and honey&mdash;a land where we eat bread
without scarceness&mdash;a land whose stones are gold, silver, and iron, and out of whose
hills we dig brass&mdash;a land aptly called the "granary of the world."
</p><p>
His words of admonition are equally applicable&mdash;
</p><p>
When thou hast eaten and art full, then thou shalt bless the Lord thy God for the good land
which he hath given thee (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/8/10#10">Deut. 8:10</a>).
</p><p>
That was the message to ancient Israel.
</p><p>
"LET NOT YOUR HEART BE TROUBLED"
</p><p>
Fifteen hundred years later a little group of men faced a future that was just as threatening
and foreboding to them as that which the world faces today. The men in that group were
Simon Peter, Thomas, Nathanael of Cana in Galilee, James and John, sons of Zebedee, and
two others of his disciples. A short time before that gloomy period Jesus had said to them:
</p><p>
Let not your heart be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1#1">John 14:1</a>).
</p><p>
He promised them the Comforter who would testify of the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>), who would bring all things
to their remembrance, who would show them things to come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13#13">John 16:13</a>).
</p><p>
Notwithstanding all those promises and divine exhortations, the disciples, following the
crucifixion of their Lord, were depressed in their feelings. Their hopes were shattered. Their
future, so far as Christ's triumph on earth was concerned, seemed all but blighted. They had
been called and set apart to be "fishers" of men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/19#19">Matt. 4:19</a>),
and to Peter had been given the keys of the
kingdom (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18-19#18">Matt. 16:18-19</a>).
Notwithstanding all this, in that hour of despondency, Peter turned to his old
vocation, and said: "I go a fishing," and the others replied, "We go also with thee" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/3,15-18#3">John 21:3,15-18</a>)).
</p><p>
CHARGE GIVEN TO APOSTLES OF CHRIST
</p><p>
They were in that state of mind when the Resurrected Christ said to the discouraged leader of
the Twelve: "Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me more than these?" Peter answered, "Yea,
Lord; thou knowest that I love thee." Said the Lord, "Feed my sheep." I have my own
interpretation of what "these" means. Keep in mind, will you please, that it was his
vocation&mdash;what he would get. He had there before him the products of his morning's fishing,
for he had fished all night and had caught nothing. "Simon, son of Jonas, lovest thou me
more than these?" Yea, Lord, thou knowest, I love thee." "Feed my sheep"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/15-18#15">John 21:15-18</a>).
</p><p>
On that occasion Peter became conscious of his responsibility not only as a fisher of men, but
also as a shepherd of the flock. It was then that he sensed finally and completely the full
meaning of the divine injunction, "Follow thou me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/22#22">John 21:22</a>).
</p><p>
With that never-failing light, those twelve humble men succeeded in changing the course of
human relations. Writes Beverley Nichols:
</p><p>
Twelve simple men with only the wind to bear them over the seas, with only a few pence in
their pockets, and a shining faith in their hearts. They fell far short of their ideal; their words
were twisted and mocked; and false temples were built over their bones, in praise of a Christ
they would have rejected. And yet, by the light of their inspiration, many of the world's
loveliest things were created, and many of the world's finest minds inspired.
</p><p>
If twelve men did that nineteen hundred years ago, what might not twelve men do today? For
God has now given us the power of whispering across space, of transmitting our thoughts
from one end of the earth to another. What shall we whisper&mdash;what shall we think? That is the
question.
</p><p>
ETERNAL PRINCIPLES THAT WILL BRING PEACE
</p><p>
The world wants peace, the winning of which seems to be more difficult than the winning of
the war.
</p><p>
No peace, even though temporarily obtained, will be permanent unless it is built upon the
solid foundation of eternal principles enunciated in the two incidents I have mentioned.
</p><p>
The first of these the Lord gave to Moses on Mount Sinai&mdash;"Thou shalt worship the Lord thy
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/10#10">Matt. 4:10</a>).
Consider what that means. When we sincerely accept God as our Father and make him
the center of our being, we become conscious of a new aim in life. No longer is the chief end
of daily life merely to nourish and to pamper the body as all animals do. Spiritual attainment,
not physical indulgence, becomes the chief goal. God is not viewed from the standpoint of
what we may get from him, but what we may give to him. Only in the complete surrender of
our inner life may we rise above the selfish, sordid pull of nature. Divine and eternal as an
element in the acquisition of peace is Christ's admonition,
</p><p>
. . . seek ye first the kingdom of God and his righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
Of equal importance is the acceptance of the Son of God as the Savior of mankind.
</p><p>
When Jesus was talking to his disciples, just immediately preceding his betrayal, explaining to
them that he would have to leave them, he said: "Ye believe in God, believe also in me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1#1">John 14:1</a>). He
desired them to understand, as he wants the whole world to know, that only through him can
man find the life abundant. Those were not mere words of defiance which Peter uttered as he
and John stood prisoners before the high priests. He proclaimed an eternal truth when he said:
</p><p>
. . . for there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
That truth is reiterated in the Doctrine and Covenants&mdash;
</p><p>
. . . all men must repent and believe on the name of Jesus Christ, and worship the Father in
his name, and endure in faith on his name to the end, or they cannot be saved in the kingdom
of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/29#29">D&amp;C 20:29</a>).
</p><p>
I like to associate with that word "saved" the power that man gets in this life to rise above his
animal instincts and passions, power to overcome or resist social evils that blight men's and
women's souls and shut them out not only from the peace of the world, but also from
membership in the kingdom of God. Men may yearn for peace, cry for peace, and work for
peace, but there will be no peace until they follow the path pointed out by the Living Christ.
</p><p>
CONFIDENCE IN FELLOWMEN
</p><p>
A third essential to our peace of mind, and eventually to the peace of nations, is to keep
confidence in our fellow men. You say how can we keep confidence when men are so
corrupt? I answer that even if two or three, or even a score of men prove themselves
dishonest and wicked, we are not justified in losing confidence in all men. Most people are
honorable and upright&mdash;I like to think that&mdash;and desirous to:
</p><p>
. . . do justly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/micah/6/8#8">Micah 6:8</a>).
</p><p>
Even if international leaders of a nation or of five nations disavow their Creator, and that's
what they are saying in their hearts, "my power and the might of mine hand have gotten me this
wealth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/8/17#17">Deut. 8:17</a>),
and even deny the Christ who redeemed them, let us remember that ten times that
number of nations still profess to believe in God and in individual freedom.
</p><p>
These three principles&mdash;faith in Gods&mdash;acceptance of Christ as the Savior of men&mdash;confidence
in our fellow men&mdash;are summed up by the Savior as follows:
</p><p>
. . . Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all
thy mind.
</p><p>
This is the first and great commandment.
</p><p>
And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37-39#37">Matt. 22:37-39</a>).
</p><p>
SLANDER OVERCOME BY GOOD WORKS
</p><p>
We learn from authentic sources that communistic countries, operating from behind the "iron
curtain" accuse democratic countries, and particularly the United States, of virtually every
political and moral crime under the sun. Our democracy is described as an instrument to
enslave people.
</p><p>
Such slander has been compared to slugs that crawl over our cabbages. You may kill them,
but there is still the slime
</p><p>
The surest method against such slander is to live it down in perseverance in well doing, and
by prayer to God that he would cure the distempered mind of those who traduce and injure
us.
</p><p>
To the Church today are applicable the words of the Savior:
</p><p>
Let your light so shine before men, that they may see your good works, and glory your Father
which is in heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
If we would face the future, no matter what it may be, with calmness of spirit, with an
assurance that God governs in the affairs of men, let us as individuals and as a group live
exemplary lives.
</p><p>
SOCIAL EVILS
</p><p>
Let us see to it that the social evils now rampant in the world that bring such sorrow and
degradation to mankind, that spread sorrow and misery throughout the world are reduced to a
minimum in our own communities; for example, there is too much drunkenness, too much
unchastity. The excessive consumption of intoxicating liquors in this state is a reflection upon
all.
</p><p>
To curtail those evils, to spread love and peace, brotherly kindness throughout the world is
our paramount duty. If we succeed to a commendable degree we can say to the
world&mdash;unbelievers, scoffers, and all others, "Come, our way of life is best because it works
best. Our people are efficient, prosperous, and happy because we are a body who aid one
another in the productive life. We waste none of our substance in vice, luxury, or ostentation.
We do not dissipate our energy in brawling, gambling, or unwholesome habits. We conserve
our resources of body and mind and devote them to the upbuilding of the kingdom of God,
which is not a mystical but a real kingdom. It is a body of people dominated by ideals of
productivity, which is mutual service. We do not strive for the things which satisfy but for the
moment and then leave a bad taste. We strive for the things which build us up, and enable us
and our children to be strong, to flourish, and to conquer. We strive to make ourselves worthy
to receive the world by fitting ourselves to use the world more productively than others. We
believe that obedience to God means obedience to the laws of nature, which are but the
manifestations of his will; and we try by painstaking study to acquire the most complete and
exact knowledge of that will, in order that we may conform ourselves to it."
</p><p>
WORLD FACES A CRISIS
</p><p>
The world faces a crisis&mdash;a terrible crisis. Opportunity is given for men to choose wisely and
live, or disregard the Master's teachings and die. Down through the ages come resounding the
cry of Joshua&mdash;
</p><p>
... choose you this day whom ye will serve; . . . but as for me and my house, we will serve
the Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
And the thrilling words of Peter when commanded not to speak at all, nor to teach in the
name of Jesus:
</p><p>
. . . Whether it be right in the sight of God to hearken unto you more than unto God, judge
ye.
</p><p>
For we cannot but speak the things which we have seen and heard
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/19-20#19">Acts 4:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
The choice today is between dictatorship with the atheistic teachings of communism, and the
doctrine of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ, obedience to which alone can make us free.
</p><p>
God bless the Church, particularly our young people who are going to maintain its standards
God bless fathers and mothers who instill this faith in the hearts of children and proclaim it
throughout the world, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
