<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marvin O. Ashton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marvin O. Ashton, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 151-153</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
If I remember correctly, I followed Brother Kirkham last conference, and as far as I am
concerned, I will be glad to follow him any time, and yes, follow in his footsteps all the way.
I am not like the gentleman who had a wife like the wife that Brother Thomas E. McKay
spoke about in conference. He didn't want her nagging at him. He wanted her away from the
battle so he could fight in peace. He had a wife who thought she was better than he. Before
she died, she had put on her tombstone, "Follow me." You see, she wanted him to land in the
celestial realms she was dead sure of. He wasn't quite satisfied with the epitaph as it was, so
he finished it. It then read, "To follow thee I'm not content, until I know which way you
went."
</p><p>
THE WORK WITH THE BOYS OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
Oscar Kirkham has done a wonderful work in this Church and particularly with boys. If I
could follow him all the way, I would be very content. I had the pleasure of riding down to
conference in the automobile this morning with Elder Merrill. We were talking about some of
the observations he made with boys in this conference. He was very kind to us, I thought, and
by virtue of his observations in the conversation this morning, I am spurred on to say some of
the things I am going to try to say this afternoon. I told him I couldn't say what I wanted to
say at our Aaronic Priesthood meeting, because if I went into too much detail the bishop and
his counselors of a certain ward would be sure to guess about whom I was talking, and I have
so much to answer for now that I wouldn't be that brave. Brother Merrill said, "Surely, you
don't mean to say that 'tyranny' towards boys exists today." When I told him the whole story,
he could hardly believe it. The trouble with many of the fine things we hear is that they
always mean the other fellow. We don't "Stop, Look, and Listen." That sign on some of your
farms says, "This means you." Some of these observations I am trying to make do mean you
and me.
</p><p>
Like Brother Merrill, I had another talk I wanted to give this afternoon, but I am throwing it
away. To hear me tell it, my very best talks I have never given. Of course, that isn't hard to
believe, and such news is comforting.
</p><p>
Someone has said the reason the boy likes a dog is because it is the only thing around the
ranch that doesn't criticize him. When he's around, he's a pain in the neck. Yes, but if you
had the experience of some of the rest of us, when he isn't around, it's a pain in the heart.
Stay with him. I saw one of the finest demonstrations of love for a boy in Yellowstone Stake.
The story is about President Hess of that stake, and I am going into some detail:
</p><p>
I was attending a big banquet in St. Anthony, about six hundred strong, the select of the land.
All the fathers of the stake were there sitting beside their sons. Yes, they hired the biggest
hall in the place. Some of us were sitting at the head table. I discovered about three chairs
from where I was sitting something that decidedly interested me. It was a half-kept kid. The
back of his head looked like the back of a dog. What I'm trying to say is that he'd been
neglected. I went on without asking any questions, and yet I got curious. After the party was
over I inquired as to who the lad was. Here is the story I got: Coming down the highway
from his home President Hess was accosted by a shabbily dressed lad. The boy was invited to
get in the car. He asked, "Where are you going, mister?" The answer was, "I'm going to a
party for fathers and their sons." The boy was a real Yankee. He said, "Where is your boy?"
"I haven't him with me tonight," came the answer of the president. "Well, say, mister, why
can't I be your son tonight?"Well, the end of the story is, that urchin sat at the head of the
table as big as you please with the rest of us. <i>Brethren, that's America. That's the Church of</i>
<i>Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</i>. You never can tell what's under that mat of shaggy hair.
You can never tell what heart beats buttoned up in that threadbare coat. Let's love him.
</p><p>
Did you ever hear the story of the lad in the slums and his little sister who desperately took
sick? There had to be a transfusion. (We'll go through the story in a hurry.) They thought her
brother's blood would match. They tried it out, and it "clicked." When asked to give his blood
for his sister, he said, "Sure." When they cleaned his arm, its whiteness, with the dirt off,
nearly scared him to death. Well, they took a pint of his blood. An hour after the pumping
procedure he was told that his sister had revived and was getting along fine. But what was the
question the kid of the slums asked? It was, "Doc, when do I croak? When do I croak?" He
thought when he was asked to give his blood to his sister that it meant he was to give his life
for his sister. I repeat, "Will you give your blood to your sister?" "Sure." That was the answer
from an American lad of the slums.
</p><p>
Christ said that no man is greater than he who gives his life for his fellows
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/13#13">John 15:13</a>). Sometimes virtue
is put up in clumsy parcels, but underneath often you've got gold.
</p><p>
A TEACHER'S EXPERIENCE
</p><p>
Talk the boy's language. Be reasonably firm. Don't let him run over you. No boy loves you if
you let him run over you.
</p><p>
I once heard a very interesting story about the boys of a certain school district years ago in a
backwoods country. They rode every teacher out of the village. The school trustees didn't
know what to do about it. As fast as a new teacher came he was ridden out.
Finally, one of the trustees said, "I have a fellow that can take care of this school." They cried
out, "Trot him out. Send him here." The teacher got to the school Monday morning at
eight-thirty and brought with him his six-shooter. (I remind you that this was a school in a
wild country.) Well, a hawk floated overhead, flying a little low. He was circling around, and
he was a real temptation. The new teacher pulled out the six-shooter, pulled the trigger twice,
and the hawk fell at his feet. Of course, the school population gathered around this crack shot.
He observed, "That wasn't so bad, was it?" Well, he next went into the schoolroom. He
noticed the blackboard wasn't kept so spick and span, that a bull's-eye on the board with a
couple of holes in it would not do any particular harm. He stepped off a few steps, took the
six-shooter, pulled the trigger a couple of times more, hitting the bull's-eye squarely, and said,
"That wasn't so bad, was it?"
</p><p>
Well, he was talking their language. But he wasn't through yet. He pulled out his watch. "It's
time to ring the bell." He picked the leader of the gang, the one that had done the most in the
past in running former teachers out of their country. He requested, "Ring the bell." The fellow
stepped back with his fingers in his vest and replied, "Ring it yourself." Out came the
six-shooter. It pointed at the bully. "Ring the bell." He did.
</p><p>
Now, I didn't say that if you want to lead a bunch of boys take a six-shooter with you. I
didn't mean that. But talk their language and have them mind.
</p><p>
PRAISE FOR STAKE LEADERS
</p><p>
God bless you fine men. To repeat again, as we go around your stakes and see what you are
doing, if we were to give way to our feelings we would sit down and cry like babies at your
accomplishing great things. You are doing a fine job. I don't know what some of us do for
you in the way of inspiration when we stand before you, but I know what inspiration we get
from you in holding your hands and looking into your eyes. God bless you. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
