<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Missionaries Labor to Fulfil Promise</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">President of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 19-21</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Yesterday, with my Brethren, I was in session with some thirty missionary presidents.
We heard a report from all in relation to their work and the work of the missionaries who
labor under them. At the close of the meeting, and all through the meeting, we felt to rejoice
because of the glowing reports that they were able to give to us.
</p><p>
There is one reason why these missionaries go forth and that is to fulfil the promise that was
made by our Redeemer that his gospel of the kingdom should be preached in all the world as
a witness before the time of his second coming
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
In his discourse as recorded in the
twenty-fourth chapter of Matthew which came in response to the request of his disciples to
know concerning his second coming, and the events that would take place before his coming,
he told them of the calamities, the distress among the nations, the wars, the rumors of wars,
the commotions, men's hearts failing them, and that they would turn away from the truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_m/1/28-30#28">JS&mdash;M 1:28-30</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/21/26#26">Luke 21:26</a>).
Then speaking of the latter days he said to them: 
</p><p>
"And again, because iniquity shall abound, the love of many shall wax cold; but he that shall
not be overcome the same shall be saved.
</p><p>
"And again, this Gospel of the Kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto
all nations, and then shall the end come, or the destruction of the wicked"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_m/1/30-31#30">JS&mdash;M 1:30-31</a>).
</p><p>
Fulfilling that prediction that the gospel would again be preached, inferring that there would
be a time when it would not be preached and it would have to be restored, these missionaries
are going forth and spending their time which is appointed among the nations of the earth.
</p><p>
Unfortunately, because of conditions which cannot be controlled by the Church, our
missionary forces are reduced. We need missionaries. It is true today, as it was one hundred
years ago, that the field is wide; the harvest is great; but the laborers are few
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/2#2">Luke 10:2</a>). Likewise the
field is white and ready for the harvest
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/4#4">D&amp;C 4:4</a>). In a revelation given to the Church November 1,
1831, the Lord said he would send forth his missionaries, or his servants.
</p><p>
"And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I
have chosen in these last days.
</p><p>
"And they shall go forth and none shall stay them, for I the Lord have commanded them.
</p><p>
"Behold, this is mine authority, and the authority of my servants, and my
preface unto the book of my commandments, which I have given them to publish unto you, O
inhabitants of the earth.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, fear and tremble, O ye people, for what I the Lord have decreed in them shall be
fulfilled" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4-7#4">D&amp;C 1:4-7</a>).
</p><p>
Now the Lord has said that his missionaries shall not be stayed and that they shall go forth
until he says the work is finished. In this same revelation he also says this: 
</p><p>
"For they [the people of the earth] have strayed from mine ordinances, and have broken mine
everlasting covenant; 
</p><p>
"They seek not the Lord to establish his righteousness, but every man walketh in his own
way, and after the image of his own God, whose image is in the likeness of the world, and
whose substance is that of an idol, which waxeth old and shall perish in Babylon, even
Babylon the great, which shall fall.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments; 
</p><p>
"And also gave commandments to others, that they should proclaim these things unto the
world; and all this that it might be fulfilled, which was written by the prophets&mdash;
</p><p>
"The weak things of the world shall come forth and break down the mighty and strong ones,
that man should not counsel his fellow man, neither trust in the arm of flesh&mdash;
</p><p>
"But that every man might speak in the name of God the Lord, even the Savior of the world; 
</p><p>
"That faith also might increase in the earth; 
</p><p>
"That mine everlasting covenant might be established; 
</p><p>
"That the fullness of my gospel might be proclaimed by the weak and the simple unto the
ends of the world, and before kings and rulers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/15-23#15">D&amp;C 1:15-23</a>).
</p><p>
And so in fulfillment of these promises to the world, our missionaries go forth. No power has
been able to stay their hands. It has been tried. Great efforts were made in the very beginning
when there was only a handful of missionaries, but the progress of this work could not be
stopped. It cannot be stopped now. It must and will go forth that the inhabitants of the earth
may have the opportunity of repenting of their sins and receive the remission of their sins and
come into the Church and kingdom of God, before these final destructions come upon the
wicked, for they have been promised.
</p><p>
There is in the world today distress, turmoil, trouble, commotion, and contention among the
nations. There is no peace. There will be no peace until the Prince of Peace comes to bring it.
And his warning is to the world to repent
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/41#41">D&amp;C 18:41</a>).
This I might have read, for it is the first verse of
this revelation I have been quoting. The righteous have been called on to come out of
Babylon (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/5#5">D&amp;C 133:5</a>),
or the world, to receive the gospel of Jesus Christ as it has been restored, and find a
place in the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
And these missionaries, mostly young men, untrained in the ways of the world, go forth with
this message of salvation and confound the great and the mighty, because they have the truth.
They are proclaiming this gospel; the honest and sincere are hearing it and are repenting of
their sins and coming into the Church. The ungodly will not repent. This truth is also stated in
this revelation. They will not repent because today, as in times of old, men love darkness
more than light
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/19#19">John 3:19</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/21#21">D&amp;C 10:21</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/44-45#44">D&amp;C 29:44-45</a>).
</p><p>
I wish to testify to you, my brethren and sisters, and to all the world, that God lives, that he
has spoken again from the heavens, and the heavens have never been closed against those who
are honest and true, who earnestly seek the guidance of the Lord. The Lord never closed the
heavens. Men closed the heavens and said there should be no more revelation, no more
commandments, only those which are in the canon of scripture. It was men who
said that, not God. Men have said that the Lord finished his work. They have
said there could be no more coming of angels, no more scripture, and that we would have to
depend on the dead letter of the law as it is recorded in the books contained within the lids of
the Bible. Men are saying that&mdash;God did not say it.
</p><p>
And he has restored to us the everlasting gospel and has given us revelation and made known
to us many of the plain and important things pertaining to his kingdom&mdash;things revealed
anciently, and also in the day in which we live, and he will give revelation to this Church
from time to time according to the needs of the people, for the heavens are not sealed, only as
men have sealed them against themselves.
</p><p>
Let us seek to know his will, hearken to the counsels of the First Presidency of this Church,
and the President, who is the mouthpiece, the servant of God, with the authority to receive
revelation for the guidance not only of the Latter-day Saints, but also for the people of all the
world if they will only hearken to it. The Lord bless you, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
