<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Their Greatest Tragedy</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 59-63</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<b>Latter-day Saints Believe</b>
</p><p>
We Latter-day Saints believe in the Lord Jesus Christ wholeheartedly and without reservation.
</p><p>
He is the Savior of the world, the Redeemer of all mankind. He is the Son of Almighty God.
He is divine.
</p><p>
All power was given to him in heaven and on earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/18#18">Matt. 28:18</a>). He is the Creator. He made this planet
on which we live and all other heavenly bodies.
</p><p>
As the scriptures say, "All things were made by him; and without him was not any thing
made that was made" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/3#3">John 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
He became flesh and dwelt among mankind (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/14#14">John 1:14</a>),
some of whom beheld his glory, even the glory
as of the Only Begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth. His mortal advent was
accompanied by much sorrow and suffering, but the greatest tragedy of his coming was that
the people generally, and more particularly their leaders, did not&mdash;or would not&mdash;either
recognize or accept him.
</p><p>
<b>His Coming Was Expected</b>
</p><p>
His coming was not unexpected.
</p><p>
Quite the contrary.
</p><p>
The people of that day were anxiously looking for their Messiah, whose advent was clearly
foretold in the scriptures with which they were well familiar. Particularly were the scribes, the
lawyers, the high priests, and the learned members of the Sanhedrin well informed. They
knew what the prophets had said about the expected Savior, but these self-centered leaders
were so steeped in their traditions that they would not admit what they must have known to
be true.
</p><p>
<b>He was rejected</b>
</p><p>
They were so jealous of their own positions that they were not willing to give way to the new
King of Israel. This jealousy was so deep and bitter that it bred thoughts of murder in their
hearts. They determined to kill him and on many occasions tried to trap him. At last, by the
use of false witnesses, they condemned and crucified him.
</p><p>
It was the greatest tragedy of their lives.
</p><p>
Their God came among them, and they would not receive him. When he revealed his true
identity, they said he blasphemed. They preferred not to associate him with the scriptures
which so unerringly designated him as the Christ, and there were many such scriptures.
</p><p>
Let us briefly review some of the prophecies by which he could have been identified by any
open-minded person.
</p><p>
<b>Despite the Prophets</b>
</p><p>
Isaiah gave the first sign when he said: "Behold, a virgin shall conceive, and bear a son, and
shall call his name Immanuel" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/7/14#14">Isa. 7:14</a>).
</p><p>
And did it not come to pass just as the prophet said?
</p><p>
Was not this virgin birth heralded among the shepherds who watched their flocks that night
and by the angelic hosts who sang their hosannahs? Did not even the wise men, far away in
the East, recognize it? And was not Herod so frightened by it that he killed the little children
in an effort to destroy the newborn King?
</p><p>
The scripture was so detailed in describing the coming of the Lord that it predicted the flight
into Egypt to escape Herod's wrath (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/2/14-15#14">Matt. 2:14-15</a>),
as it also foretold the king's destruction of the little babies in Bethlehem
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/2/16-18#16">Matt. 2:16-18</a>).
</p><p>
It said that Jesus would be reared in the village of Nazareth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/2/23#23">Matt. 2:23</a>). It indicated that he would
perform many miracles (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/5#5">Mosiah 3:5</a>) and
that he would teach in parables (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/13-15#13">Matt. 13:13-15</a>).
It forecast his triumphal entry
into Jerusalem and said: "Thy King cometh unto thee, meek, and sitting upon an ass, the foal
of an ass" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/9/9#9">Zech. 9:9</a>).
</p><p>
It told of the disbelief with which most of the people would regard him and of their hatred
toward him, saying that he would be smitten, despised, and rejected, a man of sorrows and
acquainted with grief (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/53/3#3">Isa. 53:3</a>).
</p><p>
It predicted the betrayal of the Savior, actually mentioning the price to be paid: thirty pieces
of silver, and revealed that this money would be used to buy a potter's field
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/11/13#13">Zech. 11:13</a>).
</p><p>
The prophets also predicted that at his crucifixion the soldiers would divide his clothing
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/22/18#18">Ps. 22:18</a>)
among them and explained that his bones would not be broken
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/34/20#20">Ps. 34:20</a>),
but that his body would be pierced so that his blood would be shed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/12/10#10">Zech. 12:10</a>), as with a sacrificial lamb.
</p><p>
<b>Marks Identifying the Messiah</b>
</p><p>
All these marks of identification of the true Messiah were known in that day. For years they
had been familiar to those who read the scriptures.
</p><p>
But they were ignored.
</p><p>
The Savior was rejected, and the world went back into the oblivion of its traditions.
</p><p>
Great as was this tragedy for the people of that generation, we of today are in danger of
making a similar mistake. The Savior will come again in a glorious second advent, and
definite signs are given in Holy Writ to presage this event also.
</p><p>
These signs are shown as clearly in scripture as were those of his mortal ministry. They are
unmistakable. They are about us today and readily may be seen now.
</p><p>
<b>Will Our Generation Recognize them?</b>
</p><p>
Will our generation recognize them and wisely give heed to them? Or will these modern signs
be rejected with all that they imply as were those of nearly two thousand years ago when the
people of that generation failed to identify their Lord?
</p><p>
Let us review some of these modern signs, remembering that there are many more than the
often-mentioned wars and rumors of wars (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/6#6">Matt. 24:6</a>)
and seas heaving themselves beyond their bounds (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/90#90">D&amp;C 88:90</a>).
</p><p>
The gathering of the Jews to Palestine is one of the most outstanding and significant of all the
signs of the times. The Lord said through Jeremiah: ". . . I will cause them to return to the
land that I gave to their fathers, and they shall possess it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/30/3#3">Jer. 30:3</a>). Isaiah indicated that
Palestine, long languishing in the grip of the desert, was destined to be turned into a fruitful
field (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/17#17">Isa. 29:17</a>) in connection with the gathering of the Jews to their homeland.
</p><p>
Have these predictions been fulfilled?
</p><p>
Today the nation of Israel, with a population of two and a half million people, occupies the
land which the Lord gave to their fathers. It is a direct fulfillment of prophecy. It is a sign of
the near approach of the Lord.
</p><p>
With their return the land has been revitalized. Palestine today is a fruitful field
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/17#17">Isa. 29:17</a>). We who live
in England know how fruitful it is, for there we receive its oranges, its grapefruit, and other
produce, which are likewise shipped to many parts of the world.
</p><p>
On August 15 of this year, the London <i>Times</i> reported that the nation of Israel had awarded
contracts for the construction of thirty new cargo ships to be added to its already large and
prosperous merchant marine to handle the agricultural exports of this little nation. So
productive has Israel become.
</p><p>
The land has blossomed as the rose in fulfillment of prophecy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/1#1">Isa. 35:1</a>).
</p><p>
But there is another sign closely allied to it which Isaiah said would precede Palestine's
renewed fertility.
</p><p>
<b>The Prophets of Restoration</b>
</p><p>
A sacred book was to come forth before that time&mdash;one which was new to the world, one
that told of a fallen nation which was destroyed suddenly&mdash;a book to be offered in the latter
days to a learned man who would reject it, but to be given by divine means to an unlettered
man through whom it was to be given to the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/11-12#11">Isa. 29:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
Isaiah said that the book would be of such spiritual importance that it would cause many to
rejoice in the Holy One of Israel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/19#19">Isa. 29:19</a>).
"And in that day," he said, "shall the deaf hear the words of
the book, and the eyes of the blind shall see out of obscurity, and out of darkness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/18#18">Isa. 29:18</a>)
It shall cause the meek to "increase their joy in the Lord "
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/19#19">Isa. 29:19</a>).
</p><p>
Ezekiel spoke of the same book, explaining that it is the sacred record of the descendants of
Joseph who was sold into Egypt, and that it would stand side by side with the Bible as a new
volume of scripture (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/37/15-20#15">Ezek. 37:15-20</a>).
</p><p>
Where is that book? It is one of the signs of the times.
</p><p>
Not only did the prophets predict its appearance, but Isaiah set a limit on the time of its
publication. That time limit was related to the period when fertility would return to Palestine.
Isaiah said that the book would come forth first, and then added that in "a very little while . . .
Lebanon shall be turned into a fruitful field, and the fruitful field shall be esteemed as a
forest" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/17#17">Isa. 29:17</a>).
</p><p>
The time limit has expired. This new volume of scripture must have come forth before now
or Isaiah was not a true prophet, for Palestine is fruitful again.
</p><p>
Where is that book?
</p><p>
Let us consider still another sign: The Apostle Peter taught that before the second coming of
Christ there will be a restoration of all things religious, whatsoever ". . . God hath spoken by
the mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began" 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>).
A new revelation of
God was promised for the latter days&mdash;restoring the complete gospel to mankind.
</p><p>
The scripture teaches that this restoration would be accompanied by heavenly manifestations,
including the ministry of angels. The prophet said that one of these angels must fly from the
heavens in the latter days bringing back to earth the everlasting gospel to be preached anew to
every nation, tongue, and people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6-7#6">Rev. 14:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
His coming is related to the new book of scripture mentioned by both Isaiah and Ezekiel. Has
this angel come? Is the book available?
</p><p>
As part of this restoration the prophet also said that Elijah of old must come again to earth
shortly before the great and dreadful day of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5#5">Mal. 4:5</a>) in another modern revelation of
heavenly power. Has Elijah come in this modern assignment? What was the purpose of his coming?
</p><p>
Do we believe the prophets?
</p><p>
Is the Bible true?
</p><p>
If Elijah has come, to whom did he come, and where?
</p><p>
Who saw him?
</p><p>
Who talked with him, and when?
</p><p>
His modern appearance is given as one of the signs of the near approach of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/16#16">D&amp;C 110:16</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Daniel also knew of these events. He predicted that in the latter days God would
establish his kingdom once more upon the earth, this time never to be destroyed nor given to
another people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/44#44">Dan. 2:44</a>).
</p><p>
Has that prophecy been fulfilled?
</p><p>
Has there been a new and modern establishment of God's kingdom on earth?
</p><p>
If so, is it related to the restoration of all things formerly revealed through the ancient
prophets, as indicated by the Apostle Peter?
</p><p>
How could it be otherwise?
</p><p>
<b>Preparation for His Coming</b>
</p><p>
These inspired men spoke of the same thing: God's advance preparation for the second
coming of Christ.
</p><p>
Where is that divinely established kingdom of modern times?
</p><p>
Isaiah even tells us where to look for it. He said that in the latter days God would establish
his kingdom in the tops of the mountains, and that a temple would be built there in a high
place, exalted above the hills, and that people from all nations would flow to it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/2-3#2">Isa. 2:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
Where in a high mountain area has God thus erected his temple as he built his latter-day
kingdom?
</p><p>
Look for it. It is one of the signs of the times.
</p><p>
Will we who live today be willing to accept these signs as we see them, or will we reject
them in a spiritual and temporal tragedy like that of nearly two thousand years ago?
</p><p>
Will the marvels of our so-called enlightened age blind us to the events foretold in prophecy
or convince us that they are unreal or that they are but myths and superstitions as some
already say?
</p><p>
Will mankind once again deny their Lord?
</p><p>
<b>Latter-day Saints Testify</b>
</p><p>
We Latter-day Saints testify that these important signs, telling of the near approach of the
second coming of Christ, have taken place and may be examined by any interested person.
</p><p>
The physical restoration of Palestine is a fact that no one can deny. It is part of our current
history.
</p><p>
<b>The Book of Prophecy</b>
</p><p>
The book destined to precede renewed fertility in the Holy Land is also a reality. It is now in
publication. It is the Book of Mormon, the sacred scripture of ancient America. It has taken
its place by the side of the Bible as Ezekiel said it would. Let no one ridicule it nor ask if any
good can come out of Nazareth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/46#46">John 1:46</a>).
The book is true, and it is here for all to read.
</p><p>
Elijah has made his second appearance, and the results of his work may be seen and examined
on every hand. The scripture says that the purpose of his mission was to turn the hearts of the
present-day generation to their forefathers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/6#6">Mal. 4:6</a>).
This has been done through a worldwide interest in ancestry on a scale never before known.
</p><p>
Today there are many genealogical libraries and associations in different parts of the world,
and literally millions of people of various religious denominations are tracing their ancestry,
many of them not knowing why. Each one of them is direct evidence of the present-day
ministry of Elijah.
</p><p>
Daniel's prophecy also has been fulfilled.
</p><p>
The Lord's kingdom has been established in the midst of the greatest mountain chain on
earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/2-3#2">Isa. 2:2-3</a>),
with headquarters nearly a mile above sea level, here in Salt Lake City.
</p><p>
The temple foreseen in scripture has now been built and is in daily use.
</p><p>
The kingdom of God has been re-established on the earth.
</p><p>
As Peter predicted, the time of the restoration of all things revealed by ancient prophets has
now come.
</p><p>
<b>The Church Restored</b>
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ has been restored with its full organization, headed by prophets
and apostles who, as Paul explained, form the foundation of the Church, with Christ himself
as the chief cornerstone (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20#20">Eph. 2:20</a>).
</p><p>
Acceptance of these vivid signs of the times can lead mankind back to God in this day of
widespread unbelief. Ignoring them may bring a tragedy like that of two thousand years ago.
</p><p>
It is true that we are living in a marvelous age of intellectual and scientific development. But
this, too, is one of the signs of the times and supports, rather than obscures, the prophecies of
which we have spoken.
</p><p>
<b>The Age of Marvels</b>
</p><p>
Let us not misunderstand our situation. Let us not suppose that our own wisdom is so great
that we can ignore the handiwork of God.
</p><p>
As truly as that we are in a space age, as truly as that we can fire missiles into orbit, just that
truly will the events spoken of in the scriptures come to pass.
</p><p>
The greatest miracle of the present day is not that we can send a spaceship to photograph the
planet Mars.
</p><p>
The greatest miracle is that God has spoken in our time and has appeared in person to modern
man, to be seen, and heard, and understood. He has restored his gospel in its fullest detail.
This he has done in preparation for the glorious second coming of our Lord and Savior Jesus
Christ, in whose holy name we give this as our solemn testimony. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
