<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Lord's Way&mdash;The Best Way</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 86-88</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I bear testimony to you, my brothers and sisters, that I, like others who have talked in this
conference, know that this is the kingdom of God, that this is his Church. I
have confidence in this work and in the missionaries who are teaching the gospel, for they are
teaching the truth.
</p><p>
<b>A Living, Loving Father</b>
</p><p>
I know that God lives and that he is a Loving Father, and that Jesus Christ is his Son. I know
he has patience with me as with all because he is a Loving Father, that he has gone through
such experiences previously. Otherwise I would think prayers would be useless if he weren't a
Living, Loving Father who could answer them.
</p><p>
<b>His Son, Jesus Christ</b>
</p><p>
I know that Jesus Christ is his Son both in the spirit and on the earth, for Christ himself
testified that God was his Father. I know the two both appeared to Joseph Smith, two separate
Personages and the Father said to Joseph, "<i>This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>),
putting in their proper order of organization which has always been since the
time Adam was driven out of the Garden of Eden. Unto Adam was said as he left that he
should learn obedience by his own experience. By partaking of the fruit he was shut out of
the presence of the Father, but all that he should receive from then on should come through
his Son Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Instructions to Us</b>
</p><p>
And so we, as children of Adam, receive our instructions from our Father through his Son
Jesus Christ and are here to learn obedience by our own experience. The Lord gives us
opportunity here for trials through difficulties. Many of us think we have a most difficult row
to hoe; what comes to us seems to be the hardest; but it helps us because we need that
training probably. That's what it takes for us to attain perfection, for we must be able to go
through all the trials and difficulties in this life which are necessary to attain perfection.
</p><p>
So the Lord, as a Kind, Loving Father, gives us experiences, stumbling blocks to stumble on
by which we may be strengthened; problems to overcome by which we may be strengthened;
trials by which we may grow bigger, stronger; so we may attain the perfection he has planned
for us through this life in mortality.
</p><p>
<b>Guidance Through Prayer</b>
</p><p>
I would invite all those who are not members of the Church who have a desire to seek God,
to seek God through prayer because he will answer their prayers. He is a True and Living
God. He will answer their prayers. He may not answer them as you think he may, for our
Father has many languages, but he will choose the language which is best for you. It may
come to you through experiences. Some may be difficult, yet they will be a lesson to you
which will answer your prayers. He may answer your prayer in a way which will make you
stronger, help you to progress, and give you the burning in your heart that this is the gospel
of Jesus Christ restored in these the latter days.
</p><p>
<b>His Way Best</b>
</p><p>
I testify to you that this knowledge has come to me, not from just one little experience but
over a lifetime. I have often said to myself in my younger days, as trials and difficulties came
along, "The Lord's way is the best way." As long as conditions are beyond my control, then I
leave them up to the Lord. I worry only about those things that are in my control, and those
things I try to make better and ask the Lord to help me.
</p><p>
Through those experiences through life with that as my guide and wherein the Lord is my
guide, I have learned to know without a doubt that the Father and the Son did appear to
Joseph Smith; that these truths which have been referred to by others in this conference were
given to the Prophet Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery; that the kingdom of God is now
established upon the earth in this the last Dispensation of the Fullness of Times, in the
Saturday evening of time, never again to be taken from the earth; and that this is the time of
preparation for the ushering in of the millennium when Christ himself will come and reign on
the earth.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony that I know this to be true, I know this is the gospel of Jesus Christ,
and do so in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
