<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">When the Lord Commands, Do It</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 82-84</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
As we journey through life, requests may come to us from those who have been appointed to
positions of leadership and authority to perform some labor or to accept some responsibility.
We may not comprehend nor understand the reason at the time nor even later for such calls,
but, with confidence in those making the request, we respond without question.
</p><p>
<b>Prompt and willing obedience</b>
</p><p>
One of the beautiful incidents found in the scriptures relates to our first parents, Adam and
Eve. After being driven from the Garden of Eden they began to till the soil and to have
dominion over the beasts of the field and to eat their bread by the sweat of their faces. They
called upon the name of the Lord and heard his voice speaking to them from the way toward
the Garden of Eden, but they did not see him, as they were now shut out from his presence.
</p><p>
The Lord gave them commandments that they should worship him and should offer as a
sacrifice unto him the firstlings of their flocks. No explanation was given for making such
offerings, and I suppose they wondered as to the reasons, but without hesitation they were
obedient unto the directions of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/1-5#1">Moses 5:1-5</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Example: Adam</b>
</p><p>
After many days an angel appeared to Adam and inquired: "Why dost thou offer sacrifices
unto the Lord?" Then came Adam's sublime, beautiful, trusting response as he answered: "I
know not, save the Lord commanded me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/6#6">Moses 5:6</a>).
Thus this noble couple gave sufficient
reason for their obedience to the Lord's command. What a glorious example to us, their
posterity.
</p><p>
Compliance to counsel without knowledge of the reason therefore is often referred to as blind
obedience. But obedience is not blind when it is based on faith&mdash;implicit, trusting faith.
</p><p>
<b>Nephi</b>
</p><p>
Marvelous deeds can be accomplished through faith and obedience. While in the wilderness
the prophet Nephi was instructed by the Lord to construct a vessel in which to cross the
mighty waters. To his doubting brothers this appeared to be an impossible task. But Nephi
knew that it could be done and began fashioning tools and accumulating materials for his
important assignment. When he advised his brothers of his purpose, they murmured and
scoffed, saying: "Our brother is a fool, for he thinketh that he can build a ship; yea, and he
also thinketh that he can cross these great waters" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/17#17">1 Ne. 17:17</a>).
</p><p>
In spite of their skepticism and ridicule, Nephi was moved by the spirit of obedience and had
faith and confidence that the Lord would open the way for him to carry out the
commandment he had received. Humbly, yet majestic in his trust, he proclaimed to his
brothers: "If God had commanded me to do all things I could do them. If he should command
me that I should say unto this water, be thou earth, it should be earth; and if I should say it, it
would be done" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/50#50">1 Ne. 17:50</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Abraham</b>
</p><p>
Another soul-stirring incident that is recorded in holy writ teaches a forceful lesson from
which we may profit. As a devoted and loving father, Abraham's heart must have been heavy
when he was commanded to take his beloved son, Isaac, upon a mountain and offer him as a
sacrifice. Yet with unwavering faith and implicit trust in the Lord, he responded to the charge.
He was dutifully obedient. Mercifully, however, he was relieved of the severe challenge the
Lord had imposed upon him. But he had been tested and tried. For his faithfulness and
obedience, the Lord gave Abraham this wonderful promise: ". . . in thy seed shall all the
nations of the earth be blessed, because thou hast obeyed my voice"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/22/18#18">Gen. 22:18</a>).
</p><p>
In those ancient days the offering of burnt sacrifices was a subject that was repeatedly taught
and stressed. Evidently there were many discussions as to which was the more important
practice, sacrifice or obedience. Samuel, the prophet, asked Saul, whom he was teaching, the
question: "Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the
voice of the Lord?" Then without waiting for a reply, he gave this inspired answer: "Behold,
to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/22#22">1 Sam. 15:22</a>). How
powerful to Adam, Abraham, Saul, and to us, also, is this lesson concerning the importance of
obedience.
</p><p>
Now what of our own day? As we read the daily newspapers, view television, and listen to
the radio, we are acutely aware of the unrest that exists in the world today. Wars, bloodshed,
riots, and acts of lawlessness are characteristic of the times. They are evidence of some men's
desires for unrighteous power, a lack of consideration for the rights of others, a disregard for
established laws, and a tendency to be nonconformists. The jails today are crowded with such
individuals. It is necessary, as we all know, for law-making bodies to enact legislation that
will protect the rights of the law-abiding majority against the rebellious minority.
</p><p>
But these selfish, self-appointed nonconformists, whose inspiration is derived from an evil
source rather than a source divine, have not learned to appreciate the peace and joy that come
into the soul through obeying the laws of the land and observing the commandments of the
Lord.
</p><p>
<b>"He learned obedience"</b>
</p><p>
The Savior, on the other hand, subscribed to the principle of obedience to divine law. In
referring to him the Apostle Paul observed: "Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience
by the things which he suffered; 
</p><p>
"And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation unto all them that obey
him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/8-9#8">Heb. 5:8-9</a>).
Should we not follow the Lord's example?
</p><p>
<b>Programs of the Church</b>
</p><p>
At the present time, through inspiration from the Lord, many worthwhile programs are being
given to the Church. These programs have the endorsement, approval, and blessing of the
General Authorities. Do we hearken unto the chosen servants of the Lord, who prepare these
valuable aids for us? Do we render obedience to the counsel that comes to them through
inspiration and revelation from our Father in heaven?
</p><p>
Well might we as individuals and as parents ask ourselves these questions: 
</p><p>
"In these good and prosperous times, have I accumulated an adequate reserve of food,
clothing, and savings to provide for me and my family in the event of illness, emergency, or
unemployment?"
</p><p>
"Am I living in such a way that my life will be an inspiration and an example to others? and
am I following the counsel of the prophet when he declares that every member should be a
missionary?"
</p><p>
"Am I gathering my family around me each week in a home evening and studying the
gospel?"
</p><p>
"Have I carefully analyzed my family records and engaged in prayerful research in order to
complete the history of my progenitors?"
</p><p>
Over the centuries the Lord has given many assurances of his desire to pour out blessings
upon the people, but he has made it equally clear that blessings are predicated upon obedience
and a willingness to obey his commandments. Moses in his day promised the children of
Israel: 
</p><p>
"And it shall come to pass, if thou shalt hearken diligently unto the voice of the Lord thy
God, to observe and to do all his commandments which I command thee this day, that the
Lord thy God will set thee on high above all nations of the earth: 
</p><p>
"And all these blessings shall come on thee, and overtake thee, if thou shalt hearken unto the
voice of the Lord thy God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/28/1-2#1">Deut. 28:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Blessings for the faithful</b>
</p><p>
And now in the latter days the Lord has again made it crystal clear that he is willing to bless
the faithful. That is strongly evident in this assurance: "I, the Lord, am bound when ye do
what I say; but when ye do not what I say, ye have no promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
This harmonizes with the statement that the Prophet Joseph declared he had made a rule in his
life and followed each day. It was simply this: "When the Lord commands, do it!"
(<i>Documentary History of the Church</i>, Vol. 2, p. 170.)
</p><p>
Now, may I emphasize one more thought? In this year of 1966 renewed emphasis is placed on
the importance of the home and the cultivating of the spirit of love therein. With listening
ears and responsive hearts, we should hearken to the words of our beloved prophet, President
McKay who has counseled: ". . . let us never lose sight of the principle of <i>obedience</i>.
</p><p>
Obedience is heaven's first law, and it is the law of home. There can be no true happiness in
the home without obedience&mdash;obedience obtained, not through physical force, but through the
divine element of love." (<i>Treasures of Life</i>, p. 329.)
</p><p>
That we may be blessed with the rich rewards that come to the faithful through observing the
beautiful principle of obedience to all that the Lord commands us is my humble prayer, in the
name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
