<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Not as the World Giveth"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Robert L. Simpson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Robert L. Simpson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1965, pp. 132-134</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, may I first of all share a great experience
that I had at the age of eight years. This
was a great experience of learning and taught me a lesson that I shall never forget.
</p><p>
<b>Learning Can Be Zestful</b>
</p><p>
I remember the thrill of being taught simple division. Three goes into fifteen five times. It
seemed almost like a miracle as the teacher further taught us that all we had to do was
multiply the answer by the divisor, and we would have the number that we started with. She
said that by following this simple plan and procedure we could check any division problem
and make certain that the answer was right.
</p><p>
A few days later we had our first test in simple division. I shall never forget turning to my
school chum and announcing, "I got an 'A.'" He said, "How do you know? We haven't even
graded the papers."
</p><p>
"I know I have an 'A' because I checked every answer. I multiplied the answer by the
divisor, and I was certain that it was exactly the same number we started with. I know I got
an 'A.'"
</p><p>
And sure enough it was an "A" because I was standing on solid rock. There was no doubt in
my mind. I was dealing with an exact science, and for the first time in my life I felt really
secure in something that I had been taught in school. This was an exact science, and I was
able to prove my answer beyond question.
</p><p>
Now in the world today, I think if there were one common wish among all mankind, that
wish would be for peace&mdash;peace in the world, peace in each nation; peace in the community;
even a feeling of peace in each home; and perhaps most important of all, peace of mind.
</p><p>
Our day will probably go down in history as the day of psychiatry, psychology, and
tranquilizers. Now, I don't mean to suggest that there is no place for the professionally trained
to treat the mentally disturbed or for the prescribing of proper medicine for the overwrought,
but I do believe with all my heart and soul that most of these anxieties found in the hearts
and minds of men today can be eliminated by a return to faith in God and the resultant desire
to obey his commandments.
</p><p>
<b>God's Plan Is a Super Highway</b>
</p><p>
To me, and I am sure to you, God's plan is like a superhighway. This superhighway is built
on solid rock; it is built well above the fog-shrouded valleys; and it is built well above the
swamps of infidelity, selfishness, and immorality. The Lord himself has said, "I am the light
of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the light of life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>).
</p><p>
Heavenly Father has also said that there are laws irrevocably decreed in the heavens upon
which all blessings are predicated (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/20-21#20">D&amp;C 130:20-21</a>).
If we keep the law, we reap
happiness. If we violate the law or ignore the law, we have problems, and we have
unhappiness. It is just as simple as that.
</p><p>
<b>His Laws Are Sure</b>
</p><p>
And so, as we think back to my third grade experience, how much the same are God's laws.
His laws are also undeviating, certain, proven, and all we need do is keep his laws, and we
will be happy, we will be successful, and we will regain his presence.
</p><p>
With you, I invite all men, all women, all children, all people everywhere to join in God's
plan. Let's consider his law of health, for example. Why have all the upset that we have in
the world through lack of health, when all we need do is follow God's plan as revealed in this
day, and then we will most likely have the peace of mind of a strong, healthy body.
</p><p>
With you, I would share with the world the great truth that all we have to do is give back to
Heavenly Father one-tenth of our increase, and again we have peace of mind, as we help to
build his kingdom unselfishly.
</p><p>
With you, I would give to the world the great truth that we must have love and unity in our
homes, and here again we can achieve a peace of mind unattainable in any other way.
</p><p>
The same thing can be said of the Sabbath day, of keeping it holy, and of the peace that
comes to all who keep that great commandment.
</p><p>
The same thing can be said about the principle of prayer. As we communicate with our
Heavenly Father, let him know that we love him and that we intend to keep his
commandments to the very best of our ability.
</p><p>
<b>Eternal Truths</b>
</p><p>
Yes, brothers and sisters, there are eternal truths. Two parts hydrogen and one part oxygen is
water. It was so when Heavenly Father was creating the earth. It is so today, and it will be so
forever. This is an eternal truth of chemistry. Pi(r-squared) has always been and always will be the
formula to find the area of a circle. One hundred and eighty-six thousand miles per second
has been and always will be the speed of light. Einstein has given us in our day that E is
equal to M(C-squared), the theory of relativity.
</p><p>
As we quote these basic truths, they are simple. They are not complicated. All basic truth
seems to be simple. It is only when we go beyond the realm of truth that we become
complicated, that we become mixed up in our minds and our emotions.
</p><p>
<b>Intelligence for Family Home Evenings</b>
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, can we simplify our lives, simplify our living, take time to do the things
that need to be done? If there is not time in our lives for the Family Home Evening, there is
something wrong, and we are getting away from the way Heavenly Father would have us live.
If there is not time in our lives for personal prayer, then we must take stock of ourselves. If
there is not enough faith or money to give back to Heavenly Father his one-tenth, then we are
mismanaging our affairs, and we are getting away from those things that would bring us pure
and simple happiness.
</p><p>
<b>The Gospel Is the Way to Peace</b>
</p><p>
So the gospel, brothers and sisters, is peace of mind, and only as rapidly as we get back to
the standard works and give heed to his basic principles will we have the peace of mind that
Christ himself spoke of when he proclaimed to the world: "Peace I leave with you, my peace
I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you. Let not your heart be troubled,
neither let it be afraid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, the world giveth differently from the way Christ giveth, and when we
partake of the world as the world giveth, we start reaching for our tranquilizers. But as we
reach for the gospel of Jesus Christ, and as we reach for the standard works of the Church
and the truths revealed therein, then I say we are going to have joy in our lives, and we can
promise to all men there will be happiness in their lives. We can further say that theirs will be
a peace of mind that will bring a surety to their souls and give them the happiness to which
all Heavenly Father's children are entitled.
</p><p>
I so testify and pray that we might so live in the name of his Son Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
