<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Seek Ye the Lord</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1950, pp. 55-58</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have paid particular attention in this conference to the prayers that have been offered. They
have been indeed a good example for all of us to follow. I hope that I will receive in turn my
full share of prayers asked in behalf of those who take part here in this conference as I am
sure those who have preceded me have received.
</p><p>
In the beginning, as Adam and Eve were driven out of the Garden of Eden, they were shut
out from the presence of the Lord, but the Lord did not expect them to be without some
contact with him. That one avenue he left open for man to reach God while in this life of
mortality was prayer; so Adam called upon God, and he received guidance in all things.
Neither does God expect us to get along without his help. Throughout the Old and New
Testaments and the Book of Mormon the Lord gave instructions to pray constantly. The
Doctrine and Covenants is filled with like exhortations. The disciples asked the Savior on one
occasion. "Lord, teach us to pray."
</p><p>
PRAY TO FATHER
</p><p>
Among other things the Lord said, "Pray to our Father in heaven." And herein, I think that we
need to be careful, because very often we open our prayer with the expression of praying to
our Father in heaven, then during the prayer we use the term "Lord," and before we are
through it is hard to tell whether we are addressing the Father or his Son, Jesus Christ. We
should pray to our Father in heaven, for he is indeed the Father of all mankind on the earth,
and because he is our Father, he wants us to come to him often with our joys and our sorrows
and thank him for all that he has given us. Then the Savior gave us a good suggestive sample
of the things to pray for and how to pray (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/11/1-2#1">Luke 11:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
As Jesus told his Disciples, our Father in heaven knows what we are in need of before we
start; yet he has commanded us to pray. He wants us to be thoughtful of others as we are of
ourselves. "Forgive us as we forgive our debtors"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/11/4#4">Luke 11:4</a>). He did not intend that we should always
use the exact words that he gave in the sample or to use pre-written prayers. In so doing we
would become as those Christ referred to when he said, "They draw near to me with their
lips, but their hearts are far from me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/19#19">JS&mdash;H 1:19</a>).
Do you think Joseph Smith would have received that
wonderful manifestation if he had simply read a prayer? How much of our heart goes into a
prayer of that nature? How much faith can we exercise with words and thoughts that are not
our own? Prayer without faith is dead, and if we add to the faith which President Ivins has
just spoken to us about, that prayer, I'm sure will have results, and we'll have an increase of
the statistics President Ivins has referred to in actual fact and continue as such.
</p><p>
BE IN TUNE
</p><p>
We do not read our prayers in this Church, but some of us get in almost as bad a rut. We are
so bound by set words and phrases at times that we hardly remember what we are saying. We
must have a spirit of deep humility, of repentance, an open mind, to receive
the will of God. We must not be hampered by any anger or meanness or hardness of heart, or
any selfish desires. We must tune our minds and our hearts to the Spirit of God just as we
tune our radio to receive the program from the broadcasting station. We want no interfering
static from outside influences. In the attitude of true repentance we should seek forgiveness of
our past mistakes and guidance for improvement. I like the little poem used so much in our
home: 
</p><p>
To say my prayer is not to pray,<br />
       Unless I mean the words I say,<br />
       Unless I think to whom I speak,<br />
       And with my heart his favor seek.
</p><p>
       Then let me, when I come to pray,<br />
       Not only mean the words I say,<br />
       But let me strive with earnest care,<br />
       To have my heart go with my prayer.
</p><p>
SINCERITY OF CHILDREN
</p><p>
Unless our whole heart is in what we are doing, we are not really praying. A child is
naturally sincere and can be taught to pray almost with its first words. His own private prayer
should become a habit never to be broken. If he greets the day with a prayer for guidance and
help, if he goes to sleep with a prayer of thanksgiving, more than half the battle is won in
trying to do right. The Lord tells us in the Doctrine and Covenants, sixty-eighth section,
twenty-eighth verse: 
</p><p>
And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
</p><p>
Children will learn more from observation than they ever will from just being told. If parents
have a prayerful attitude, the children are more than likely to have the same. Family prayer
cannot be too highly praised. In no other way can we obtain such a spirit of unity, nor is
there any better place for the child to learn to pray in public. The Lord also tells us in the
Doctrine and Covenants, nineteenth section and twenty-eighth verse: 
</p><p>
And again, I command thee that thou shalt pray vocally as well as in thy heart; yea,
before the world as well as in secret, in public as well as in private
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/28#28">D&amp;C 19:28</a>).
</p><p>
FAMILY PRAYER
</p><p>
It is surprising how soon a child can take his turn in family prayer, and just think of the good
that comes to the family. If we kneel down together and unitedly thank God for his many
blessings; pray for guidance, for peace and love in our hearts; if we pray for others who are
in need; for the advancement of God's work here; can it help but make our home a better
place? Can we help but be more thoughtful of others, more kind and loving?
A man and wife who will pray together and pray vocally will have more love and
contentment in their home. If we would learn to call upon God more often, we should not
have to call upon the divorce courts so much. Teach your children the one source of strength
that will never fail them. Help them to realize that they have an everlasting friend, one that
they can call upon when their hearts are filled with joy as well as when they are filled with
doubt or sadness or despair. Then when they have grown up and are on their own, living at
home, away at school, or in the far-flung battlefields of war, they have God as their partner;
they are not afraid. This would bring peace, happiness, and joy. A sin-sick world could be
lifted from its depths if we could only turn to the Lord in prayer. What more could we do for
our children? I pronounce the blessings of God upon all who humbly seek him in prayer, in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
