<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Zion Must Arise</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 116-120</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I rejoice in being with you in this conference today. I feel very weak
and humble in this position, and I do earnestly pray for an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
I wish to extend my appreciation and gratitude to the great number of you who received me
so kindly in this appointment.  I appreciate the many prayers that have gone up in my behalf.
With you, I feel a keen loss in our beloved President George Albert Smith.  Coming from an
outside stake, I feel in a measure that I represent the good people who live on the fringe of
the Church, who do not always have opportunity to express the love that is in their hearts for
these great leaders who depart from among us.
</p><p>
LOVED BY ALL
</p><p>
President George Albert Smith was close to me, he always seemed to be around for some of
the important events of my life. I appreciated sincerely his confidence and love, and I rejoice
that it was he who called me to this present assignment. As a boy, I remember his coming
into my father's and mother's home to attend quarterly conferences representing the General
Authorities of the Church. And as I relive those occasions, I rejoice in the goodly effect that
he had upon my life. He was loved by all good members of the Church everywhere. He
radiated a kindly and lovable spirit wherever he went, he brought good will to the Church and
its people. As has been said, he was a man without guile
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/47#47">John 1:47</a>). I think he has left with us a gem of
counsel as so many times in his talks he has advised us to stay on the Lord's side of the line.
That counsel will live throughout eternity in our hearts. A very simple statement, yet one that
will produce great good in the lives of individuals if they will but follow it.
</p><p>
The eighth chapter in the leadership of this Church has been closed in the departing of this
good man. As I reflect back over the eight spiritual leaders of this people, in my heart I feel
that God wanted each of them to lead his people, and that each was specially fitted and
endowed for the work of his time and generation. The chapter now closed in the book of the
life and activities of President George Albert Smith is a glorious one of great attainment on
the part of the Church. He built ably upon the foundation laid, so now this people can
continue to go ahead in the accomplishment of the great purposes that God has for his people
to accomplish.
</p><p>
GOD AT THE HELM
</p><p>
As I have thought about the past three days and all that has taken place, my testimony has
increased in relation to the work we are engaged in. All plans have gone forward for this
great general conference of the Church. And almost on the eve of the conference meetings,
the Lord took from us our beloved President. At first there was a great feeling of loss, but I
don't think ever a feeling of frustration, for the Quorum of the Twelve realized that vested
within them were all the powers, authorities, and keys necessary to carry forward the
important work of this great Church. Committees were appointed to plan the services that
would honor and recognize our beloved prophet-leader. Everything seemed to fit into a proper
pattern, the services were held, and our hearts were touched by the beautiful thoughts
expressed, the consolation given to members of the family and to all of us who mourn the
passing of our President.
</p><p>
Yet the 121st annual conference went on as scheduled and there was a feeling that God was at
the helm; that the affairs of his Church, even at such a critical time, were being properly
handled. And so we come here today, not disturbed in our faith, not disturbed in the
leadership now handling the affairs of the Church. Everything has fit into a pattern, for God
established the pattern, and the people know where the authority of leadership is vested when
the President prophet-leader is taken. There has hardly been a ripple in the scene of our work
or activities, and yet we have paused properly to honor and recognize our great spiritual
leader.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, this is to me a testimony of the strength and divinity of this work. In my
heart, I feel that God is with us and directing his work, that as we go from this conference to
our homes, we will not be confused, nor will we feel in our hearts that this work will stop.
there will be unity in our faith, we will go away in confidence, knowing that the work of the
Lord will continue to go forward and fulfil its destiny in the earth. And as I reflect upon these
things, I remember what the Lord said to the Prophet Joseph Smith before the Prophet had
been endowed with the priesthood and before the Church itself had been organized. He said
that "a great and a marvelous work is about to come forth unto the children of men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/1#1">D&amp;C 6:1</a>); and
surely this is a great and marvelous work which we represent. Very shortly after the
organization of the Church, less than a year and a half, the Lord speaking to the elders of the
Church said: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, be not weary in well-doing, for ye are laying the foundation of a great
work. And out of small things proceedeth that which is great
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/33#33">D&amp;C 64:33</a>).
</p><p>
According to the law that God had revealed, and in keeping with the law of the land, this
Church was established with only six members. Yet the early rise of the Church from that
humble beginning was great and marvelous, the Lord was pleased, and the brethren engaged
in the work of the ministry had been very diligent and devoted. The Lord didn't want them to
be weary in well-doing because they were laying the foundations of a great work. In the
preface to the book of Doctrine and Covenants, the Lord said: 
</p><p>
. . . those to whom these commandments were given, might have power to lay the
foundation of this church, and to bring it forth out of obscurity and out of darkness,
the only true and living church upon the face of the whole earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30#30">D&amp;C 1:30</a>).
</p><p>
And then again, a little later the Lord said: 
</p><p>
For Zion must increase in beauty, and in holiness; her borders must be enlarged; her
stakes must be strengthened; yea, verily I say unto you, Zion must arise and put on her
beautiful garments (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/14#14">D&amp;C 82:14</a>).
</p><p>
MEN OF STRENGTH
</p><p>
We know the Church passed through many trials and many tribulations, that brethren along
the way deserted the Prophet, and the Saints suffered mobbings and all types of hardships and
privations, but there were in the Church men of strength and character men who believed in
this great latter-day work; and the power of the Lord rested with them. They were undaunted
in the face of these difficulties. But the work of the Lord went on, and our people were led
here to the valleys of the mountains by President Brigham Young. He had the vision of
enlarging the borders of Zion and sent out groups to colonize and settle the fertile valleys of
these mountains, both north and south and east and west. Thus the great work of the Church
has continued to grow, even until the present time, and each of our prophet leaders took his
place, gave of himself and of the talents that God had blessed him with to establish firmly the
foundations of this work. And as surely as we are here today, it has been brought forth out of
obscurity and out of darkness, and stands as a beacon of light upon the hill to all peoples and
nations of the earth. We have witnessed in the progress of the Church, a great enlarged
program to take care of our people. This program encircles the entire life of the Church
membership and gives them every opportunity for growth, for development, and for training.
Surely in this work, the Lord has been with his people; so today with pride in our progress
we claim almost sixteen hundred wards and branches of the Church, 184 stakes, scattered up
and down this western area with some to the east of us. We also have many missions
established throughout the world, and with all our program and activity, the Church itself is
known far and wide and assuming its place of leadership and of power in shaping the lives of
men and of nations.
</p><p>
PROSELYTING IN STAKES
</p><p>
And it seems to me, my brothers and sisters, that the Lord in this enlargement of our borders
has been with this people, and has so arranged it that we are now established in the
population centers of this western area. We have built our places of worship, our places of
recreation, and in all this building, and in all this planning, and in all this preparation, the
leadership of the Church under the inspiration of God have not had in mind only that we
should take care of our own, but that the facilities we have provided should be made available
to our friends. We have been counseled to warn our neighbors, not to hide our light under a
bushel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/15-16#15">Matt. 5:15-16</a>),
but to place it where it can be seen of men, that they may have the opportunities and
the blessings this Church affords and that you and I enjoy.
</p><p>
And it does seem to me, brothers and sisters, in this present critical situation where it is
impossible to send all the missionaries into foreign fields we need to send, that we must take
advantage of the proselyting opportunity that is ours in the branches, wards, and stakes of the
Church; and through our stake missionary program make available to those who are
investigating, the facilities of our Church, that the children of our friends and investigators
can come to Primary, to Sunday School, the young men and women to Mutual, the mothers to
Relief Society, and all to our sacrament meetings. If we as God's people would warn our
neighbors (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/81#81">D&amp;C 88:81</a>),
and if we would be friends with our neighbors, we will invite them to come with
us and investigate this thing we know to be true and of God.
</p><p>
INVITATION TO COME AND SEE
</p><p>
I think it was only a year ago that President George Albert Smith from this pulpit said that
we should invite our friends and our associates to come and see. There is much in the Church
for people to come and see, and if we who are members of the Church would live as we
should live, we would never be ashamed of that which our friends and our associates do see.
Not so long ago in attending a conference, I heard a young lady missionary in making her
report say that in her missionary experience she felt the Spirit of the Lord working with her.
And I thought what a grand thing it would be if all people of the Church felt that in their
callings and appointments the Spirit of the Lord was working with them. I am just as
confident as I can be that regardless of our calling and appointments or holding the
priesthood, we who are the men of the Church, that unless we have the Holy Spirit of the
Lord abiding with us in our work and ministry, we will never accomplish the purposes of
God. We need the Holy Spirit, we need its power and its gifts and its influences with us in
our callings and offices if we carry out successfully the responsibility associated with those
callings and appointments.
</p><p>
I have a testimony of this work, I know it is true. I hope and pray, brothers and sisters, that
we will devote ourselves to its high responsibilities. It is the most important thing we have at
hand to do. May we be appreciative of the Church, of its leadership, of its doctrines, and all
the blessings we enjoy, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
