<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Every Good Tree</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 54-57</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Isn't it thrilling, brothers and sisters, to hear these young people sing praises to God and express
their trust in him?  It gives you a wonderful feeling of confidence, doesn't it, to know that the
rising generation is made up of such marvelous young people.
</p><p>
Two weeks ago my wife and I had the opportunity of attending a meeting of some hundreds
of M Men and Gleaner Girls, and there again we were impressed with the fact that our young
people are great.  Those hundreds of young people stood up in that meeting and gave the
MIA theme for this year.  I wish you could have heard them because they spoke with such
clarity.  They were in almost perfect unison, and as they said these words, it gave me a great
thrill: 
</p><p>
Seek not for riches but for wisdom, and behold, the mysteries of God shall be
unfolded unto you, and then shall you be made rich.  Behold, he that hath eternal life
is rich (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>).
</p><p>
As I say, hearing those voices in unison say those inspired words, moved me deeply inside.  I
was so thrilled that young people could stand and say and believe that "he that hath eternal
life is rich."
</p><p>
When my wife and I were in South America recently, we had the same kind of thrill because
there we saw your sons and daughters, sometimes under difficult and even adverse
circumstances standing in the glory of their young manhood and womanhood, in the glory of their
membership in this Church,  in the glory of being missionaries for the Son of God, speak in
languages previously unknown to them, bearing testimony of the restoration of the gospel of
Christ.  Oh, how happy we were! How humble we felt in their presence, and again came to us
this great conviction that the youth of Zion are a great people.
</p><p>
As I reflect upon the youth of Zion, I reflect also upon the homes from which they come.  I
know that great homes produce great people.  Those homes need not be rich in this world's
goods, but if they are rich in the wisdom of God, they are rich indeed, and young people who
grow up in homes such as those are great young people.
</p><p>
You recall that the Savior at one time said: ". . . every good tree bringeth forth good fruit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/17#17">Matt. 7:17</a>).
I know that even from a good tree occasionally a piece of fruit may fall, and as
the prodigal go the way of all the earth, but that does not change the great underlying fact
that "every good tree bringeth forth good fruit."
</p><p>
As I have studied your young people and mine, I have come to the conclusion that they are
great because by and large they come from great homes.  It has been my observation that
where young people are active in the Church, as a general rule they come from homes where
parents also are active in the Church.
</p><p>
Now, there are some exceptions, I know, but I say as a general rule great homes produce
great young people. Parents who are active in the Church usually produce children who are
active in the Church, again proving the truth of the Savior's words that "every good tree
bringeth forth good fruit."
</p><p>
But I would like to read to you the rest of the Savior's words in that quotation.  He said:
"Every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/17#17">Matt. 7:17</a>).
</p><p>
Now what about the meaning of those words?  Do homes which are not classed as good
homes produce evil young people?  And if they do, who must bear the blame?
</p><p>
There have been many public opinion polls taken in the United States, as you know, and I
suppose they have touched almost every subject under the sun.  There is not very much left
uncovered by the time they get through.
</p><p>
I have been shocked and astonished at one of these public opinion polls which indicates that
there is a higher percentage of drinkers of alcoholic beverages in the age group of fifteen to
thirty years than in any other age group. This particular poll indicated that sixty-seven percent
of American young people from fifteen to thirty years of age use alcoholic beverages
occasionally or more or less regularly.
</p><p>
Now these studies, and others, tell us where these young people learn to drink.  Again I was
astonished to learn that the majority of the American young people who drink liquor learn to
drink from their own parents.
</p><p>
A number of studies, as I say, have been made on this subject, some of them among college
students, some among high school students, and even some elementary students have been
brought into the study.  One of the studies having to do with college students indicated that
eighty-five percent of the drinking students have drinking parents.  This same study, which
included information on students who abstain from the use of liquor, said that seventy-seven
percent of the students who abstain from the use of liquor have both parents who abstain from
the use of liquor.  Isn't that a great lesson?  The majority of the drinking students drink
because their parents drink.  The majority of the abstaining students have parents who abstain.
</p><p>
One of these studies was conducted in the state of Idaho by the department of social studies
of the University of Idaho, and the figures sustain the general results as obtained in other
studies in eastern United States.  They found that the drinking habits of students follow
almost exactly the drinking habits of parents.  I quote just one line from their report: 
</p><p>
"The proportions of students who drank are approximately equal to the proportions of parents
who drank with the knowledge of the students."
</p><p>
In eastern United States a study was made along the same lines.  After the completion of the
survey those who conducted it reported: "It certainly is not surprising to find a tendency for
students to follow the example of their parents in deciding whether or not to drink."
</p><p>
Dr. Andrew C. Ivy, head of the department of clinical science at the University of Illinois,
recently wrote an article in the magazine, <i>Life and Health</i>, entitled, "Why I Don't Drink." He
commented on the fact that there are over sixty million drinkers in the United States, and after
discussing that horrible fact, asked this question: "Who can save future citizens from drink?"
He answered, "The fathers and mothers of today's children."
</p><p>
And then he said this: "Children, teenagers, and college students drink and do other things
that harm their bodies, characters, and lives largely because their parents do.  If we are going
to reverse the trend to moral decline and degeneration in our country, mothers as well as
fathers are going to have to correct their own irresponsible behavior."
</p><p>
He goes on to say, "The question for parents to answer is: 'Has drinking alcoholic beverages
contributed so much to my happiness that I want my child and all children to take the one in
twenty chance of becoming an alcoholic?'"
</p><p>
Then he said, "Seventy percent of the chronic alcoholics in the United States started drinking
as teenagers."
</p><p>
In studies that have been made with regard to smoking habits, the same type of thing has been
developed.  It is discovered that by and large smoking parents have smoking children, and
abstaining parents, by and large, have abstaining children.  The same thing is true with
Church activity, as I have already indicated.  If parents reject religious activity, their children
generally reject religious activity. If, on the other hand, as we have points out, parents are
active and enthusiastic and faithful about their Church responsibilities, as a rule the children
likewise are active.
</p><p>
And so we may reach some definite conclusions and say that where parents smoke they can
expect their children to smoke.  Where parents drink, they may expect their children to drink.
Where parents deny religious activity and interest, they can expect their children to deny
religious interest.
</p><p>
Now these same studies have gone into the questions: Why do people drink?  Why do people
smoke?  I do not know anybody, with his eyes open, who would suppose that drinking would
do him any good, or that smoking would do him any good.  Even the merchants of these
commodities are now changing the claims in some advertising that they are good for a person.
I remember there was a time when they used to advertise that smoking was good for
digestion, but they do not any more since the doctors have discovered that tobacco is one of
the very worst things for your stomach, and that whether you smoke or chew the tobacco, you
can get stomach ulcers from it, and you can develop cancer of the stomach from the ulcers. 
So tobacco companies have stopped advertising about how good for your digestion it is if you
smoke cigarettes.
</p><p>
Why do people smoke, and why do they drink?  According to these surveys, it is because
they think it is smart. They think it is popular.  They think it is the thing to do because the
Joneses and others they happen to know and regard as smart also smoke or drink. For that
reason they think they should take up the habit, and because parents who are blinded by this
false notion of popularity lead their children, who are blinded by the bad example of their
parents, they both fall into the ditch.
</p><p>
So we can begin to see the truth in the Savior's words, can't we, that a corrupt tree will bring
forth evil fruit.  I ask you parents if you have the right to gamble with the future lives and
happiness of your children.  If we set our children an example which is almost sure to lead to
failure, what is our responsibility? If we should lead our own children into disaster, would we
ever forgive ourselves?
</p><p>
Two weeks ago Brother [Delbert L.] Stapley and I happened to have the privilege of being in
the same conference together. Brother Stapley there delivered one of his wonderful talks, and
in his discussion gave me a new point of view on an old subject, and with his permission I
would like to mention it here.
</p><p>
Brother Stapley was talking about the fact that children cannot be tempted by the devil before
they are eight years of age because the Lord has not given Satan that right
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/47#47">D&amp;C 29:47</a>). Just suppose that
there was a basketball game, and for eight minutes one of the teams was ruled off the floor
while the remaining team stayed in there and pitched as many baskets as it could for eight
minutes, and every basket would count.  Just think about that.
</p><p>
And suppose there was a football game in which one of the teams was ruled off the field
while the other made touchdowns for eight minutes, and every touchdown would count, and it
could make these touchdowns without any opposition from the other team.  Just think what
kind of score it could develop!
</p><p>
You do not get that in athletics, but you do get it in the rearing of your children because
during the first eight years of their lives, Satan has no right and no power to tempt those
children. If they are tempted, if they sin, you have to blame somebody else besides Satan. 
During those first eight years you are left in the field without the opposition of Satan in the
training of your children.  For eight years you can train them, mold their characters, develop
their faith, and teach them to pray, and to love God, and to keep his commandments, without
any interference or any opposition from Satan.
</p><p>
Have you ever thought of it that way?  I hadn't until Brother Stapley mentioned it, but I was
glad he did because, as I say, it gave me a new point of view. The first eight years of a
child's life in a Latter-day Saint home form the golden age for parents in the rearing of their
children&mdash;a golden age when Mother and Father may set them the proper example, and play
with them, and pray with them, and enjoy them, and develop Christlike traits of character in
their children without the opposition of Satan.
</p><p>
Have you that kind of home?  In your home are you setting up the circumstances and the
surroundings whereby those children can get the most out of this golden age?  Are you doing
all you can while you do not have the interference of Satan to train those children?  Or, on
the other hand, are you careless enough so that you tempt your own children, so that you will
lead them into paths of sin, so that you teach them by your own bad example how to do things  of the
world?
</p><p>
Well, I come back again to the Savior's words: ". . . every good tree bringeth forth good
fruit; but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/17#17">Matt. 7:17</a>).
</p><p>
May our homes be good homes, from which we may send good young people, trained and
reared in the gospel of Christ, is my humble prayer, in his holy name.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
