<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">God's Gifts to Polynesia's People</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas S. Monson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas S. Monson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 8-11</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, I know that I speak the innermost thoughts of all assembled here and those
listening and watching by radio and television everywhere in expressing a prayer to our
Heavenly Father, wherein we would say, "We thank thee, O God, for a prophet, to guide us
in these latter days." (William Fowler, <i>Hymns</i> 196.) As a part of that prayer, I would also
include another feeling of gratitude an expression of appreciation to President McKay, for the
precious privilege that he has afforded me, together with Elder Paul H. Dunn, to work so
closely with Polynesia's people scattered upon the isles of the sea.
</p><p>
<b>Polynesian paradise threatened</b>
</p><p>
The choir brings to us a message of hope, of gratitude, of peace. However, the daily
newspaper from distant Tahiti tells of fear, frustration, and conflict, for on the atolls of
Mururoa and Fangataufa, thermonuclear testing has begun. Atomic and hydrogen explosions
thrust a new dimension upon Polynesia. One native was heard to say, "The kiss of death has
been bestowed upon Tahiti, the queen of the islands of the Pacific." Well might we who most
love these people ask the perplexing question, "Has paradise caught up with progress, or has
progress overtaken paradise?"
</p><p>
But then, the people of Polynesia have survived a variety of threats from a multitude of
sources through many periods of time.
</p><p>
When Captain James Cook and his ship's crew of the <i>Endeavor</i> first sailed into Matavai Bay
in the mid-1700's, they found a literal Polynesian paradise, with fresh water in torrents and
flowers and fruit everywhere. They found a people every bit as beautiful as their
surroundings. There was food all around them: fish in the lagoons, breadfruit and coconuts in
the branches overhead, bananas, yams, and sugarcane growing wild in prolific abundance. For
the most part, the people knew no sickness, except the gentle decline into old age and death.
But then came what has been called the "fatal impact" of European civilization. Firearms,
disease, alcohol, an alien code of laws became a threat to the people and their culture, just as
the current products of our advanced society pose the threats of today.
</p><p>
But Polynesia remains synonymous with paradise. The word itself, meaning "many islands," is
descriptive of the area of Polynesia that covers a major portion of the Pacific Ocean.
Geographically, it is bounded roughly by an imaginary triangle drawn from Hawaii southward
to New Zealand, thence eastward to Easter Island, and thence back to Hawaii. Here we find
major island groups, large volcanic islands, smaller coral atolls, and tiny, uninhabited islets.
</p><p>
<b>Blessings to the Polynesians</b>
</p><p>
Robert Louis Stevenson described the Polynesian sky as "immoderately blue"; but for the
Polynesians themselves, he reserved the fitting tribute: ". . . the sweetest people God ever
made." Polynesians are friendly, loving, handsome, and intelligent people. Their history is
exciting, their spoken words like a beautiful melody, their hospitality genuine, and their
beauty legendary.
</p><p>
Many ask "Why are these people so bounteously blessed?" "Why do returning missionaries
always retain in their hearts a love for the islands and their people?" "Why do Polynesia's
people so love the Lord?" The answer is found recorded in sacred scripture: "Know ye not
that I, the Lord your God, have created all men, and that I remember those who are upon the
isles of the sea"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/29/7#7">2 Ne. 29:7</a>).
". . . great are the promises of the Lord unto them who are
upon the isles of the sea"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/21#21">2 Ne. 10:21</a>).
</p><p>
These promises, these gifts from God, are apparent to those who visit Polynesia. May I invite
you today, for a few moments, to accompany me on a journey to the islands of the Pacific
and look in on Polynesia's people, that we might learn of God's gifts to them. Whether we
stop at New Zealand among the Maori, at Samoa, "the heart of the South Seas" at
Nuku'alofa, Tonga, in the Friendly Islands, at Papeete in Tahiti, or at beautiful Rarotonga, we
find people who are recipients of choice and cherished gifts.
</p><p>
<b>Gifts of the Polynesians</b>
</p><p>
Time permits a review of but five such gifts. I have chosen the gift of song, the gift of faith,
the gift of love, the gift of obedience, and the gift of gratitude.
</p><p>
<b>Gift of song</b>
</p><p>
We have witnessed today an expression of this gift of song. Polynesians need no formal
lessons in music Their voices are naturally resonant, their ears tuned to melody. A ukulele is
as common to a lad there as a jackknife is to a boy here. Dancing and song become parts of a
way of life.
</p><p>
Just this past June in New Zealand a tragic drowning claimed the lives of two instructors at
the Church College at Temple View. The young widows and their children were overcome by
grief and heartache. Many wellwishing and sympathetic friends offered words of consolation,
but the remorse remained. There came a soft knock at the door; a group of Maori Saints
entered the room. Not a word was spoken, but song came forth from their lips and hearts. The
bereaved families received a sustaining influence that accompanied them through the lonely
and long journey homeward and even today turns tears of sorrow to warm smiles of gratitude.
". . . the song of the righteous is a prayer unto me [saith the Lord], and it shall be answered
with a blessing upon their heads"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/25/12#12">D&amp;C 25:12</a>).
The Polynesians have the gift of song.
</p><p>
<b>Gift of faith</b>
</p><p>
The gift of faith, which they also enjoy, at times takes the form of miraculous healings of
body and mind. In other instances it is reflected by simple trust and calm assurance that God
will provide.
</p><p>
On my first visit to the fabled village of Sauniatu, so loved by President McKay, my wife and
I met with a large gathering of small children. At the conclusion of our messages to these shy,
yet beautiful, youngsters, I suggested to the native Samoan teacher that we go forward with
the closing exercises. As he announced the final hymn, I suddenly felt compelled to
personally greet each of these 247 children. My watch revealed that the time was too short for
such a privilege, so I discounted the impression. Before the benediction was to be spoken, I
again felt this strong impression to shake the hand of each child. This time I made the desire
known to the instructor, who displayed a broad and beautiful Samoan smile. He spoke in
Samoan to the children, and they beamed their approval of his comments.
</p><p>
The instructor then revealed to me the reason for his and their joy. He said, "When we
learned that President McKay had assigned a member of the Council of the Twelve to visit us
in far-away Samoa, I told the children if they would each one earnestly and sincerely pray
and exert faith like the Bible accounts of old, that the Apostle would visit our tiny village at
Sauniatu, and through their faith, he would be impressed to greet each child with a personal
handclasp." Tears could not be restrained as each of those precious boys and girls walked
shyly by and whispered softly to us a sweet <i>talofa lava</i>. The gift of faith had been evidenced.
</p><p>
<b>Gift of love</b>
</p><p>
The gift of love is found throughout Polynesia: a love of God, a love of sacred things, and
love for family, friends, and fellowmen. At Papeete, Tahiti, I met a distinguished yet humble
man, extraordinarily blessed with the gift of love. He was 84-year-old Tahauri Hutihuti from
the island of Takaroa in the Taumotu Island group. A faithful Church member all his life, he
had longed for the day when there would be in the Pacific a holy temple of God. He had a
love for the sacred ordinances he knew could only be performed in such a house. Patiently,
and with purpose, he carefully saved his meager earnings as a pearl diver. When the New
Zealand Temple was completed and opened, he took from beneath his bed his life savings of
$600, accumulated over a 40-year span; and together with loved ones, he journeyed to the
temple and thereby brought a fond dream to final fulfillment.
</p><p>
As I said a tender good-bye to the Tahitians, each one came forward, placed an exquisite shell
lei about my neck, and left an affectionate kiss upon my cheek. Tahauri, who did not speak
English, stood by my side and spoke to me through an interpreter. The interpreter listened
attentively and then, turning to me, reported: "Tahauri says he has no gift to bestow except
the love of a full heart." Tahauri clasped my hand and kissed my cheek. Of all the gifts
received that memorable night, the gift of this faithful man remains the brightest.
</p><p>
<b>Gift of obedience</b>
</p><p>
Allied with this gift of love is the gift of obedience. When a Polynesian hears God's Prophet
speak, he obeys. When he sings, "We thank thee, O God, for a prophet," he sings with his
heart, as well as his voice, and the walls resound.
</p><p>
Lauvale Tialavea, a counselor in the Samoan Mission presidency, typifies the spirit of
obedience. He is handsome in appearance, sincere in his testimony, and responds to each call
with seldom equalled enthusiasm A convert to the Church, he formerly studied for the
ministry of another faith. Intelligent, educated, keen thinking, and fearless, his actions
demonstrate his love for the newly found truth that is his very life. A kind husband and father
of ten, he has, since his baptism in 1961, taught the gospel to many hundreds of persons and
has himself baptized 174 as they have entered the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Ridiculed by the unbelievers for lifting his voice in testimony, stoned for his teaching of the
truth, mocked for his adherence to a rigid code of conduct, he courageously tells others of an
apostasy from the Church that followed the death of the Lord and his apostles, and of the
restoration of the gospel in this dispensation through the Prophet Joseph Smith. I asked,
"What provides your incentive, your strength to carry on such a missionary crusade amidst
such a storm of protest?" He replied: "Our prophet, God's mouthpiece, has asked that 'every
member be a missionary.' My desire is to be obedient to the Prophet." I thought of the words
of Samuel: ". . . to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/22#22">1 Sam. 15:22</a>).
I heard the clarion call of Joshua: ". . . as for me and my house, we will serve the
Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
To these people, obedience is a gift, and they honor it.
</p><p>
<b>Gift of gratitude</b>
</p><p>
I introduce next the gift of gratitude. Late one evening on a Pacific isle, a small boat slipped
silently to its berth at the crude pier. Two Polynesian women helped Meli Mulipola from the
boat and guided him to the well-worn pathway leading to the village road. The women
marveled at the bright stars that twinkled in the midnight sky. The friendly moonlight guided
them along their way. However, Meli Mulipola could not appreciate these delights of
nature&mdash;the moon, the stars, the sky&mdash;for he was blind.
</p><p>
His vision had been normal until that fateful day when, while working on a pineapple
plantation, light turned suddenly to darkness and day became perpetual night. He had learned
of the restoration of the gospel and teachings of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints. His life had been brought into compliance with these teachings.
</p><p>
He and his loved ones had made this long voyage, having learned that one who held the
priesthood of God was visiting among the islands. He sought a blessing under the hands of
those who held the sacred priesthood. His wish was granted, a blessing provided. Tears
streamed from his sightless eyes and coursed down his brown cheeks, tumbling finally upon
his native dress. He dropped to his knees and prayed: "Oh God, thou knowest I am blind. Thy
servants have blessed me that my sight return. Whether in thy wisdom I see light or whether I
see darkness all the days of my life, I will be eternally grateful for the truth of thy gospel
which I now see and which provides the light of my life." He arose to his feet, thanked us for
providing the blessing, and disappeared into the still of night. Silently he came. Silently he
departed. But his presence I shall never forget. I reflected upon the message of the Master: "I
am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have the
light of life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>).
</p><p>
There came to me an appreciation of these gifts of God to Polynesia's people: The gift of
song, the gift of faith, the gift of love, the gift of obedience, and the gift of gratitude. But
such gifts were suddenly dwarfed as I remembered God's greatest gift, given not only to the
Polynesians, but to you, to me, and to all persons everywhere&mdash;the gift of his Only Begotten
and precious Son, Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
We may never open gates of cities or doors of palaces, but we will find true happiness and
lasting joy when there enters our heart and soul a knowledge and understanding of this
supreme gift. "He comes to us as one unknown, without a name, as of old, by the lakeside,
when he came to those men who knew him not. He speaks to us the same words, 'Follow thou
me,' and sets us to the tasks that he has to fulfill for our time. He commands; and to those
who obey him, whether they be wise or simple, he will reveal himself in the toils, the
conflicts, the sufferings that they shall pass through in his fellowship; and they shall learn in
their own experience who he is" (Albert Schweitzer, <i>The Quest for the Historical Jesus</i>).
</p><p>
Like a bright searchlight of truth, his gospel will direct our journey along the pathways of
life. Oh, how blessed are we to have this never dimming, always glowing hope and the
eternal knowledge that belongs to us and that we share with the world: that the gospel has
been restored to earth, that God lives, that Jesus is his Son, our elder brother, our mediator
with the Father, our Lord and our Savior, God's greatest gift to us.
</p><p>
May our Heavenly Father bless us with an appreciation of his sacrifice; may our lives reflect
our gratitude, I ask in the name, the blessed name, of Jesus Christ, God's gift to us. Amen
</p>
</div>
</div>
