<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Aaronic Priesthood Responsibility</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop John H. Vandenberg</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Vandenberg, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1962, pp. 84-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren, it is an honor to meet with you tonight in this great assembly of the
priesthood of the Church. I am very grateful for my two great counselors who have helped me
so much in this new assignment that has come to me.
</p><p>
Sometime ago a letter came to my desk written by a woman investigator which carried with it
a great deal of enthusiasm and testimony, and I would like to share with you tonight the
following excerpts from this letter. Her salutation was this: 
</p><p>
"My dearest Father Bishopric: 
</p><p>
"You are going to be rather surprised to hear from me, but I attended Sunday services of The
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints today and was so inspired . . .
</p><p>
"I owe my gratitude to just about the finest, well-cultured, and intellectual gentlemen . . . They
graciously invited themselves into my home and explained the Mormons . . . I just had to go to
Church with them on the following Sunday. The book on how Joseph Smith tells his own
story was so outstanding, with great love of God for each and every human being, that my
knowledge of religion certainly broadened just by meeting these two elders . . .
</p><p>
"On entering the Church I was so astonished to see how many young people of today are
attending church, and especially thrilled to see how the young mothers bring their lovely
children . . . The thing that touched me deeply is how the elders or brothers were so anxious
just to be able to say, 'How do you do.' . . . This is something you don't see in other
churches . . .
</p><p>
"The Aaronic Priesthood conducted the Sacrament . . . which was so pure with delight
followed by the separation to classes. At this time the elders led me to the adult class . . . Here
is where I accumulated knowledge in one half hour that I did not know in a lifetime of fifty
years . . .
</p><p>
"I also enjoyed the opening prayer . . . which put a dent in my mind that these are a group of
people that have to be made more known in our United States of America . . . "Again I say
how happy I was to attend services in your Mormon Latter-day Saint Church, and how
mighty proud the mission must be of the elders. They are an inspiration that many mothers
and fathers today can learn the message from God to his children to make this a better world
to live in like God intended it to be."
</p><p>
As I read this thrilling letter, I thought what a great blessing to the elders' parents and to
those missionaries, although they are unaware of the great spiritual lift that they gave to this
woman. As the woman stated, "I owe my gratitude to just about the finest, well-cultured, and
intellectual gentlemen." I wondered what greater honor could there be than to be so highly
esteemed by one's neighbors. No doubt this experience is happening time and time again the
world over.
</p><p>
Then to think that these missionaries came from the ranks of the Aaronic Priesthood, having
faithfully served until they became eligible to be ordained to the Melchizedek Priesthood and
called to the ministry of the Savior. One cannot help feeling the warmth of the Spirit as he
contemplates the great Aaronic Priesthood work of this Church
</p><p>
Tonight I cannot help thinking of more than 237,000 living men and boys
who have the privilege of bearing the Aaronic Priesthood. Obviously our thoughts are turned
toward them because of the great responsibility that follows the offices of the Presiding
Bishopric which have been placed upon us.
</p><p>
This great body of Aaronic Priesthood, under and over twenty-one years of age, becomes our
charge, and we feel the impact of this responsibility very keenly.
</p><p>
While my counselors were talking about the more than 100,000 young men under twenty-one
bearing the Aaronic Priesthood, my thoughts turned to the more than 100,000 over twenty-one
who may be working to qualify themselves to receive the blessings of the Melchizedek
Priesthood.
</p><p>
I have been thinking of their wives, their sons, their daughters, and their future. We realize
that some of these mature brethren who bear the Aaronic Priesthood have again become
active, faithful, and devoted members of the Church in order to achieve their goal. We also
realize that many are recent converts to the Church who are working toward their ordination
to the Melchizedek Priesthood. These brethren are anxiously waiting for the day when they
may enter a temple of the Lord to receive their endowments and sealings through the Holy
Melchizedek Priesthood. We pray that all of these may continue to enjoy the warmth of
fellowship in the priesthood without any interruption. But knowing as I do that there are some
who are dormant, I must confess that we will not be contented until we reason with them,
until we hold out the hand of fellowship, until we assure them that the Lord calls to them,
"Cast away from you all your transgressions, whereby ye have transgressed; and make you a
new heart and a new spirit: for why will ye die . . .
</p><p>
"For I have no pleasure in the death of him that dieth, saith the Lord God: wherefore turn
yourselves, and live ye" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/18/31-32#31">Ezek. 18:31-32</a>).
</p><p>
These brethren and their families are precious in the sight of God. He loves them, and we
love them. But their lives need a "new heart and a new spirit" so that they will perpetuate no
regrets of the lost opportunities of yesterday.
</p><p>
While Bishop Simpson and Bishop Brown were speaking, my thoughts also turned to the
special invitation extended by the First Presidency to all young men who bear the Aaronic
Priesthood to attend this great priesthood meeting. We feel confident that if our eyes could
travel over the closed circuit wires and peer into the multitude of gathering places, our hearts
would swell with joy at the great numbers who have honored their priesthood by responding
to this call.
</p><p>
As we speak to you young men, we speak also to your leaders, calling to their minds the
challenging responsibilities of meeting your needs for spiritual growth and stability, that there
may be no structural weaknesses in your faith, your integrity, and your devotion.
</p><p>
To emphasize the responsibilities of leadership of boys, we recall the words of the poetess W.
A. Dromgoole: 
</p><p>
<i>Building the Bridge for Him</i>
</p><p>
          "An old man, traveling a lone highway,<br />
          Came at the evening cold and gray<br />
          To a chasm deep and wide.
</p><p>
"The old man crossed in the twilight dim,<br />
          For the sullen stream held no fears for him.<br />
          But he turned when he reached the other side,<br />
          And builded a bridge to span the tide.
</p><p>
"'Old man,' cried a fellow pilgrim near,<br />
          'You are wasting your strength with building here; <br />
          Your journey will end with the ending day,<br />
          And you never again will pass this way.
</p><p>
"'You have crossed the chasm deep and wide.<br />
          Why build you a bridge at eventide?'<br />
          And the builder raised his old gray head: <br />
          'Good friend, on the path I have come,' he said,<br />
          'There followeth after me today<br />
          A youth whose feet will pass this way.'
</p><p>
"'This stream, which has been as naught to me,<br />
          To that fair-haired boy may a pitfall be; <br />
          He, too, must cross in the twilight dim&mdash;<br />
          Good friend, I am building this bridge for him.'"
</p><p>
Leaders give heed to the words of Paul to the Corinthians: "For if the trumpet give an
uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself to the battle?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/8#8">1 Cor. 14:8</a>).
</p><p>
You are the trumpeters to the youth who are listening for certain sounds&mdash;positive,
unwavering teachings, examples&mdash;a steady beam to guide them in preparation for a useful
life of service in the dignity of the priesthood. If we, the trumpeters, do not guard our actions,
our language&mdash;do not set worthy examples&mdash;how then can we expect our young men to
prepare themselves "to the battle," battle against wrongdoing&mdash;the battle they fight every day
of their lives?
</p><p>
Now, young men, may we say to you, responsibility is a two-way street. One cannot give
unless there is someone to receive. Your stake president, stake committee, bishoprics, general
secretaries, quorum advisers, and auxiliary leaders are spending more time, giving more
thought and prayer to your cause than ever before. They are the ones who give, and you are
the ones who receive. We urge you to receive well, to qualify for the tasks to come. You
cannot expect success without preparation.
</p><p>
James A. Garfield said: "Young men talk of trusting to the spur of the occasion. They trust in
vain. Occasion cannot make spurs. If you expect to wear spurs you must win them. If you
wish to use them you must buckle them to your own heels before you go into the fight."
</p><p>
We think you should know that once each week it is our privilege as the Presiding Bishopric
to receive counsel from the First Presidency on all matters pertaining to the Aaronic
Priesthood work of the Church. Through this association and direction, the blessings of the
Aaronic Priesthood program flow out to the whole Church. Also you should know that on
frequent occasions, the Presiding Bishopric meet with the general priesthood committee of the
Church to co-ordinate all our efforts in your behalf.
</p><p>
As I observe the prophets, seers, and revelators of the Church in council meetings, I think of
the words which Joseph J. Daynes set to music: 
</p><p>
"Come, listen to a prophet's voice<br />
                   And hear the word of God<br />
          "And in the way of truth rejoice,<br />
                   And sing for joy aloud.
</p><p>
"We've found the way the prophets went<br />
                   Who lived in days of yore; <br />
"Another prophet now is sent<br />
                   This knowledge to restore."
</p><p>
The inspiration and revelation of God come through his prophets to direct the destiny of this
Church. You young men belong to that Church&mdash;the greatest organization for good in all the
world. Membership carries with it great responsibilities, but not greater than you can carry on
your young, strong shoulders. You are young, but, as bearers of the Aaronic Priesthood, you
are expected to: 
</p><p>
1. Discipline yourselves to do that which is right.<br />
2. To be close to your father and mother and give heed to their counsel.<br />
3. To pray to God and to give thanks to him for his blessings.<br />
4. To sustain the ward, stake, and General Authorities&mdash;attesting thereto by your actions.<br />
5. To cultivate a pure heart and a clean mind.<br />
6. To fill every assignment willingly.<br />
7. To refuse to participate in any action or conversation which would offend the dignity of the
priesthood you bear.<br />
8. To attend all your meetings and put into practice the lessons you learn at those meetings.
</p><p>
Now, to the fathers, we solicit and encourage your full co-operation. It is so much easier to
help your sons reach the goal when we and they know of your full support. The place of the
father in the home, and his responsibilities to his family, are clearly defined in the words of
President Lorenzo Snow, and I quote: ". . . if you ever secure a union in any family in Zion, if
you ever secure that heavenly union which is necessary to exist there, you
have got to bind that family together in one, and there has got to be the Spirit of the Lord in
the head of that family, and he should possess that light and that intelligence, which, if carried
out in the daily life and conduct of those individuals, will prove the salvation of that family,
for he holds their salvation in his hands." (<i>JD</i> 4:243.)
</p><p>
Now, we should all ever keep before us that sacred moment in Nephite history when Jesus
was giving his last instructions to the twelve disciples: ". . . Therefore, what manner of men
ought ye to be? Verily I say unto you, even as I am"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/27#27">3 Ne. 27:27</a>).
</p><p>
I bear testimony to the truthfulness of this great work, and I pray our Heavenly Father to
bless the great priesthood of this Church, and I do it in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
