<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"That All Men Might Repent"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 79-82</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, President McKay has been kind enough to advise the General
Authorities in advance that they might be expected to speak at certain sessions of the
conference.  My turn was to come next Wednesday.  During a half century of active service
in the Church, I have never felt so wholly inadequate, so totally dependent on divine guidance
as I feel right now.  For that guidance I humbly pray.
</p><p>
We sang yesterday, "We thank Thee, O God, for a Prophet." This hymn referred originally to
the Prophet Joseph Smith. In a meeting not long ago when President McKay announced that
the congregation would sing, "We Thank Thee, O God, for a Prophet," he said,
characteristically, "I wish you would have in mind the Prophet Joseph Smith when you sing
today."
</p><p>
I should like to offer a prayer that has been in my heart for years, a prayer which I believe is
in the heart of every Latter-day Saint throughout the world.  "We thank thee, O God, for the
Prophet, David O. McKay, to guide us in these later-latter days.  We thank thee that through
thy blessings he has had the vitality, the vigor, and the health to carry the message of the
gospel to the four corners of the earth.  We thank thee that his influence and his presence
have revitalized the Saints wherever he has gone and have given them courage and ape.  We
thank thee that he more than any man among us, more than any of his predecessors, has
carried the inspiration and the message of the gospel to the greatest and to an ever-increasing
international audience.  We pray that thou wilt bless him continually and spare him to us, that
we may enjoy his great leadership for many years to come."
</p><p>
From the bottom of my heart I sustain and support these men, the President of the Church and
his Counselors, the President of the Council of the Twelve, and each individual member of
that Council, and the Patriarch as prophets, seers, and revelators to the Church.  I am grateful
for the privilege of meeting with them occasionally.
</p><p>
Some of our friends have said we are inclined to worship the General Authorities.  We love
them; we listen to their counsel; we thank God for them; but they would not permit us to
worship them.  If we should be so inclined, they would be the first to rebuke us.  They would
doubtless say to us what the angel said to John on the Isle of Patmos, when he was about to
kneel before him,
</p><p>
See thou do it not: I am thy fellowservant . . . worship God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/10#10">Rev. 19:10</a>).
</p><p>
But it is our privilege to be guided by their inspired counsel.  I pray that God will help us
never to lose sight of and ever be grateful for the outstanding leadership in the Church today.
</p><p>
Elder Alma Sonne mentioned Easter-tide.  This is the season of the year when we know
spring is coming, although here in Salt Lake City today it takes a lot of faith to believe it. 
But it is the season of the year when things are revitalized and renewed, and it is the time of
year when Christians everywhere celebrate Easter in commemoration of the resurrection of the
Lord.
</p><p>
As I speak of these men and of their leadership, I am reminded of some additional reasons
why we should be grateful for the Easter season. Through the restoration of the gospel we
have knowledge and assurance regarding the actual resurrection of the body of the Lord Jesus
Christ. Not only that he was resurrected from the dead, but also that he ascended into heaven
with his glorified body, and he will come again in material form and substance.  We are
grateful for the comfort and the hope which comes with this assurance.
</p><p>
The revelations concerning the nature and attributes of our Heavenly Father and of his Son,
Jesus Christ, are of transcendent importance to all men everywhere.  Modern confirmation and
elucidation of biblical evidence on this all-important subject began with the first vision in the
Sacred Grove in 1820, and it was renewed and continued in that glorious vision in 1832 at
Hiram, Ohio, when the Lord declared,
</p><p>
Hear, O ye heavens, and give ear, O earth, and rejoice ye inhabitants thereof, for the Lord is
God, and beside him there is no Savior.
</p><p>
Great is his wisdom, marvelous are his ways, and the extent of his doings none find
out.
</p><p>
His purposes fail not, neither are there any who can stay his hand.
</p><p>
From eternity to eternity he is the same, and his years never fail
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/1-4#1">D&amp;C 76:1-4</a>).
</p><p>
The restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ came pursuant to prophetic promise and was a
necessary sequel to the great apostasy.  It was during the apostasy that an attempt was made
to harmonize pagan philosophy with Christian truth.  This task was undertaken at the behest
of non-Christian emperors and resulted in uninspired declarations in which God was
defined&mdash;or rather denied&mdash;by declaring him to be immaterial, incomprehensible, and without body or
parts, occupying no part of finite or infinite space, in other words, non-existent.
</p><p>
We thank God for the restoration of the gospel which refutes such doctrine. In their attempt to
incorporate Jesus the Christ into their pagan concept of the Godhead, the Roman emperors,
through their appointed delegates to various councils, undertook to have him divest himself of
his body, that body which came from the tomb when the angel rolled the stone away, that
glorified body with which he ascended into heaven before the wondering gaze of his disciples. 
Obviously this resurrected body, being material, could not become a part of their immaterial
God which had no parts.  They would have him shed that body and thereby everything that
Easter stands for; for if he is incomprehensible and immaterial, then he is not a resurrected
being; and if he is not a resurrected being, Easter is meaningless.
</p><p>
Again I say let us thank God for the clarification that has come through modern revelation
concerning the personal attributes of the three members of the Godhead.
</p><p>
Jesus Christ revealed the Father to us and said, ". . . he that hath seen me hath seen the
Father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/9#9">John 14:9</a>).
The Son was in his express image
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/1/3#3">Heb. 1:3</a>).  He revealed a compassionate
Father, a divine Parent, one in whom were incorporated the attributes of justice, judgment,
mercy, and truth.  He revealed a God of love, of forgiveness, and understanding.  The
restored gospel supplants the motives of fear and awe with faith and trust.  The beloved
disciple tells us, ". . . perfect love casteth out fear"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/18#18">1 Jn. 4:18</a>). Love as a dominant
attribute of God and a saving quality in man is reasserted and emphasized.
</p><p>
The new commandment which Jesus gave was, "That ye love one another, even as I have
loved you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/34#34">John 13:34</a>).
His love for us is eternal.  Nothing can separate us from it.  Sin may separate us
from him, but his love endures forever. Listen to Paul's testimony: 
</p><p>
For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor
powers, nor things present, nor things to come,
</p><p>
Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the
love of God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/8/38-39#38">Rom. 8:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
I should like to speak to these young people who have been singing for us, and to other
young people of the Church, for like others who have spoken, my heart is with the youth of
Zion. I should like to say to these young people that God is their Father, that the Savior is
pleading for and with them to keep clean, clean in their thinking, in their speaking, in their
conduct, that he expects them to be worthy of him and of the sacrifice he made for them and
for all of us. He is the Good Shepherd who gave his life for the sheep
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/14-15#14">John 10:14-15</a>).  He evinced the
solicitude of the Good Shepherd in his last injunction to Peter, "Feed my sheep"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/16#16">John 21:16</a>).
</p><p>
I should like to add another word to the young people.  One of the most lethal weapons
which the Adversary has devised to destroy the young people of the Church and of the world
is to persuade them that if they have made a mistake they are lost, there is no hope.
According to that doctrine, if a young person, in a weak moment, becomes guilty of some
misdemeanor, he might as well go on to juvenile delinquency and crime and felony because
he is lost anyway.  So the devil would have them believe and thus lead them down to hell.
</p><p>
Young people, your Father in heaven loves you; he loves you with a love beyond what your
earthly parents can know. If you make mistakes&mdash;and you will and all of us have&mdash;our
Heavenly Father stands ready to forgive and to welcome you when you come to yourselves
and turn your backs on the husks and your faces toward home
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/16-17#16">Luke 15:16-17</a>).
He will embrace you and say,
"For this my son was dead, and is alive again; he was lost and is found"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/24#24">Luke 15:24</a>). But
let no one think he will not have to pay for his folly.  The Father could not in justice say to
the prodigal what he said to his older son, "All that I have is thine"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/31#31">Luke 15:31</a>).
</p><p>
Our Father is kind and loving and forgiving, but there is an inexorable law which has not
been repealed.  It Is the law of the harvest,  "<i>As ye sow, so shall ye reap</i>" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/7#7">Gal. 6:7</a>).
We cannot sow thistles and reap figs, nor plant thorns and harvest grapes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16#16">Matt. 7:16</a>). But when we
have had enough of thistles and thorns, we may have the grapes and the figs if we are willing
to pay the price&mdash;and they cost less.  While ours is a world governed by rigid and
unwavering law, man has free agency, he may choose to obey or disobey the law, but he must
of course abide the consequences of his choice.
</p><p>
One other thing to the young folk&mdash;sometimes you come to us with problems when you are
perplexed and confused and feel that you are inhibited, not free to think or express opinions.
When we talk to you of free agency and explain that it refers not only to actions but to
thoughts and opinions, you wonder if that is always the case. Some of you have said to us,
"But our right to express our own opinions is trammeled or abridged by the authoritative
statements of parents, teachers, and others."
</p><p>
Young people, we will protect your freedom to think, to express your thoughts, and to search
for truth.  We want you to continue that search fearlessly.  We promise you will be
uninhibited in that search.
</p><p>
You should remember, however, that God has given us sources through which we may have
some authoritative answers. Not all the answers, no!  If we had all the answers, there would
be an end to the search. We must not expect to have all the answers immediately, for God
himself in his wisdom has withheld some of them. We believe in continued and continuing
revelation, and that means that we believe there are things to be made known which we do
not now know.  We believe it is a good thing to reserve judgment on problems that are difficult of
solution until more light comes.  This principle of withholding judgment and waiting for new
revelation should apply in all fields of learning.  Scientists make rather definite statements at
times, but some of us have lived to see them either amend or abandon their findings in the
light of newly discovered truth. As long as scientists are still searching and discovering and as
long as new revelation is promised, why insist upon final answers now? It is my conviction
that new revelation will come when we have learned to live up to the truth we now have. 
Wisdom counsels patience.
</p><p>
And so, with respect to some things that now seem difficult to understand, we can well afford
to wait until we have all the facts, until all the evidence is in.  Now do not misunderstand me.
There will never come a time when any revelation of truth from God will be in conflict with
any other truth revealed from him, whether it comes as direct revelation or as reward for
diligent search.  If there seems to be conflict, it is because men, fallible men, are unable
properly to interpret God's revelations or man's discoveries.
</p><p>
May he help us that we may go forward fearlessly but reverently in our search for truth and
have due respect not only for our parents and our teachers, but also for those through whom
God has promised his revelations.
</p><p>
By the same token, we should not undertake to state the time nor the order in which the
gospel shall be given to any of the races or nations of the earth.  We should not attempt to
regulate God's program by our little wrist watches nor insist that he be governed by our
schedule of events.  He has promised the gospel to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>),
and he and only he knows when they are ready for its message and its blessings. When that
time comes, I bear you my witness, prophetic witness, if you will, that he will reveal his will
to the leaders of the Church concerning all of his people. He has said,
</p><p>
Remember the worth of souls [all souls] is great In the sight of God; 
</p><p>
For, behold the Lord your Redeemer suffered death in the flesh; wherefore he suffered
the pain of all men, that <i>all men</i> might repent and come unto him.
</p><p>
And he hath risen again from the dead, that he might bring <i>all men</i> unto him, on
conditions of repentance.
</p><p>
And how great is his joy in the soul that repenteth!
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/10-13#10">D&amp;C 18:10-13</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, I humbly bear my testimony to you that I do know that God is my
Father, that Jesus of Nazareth is my Redeemer and my friend.  I thank him for the blessed
privilege of engaging in the ministry, and I praise his holy name that through his servants he
has shown his willingness to use the weakest of us to do some little good in that ministry.
</p><p>
God bless us to recognize him as the Good Shepherd and to go forward with faith, unafraid of
the future, and with complete confidence to say with the Psalmist: 
</p><p>
The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want.
</p><p>
He maketh me to lie down in green pastures: he leadeth me beside the still waters.
</p><p>
He restoreth my soul: he leadeth me in the paths of righteousness for his name's sake.
</p><p>
Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for
thou art with me; thy rod and thy staff they comfort me.
</p><p>
Thou preparest a table before me in the presence of mine enemies: thou anointest my
head with oil; my cup runneth over.
</p><p>
Surely goodness and mercy shall follow me all the days of my life: and I will dwell in
the house of the Lord forever (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/23/1-6#1">Ps. 23:1-6</a>).
</p><p>
We pray this may be true for all of us in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
