<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Need for Witness of the Spirit</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder A. Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 95-96</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, I have had more compliments on the talk I did not give
yesterday, than I have ever had on one I actually gave. I am sure those who thus commented
were thinking of the advice that Brother Henry Taylor gave yesterday about the responsibility
of improving upon silence.
</p><p>
Last night in priesthood meeting, I missed the voice that has always made an eloquent plea
for unity, and I am grateful this morning that I heard that voice bear such a powerful
testimony to the divinity of this work. [President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., could not attend
priesthood meeting.]
</p><p>
Where else could you go in the world and find such certainty and knowledge that God lives
and that Jesus Christ is his Son. Contrast what we have heard the past few days with this
statement:
</p><p>
"Several years ago in a seminary recognized as perhaps the greatest in this country, a doctor
of divinity, who had a string of honorary doctoral degrees and who is on the board of
directors of one of the largest Protestant churches in America, in lecturing to a large group of
students, most of whom already had bachelor of divinity degrees, said, sympathetically:
</p><p>
"'I know that it is difficult for you men to teach creeds which you, yourselves, do not believe,
but you have the social obligation to do it.'"
</p><p>
Another man in the same institution, having about the same academic credentials, declared:
"Who knows but what in the year 2004 or some other year, there will live a man who will
live more perfectly than did Jesus. Then we will worship him as the Son of God, rather than
Jesus. The reason we worship Jesus as the Son of God is because he lived the most perfect
life of any man of whom we have knowledge."
</p><p>
Does the world need the message of Mormonism? I think it needs nothing more than to know
the true concept of the Godhead, to have borne upon their souls the testimony that has been
borne here these days of conference&mdash;the testimony that comes through the gift and power of
the Holy Ghost, that bears witness to our souls and our hearts that God does live. He is real.
He is a glorified, resurrected Being, and he is our Father, and he loves us. He "... so loved the
world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus is the Savior. We declare boldly, yet humbly, to all of the world [p. 96]
that he is the Redeemer; that he atoned for the sins of man, and he is veritably the Son of
God.
</p><p>
I am grateful that we have had restored to us today, another witness that this is so. This
witness comes from the Book of Mormon. Nephi saw in vision that Mary was to be the
mother of the Son of God after the manner of the flesh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/18#18">1 Ne. 11:18</a>). The Book of
Mormon further witnesses that Jesus Christ did come to this people on this continent. They
bore testimony that he lives.
</p><p>
I am grateful for the Prophet Joseph Smith, who said he saw two Personages stand above him
in the air, and that the one called him by name and said, "This, is My Beloved Son. Hear
Him!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
And I would add to the testimonies that have been borne in
conference, my own testimony. It has come to me through the gift and power of the Holy
Ghost. I know that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of God. I am grateful for this
witness of the Spirit to my soul.
</p><p>
I would plead with the parents of this Church to prepare their sons to bear this testimony to
the world, the only power that will bring peace, because peace is rooted in righteousness.
When the hearts of men on this earth can be prepared to receive the witness of the Spirit, all
men will be brothers, and then peace can come to our hearts.
</p><p>
I pray that we shall hasten this day through our united efforts by wholeheartedly supporting
these brethren who direct the affairs of the Lord on earth, and can contribute both service and
substance to help the work of the Lord forward. I humbly pray his blessings upon us, and
bear this testimony in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
