<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Expressing Appreciation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas E. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas E. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 43-45</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, Counselors, President Smith and other General Authorities of the Church,
my brethren and sisters and friends: 
</p><p>
I appreciate more than I can express in words the privilege of being here this morning, to
express to you all my love and my thankfulness, for these General Authorities, for all my
brethren and sisters, and my loved ones. I want you to know that I appreciate your
thoughtfulness in my behalf, I trust that I will merit this kindness throughout my life.  I am
grateful, especially, to my Father in heaven for his many blessings, for answering your
prayers for me.  I am a great believer in prayer.  "More things," we are told "are wrought by
prayer than this world dreams of," and I know that is true.  I know that prayers have been
answered; otherwise I would not be here.
</p><p>
I was very thankful to hear announced this morning that Sister Lohner, Margrit Feh Lohner,
would conduct the singing, and that Elder Edwin Q. Cannon would offer the invocation. Sister
Lohner, or Margrit Feh as we knew her in Europe, was just a little girl when I met her first in
the Sunday School.  She was the life of the Sunday School in Zurich, Switzerland.  Brother
Cannon was one of my missionaries, and a wonderful missionary he was. This makes me feel
more at home.
</p><p>
I love the gospel, brethren and sisters, and with President Clark who has just delivered a
wonderful address and the others who have spoken yesterday and today, I bear my testimony
with them that the gospel is true, that the gospel has been given to us for our happiness, not
altogether in the life to come, but in this life.  I think the Lord has meant that we should be
happy here and not wait until the hereafter, and I know we can be.
</p><p>
"Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they might have joy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>), joy in
this life, and the greatest joy that any person can have is through obedience to the gospel of
Jesus Christ.  It has been given to us for that purpose, that we might have joy, and I testify to
you that through obedience to the gospel we will be happy, the happiest people in the world. 
I believe we are, today, because of the gospel.  I like the expression, too, in
the Declaration of Independence: 
</p><p>
. . . all men are created equal; that they are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable
rights, that among these are life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.
</p><p>
We all like that expression, "the pursuit of happiness."
</p><p>
God help us to understand the gospel, and to live it, and to appreciate it.  It is a beautiful
world.  These beautiful flowers, how they add to the enjoyment of all of us, more than we
realize!  I was delighted, too, more than I can express, that the brethren and sisters in Hawaii
remembered the wives of the Authorities, and sent them beautiful orchids.  That touched my
heart.
</p><p>
Our wives and our mothers are too often forgotten in this world, and, brethren and sisters,
you cannot estimate what they mean toe of us, and I think that we should express our
appreciation for them more than we do. We men love our wives, of course, but we take it too
much for granted, I think, sometimes, and we forget to tell them that we love them.  We go
home from our work at the office, a little tired, find a wonderful meal prepared for us.  What
do we do?  Get the newspaper, get it in our left hand, and then swallow the meal down with
our right, not knowing sometimes what we are eating even.  Our wives have spent a lot of
time preparing the meal for us, and it would not hurt us to express our appreciation.  I think
that some of the wives have not had a bouquet of flowers since before we were married.  We
used to take them a bouquet once in a while when we were "sparking" them, as we say, a box
of candy perhaps, and that is the last they have had.  It would not hurt us occasionally; in
fact, it would help us as well as them, if they were remembered. Many of us do not know
when their birthday is; we do not remember the anniversary of our marriage; these little
things we forget.  My favorite theme is appreciation; I like to talk along this line.  My
favorite song is "There is beauty all around when there's Love at Home," and I like to hear
that. I am glad the home was mentioned so often yesterday.  In fact, I appreciate everything
that has been done and said in this conference, the singing yesterday and the singing today,
the sermons that have been delivered.  I am glad I am in harmony with them.
</p><p>
I have not time, it would not be wise to take more time to develop some of these principles. 
President Clark did it so beautifully this morning, and I am in harmony with everything he
said.  God bless him and the other Authorities of the Church, they have been very kind to me,
and I want to testify to you that I am here today because of their faith, because of the
authority of the priesthood which they bear, and with which they used that authority in laying
their hands upon my head while I was lying in the hospital.  I love these brethren with all my
heart, and I love you, my brethren and sisters.
</p><p>
I love the gospel, as I say.  There are many tourists in our midst that come and go.  I wish
they would call at the Bureau of Information, or perhaps the Church Office Building and ask
for a little card on which are printed our Articles of Faith.  They are wonderful. Many of
these tourists do not know whether we are Christians or not, for example they ask: "Where do
you fit in?  Are you Protestants?" "No." "Are you Catholics?" "No." "Well, what are you?"
"We are members of the Church of Jesus Christ.  Jesus is our head. It is his Church to which
we belong." Our First Article of Faith would answer that question. "We believe in God, the
eternal Father, and in his son, Jesus Christ, and in the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>). And then the other
articles&mdash;they are very short.  It is wonderful how concisely they are written, and yet how
instructive they are.
</p><p>
We are thought by some to be a little narrow.  Well, the gospel is for all. "We believe that
through the atonement of Christ, all mankind may be saved"&mdash;not just Mormons, but "all
mankind may be saved, by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the gospel"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>). And so on
down.
</p><p>
We love all mankind.  "We claim the privilege of worshiping Almighty God according to the
dictates of our own conscience," another article says, "and allow all men the
same privilege, let them worship how, where, or what they may"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/11#11">A of F 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
And the thirteenth article is my favorite: 
</p><p>
"We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men;
indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all things, we hope all
things, we have endured many things, and hope to be able to endure all things." Then in
conclusion, "If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek
after these things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, it would be well for all of us to learn these Articles of Faith, as well as
the tourists, and not only learn them, but also live them, and may God help us so to do, I pray
in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
