<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"The Heavens Are Not Stayed"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Gordon B. Hinckley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Gordon B. Hinckley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 36-39</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved associates in the work of the Lord: I seek the inspiration of the Spirit. My heart
has been warmed, and my testimony has been strengthened by the things to which we have
listened.
</p><p>
I would be remiss in my duty if before I get into my text I do not say a word in behalf of my
faithful associates in the distant missions of the Far East. I was delighted with the reports of
President Tuttle and of Elder Petersen concerning the work in South America, the Isles of
Britain, and the lands of Europe.
</p><p>
<b>The Gospel to Ancient Asia</b>
</p><p>
I should like to add that a great work is going on among the people of the ancient lands of
Asia. I have an appointment in the next few days in Hong Kong, where we shall meet in a
conference of the Chinese Saints. There will be approximately a thousand of them gather in
that city, and as I look into their faces, there will come into my mind renewed faith and
increased testimony in the power of God to touch men's hearts everywhere.
</p><p>
My heart skipped a beat this morning when I looked into this group and saw a man from
Korea, one of my beloved brethren. The Lord is pouring out his Spirit upon
that part of the world, and I thank him for that manifestation. Now to my text.
</p><p>
<b>Faith in Revelation</b>
</p><p>
I believe all that God has revealed, all that he does now reveal, and I believe that he will yet
reveal many great and important things pertaining to the kingdom of God (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
This paraphrase of a statement from the Prophet Joseph Smith is the creed and the guide of
my life. It is the foundation of the faith of all members of The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
<b>The "Fount" of Inspiration</b>
</p><p>
God is the one sure source of truth. He is the fount of all inspiration. It from him that the
world must receive direction if peace is to come to the earth and if goodwill is to prevail
among men. This earth is his creation. We are his children. Out of the love he bears for us,
he will guide us if we will seek, listen, and obey. "Surely the Lord God will do nothing, but
he revealeth his secrets unto his servants the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
Our world is changing. We live in an age of great material progress. Can religion remain
static when all else is moving forward?
</p><p>
It is true that man's essential nature does not change, and that principles laid down centuries
ago by the prophets are as applicable today as they were when they were first enunciated; but
the world evidently knows not how to apply them. Today that application needs the direction
of the Almighty as certainly as when Jehovah spoke to Enoch and Moses and Isaiah and
Elijah.
</p><p>
"For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God spake as
they were moved by the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21#21">2 Pet. 1:21</a>).
And prophecy, which is revelation,
comes not now, nor will it come in the future, by the will of man, but only as men of God
speak as they are moved upon by that same spirit.
</p><p>
How poverty-ridden is our world in the wisdom of living one with another. The stresses, the
strains, the tensions in human relationships, the wars and rumors of wars that constantly afflict
us all become evidence that ". . . the wisdom of the wise has failed and the understanding of
the prudent is hid" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/14#14">Isa. 29:14</a>).
Religion, to be effective, must be a vital and timely force
in the lives of men.
</p><p>
The people today need a prophet as surely as Israel needed a prophet when it groaned in the
toils of Egypt, and Moses was called to lead it from bondage.
</p><p>
<b>Channels of Communication Open</b>
</p><p>
Israel today has a prophet, and we give our witness to the world that the channel of
communication is open between God and his appointed servant.
</p><p>
We would not take from men of goodwill anywhere the standards of truth by which they live.
But we say to all, "Come, feast upon that which the Lord has offered in our day. To that
which you have and cherish, we invite you to add that which your Father has further offered,
for there is a prophet in the land today as certainly as there was in ancient Israel."
</p><p>
There are those who have declared that the canon of scripture is full, that revelation ceased
with the ancient Apostles, that the heavens are sealed. Well might we ask such, "Why, then,
do you pray? If God is unwilling to speak, is unwilling to guide, if there can be no revelation,
why seek him?" The fallacy of this position is evident; yet the world would deny the
possibility of modern revelation.
</p><p>
<b>Opening of Mission in the Philippines</b>
</p><p>
Three years ago I had the opportunity of participating in the opening of our mission in the
Philippines. It was an inspirational experience. We gathered at dawn in the American military
cemetery on the outskirts of the city of Manila. There before us stood "row on row" the
crosses that mark the graves of more than 17,000 American dead, and inscribed on marble
tablets we saw the names of some 36,000 more who died in the battles of the Pacific and
whose remains were never found&mdash;a grim and solemn reminder of man's foolish inhumanity
to man.
</p><p>
Among those who spoke on that sacred occasion was a young Filipino. He recounted the story
of how, when he was a child, he had found an old magazine in a pile of trash. It contained an
article on the history of our people. It spoke of Joseph Smith. It described him as a prophet.
That word "prophet" caught in his consciousness. It impressed him. It raised questions in his
young mind. "Could there really be a prophet in the earth in this time of the world?" he asked
himself.
</p><p>
<b>A Filipino Seeks a Prophet</b>
</p><p>
Years passed. There came to his land the terrible tragedies of Corregidor and Bataan and the
death march to Tarlac; the strafing and bombing of Clark Field near his home; the hunger and
fear and oppression of the enemy occupation; and then, finally, the liberation of the
Philippines and the re-establishment of Clark Field as an American air base. He secured
employment there. One day he heard that one of the American officers for whom he worked
was a Mormon. There flashed again into his mind the word "prophet." He found courage to
ask the man if a prophet really stood at the head of his Church. Without equivocation the
officer replied yes, and there followed an explanation, a recounting of the simple and
beautiful story of the appearance of God the Eternal Father, and his Son, the Lord Jesus
Christ, to a boy who had come in faith and prayer to find wisdom. That testimony touched
this young Filipino's heart. His life has been changed by the conviction that revelation from
God is available to man in our time. Today he holds the priesthood and walks in the dignity
of that priesthood, a leader of the Church in his own land.
</p><p>
Can one doubt the need for revelation in this day of complex human problems? Some weeks
ago news was broadcast over the country that at a particular hour on a particular day the
surgeon general of the United States would issue a report on the effects of smoking. The
release time was carefully planned, presumably to affect the stock market least seriously.
Then, as President McKay indicated this morning, at the appointed hour radio, television, and
the news services dramatically announced the finding of causal relationships between the
smoking of cigarettes and lung cancer. Lengthy tables of statistics, page upon page of data,
were enumerated to produce the conclusion that cigarette smoking is harmful to health.
</p><p>
<b>"Tobacco Is Not Good for Man"</b>
</p><p>
I thumbed through that 387-page report, and then I turned to the revelation of the Lord given
through the Prophet Joseph Smith wherein he said simply but unequivocally, ". . . tobacco . . .
is not good for man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/8#8">D&amp;C 89:8</a>).
</p><p>
I am grateful for the work of those scientists who made the report on smoking. I am confident
that their discoveries will save untold suffering and add untold years of useful living to those
who will heed their counsel. But how much suffering, how many deaths upon which their
conclusions were based, might have been avoided had those who became statistics for a
government report listened to the word of revelation given by a prophet of God.
</p><p>
As I reflected on that situation&mdash;the months of research by able men of science, the vast
calculations of electronic computers, the great fanfare of announcements, the background
stories, the editorials, the debates, all of this and more, in contrast with the simple, revealed
word of the Lord&mdash;there came to mind the experience of Elijah on Mt. Horeb, as sung so
beautifully by this chorus at the opening of this meeting: ". . . and a great and strong wind
rent the mountains, and brake in pieces the rocks before the Lord; but the Lord was not in the
wind: and after the wind an earthquake; but the Lord was not in the earthquake:
</p><p>
"And after the earthquake a fire; but the Lord was not in the fire: and after the fire a still
small voice" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/11-12#11">1 Kgs. 19:11-12</a>).
</p><p>
Such almost invariably has been the word of God as it has come to us, not with trumpets, not
from the council halls of the learned but in the still small voice of revelation. Listening to
those who seek in vain to find wisdom and who declaim loudly their nostrums for the ills of
the world, one is prone to reply with the Psalmist, "Be still, and know that I
am God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/46/10#10">Ps. 46:10</a>) and with the Savior,
"He that hath ears to hear, let him hear"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/15#15">Matt. 11:15</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Wisdom by Revelation</b>
</p><p>
I wish to make it clear that I do not disparage education, research, study, counsel. I believe
most strongly in these. But I believe more so that this troubled world would do well to listen
to the source of all true wisdom, to accept all that God has revealed, all that he does now
reveal, and to believe that he will yet reveal many great and important things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
Let it be remembered that "the things of God are understood by the Spirit of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11#11">1 Cor. 2:11</a>), and that
revelation is fruitless unless it be listened to and obeyed.
</p><p>
We have a simple and marvelous hymn among us. It came from the pen of an English
convert, an orphan boy, a man of Sheffield, a cutler in the steel mills, who more than a
century ago wrote out of the testimony of his soul this great song of gratitude, "We thank
thee, O God, for a Prophet to guide us in these latter days."
</p><p>
<b>Revelation for the Atomic Age</b>
</p><p>
To the world we give our witness that there is revelation of the word of God as certainly in
the atomic age as there was in the age of Jeremiah. It is just that simple and just that true.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith was the anointed of the Lord to this dispensation. Well might we repeat the
words of the Lord: ". . .What power shall stay the heavens? As well might man stretch forth
his puny arm to stop the Missouri river in its decreed course, or to turn it up stream, as to
hinder the Almighty from pouring down knowledge from heaven upon the heads of the
Latter-day Saints" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/33#33">D&amp;C 121:33</a>).
Knowledge has been and is being revealed. Those who
accept is and obey it find that peace which passeth understanding
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/4/7#7">Philip. 4:7</a>) and that growth which leads
to eternal life.
</p><p>
As surely as Joseph was a Prophet, so also is his successor in office, President David O.
McKay, who has stood before us this day. Who, seeing this man of God this morning
standing at this pulpit and speaking to the world words that would save them, could doubt
that God is manifesting his will through him?
</p><p>
God help us to be obedient to his counsel.
</p><p>
Of these truths we testify and invite men of goodwill everywhere to listen and learn and
partake of that peace and that growth which our Father would have us enjoy, I humbly pray
in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
