<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Organization of the Church of Christ</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Howard W. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Howard W. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 111-115</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The scholars of ecclesiastical history cannot date the time of the commencement of the
Church of Christ. There is no specific event or any certain occurrence in the writings of the
New Testament upon which they can agree as being the definite beginning. The Church came
into existence over a period of time in which there were many important events. The
groundwork was laid by a ministry which changed the lives and thinking of those who
became the body of Christ. After the commencement of the ministry of Jesus, his followers
were many. Mark said, "And immediately his fame spread abroad throughout all the region
round about Galilee" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/1/28#28">Mark 1:28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Time of Christ</b>
</p><p>
He went from place to place teaching in the cities and in the synagogues, and the people
gathered to hear him. They were impressed by his teachings and astonished by his power to
heal the sick. He taught them as they came to ask questions and he conversed with them in
small groups along the wayside. On many occasions great multitudes gathered to hear the one
who often called himself the Shepherd (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/14#14">John 10:14</a>).
Many believed upon him, and some he called to
follow after him. Groups of believers sprang up in Jerusalem and in many other places.
</p><p>
This period of time becomes the focal point of history. We measure time by the years that
have preceded Christ and by the years that have come after him. His life, teachings, death,
and resurrection in the center of time have had a profound effect upon all those who have
lived since his ministry and all those who died prior to his resurrection. The establishment of
his Church has blessed all Christendom
</p><p>
<b>"Some say that thou art John, Elias, Jeremias"</b>
</p><p>
Some writers, seeking a doctrinal beginning rather than a specific event for the
commencement of the Church of Christ, give great weight to the reply of the Lord when Peter
bore his testimony that Jesus was the Christ. It was on the occasion when they were near
Caesarea Philippi that Jesus asked his disciples, "Whom do men say that I the Son of man
am?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/13#13">Matt. 16:13</a>). It doesn't seem reasonable to suppose that he didn't know what people
thought and were saying about him. He was giving his disciples the opportunity to express
their faith and to be strengthened. "And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist:
some, Elias; and others, Jeremias, or one of the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/14#14">Matt. 16:14</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Thou art the Christ"</b>
</p><p>
The Pharisees believed, of course, that the soul is imperishable and the soul of a good person
passes into another body while the soul of the wicked suffers eternal punishment. "He saith
unto them, But whom say ye that I am?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/15#15">Matt. 16:15</a>).
The Master may have been prompted
to ask this question because of their surroundings. Caesarea Philippi is near the grotto and the
temples of the Greek god Pan, a center of pagan worship, and he may have wanted his
disciples to think about the contrast between pagan gods and the true God. "And Simon Peter
answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16#16">Matt. 16:16</a>). In answer
to this positive testimony of Peter, ". . . Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou,
Simon Bar-jona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in
heaven.
</p><p>
"And I say also unto thee, That thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and
the gates of hell shall not prevail against it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/17-18#17">Matt. 16:17-18</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Upon this rock, I will build my Church"</b>
</p><p>
This is a very significant statement. The Lord in effect said to Peter that this knowledge that
Jesus was the Christ did not come to him from mortal men or from the reasoning or learning
of men, but by revelation from on high, that is, direct, divine revelation of the divinity of the
Master. In answer to the statement "Thou art the Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16#16">Matt. 16:16</a>),
Jesus replied, ". . . thou art Peter" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18#18">Matt. 16:18</a>) in
friendly acknowledgment of his disciple. The Lord then added, ". . . and upon this rock I will
build my church" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18#18">Matt. 16:18</a>). Upon what rock? Peter? Upon a man? No, not upon a man, upon the rock
of revelation, the thing which they were talking about. He had just said, ". . . flesh and blood
hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/17#17">Matt. 16:17</a>). This revelation that Jesus is
the Christ is the foundation upon which he would build his Church.
</p><p>
<b>Pentecost</b>
</p><p>
There are others who, searching for the commencement of the Church of Christ, point to the
day the apostles were engaged in the devotions of the Pentecost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/1#1">Acts 2:1</a>). This was only nine days after
the ascension of the Savior of the world. The date becomes important because it was on this
occasion that the baptism by fire and the Holy Ghost descended upon the apostles as had been
promised by Jesus
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/49#49">Luke 24:49</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/7#7">John 16:7</a>).
They began to speak in other tongues as the spirit gave them utterance.
When the Jews heard of this, a crowd gathered and Peter, the president of the Twelve, stood
before them and delivered that great sermon condemning them for the sin of disbelief that the
one crucified by them was the Christ. "Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their
heart, and said unto Peter and to the rest of the apostles, Men and brethren, what shall we do?
</p><p>
"Then Peter said unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus
Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37-38#37">Acts 2:37-38</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Followers of the Messiah</b>
</p><p>
Even though this event may be accepted by some as the origin of the organized Church, it has
deeper meaning. The power of the Holy Ghost descended upon the apostles as the Savior had
promised, bringing to them a dynamic conviction that they were the followers of the Messiah
of whom the prophets of old had spoken, who had come to earth in fulfillment of these
prophecies completed his mission, had been crucified and resurrected as the Savior of all
mankind.
</p><p>
<b>The Church of Christ</b>
</p><p>
It might be best said that the Church was founded as the result of the personal ministry of
Christ and also by the testimony of the apostles who made the person and divine work of
Christ known to men. This testimony on the day of Pentecost touched the hearts of those who
listened. Apparently all of the apostles preached on that occasion, some in one language and
some in another, so that all understood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/4-13#4">Acts 2:4-13</a>).
They bore witness of the death, resurrection, and
ascension of Christ; and out of the great multitude which had been taught on that day, three
thousand were baptized (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/41#41">Acts 2:41</a>).
</p><p>
The earliest account of communal church life in the New Testament describes those who were
baptized on the day of Pentecost in these words: "And they continued steadfastly in the
apostles' doctrine and fellowship, and in the breaking of bread, and in prayers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/42#42">Acts 2:42</a>).
People of a common belief are drawn together because they enjoy a community of interest,
and the church becomes the center of this life because there is comfort and support in the
association of those who share the same understanding.
</p><p>
<b>"He ordained Twelve"</b>
</p><p>
During his lifetime the Master selected the apostles, and Mark states, "And he ordained twelve,
that they should be with him, and that he might send them forth to preach,
</p><p>
"And have the power to heal sicknesses, and to cast out devils"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/3/14-15#14">Mark 3:14-15</a>). God the
Father had sent his Son into the world to bring salvation to the world. The Son chose apostles,
conferred upon them authority, and said to them, "Go ye therefore, and teach all nations,
baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost: 
</p><p>
"Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you: and, lo, I am with
you alway, even unto the end of the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>).
The atoning sacrifice of Christ
brings redemption from the grave to all men, but in addition to this it is necessary that there
be witnesses to the divinity of Christ and his death and resurrection. To be such a witness was
inherent in the call and the ordination of the Twelve.
</p><p>
<b>Authority Over the Whole Church</b>
</p><p>
The apostles were not local officers of the Church. Their authority extended over the whole
Church and to all of the world, to the Jews and to the gentiles. In the same manner that the
apostles were clothed with authority, they empowered other officers of the Church to carry
forward the work as it grew and spread. Elders were ordained in the branches as local
officers. The record is not clear as to when the first elders were ordained, but we find
reference to this office in the Jerusalem Church at an early date. In the missionary tours of
Paul and Barnabas they ordained elders in the branches they established. Paul makes reference
to his meeting with the elders in Ephesus as he was traveling to Jerusalem 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/20/17#17">Acts 20:17</a>). The government
of the local branch was in the hands of a body of men called elders, and they were charged
with the instruction and the leadership. The term elder is also used in the New Testament in a
general way and refers to any ecclesiastical function such as apostles, pastors, bishops, or
other church officers. In his exhortation to the elders of the Church, the Apostle Peter refers
to himself as a fellow elder (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/5/1#1">1 Pet. 5:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Call of the Seventy</b>
</p><p>
Another step in the organization of the Church was the selection and call of the seventy who
were sent two and two as missionaries into the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/1-24#1">Luke 10:1-24</a>). Mention is also made
of the priests of the Levitical order and high priests after the order of Melchizedek
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/1-6#1">Heb. 5:1-6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/7/11#11">Heb. 7:11</a>).
Until the time of Christ there appears to have been no other office in the
Levitical Priesthood than that of priest, but in the writings of Paul he includes the office of
teacher (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>).
</p><p>
One of the important ministers of the early Church was the deacon. The name comes from the
Greek verb meaning to minister or to serve. Although his duties are not fully set forth, it
appears that he was the assistant to the bishop and received his assignment of duty from the
bishop. The deacons were the ones who received the offerings of the members and served to
the Church the bread and wine of the consecrated sacrament.
</p><p>
<b>Bishops Preside Over the local Church</b>
</p><p>
The bishop in the Church of Christ was the one who presided over the local church
community. He was the chief pastor of the flock. He was ordained to his office by an apostle
in the usual manner by prayer and the laying on of hands. He was responsible for the
preaching and teachings in his church, although he could delegate many of the functions to
others. All things were done under his authority and direction, and the officers and those
holding the lesser priesthood were subordinate and took their instruction and direction from
him. He administered the offerings of the people and the charity to those in need. As the
judge he determined the standing of the members of the Church and had the power to
excommunicate. In short the bishop was the chief priest, pastor, and presiding officer of his
church.
</p><p>
<b>Modern Church Organizations</b>
</p><p>
Modern Christian churches have not found it important to have the organization or officers as
existed in the primitive Church as founded by Christ and those he called and ordained for this
purpose. This is evidenced by the fact that the original organization and officers are lacking in
these churches today. If modern Christian churches claim to follow after the Church
established by Christ, it would seem that they would follow the same organization. They
assert, however, that it is not necessary that there be continuation of the organization of the
primitive Church.
</p><p>
<b>Apostolic Succession</b>
</p><p>
This same argument is used with respect to the subject of apostolic succession. Those who
make this claim say that there cannot be apostles except those chosen by Christ during his
ministry. This is based on the premise that an apostle must be a witness of the resurrected
Savior and because there have been no appearances since his ascension, there cannot be such
a witness. This gives rise to the belief that no new apostle could succeed one who died. We
remember, however, that Matthias was called to take the place of Judas
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/21-26#21">Acts 1:21-26</a>). The answer of the
proponents is that he did not take the place of one who died, but rather one who had forfeited
his office because he had been unfaithful by betraying Jesus. A succession is nevertheless
admitted. As proof that there was no succession on the death of an apostle, the case of James
the son of Zebedee is cited (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/12/2#2">Acts 12:2</a>).
The record does not state there was no successor, it is merely
silent. There is some evidence that James the brother of the Lord may have been ordained a
successor member of the Twelve, because he took a prominent part in the council at
Jerusalem and was with Peter in the leadership of the apostles. And Paul said of him, "Then
after three years I went up to Jerusalem to see Peter, and abode with him fifteen days.
</p><p>
"But other of the apostles saw I none, save James the Lord's brother"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/1/18-19#18">Gal. 1:18-19</a>). We
have little information concerning the acts of some of the apostles, and there are a number of
whom we have no information after the time of their calling.
</p><p>
<b>Paul</b>
</p><p>
Paul was not one of the named Twelve, and the writings of the New Testament make it clear
that he was not a witness of the Savior prior to his ascension, yet Paul claimed the apostleship
undoubtedly from his experience as he journeyed to Damascus. Paul referred in his writings to
a number of other persons as apostles who were not named as the Twelve. Because the record
gives no information concerning them, scholars cannot ascertain if they were successors or if
the word "apostle" was used in another sense. In any event, it would be fallacious to argue
that because the record is silent it must be inferred that there was no succession.
</p><p>
The last and perhaps the weakest argument of all is that there is no need for apostolic
succession because their testimony has been preserved for future generations by the writings
of the New Testament. This of course violates all of the rules of evidence because the
witnesses' lips have been sealed in death.
</p><p>
<b>Today, the same organization as the primitive Church</b>
</p><p>
There exists today in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints the organization of the
primitive Church of Christ with the same officers that have been mentioned: deacons,
teachers, priests, bishop, elders, seventies, high priests, and apostles. Without taking into
consideration revelation which reestablishes this organization, reason alone would dictate that
Christ's Church should be the same today as when organized under his direction.
</p><p>
The principles embodied in the gospel of Jesus Christ are everlasting. It would logically
follow that the Church founded upon these eternal and everlasting principles would have the
same organization as that established under his direction, and it would be difficult to show
good reason for the necessity of change or improvement. The historical facts themselves bear
out that there has been a falling away, a corruption of the original, an unauthorized change of
church organization in modern churches.
</p><p>
I have a personal conviction that after the long period of spiritual darkness in the world, the
gospel has been restored in its fullness through divine revelation, and the Church of Christ has
again been established on earth; that this restored Church has the same organization that
existed in the original Church, including those of apostolic calling who do bear witness of the
divinity of Christ, his death, and resurrection, and that he is the Son of God. To their witness,
I humbly add my witness in the name of the Savior of the world. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
