<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Need for a Prophet</p>  
<p class="gcspeaker">President Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Acting President of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 117-122</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The proceedings of this day have been most impressive and awesome. May I extend to Elder
Boyd K. Packer a warm welcome personally and for the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles. We
have watched him grow since his first days as an Assistant to this day of highest call. Here he
will find true fraternity in its highest reach.
</p><p>
We welcome also to the ranks of the General Authorities Elder Joseph Anderson, whom we have
loved and appreciated these many years, and Elder David B. Haight and Elder William H.
Bennett, men of power and dedication and long service.
</p><p>
<b>A new era begins</b>
</p><p>
This is a notable year in this world's life. It is January. History swings on its hinges. Another
page is turned and a new era comes to the front.
</p><p>
It is Sunday morning, January 18, 1970. A great heart stops beating and an aged body relaxes
and slumbers. Like an earthquake sends a tidal wave around the earth, communications now
cover the earth and millions of serious-minded people in even faraway places stop to pay
saddened tribute to a mighty man of God who has passed from mortality.
</p><p>
For days, long lines of loving followers inch their way along the street, even in the rain, to see
once more the visage of their departed leader.
</p><p>
The Tabernacle is crowded with those who loved him, and sweet tributes are paid.
</p><p>
The earthly body of the prophet, David O. McKay, is laid to rest in dignified reverence.
</p><p>
Our heads are bowed, our hearts are hurting, but there will be a happy reunion when this inspired
prophet joins the hosts of his peers&mdash;the Josephs, the Brighams, and the Wilfords.
</p><p>
In our feeling of emptiness, it hardly seems that we could go on without him; but as one star
sinks behind the horizon, another comes into the picture, and death spawns life.
</p><p>
The work of the Lord is endless. Even when a powerful leader dies, not for a single instant is the
Church without leadership, thanks to the kind Providence who gave his kingdom continuity and
perpetuity. As it already has happened eight times before in this dispensation, a people
reverently close a grave, dry their tears, and turn their faces to the future.
</p><p>
<b>The Quorum of the Twelve</b>
</p><p>
The moment life passes from a President of the Church, a body of men become the composite
leader&mdash;these men already seasoned with experience and training. The appointments have long
been made, the authority given, the keys delivered. For five days, the kingdom moves forward
under this already authorized council. No "running" for position, no electioneering, no stump
speeches. What a divine plan! How wise our Lord, to organize so perfectly beyond the weakness
of frail, grasping humans.
</p><p>
Then dawns the notable day (January 23, 1970), and 14 serious men walk reverently into the
temple of God&mdash;this, the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles, the governing body of The Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, several of whom have experienced this solemn change before.
</p><p>
<b>A new prophet</b>
</p><p>
When these 14 men emerge from the holy edifice later in the morning, a transcendently vital
event has occurred&mdash;a short interregnum ends, and the government of the kingdom shifts back
again from the Quorum of the Twelve Apostles to a new prophet, an individual leader, the Lord's
earthly representative, who has unostentatiously been moving toward this lofty calling for 60
years. He now presides over the Church.
</p><p>
Not because of his name, however, did he accede to this high place, but because when he was a
very young man, he was called of the Lord, through the then living prophet, to be an
apostle&mdash;member of the Quorum&mdash;and was given the precious, vital keys to hold in suspension pending a
time when he might become the senior apostle and the President.
</p><p>
In that eventful temple meeting, when he has been "ordained and set apart" as the President of
the Church by his brethren, the Twelve, he chooses his counselors&mdash;two mighty men of valor:
Elder Harold B. Lee and Elder Nathan Eldon Tanner, with their rich background as teachers,
businessmen, public officials, and especially Church leaders.
</p><p>
And a presidency of three and a newly constituted Council of Twelve walk humbly to their
offices without fanfare or ostentation, and a new administration moves into a new period with
promise of great development and unprecedented growth.
</p><p>
<b>Presidents of the Church</b>
</p><p>
It was a very young man who introduced the restored program to this new world. Joseph Smith
(December 23, 1805&mdash;June 27, 1844) was but 24 years of age when the Church was organized.
</p><p>
When he was martyred at 38, the second President, Brigham Young (June 1, 1801&mdash;August 29,
1877) became senior apostle and the President of the Church (December 27, 1847) at 46 years of
age and presided 30 years (until he was 76). The other Presidents, each in his turn, became
President at ages ranging from 62 to 84, and died at ages 79 to 96.
</p><p>
John Taylor (November 1, 1808&mdash;July 25, 1887) was 71 when he became President of the
Church (October 10, 1880) and died at 78, and upon his death, Wilford Woodruff (March 1,
1807&mdash;September 2, 1898) became the senior apostle (July 25, 1887). Two years later (April 7,
1889), he was sustained President of the Church at 82 years of age. He died at 91, whereupon
President Lorenzo Snow (April 3, 1814&mdash;October 10, 1901) became the senior apostle. He was
84 years of age when he became the President of the Church (September 13, 1898). His
presidency was short-lived. He served about three years (until October 10, 1901).
</p><p>
President Joseph F. Smith (November 13, 1838&mdash;November 19, 1918) was senior apostle (from
October 10, 1901) seven days; he became the President of the Church October 17, 1901, at 62
years of age; he died at 80.
</p><p>
President Heber J. Grant (November 22, 1856&mdash;May 14, 1945) was senior apostle less than a
week (on November 23, 1918), when he became the President of the Church at 62; he died at 88.
</p><p>
President George Albert Smith (April 4, 1870&mdash;April 4, 1951) was the senior apostle for seven
days and became President of the Church (May 21, 1945) at 75; he died at the age of 81. Last
Saturday was his one hundredth birthday.
</p><p>
President David O. McKay, the ninth President (September 8, 1873&mdash;January 18, 1970) was
senior apostle five days and was sustained as President of the Church (April 9, 1951) at 77; he
died at the age of 96.
</p><p>
President Joseph Fielding Smith, whose birthdate is July 19, 1876, became the senior apostle
January 18, and President of the Church January 23, 1970, at the age of 93.
</p><p>
<b>Average ages</b>
</p><p>
The Presidents from John Taylor to David O. McKay, inclusive, became President at ages
ranging from 62 to 84 and died at ages from 79 to 96.
</p><p>
It is interesting to note that these eight Church Presidents assumed their presiding responsibility
at an average age of 73 years, and relinquished it by death at 85 years. They served an average of
a little less than 12 years; consequently, the average age of the living President of the Church has
been about 79 years.
</p><p>
We may expect the Church President will always be an older man; young men have action,
vigor, initiative; older men, stability and strength and wisdom through experience and long
communion with God.
</p><p>
In President McKay's declining days, speculation ran high among the curious and the concerned
and the less knowledgeable and continued as a major topic of discussion through the
interregnum.
</p><p>
More than a million members had never known any other President than David O. McKay;
consequently, it was natural for some to be confused.
</p><p>
They talked about age. The old patriarchs were not young. Adam was very old as he presided
over his posterity, which spread over many generations. Abraham, Isaac, Joseph, and Moses
presided over the people, dying at 175, 180, 110, and 120 years. They were old in years, but from
their accumulated experience came massive wisdom and security.
</p><p>
<b>The senior apostle</b>
</p><p>
People talk about precedent. If it is precedent, it has become such by the repetition of the
revealed order since the beginning. Brigham Young was the senior apostle, holding all the keys
and authorities, and in the present case, President Smith was the senior apostle. This is the way
of the Lord, and he retains the leadership in his divine hands.
</p><p>
When the first succession took place, the restored church was an infant only 14 years old. There
had been no prophet nor "open vision" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/3/1#1">1 Sam. 3:1</a>) for numerous centuries. Little wonder, then, that the
people should be full of questions when the bullets at Carthage terminated the life of the one in
whom all these priceless blessings&mdash;the church, revelation, prophets&mdash;seemed to be centered.
When the apostles returned from their missions, had buried their dead prophet, and considered
the future, all doubt was dissipated when the senior apostle, already holding all the keys, stood
forth like Moses and led the way.
</p><p>
<b>Succession in presidency</b>
</p><p>
The editorial of September 2, 1844, on the succession said: 
</p><p>
"Great excitement prevails throughout to know 'who shall be the successor of Joseph Smith!'
</p><p>
"In reply we say, be <i>patient</i>, be patient a little till the proper time comes, and we will tell you all.
'Great wheels move slow.' At present, we can say that a special conference of the church was
held in Nauvoo on the 8th, ult., and it was carried <i>without a dissenting voice</i>, that the 'Twelve'
should preside over the whole church, and when any alteration in the presidency shall be
required, seasonable notice will be given; and the elders abroad, will best exhibit their wisdom
to all men, by remaining silent on those things they are ignorant of." (<i>Times and Seasons</i>, Vol. 5,
Sept. 2, 1844, p. 632.)
</p><p>
This eventful 140 years has seen ten Presidents preside over the Church and 78 apostles serve in
the Quorum of the Twelve.
</p><p>
<b>President Joseph Fielding Smith</b>
</p><p>
As we tighten our tugs and strain our weight against the collar, we move forward on a new
journey with a strong will under our inspired leaders, led by our prophet, Joseph Fielding Smith.
</p><p>
He is venerable and worthy of respect by reason of his character, dignity, age, position. He is one
of whom his beloved wife sang this morning, one who has "clean hands and a pure heart, who
has not lifted up his soul unto vanity, nor sworn deceitfully." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/24/4#4">Ps. 24:4</a>) He is a son of his Maker and a
clean and holy man of God. He takes his high place as the appointee of the Lord. He has carried
for 60 years the keys of the kingdom, gradually moving toward this day. For six decades he has
been sustained by the Church as <i>a</i> prophet. Today he is sustained as <i>the</i> Prophet, the one who
alone holds the keys in total use under the Lord Jesus Christ, who is the chief cornerstone, and
the head of his church.
</p><p>
<b>A prophet-leader who gives example</b>
</p><p>
To be a prophet of the Lord, one does not need to "be everything to all men." He does not need
to be youthful and athletic, an industrialist, a financier, nor an agriculturist; he does not need to
be a musician, a poet, an entertainer, nor a banker, a physician, nor a college president, a
military general, nor a scientist.
</p><p>
He does not need to be a linguist to speak French and Japanese, German and Spanish, but he
must understand the divine language and be able to receive messages from heaven.
</p><p>
He need not be an orator, for God can make his own. The Lord can present his divine messages
through weak men made strong. He substituted a strong voice for the quiet, timid one of Moses,
and gave to the young man Enoch power which made men tremble in his presence, for Enoch
walked with God as Moses walked with God.
</p><p>
The Lord said: ". . . whether by mine own voice or by the voice of my servants, it is the same."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/38#38">D&amp;C 1:38</a>)
</p><p>
What the world needs is a prophet-leader who gives example&mdash;clean, full of faith, godlike in his
attitudes with an untarnished name, a beloved husband, a true father.
</p><p>
<b>The voice of God</b>
</p><p>
A prophet needs to be more than a priest or a minister or an elder. His voice becomes the voice
of God to reveal new programs, new truths, new solutions. I make no claim of infallibility for
him, but he does need to be recognized of God, an authoritative person. He is no pretender as
numerous are who presumptuously assume position without appointment and authority that is
not given. He must speak like his Lord: ". . . as one having authority, and not as the scribes."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/29#29">Matt. 7:29</a>)
</p><p>
He must be bold enough to speak truth even against popular clamor for lessening restrictions. He
must be certain of his divine appointment, of his celestial ordination, and his authority to call to
service, to ordain, to pass keys which fit eternal locks.
</p><p>
He must have commanding power like prophets of old: ". . . to seal both on earth and in heaven,
the unbelieving and rebellious . . . unto the day when the wrath of God shall be poured out upon
the wicked without measure" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/8-9#8">D&amp;C 1:8-9</a>), and rare powers: ". . . that whatsoever you seal on
earth shall be sealed in heaven; and whatsoever you bind on earth, in my name and by my word,
saith the Lord, it shall be eternally bound in the heavens; and whosesoever sins you remit on
earth shall be remitted eternally in the heavens; and whosesoever sins you retain on earth shall
be retained in heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/46#46">D&amp;C 132:46</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The need for prophets</b>
</p><p>
What is needed is more a Moses than a Pharaoh; an Elijah then a Belshazzar; a Paul than a
Pontius Pilate.
</p><p>
He needs not be an architect to construct houses and schools and high-rise buildings, but he will
be one who builds structures to span time and eternity and to bridge the gap between man and
his Maker.
</p><p>
When the world has followed prophets, it has moved forward; when it has ignored them, the
results have been stagnation, servitude, death.
</p><p>
Every moment of every day, there are numerous programs on the air. We hear very few,
relatively, for we are engrossed in our day's duties, but with powerful beaming broadcasting
stations, we could hear any of the programs if we are tuned in.
</p><p>
<b>Broadcasts of vital messages</b>
</p><p>
For thousands of years there have been constant broadcasts from heaven of vital messages of
guidance and timely warnings, and there has been a certain constancy in the broadcasts from the
most powerful station. Throughout all those centuries there have been times when there were
prophets who tuned in and rebroadcasted to the people. The messages have never ceased.
</p><p>
One such message came to Daniel in the presence of others, and he who was on the proper
frequency said: "And I Daniel alone saw the vision: for the men that were with me saw not the
vision." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/10/7#7">Dan. 10:7</a>)
</p><p>
On the road to Damascus, a company of men traveled together. A spectacular event came from
the heavens, but only one man was in tune to receive it. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/7#7">Acts 9:7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/9#9">Acts 22:9</a>) That which was but static to all the other
ears was an awesome call to duty to Saul of Tarsus, and changed his life, and contributed toward
the transformation of millions of lives, but he was the only one who was attuned.
</p><p>
<b>Spiritual not understood by finite</b>
</p><p>
It is said that certain Russian fliers reported that as they penetrated the far outer space, they saw
no God nor angels. Our prediction to any unbelieving, godless spacemen is that though they
could go a thousand times farther and a thousand times higher, that they will be still farther from
God and eternal things, for the spiritual is not understood by the finite.
</p><p>
Abraham found God on a tower in Mesopotamia, on a mount in Palestine, and in royal quarters
in Egypt. Moses found him on a backside desert; at a red sea; on a mount called Sinai; and in a
"burning bush" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/3/1-4#1">Ex. 3:1-4</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/17#17">Moses 1:17</a>). Joseph Smith found him in the cool freshness of a primeval forest and on a hill
called Cumorah. Peter found him at the Sea of Galilee and on the Mount of Transfiguration.
</p><p>
<b>Sustaining of new prophet</b>
</p><p>
May the Lord, our God, sustain this newly appointed prophet, Joseph Fielding Smith, who will
from this time "be about his Father's business," (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>) who will continue to serve the Lord's "bread of
life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/6/35#35">John 6:35</a>) and "living water," (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/10#10">John 4:10</a>) who will now begin "to light the lamps of Israel" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/num/8/3#3">Num. 8:3</a>) and verily become the
mouthpiece of God; and our prayer is that the Lord will speak to him as he did to Joshua: 
</p><p>
"This day will I begin to magnify thee in the sight of all Israel, that they may know that, as I was
with Moses, so I will be with thee." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/3/7#7">Josh. 3:7</a>)
</p><p>
And may the Lord bless us, his servants, who have raised our hands this day, and all others
without that opportunity, that from this time forth we may, like the children of Israel, uphold his
hands and shout as did the children of Israel in one voice: 
</p><p>
"All that thou commandest us we will do, and whithersoever thou sendest us, we will go.
</p><p>
"According as we have hearkened unto Moses in all things, so will we hearken unto thee: only
the Lord thy God be with thee, as he was with Moses." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/1/16-17#16">Josh. 1:16-17</a>)
</p><p>
"To your tents, O Israel," (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/12/16#16">1 Kgs. 12:16</a>) stand firm and loyal and immovable.
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
