<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">When the Spirit Speaks</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Seymour Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 116-117</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Yesterday Elder Marion G. Romney mentioned the matter of the Holy Spirit and said that one
does not hear it with his ears. May I read to you a verse of scripture which verifies that.
Nephi was rebuking his two brothers who were intent upon killing him as they journeyed
toward the Promised Land. He reminded them that they thought to murder his father, but also
their intent was to murder him, and therefore in their hearts they were murderers. Then he
reminded them of the times which the Lord had tried to impress them in these words: 
</p><p>
"Ye have seen an angel, and he spake unto you; yea, ye have heard his voice from time to
time; and he hath spoken unto you in a still small voice,"&mdash;and this is the part I would like to
have you hear&mdash;"but ye were past feeling, that ye could not feel his words"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/45#45">1 Ne. 17:45</a>).
</p><p>
I used to wonder why Nephi didn't say "hear his words." Now I know that one doesn't hear
them with his ears, as Brother Romney said. But into a person's mind there come words.
These seem to be his own words, but with the Spirit upon him, are not his words. With these
words comes a feeling. One actually feels the words, just as Nephi said. These brothers had
lost that feeling, and therefore could not detect words given by the Spirit as apart from their
own thoughts.
</p><p>
This "feeling" comes to all who will hear. One's first experience in this likely is akin to those
of all converts to the Church when they read what Moroni said. He told
them that after they had heard these things, if they would ask God they would know of their
truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4#4">Moro. 10:4</a>).
I believe that James was referring to this fundamental truth when he
wrote these words, "If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>). The
Prophet Joseph, reading, was impressed to go to the woods and pray. Anybody who cannot
learn to hear by feeling will not go very far in the Church, in my humble opinion, for I
believe that to be the way the majority of us know if these things are true.
</p><p>
By that Spirit which whispers in my soul, and which I feel with my heart and my feelings at
the same time, the knowledge of which rings constantly in my whole being, I know that
Joseph Smith received many of his revelations by that means. By that whispered feeling, too,
I know that he was a prophet of the Living God and that President McKay is likewise a
prophet of the Living God. I would ask only one thing, that each of us as we leave this
conference ask ourselves if during any of these meetings, we felt in our hearts the whispering,
and had the words form into our minds as the whispering became feeling, and the message
came clearly into our minds that the speaker has spoken truly. "That is true doctrine. He is
speaking truth to us," it tries to say.
</p><p>
To me this conference has been filled with that type of thing. I am proud to be a member of
the Church. I am delighted to have the opportunity of bearing my testimony that I know these
things are true, and I do it in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
