<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 107-111</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is indeed an inspiring sight to stand here and look into the faces of the thousands of holders
of the priesthood in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. I have been thinking
while sitting here tonight that there is more divine authority, more right to use that divine
authority in this building tonight than in all of the rest of the world combined. We have here
the President of the Church, who holds the keys of the priesthood, the keys of the kingdom of
God; we have here the General Authorities, who have been delegated certain rights, authority,
and power of that priesthood, and we have many other holders of the priesthood in this
audience. I trust and pray that we will carry on our work in this priesthood in a desirable way
before our Heavenly Father. I trust that the few words that I say tonight will be inspired by
the Spirit of God, because I do feel a weakness in standing before this great assembly.
</p><p>
THE CONDITIONS AT THE CLOSE OF THE WAR
</p><p>
We are all rejoicing during recent days in the fact that the terrible war has come to a close
and that the ruthless killings and destruction have been replaced by peace. I, with all of you,
hope and pray that all of God's children throughout the entire world will cooperate with our
Heavenly Father and his Only Begotten Son in bringing about a permanent peace; but such
will be the case only when we all accept and obey the pattern of life established by the
Savior, which is conducive to peace.
</p><p>
For a number of years human life has been regarded by the leaders of many nations of the
earth as being very cheap. Thousands, yes, millions, of men and women have been ruthlessly
sacrificed on the fields of battle. The philosophy of some of the major races of people has
completely disregarded the sacredness of human life. Instead of honoring the dignity and
worth of mankind, these nations referred to have honored and practically worshipped the glory
of the group that is, the strength, power, and hope of world-dominance by their nation or race. I believe that throughout the world, generally speaking, the
philosophies of men have almost completely disregarded the sacredness and purpose of human
life; therefore, I feel a definite need today to present a few ideas regarding the Mormons'
concept of the sacredness and purpose of life.
</p><p>
MAN'S EXALTED POSITION IN THE UNIVERSE
</p><p>
Human life is sacred to the Latter-day Saints&mdash;as sacred and precious as anything that
exists&mdash;because of its divine nature. God has revealed to the Prophet Joseph Smith and to the
other holy prophets that we are his children, the divine offspring of heavenly beings. Men and
women in general are the greatest of God's creative work, being made in his own image, and
endowed through inheritance from our heavenly parents with godly characteristics just as
mortal children are endowed with the characteristics of their earthly parents. In other words,
we are gods in embryo, for, as Paul, the apostle to the Gentiles, has said:
</p><p>
. . . [God] hath made of one blood all nations of men for to dwell on all the face of the earth,
. . . For in him we live, and move, and have our being; . . . For we are also his offspring
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/26-28#26">Acts 17:26-28</a>).
</p><p>
All the prophets of the Church from Joseph Smith's day to the present time have confirmed
the teachings of Paul. The following statement was made by President Joseph F. Smith:
</p><p>
Man, as a spirit, was begotten and born of heavenly parents, and reared to maturity in the
eternal mansions of the Father prior to coming upon the earth in a temporal body to undergo
an experience in mortality.
</p><p>
This beautiful doctrine of the divinity of man does not detract in the least from the glory and
great exaltation of God the Eternal Father. It merely dignifies and exalts man and makes
human life more sacred and purposeful. It fills the universe with meaning, with design, and
attaches to life a goal; and an understanding of this doctrine should fill man's heart with love,
charity, and good will toward all of the human family.
</p><p>
If one accepts that he is a son of God, in contrast to the concept that he is the offspring of an
animal, he becomes impressed with the unlimited potential possibilities which are his. His
eyes are turned heavenward instead of toward the ground. His hope is to become
glorified&mdash;exalted&mdash;even like unto his heavenly parents.
</p><p>
Because of the closeness of the relationship between God and man and because of the great
value and sacredness of human life, the Eternal Creator has always shown a special interest in
the human family. He revealed to Father Adam the gospel plan of salvation, and has
continued to reveal to his children from that day forward eternal truths to the full amount and
extent that they were capable of receiving. He has established several gospel dispensations
upon the earth; and throughout the entire course of human history he has earnestly pleaded
with men to live in peace, in love, and in harmony with each other, as advocated in that
divine plan. But ruthless and ungodly men from time to time have disregarded the sacredness
of human life, and have brought wars, suffering, disease, and shame upon the human family.
</p><p>
HUMAN LIFE PRECIOUS IN THE SIGHT OF GOD
</p><p>
In spite of the actions of his children, God has continuously retained his interest in them. He
sent his Only Begotten Son into the world to teach us that we should love the Lord our God
with all our hearts and that we should love our neighbors as ourselves. This divine
teacher&mdash;the Man of Galilee&mdash;attached a sacredness to human life that has never been fully
appreciated nor comprehended by mortals. It is true that chosen Israel had known the
perennial law of "Thou shalt not kill"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/13#13">Ex. 20:13</a>); but the magnificent doctrine declared by the Son of
God was that ". . . there is joy in the presence of the angels of God over the sinner that
repenteth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/10#10">Luke 15:10</a>).
In words of tenderness and power the Master of life and death told
his eager listeners the beautiful parables of "The Lost Sheep," of "The Lost Coin," and that
the well need no physician, but he who is ill
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/9/12#12">Matt. 9:12</a>).
With open arms he cried, "All ye who are sick
and weary come unto me, and I will give you rest"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/28-30#28">Matt. 11:28-30</a>).
Never before had the downtrodden, the
outcast, and the discouraged of the human family received such a powerful ray of light to heal
them of their afflictions and to turn them unto God and unto a better life as when they felt the
power of the message of the Master. Even the sinner learned that he and life were important,
and that there was hope for him to receive something more beautiful, more joyous, and more
godly than he had hitherto experienced.
</p><p>
After delivering a message of peace and hope to a troubled world, Jesus Christ gave his life
as a voluntary sacrifice in order that we might live. Human life is so sacred and so valuable
to the Eternal Father "that he gave his Only Begotten Son in order the we might gain eternal
life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
Even in our day Jesus has again emphasized the importance of a human soul in the
following declaration:
</p><p>
. . . if is so be that you should labor all your days in crying repentance unto this people, and
bring, save it be one soul unto me, how great shall be your joy with him in the kingdom of
my Father! And now, if your joy will be great with one soul that you have brought unto me
into the kingdom of my Father, how great will be your joy if you should bring many souls
unto me! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15-16#15">D&amp;C 18:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
It is no wonder that the angels of heaven rejoice when God's children repent and seek after
eternal life (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/10#10">Luke 15:10</a>).
</p><p>
THE RELIGION OF THE LATTER-DAY SAINTS A PRACTICAL ONE
</p><p>
Another reason why Mormons maintain that life is sacred is that God has revealed to them
that life is eternal. We believe that we build our own characters through the actions we
commit&mdash;whether they be evil or good; and the type of characters we mould for ourselves will
be ours throughout the eternities.
</p><p>
Thus, thinking upon the sacredness and eternal nature of life leads us into the doctrine of the
purpose of life. One of the most clear-cut statements given in the scriptures on the purposes
of life was a remark made by Father Lehi to his children. In his own words: "Men are that
they might have joy" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
That concept is basic in the philosophy of Mormonism. We maintain
that life and religion are the same thing: that religion is a seven-day-a-week concern of our
people, and that it concerns itself with the temporal as well as the spiritual phases of life. To
the Mormons the bread-and-butter problem is as much religion and of interest to our Church
as is attending meetings or taking care of the other spiritual duties. If men have joy in
sufficient abundance, they must have a proper amount of economic prosperity. Therefore, one
of the purposes of life is to arrange, distribute, and equalize wealth in such a manner as to
bring joy to the largest number of people. If the gospel of Jesus Christ were lived as the
Master intends that it should be, all of God's children throughout the world, would enjoy the
blessings derived from economic security
</p><p>
A life of joy is a life free from sin. In the words of another Nephite prophet: "Sin never was
happiness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/41/10#10">Alma 41:10</a>).
It should be said, then, that one of the main purposes of life is to have
opportunities to learn the will of God and choose for ourselves the amount of obedience
which we desire to render. In fact, Mormonism teaches that one of the main purposes of
mortal existence is to give us the opportunity to partake of all the good experiences of
mortality, and through the great principle of faith follow the road of progression and
righteousness which will eventually bring us back into the presence of our Eternal Father and
his Only Begotten Son.
</p><p>
In other words, the Mormon concept of the purpose of life is growth&mdash;growth intellectually,
growth physically, growth morally, and growth spiritually. We call that principle of growth,
eternal progression. Mortality marks one short span in the process, but to us today it is the
most important period, because God has declared that if we keep this estate in righteousness
we shall have glory added upon our heads forever and ever.
</p><p>
The immortal beings in the unseen world and the children of men upon the earth are working
in cooperation to bring about this perpetual growth of human personality. The greatest
revelation ever given on this subject was when God informed Moses as follows:
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of
man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
If we add to this statement the following pertinent remarks made by the Master of life,
wherein he said:
</p><p>
I am come that they [men] might have life, and that they might have it more abundantly
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/10#10">John 10:10</a>).
</p><p>
And again,
</p><p>
. . . this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom
thou hast sent (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>),
</p><p>
then we see more clearly God's purpose of our mortal and eternal existence.
</p><p>
THE WAY TO KNOW GOD
</p><p>
The only way we can know God is to live as he lives, to think as he thinks, and to experience
what he experiences. Interpreted in this light, we are brought face to face with the powerful
Mormon doctrine which declares that "As man is God once was, and as God is man may be."
It is positively true that the growth, the eternal progression, for which life offers opportunities
reach their culminating point in a life patterned after that of Jesus; therefore, it is the purpose
of life to live as the Savior taught us to live and as he himself lived.
</p><p>
I trust in faith to our Heavenly Father that he will help us that we may live that type of life.
Before closing I wish to bear testimony that I am sure that we are all engaged in the work of
God. I feel thankful to him for the opportunity that I have and that you have in the
priesthood, in helping in his great cause. I know that the prophets of the Lord from Joseph
Smith's time, to and including the present President of the Church, are divinely inspired and
called of God our Eternal Father, and I wish to sustain the President of the Church with all
my heart in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
