<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Stand up and Be Counted with the Lord</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Oscar A. Kirkham</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Oscar A. Kirkham, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1950, pp. 31-34</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I pray that I may enjoy the blessings of the Spirit of the Lord. I thank him for my
membership in this Church. I wish I had the power and the ability to make that expression of
appreciation more real, that it might be not only more helpful to me but also
to those with whom I associate.
</p><p>
MUCH GIVEN AND EXPECTED
</p><p>
Much has been given to us. Much is expected of us. I sincerely feel that there never was a
time when greater opportunities faced our Church. I know that every year, every score of
years, brings to that group and that generation like feelings, but truly great things are now
being wrought in the world, and great opportunities now face us. Nations fear each other.
There is much that is being done, but we have a task that challenges truly the best that is
within us, me in my home, you in yours, all of us wherever we may be.
</p><p>
These lines from John: 
</p><p>
He that hath received his testimony has set to his seal that God is true
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/33#33">John 3:33</a>).
</p><p>
BAPTISM OF KARL G. MAESER
</p><p>
I want to refer to the baptism of Karl G. Maeser, one of the great spirits of our Church, one
of the great leaders of the Brigham Young University. Just after his baptism in Germany, he
said these words: 
</p><p>
On coming out of the water, I lifted both my hands to heaven and said, "Father, if
what I have done just now is pleasing unto thee, give me a testimony, and whatever
thou shouldst require of my hands, I shall do, even to the laying down of my life for
this cause" (<i>The Improvement Era</i> 3:25).
</p><p>
Soon after this covenant with the Lord, he and President Franklin D. Richards of the
European Mission received the answer to this promise to the Lord, for while neither one of
them could speak the language of the other, that is, Brother Richards could not speak German,
Karl G. Maeser could not understand English, yet the Lord gave them the gift of tongues and
of understanding. The promise was fulfilled at once. You know, hundreds of you in this
audience today, that the Lord continued his blessings with Karl G. Maeser, for numbered
among his pupils were George Sutherland of the Supreme Court of the United States, Reed
Smoot of the United States Senate, William H. King of the United States Senate, and many,
many others. I feel in like fashion we have also in our hearts with all good intent made a like
promise to the Lord.  And again I repeat, this is our opportunity to prove to the Lord that
promise.
</p><p>
GLORY OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
At one of our recent conferences in one of the stakes, we asked a young lady to tell of her
experience at a national convention. She had received lovely honors. She told the story in
some detail of what had happened at the convention, but then as the detail of
it got wearisome to her, she took hold of the stand and seemed to rise several inches higher as
she said, "I want to bear my testimony. That is what is on my heart." Then this youth in all
her glory expressed what her testimony meant to her.
</p><p>
Years have been somewhat many in my life. I'm easily up to the top of the crest, but I
challenge myself with you, the great majority of this audience, if we do not take the
opportunity that is ours to serve him and courageously do his will, he will bring forward a
generation that will keep his commandments and prove the glory of the gospel of Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
SPIRIT OF AMERICAN YOUTH
</p><p>
I listened to a talented pressman a few days ago who had just returned from Korea. He said
the question was often asked of the soldiers up in the front lines what they were fighting for.
He told only one simple incident. He said they know. Down the highway when thousands of
Koreans were evacuating a city, there came a young fellow in a jeep. In the crowd that was
hurrying on in confusion was an old lady bent with age, a large bundle on her back. The jeep
stopped, the GI boy threw the bundle in, then lifted the old lady into the seat. Down the road
they went to safety. Well, the pressman made quite a bit of that simple incident, and I believe
that I caught the spirit of it. Surely the American youth know what they are fighting for. God
bless them with courage when they return home, that they will take their place and do their
best. May the destiny that is theirs to have and enjoy be with them.
</p><p>
SERVICE OF MISSIONARIES
</p><p>
A like spirit has gone out with 5800 young men and women into different parts of the world.
One simple, yet to me a glorious, experience was enjoyed last month in the East Central
States Mission. As is our custom, we meet with all the missionaries as we go through a
mission. Their testimonies are truly inspiring. We are thrilled as we listen to them. I seldom
leave a meeting but what I have to hold back my tears of pride and joy for the youth of this
Church. I received a lovely reflection of their service in one experience. A brother came to
me after the dedication of one of the little chapels in the mission and said, "Brother Kirkham,
I have been in the Church now for about nineteen years, and I am extremely grateful for what
God has given us. The light and the truth of the gospel has truly enriched my life. Let me tell
you how it happened."
</p><p>
He said: "I had a young missionary come to my home. I used to drink a cocktail occasionally.
I smoked freely, but the young chap clean, sweet in his nature, and in his appearance so
delightful, came to our place and told us that he had something for us. I called Mother in, and
we sat and listened. This continued for several evenings, until one night
when we were quite free in our conversation and felt we knew each other quite well, I took
the liberty of rolling a cigarette. And the young man said: 'I suppose it's time that I told you
about another great principle of the Latter-day Saints.' He said, 'I want to read you what we
call the Word of Wisdom' (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/8#8">D&amp;C 89:8</a>),
and he started to read to me. I had taken the cigarette out of my
mouth and, as this young chap read this Word of Wisdom, something happened to me. I
found myself trying to crush that thing in my fingers. I felt the fire once but held my nerve
and kept crushing it, and I said, as now I say to you, Brother Kirkham, he spoke the truth.
This boy brought me a message from God and cleared up my life."
</p><p>
ACCEPT OPPORTUNITIES
</p><p>
Well, these opportunities are also ours. Just over the fence from where we live is someone
waiting to hear us speak the word. Consider the way we accept our opportunities in
citizenship. Yes, I appeal to every Latter-day Saint: Vote&mdash;it's one of the high privileges of
your American citizenship. Bear your testimony every opportunity that comes to you. "Stand
up and be counted with the Lord."
</p><p>
God bless us and help us that these great hours may to us be great realities and opportunities.
May it be said of us, "Much was given to you; much was expected
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/12/48#48">Luke 12:48</a>); and you did your part."
God bless us and be with us that we may make of our glorious religion a reality. In the name
of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
