<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Why a Prophet?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 144-148</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brothers and sisters, we are about to come to the end of a most inspirational and historic
conference of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints; historic because today we have
voted to sustain the man whom God has chosen to stand at the head of his work here upon this
earth under the direction of his Son Jesus Christ, because this church, as Paul of old said, is built
upon the foundation of apostles and prophets, with Christ our Lord as the chief cornerstone (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20#20">Eph. 2:20</a>). I am sure that those of us who know President Joseph Fielding Smith and the men
whom he has selected to be his counselors feel grateful to the Lord for them. We feel secure in
our hearts to know that this work will continue to roll forth in the earth, building upon the
foundation that has been laid by their predecessors, until it shall become as a great mountain and
fill the whole earth. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/35#35">Dan. 2:35</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Eulogy to Joseph Smith</b>
</p><p>
During this conference, eulogy and compliments have been paid to the Prophet Joseph Smith
and his successors. I think of what the Prophet Lehi said to his son Joseph in the
wilderness&mdash;that the Lord promised Joseph who was sold into Egypt that in the latter days he would raise up
from his loins a prophet whose name would be Joseph, and that his father's name would be
Joseph. (See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/15#15">2 Ne. 3:15</a>) He said he would bring forth his word. He brought us the Book of
Mormon, the Doctrine and Covenants, the Pearl of Great Price, and many other writings. As far
as the records indicate, there has never been a prophet upon the face of the earth who has given
as much revealed truth as we have obtained through this prophet whom God raised up in our
day. And he said he would not only bring forth his word but would also bring men to a
conviction of his word that had already gone forth among them. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/11#11">2 Ne. 3:11</a>)
</p><p>
Now when you talk to men as I have in my missionary work, who have been taught for years,
some even in the ministry, you find that you can talk to them for hours and they have no
questions to ask. You tell them things they have never heard of, and prove these things to them
out of their own scriptures. That I can tell you from my own experience. One man was brought
into the Church who had been a minister for 30 years, and he sat in my office and said, "Brother
Richards, when I think of how little I had to offer my people as a minister of the gospel
compared with what I now have in the fullness of the gospel as it has been restored, I want to go
back and tell all my friends what I have found. Now," he said, "they won't listen to me."
</p><p>
<b>Endowed with authority</b>
</p><p>
The Lord said in his promise to Joseph regarding this prophet of our day that he shall bring men
unto salvation. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/15#15">2 Ne. 3:15</a>) Why? Because he would be endowed with that same authority that Jesus gave to
his twelve when he said, "Ye have not chosen me, but I have chosen you, and ordained you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/16#16">John 15:16</a>). ". . . and whatsoever
thou shalt bind on earth shall be bound in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/19#19">Matt. 16:19</a>).
Without that authority, there can be no Church of Jesus Christ upon the earth
that he will recognize.
</p><p>
The Lord adds in that promise concerning the Prophet Joseph, "And I will make him great in
mine eyes" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/8#8">2 Ne. 3:8</a>). Whatever the world may think of this prophet of this dispensation, there
is the promise and the statement of the Lord that he will be great in his eyes. The Lord had him
in waiting, three thousand years before he was even born, for the great mission to which he was
called, just as the Savior was called to his mission&mdash;not the same kind of mission but of equal
importance in that it was a part of the Lord's great eternal plan for the salvation of his children.
</p><p>
<b>Successors of the prophet</b>
</p><p>
We could refer to each of the successors of the Prophet Joseph Smith. Take Brigham Young, for
instance. I think history records no colonizer like Brigham Young. Just look at what we enjoy
right here in these valleys of the mountains, this tabernacle, that holy temple. The city itself is
part of his work as he led the pioneers to this desert place and built this great commonwealth.
</p><p>
You could consider each of the other prophets who have succeeded him. My father used to bring
us boys here, travel 40 miles by team, so that we could become acquainted with the leaders of
the Church. I remember as a boy sitting in this tabernacle when Wilford Woodruff gave his last
talk (I think it was his last talk before he passed away) when he told how marvelously the Spirit
of the Lord had guided and directed him. He was a man who really lived near the Lord. Now
you've heard his story of how he was inspired to get up in the middle of the night and move his
team that was tied to an oak that had stood on that spot for over a hundred years. Then along
came a twister and picked up that oak and threw it right where his team and wagon in which he
and his wife were sleeping had been standing. If he hadn't listened to the promptings of the
Spirit, this might have cost him his life.
</p><p>
He told about bringing a company of pioneers and Saints from Great Britain. When they landed
in New Orleans, he was about to enter a boat, making arrangements, and something seemed to
say, "Don't go on that boat, either you or your company." So he thanked the captain and decided
to wait. Then he said the boat had no more than sailed up the river when it caught fire and not a
soul was saved. He said, "If I hadn't listened to the promptings of the Spirit of the Lord, we
wouldn't have had Brother So-and-So and Brother So-and-So," and he began naming men who
were in that company.
</p><p>
Now I could go on with the other prophets it has been my privilege to know. How I loved
President Heber J. Grant! He called me to be the Presiding Bishop of the Church. How I loved
President Joseph F. Smith, the father of our new President! He was one of the greatest prophets I
have ever known. I have heard him speak in this tabernacle and bless the people, and I don't
think there was a dry eye here because of the spiritual power that man had. When I had filled
two missions and went in his office to report, he took me in his arms and said, "LeGrand, we
love you." That paid or all the missionary work I had done up to that time.
</p><p>
<b>President David O. McKay</b>
</p><p>
Then I think of President David O. McKay. For years, everywhere we have gone in the Church,
the Saints have said, "Take our love back to President McKay." Even little children would write
their messages and ask us to hand them to the President. What a leader he really was!
</p><p>
I was told the story of a businessman who came here from the East a few years ago, and in
talking to the secretary of the Chamber of Commerce, he said, "Do you know what I'd rather do
than anything else while I'm here?" The secretary said, "What's that?" He said, "I would like to
meet that man, David O. McKay, the President of the Mormon Church." "Well," the secretary
said, "I think I can arrange it." And he did, and President McKay talked to him for about an hour.
As he walked down the front steps of the Church Office Building, he turned to the secretary and
said, "If I were asked to name the one man whom I have met in all my life that comes the nearest
in approximating my appraisal of the Redeemer of the world, I'd name that man." He was
beloved in and out of the Church.
</p><p>
And now, brothers and sisters, we have a man who has come to us from the loins of the holy
prophets, who has devoted his life to the Church, and who has probably written more in
explanation of the truths of the gospel than any other man since the days of the Prophet Joseph. I
am sure that it was pleasing to the Lord to see how we sustained him here in our vote today.
</p><p>
<b>Why a prophet?</b>
</p><p>
I think the theme that has distinguished this conference in my thinking has been "Why a
Prophet?" Why should we have a prophet? And then I think of the passage Brother Petersen
quoted yesterday, where the Lord said through the prophet Amos, "Surely the Lord God will do
nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>). What does that
mean? It means that no honest person believing in the holy scriptures could look to find God's
eternal truth upon the earth without a prophet at its head, because we have no record that he has
ever had a church or a movement without a prophet.
</p><p>
Then I think of the words of the Savior as he stood overlooking Jerusalem and said: 
</p><p>
"O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them which are sent unto
thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her
chickens under her wings, and ye would not!
</p><p>
"Behold, your house is left unto you desolate.
</p><p>
"For I say unto you, Ye shall not see me henceforth, till ye shall say, Blessed is he that cometh in
the name of the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/37-39#37">Matt. 23:37-39</a>).
</p><p>
And when one comes in the name of the Lord, that person can be none other than a prophet of
God.
</p><p>
<b>Preparation for second coming</b>
</p><p>
The Savior testified of John, who was sent to prepare the way for his coming in the meridian of
time. He said there was no greater prophet born of woman than John the Baptist. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/11#11">Matt. 11:11</a>) Then I think of
the words of the Lord to the prophet Malachi, wherein he said: 
</p><p>
"Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord, whom
ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple . . . 
</p><p>
"But who may abide the day of his coming? . . . for he is like a refiner's fire, and like fullers'
soap" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/1-2#1">Mal. 3:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
Obviously that had no reference to his first coming, as he did not come swiftly to his temple, and
all men could abide the day of his coming. He didn't come cleansing and purifying as refiner's
fire and fullers' soap; but we are told in the holy scriptures that when he shall come in the latter
days, the wicked will cry out, "[Let the rocks] fall upon us, and hide us from the face of him that
sitteth on the throne" (See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/6/16#16">Rev. 6:16</a>). From my way of thinking, that prophet was the Prophet
Joseph Smith, sent to prepare the way for his coming by being the instrument in the hands of the
Lord to bring forth his great latter-day work.
</p><p>
Now as I read the scriptures, I just can't comprehend how the marvelous things that the ancient
prophets declared that God would accomplish in our day and time could be accomplished
without a prophet. The apostle Paul said the Lord had revealed the mystery of his will unto him.
(See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/9#9">Eph. 1:9</a>) That is important. "That in the dispensation of the fulness of times he might
gather together in one all things in Christ, both which are in heaven, and which are on earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10#10">Eph. 1:10</a>). We are the only church in the world that has a program to complete and fulfill that
declaration revealed by the Lord to the apostle Paul, and we couldn't do it except for the
prophets whom he has raised up in our day.
</p><p>
<b>Restitution of all things</b>
</p><p>
I think of the time when Peter talked to those who had put to death the Christ, and he told them,
"And he [the Lord] shall send Jesus Christ, which before was preached unto you: Whom the
heavens must receive until the times of restitution of all things, which God hath spoken by the
mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/20-21#20">Acts 3:20-21</a>). How could there be a
restitution of all things unless there was a prophet to receive what the holy prophets would
bring? We testify that that has been fulfilled through the restoration of the gospel.
</p><p>
I think of the words of Malachi when he said: 
</p><p>
". . . I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of the
Lord: 
</p><p>
"And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their
fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6#5">Mal. 4:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
What consequences, were it not for the coming of Elijah? And to whom would he come save
there was a prophet here at the head of the Lord's work? We testify that Elijah has come and
delivered the keys of his dispensation.
</p><p>
<b>A marvelous work and a wonder</b>
</p><p>
I think of the words of the Lord through Isaiah. He said: 
</p><p>
"Forasmuch as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me, but
have removed their heart far from me, and their fear toward me is taught by the precept of men.
</p><p>
"Therefore, behold, I will proceed to do a marvelous work among this people, even a marvelous
work and a wonder: for the wisdom of their wise men shall perish, and the understanding of their
prudent men shall be hid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/13-14#13">Isa. 29:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
I think this church is the marvelous work and a wonder that Isaiah saw, and how could it be
unless there was a prophet unto whom the Lord could reveal his will? "Surely," as Amos said,
"the Lord God will do nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
I think of the experience when Daniel was called to interpret Nebuchadnezzar's dream; you
remember how Nebuchadnezzar had forgotten the dream, and he called in the soothsayers and
the wise men and the astrologers, and none of them could give him the dream. He sent for the
man Daniel. And Daniel came and he said, there is a God in heaven that revealeth secrets, and
maketh known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the
visions of thy head upon thy bed, are thes." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/28#28">Dan. 2:28</a>). Then he told them about the rise and
fall of the kingdoms of this world until the latter days, when the God of heaven would set up a
kingdom that should never be destroyed nor given to another people, but instead it would be like
a stone cut out of the mountain without hands and would roll forth until it would become as a
great mountain and fill the whole earth. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/34-35,44-45#34">Dan. 2:34-35,44-45</a>)
</p><p>
I ask you&mdash;why a prophet? How could the God of heaven set up a work like that without a
prophet through whom he could work and reveal his mind and will?
</p><p>
<b>Kingdom of God</b>
</p><p>
Incidentally, when I was president of the Southern States Mission, one of our missionaries down
in Florida preached on that particular passage of scripture one night. At the close of the meeting
I stood at the door, and a man came up and introduced himself as a minister of the gospel. He
said, "You don't expect us to believe that the Mormon church is that kingdom, do you?" And I
said, "Yes, sir. Why not?" He said, "It couldn't be." I said, "Why couldn't it?" "Well," he said, "we
can't have a kingdom without a king, and we don't have a king, so we haven't a kingdom." "Oh," I
said, "my friend, you didn't read quite far enough. You just read the seventh chapter of Daniel
and you will see where Daniel saw one like the Son of Man coming in the clouds of heaven, and
unto him was given the kingdom that all other kingdoms, powers, and dominions under the
whole heavens should serve him" (See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/13-14#13">Dan. 7:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
Then I said to this minister, "My friend, tell me, how can the kingdom be given to him when he
comes in the clouds of heaven, if there is no kingdom prepared for him? That is what this church
is, the preparation, the restitution of all things spoken by the mouth of all the holy prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>).
Then I said, "Probably you would like to know what is going to become of that kingdom, and if
you will read just a little further in that seventh chapter, you will see where Daniel said, 'But the
saints of the most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever'" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/18#18">Dan. 7:18</a>).
And as if that were not quite long enough, Daniel adds, "even for ever and ever."
</p><p>
<b>Help work to roll on</b>
</p><p>
Now the saints of the most high God have been attending this conference, and to you there is the
promise that this kingdom will be given to you if you make yourselves worthy of it. Therefore, I
say to you that there is no other thing you can do in this world that will bring you greater eternal
happiness than to help to roll this majestic work on, this marvelous work and a wonder, until it
shall fill the whole earth.
</p><p>
Now I could go on for an hour telling you other things that the God of heaven has decreed that
he would do in our day, and he couldn't do them without a prophet of God, and so I stand here to
bear you my witness that this church is led and has been led by living prophets. I sustain with all
my heart our new prophet, seer, and revelator, and his counselors; I pray God to bless them, and
to bless the saints of Zion the world over, that they may he worthy of their great heritage to be a
part of this great latter-day movement, with God at its head and his prophets to direct it. I ask
this prayer, and pray God to bless you all, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
