<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"If It Be Just..."</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 8-10</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, after listening to President McKay's inspiring message, I feel
that all of us, from the bottom of our hearts, can say, "We thank thee, Heavenly Father, for a
prophet to guide us in these latter days."
</p><p>
While World War I was raging in Europe, there were certain individuals here at home who
would sit back in their easy armchairs, surround themselves with maps, and follow the
progress of battle by reading the newspapers. They were extremely critical of the generals and
those who were directing the campaigns and were very eager and vocal in outlining the
strategy they would employ if in similar positions of leadership. These individuals were
referred to as "armchair generals."
</p><p>
Prior to demolition of old buildings or the construction of new buildings, a solid fence is built
to protect passersby. It has become a practice to bore holes in the fence or to instal glass
portholes. From these observation points many pause and watch with interest the demolition
or construction activities. There are those among the viewers who would improve the way the
job is run. Some would knock a building down immediately, while others would have it done
bit by bit. Then there are those who would make changes in the architectural design of the
building. Others are critical of the manner in which the cement is poured, the bricks are laid,
and the glass is installed. These persons are known as "sidewalk superintendents."
</p><p>
Then there is another group belonging to this category. While riding in a car they are
continually offering suggestions to the driver as to how the car should be operated, the speed
that should be traveled, when to turn, and the signals to be employed. These are the "back
seat drivers."
</p><p>
The Church becomes an object of criticism from just such "experts." They are dissatisfied
with the manner in which the superintendent manages the Sunday School. They find fault
with the way the bishop conducts the affairs of the ward. The stake president does not please
them, and they criticize his administration. They are unhappy with the way the tithing is
disbursed. These are the persons who find no fault with their own actions, but seem willing
and anxious to confess another person's sins.
</p><p>
The Savior was chastising such groups as these when he said: "And why beholdest thou the
mote that is within thy brother's eye, but considereth not the beam that is within thine own
eye? . . . Thou hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of thine own eye; and then shalt thou see
clearly to east out the mote out of thy brother's eye"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/3-5#3">Matt. 7:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
I believe that is the same thought that the poet Burns desired to express when he penned the
lines:
</p><p>
"O wad some Power the giftie gie us<br />
To see oursels as ithers see us!"<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          (Robert Burns, <i>To a Louse</i>)
</p><p>
I assure you that I am not against criticism, if it is the right kind. Constructive criticism can
be good and helpful. Destructive criticism can be bad and harmful. Many years ago my
mission president gave this sound advice: "If criticism is just and given kindly, accept it and
give thanks for it. If it is just and given unkindly, accept it. But if it is unjust and given
unkindly, pay no heed to it."
</p><p>
A critical attitude and faultfinding with the Church, if persisted in, can easily lead to apostasy.
A good motto to adopt and follow is, "If you can't improve on silence, say nothing." It is my
deep and firm conviction that the Lord set up his Church in these latter days and has selected
prophets to lead the Saints. There is but one on earth at a time called to exercise the keys of
the Holy Priesthood. He may delegate to others the power and authority to act for him in such
capacity as he will, but he alone holds the keys for such actions. Today that person is
President David O. McKay.
</p><p>
Associated with him in the First Presidency are two other wise and good men. Together they
constitute the "three great Presiding High Priests"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/22#22">D&amp;C 107:22</a>). President Joseph F. Smith made this plain
in a talk from this pulpit near the turn of the century, when he declared: "God has established
all things in their order. The house of God is a house of order, and not a house of confusion
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/8#8">D&amp;C 132:8</a>).
In this house God himself is the Supreme Head, and he must be obeyed. Christ is in the
image and likeness of his Being, his Only Begotten Son, and he stands as our Savior and our
God . . . Next unto God and Christ, on the earth is placed one unto whom the keys and
authority of the Holy Priesthood are conferred, and to whom the right of Presidency is given.
He is God's mouthpiece to his people in all things pertaining to the building up of Zion, and
to the spiritual and temporal salvation of the Saints . . .
</p><p>
Those who have entered into covenant to keep the commandments of the Lord must hearken
unto the voice of him who is placed to preside over them; and secondarily, to those who are
called to act with him as his counselors in the Holy Priesthood. It takes this Council of three
to constitute the presiding and governing authority of the Priesthood in the earth."
</p><p>
These brethren, together with the Quorum of the Twelve and others of our Church leaders, are
blessed with vision and foresight far beyond normal powers and ability. The Lord has
designed that they should sit in the "driver's seat," to use our figure of speech, and direct the
affairs of the Church. From their vantage point they can clearly see the road ahead, which
way to turn, how to avoid the rocks and the chuckholes, much better than those of us sitting
in the back seat. It is our duty, responsibility, and privilege to uphold and sustain them with
our words, our actions, and our prayers.
</p><p>
How best can we do this? By magnifying them in the eyes of our families, our friends,
associates, neighbors, and even strangers, and allowing no evil speaking of the Lord's chosen
leaders. We can substitute support for complaint, commendation and praise for adverse
criticism. We can pray for them in public and in private and in our family prayers, teaching
our children to pray for them.
</p><p>
It is my sincere desire that each of us will become "lifters" instead of "leaners"; that we will
share in the responsibility of building up the kingdom of God here upon the earth, and not
shift it all to the shoulders of our leaders. We shall then never become "armchair generals,"
"sidewalk superintendents," or "backseat drivers," but rather "doers of the word and not
hearers only" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/22#22">James 1:22</a>).
</p><p>
If we will follow the counsel and leadership of our President and Prophet, we shall then
become eligible for all of the blessings promised by the Lord when he said:
</p><p>
"Wherefore, meaning the church, thou shalt give heed unto all his words and commandments
which he shall give unto you as he receiveth them, walking in all holiness before me;
</p><p>
"For his word ye shall receive, as if from mine own mouth, in all patience and faith.
</p><p>
"For by doing these things the gates of hell shall not prevail against you; yea,
and the Lord God will disperse the powers of darkness from before you, and cause the
heavens to shake for your good, and his name's glory"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/21/4-6#4">D&amp;C 21:4-6</a>). To which I testify in
the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
