<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Latter-day Prophets</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 34-36</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
From the inspiration of these two meetings today and after listening to the reports of my
brethren from the four corners of the earth, along with my own deep-seated testimony as to
the divinity of this great latter-day work, I should like to address my remarks to the subject of
nine great latter-day prophets.
</p><p>
I reflect back 130 years last February when the Lord spoke to Joseph Smith saying,
</p><p>
"Now, behold, a marvelous work is about to come forth among the children of men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/1#1">D&amp;C 4:1</a>),
</p><p>
During this conference we have heard about the prophets in the Old and New Testaments. In
the few moments which are mine I should like to speak briefly about the nine great men,
modern-day prophets, who have been responsible under the inspiration of the Almighty for
directing this latter-day marvelous work.
</p><p>
First, of course, there was Joseph Smith, the prophet, the seer, the revelator. Yes, he was
given the keys of the kingdom in this, the Dispensation of the Fullness of Times. He received
a personal visit from God the Father and Jesus Christ, his Divine Son. Reflect upon his
accomplishments in the thirty-nine years of his mortal life: organized the Church of Jesus
Christ in correct and lawful manner; translated the Book of Mormon; received the revelations
from the Lord as contained in the Doctrine and Covenants, also the book of Moses in the
Pearl of Great Price; translated some writings of Abraham from one ancient record; wrote a
3200 page history of himself and the Church; and was visited and given instructions and
authority by the Savior, John the Baptist, Peter James, and John, Moses, Elias, and Elijah and
then sealed his testimony to the truthfulness of all these things with his life's blood, following
the pattern of the Savior himself.
</p><p>
Before Joseph Smith was murdered, he had told the Council of the Twelve
on several occasions as reported by Brigham Young: 
</p><p>
"I have laid the foundation and you must build thereon, for upon your shoulders the kingdom
rests" (<i>History of the Church</i>, VII: 230, August 7, 1844).
</p><p>
Upon the death of the Prophet Joseph Smith, the keys of the kingdom and mantle of authority
were passed on to the second great latter-day prophet, Brigham Young, the leader of
modern-day Israel. He was a great colonizer in the face of adversity, crossing the plains under
most difficult conditions but with great and simple faith in God and his Son Jesus Christ.
Though persecuted and reviled, he knew Joseph Smith was a true prophet.
</p><p>
Upon hearing of the death of Joseph Smith, he declared "The keys of the Kingdom are right
here with the Church," for Brigham knew that the Prophet had conferred upon the twelve
"keys of the kingdom." How often had Joseph said to the twelve, "I have laid the foundation,
and you must build thereon, for upon your shoulders the kingdom rests"
(<i>Comprehensive History of the Church</i>, vol. 2, p. 415). Brigham Young died at the age of seventy-six having
built a great empire in the desert.
</p><p>
He was succeeded by John Taylor, a loyal devoted servant of the Lord, who was honest and
industrious; loving liberty, truth, and righteous living&mdash;sweet-spirited, kind to friend and
stranger alike, tolerant, he nevertheless set his face as flint against any form of evil or
wrongdoing (<i>The Presidents of the Church</i> by Preston Nibley, page 87). He received the
appropriate title, "Champion of Liberty."
</p><p>
Upon his death, the keys were then passed to another great leader, Wilford Woodruff.
Wilford, the faithful! This title was earned because of "his integrity and unbounded devotion
to the worship and purposes of his God." While on a mission in the Southern States in 1834
he and his companion walked sixty miles between sunrise and 10 o'clock at night without a
morsel of food to eat. At the end of this journey, he asked himself the question: "For what?"
He answered his own question, "To teach the gospel of Jesus Christ!" Wilford had loved to
mingle with the Prophet Joseph Smith and had this to say of him: 
</p><p>
"There is not so great a man as Joseph standing in this generation. The gentiles look upon
him, and he is like a bed of gold, concealed from human view. They know not his principles,
his wisdom, his virtue, his calling. His mind is like Enoch's, expands as eternity, and God
alone can comprehend his soul" (<i>The Presidents of the Church</i> by Preston Nibley, pp.
138-139).
</p><p>
One prophet speaking of another prophet of God! Wilford Woodruff lived to be ninety-one.
</p><p>
Lorenzo Snow then received the mantle of authority. Though he was eighty-four when called
to this responsible position, he carried on the great work. The people and the Church at the
time were heavily indebted, and he promised that they would get out of debt if they would
pay their tithes and offerings. That doctrine has not changed. It is just as effective today as it
was in the day of President Lorenzo Snow. Tithing became a spiritual gift rather than a
material duty.
</p><p>
Then the keys of the kingdom passed on to Joseph F. Smith. He was the first prophet, seer,
and revelator with whom it was my privilege to shake hands. Since then I have personally
known all the other prophets. I shall ever be grateful for the experience as a boy to feel the
tenderness of the Prophet Joseph F. Smith. He was kind; he was lovingly devoted. If you
desire to understand the depths of his spirituality, read his messages of inspiration contained
in the volume <i>Gospel Doctrine</i> on such subjects as "Priesthood," "First Principles of the
Gospel," "The Mission of the Church," "Prayer," "Spiritual Gifts," "Tithing," "Industry,"
"Many Duties of Man," "Marriage," "Home," "The Family," "Political Government," "Eternal
Life and Salvation," and many others. He, like all the others, left his strong testimony to bless
the generations to come.
</p><p>
Then the keys of the kingdom passed to President Heber J. Grant, a man who taught all a
lesson in persistence, proving what could be accomplished by sheer persistence. He learned to
write. He learned to sing. He learned to speak. His example reminds me of
the counsel given by my mission president, Samuel O. Bennion, thirty-seven years ago, "You
learn to do by doing."
</p><p>
In 1901 before he was President of the Church and before leaving to fill a mission to Japan,
Heber J. Grant addressed a congregation of young people in which he bore this testimony: 
</p><p>
"Young men and young ladies, I leave with you my testimony that God lives, that Jesus is the
Christ, that Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of God, and that Lorenzo Snow, today is a
prophet of God. How do I know it? I know it as well as I know that I stand before you
tonight. I know heat. I know cold. I know joy and I know sorrow, and I say to you that in the
hour of sorrow, in the hour of affliction, in the hour of death, God has heard and answered
my prayers, and I know that He lives, and I leave my testimony with you" (<i>Presidents of the Church</i>,
Preston Nibley, p. 298).
</p><p>
Then at his death, the keys of the kingdom passed to another great leader, President George
Albert Smith, an apostle of love. He had a great love in his heart for all men, not only the
membership of the Church, but also all men! He desired to share with others the light of the
gospel which had come into his life. I have heard him suggest many times to those not of our
faith that they do not give up the truths they have, but that they accept further truths from us.
</p><p>
After he had received the keys and the mantle of authority and was sustained by the
membership present in this marvelous building, he expressed his great love for his counselors
who stood by his side on that occasion, President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., and President David O.
McKay.
</p><p>
President Smith held positions of responsibility and was honored by such organizations as the
Sons of the American Revolution, International Irrigation Congress, Boy Scouts of America,
Utah Pioneer Trails and Land Marks Association. At eighty-one his mortal life came to a
close. The keys of the kingdom and the mantle of authority were passed on to President
David O. McKay, the missionary prophet! I believe President McKay has visited all the
missions of the Church where in each one he has touched the lives of people for good. He has
built them in their faith and in their courage and strengthened their testimony in the divinity
of this great work.
</p><p>
President McKay has also dedicated four temples: one in Berne, Switzerland, in Los Angeles,
California, in Auckland, New Zealand, and in London, England. Also he has dedicated many,
many other Church buildings. Not only has he dedicated buildings, but his whole life has also
been dedicated to the building of the kingdom of God. I am grateful for his life, for his power
and strength. He and his lovely, devoted wife have set the world a high example in the
concept of a good marriage good in all its connotations! He has said so much about the
importance of a clean life, of honoring womanhood, of understanding the gospel and of
serving the Master. He will leave so many truths for coming generations. I give you one
admonition from President McKay which is so timely and most important for all of us, young
and old, (I have heard him say this on numerous occasions) "We are here to develop the
power of self-mastery." Analyze this statement. Live by it and see what it will do for you!
</p><p>
Truly, as his predecessors passed on the keys of the kingdom, the mantle of authority is now
held by our Prophet David O. McKay. Because of this authority, we have been given the right
to legitimately administer in the name of our Heavenly Father, the Father of our spirits, and in
the name of his Son Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
And so upon the shoulders of nine great men in our day has fallen the mantle of priesthood
leadership. The chain is unbroken. God the Father and his Son, Jesus Christ, our Lord and
Savior, bestowed upon Joseph Smith the authority to act in their names. There have been nine
prophets who have held the keys of the kingdom&mdash;nine Presidents of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints in this generation. None other on the earth has this authority. Each
prophet has left behind a monument for good that time cannot efface or obliterate. No
individual has ever gone astray by following the counsel of these prophets,
but many have experienced tragedy and sorrow by going counter to their counsel.
</p><p>
I should like to suggest to young people as they study their history lessons that they reserve
enough time to the history of the lives of these fine great men and seek a witness of their
divine authority.
</p><p>
May we realize the power of these great men. I bear witness that they were and are prophets
of God; that David O. McKay is the mouthpiece of our Heavenly Father in the earth today
who does hold the keys of the kingdom and the mantle of authority, and this testimony I bear
in humility and in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ, our Savior. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
