<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Acceptance of Call to Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1952, pp. 111-115</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I suppose only the men on this stand can know what has gone through my mind and my heart
since President McKay called me to his office following the morning meeting.
</p><p>
I first want to tell you that I'm proud that Brother Wirthlin has been called as the Presiding
Bishop of this Church. He and I have labored side by side for fourteen years, and I doubt if
any two men have ever been closer to each other than we have been. He is a noble character,
and he is as true and loyal to this Church as any man I have ever met. If we ever questioned
the instruction of the brethren, he would say, "Well, you know, if the brethren were to tell us
to put the Presiding Bishop's Office up on Ensign Peak, there it would go." That is the kind
of faith he has.
</p><p>
And I have learned to love Brother Isaacson so much in these few years, five and a half
years, that he has served as my counselor, and I am so happy that Brother Wirthlin saw fit to
choose him to stand by his side.
</p><p>
And I love Brother Buehner. I have only been out with him once or twice but I think they
have made a wonderful choice.
</p><p>
Now I want to pay a tribute of respect and an expression of deep appreciation to the
employees of the Presiding Bishop's office. We have some wonderful help there, and they
have been so loyal and willing to do anything we have ever asked them to do. I should like to
name them, but the list would be too long. God bless them in their further responsibilities in
that office.
</p><p>
I cannot find words to express what is in my heart. I think of what Brother Alonzo Hinckley
said when he stood here in a similar position and said "My soul is subdued." I do not know
what it takes to subdue the soul of a man, but for the past two hours, I have been trying to
figure out how I could measure up and not disappoint you people, and not disappoint the
Lord.
</p><p>
How grateful I feel to the brethren President McKay and his Counselors that they have
enough confidence in me to nominate me for this position and that the Quorum of the
Twelve, knowing that I should become one of them, sustained them in the nomination.
</p><p>
And I thank you for your sustaining vote here this day, and I pledge you all the strength and
ability that the Lord has given me to continue to help build up his kingdom on the earth.
</p><p>
I thank God for the opportunities that I have enjoyed of working among you, and in his
Church, the missions that I have been able to fill, and the other sundry odd jobs, because I
truly love the work more than anything else in this world, and I know it is true. I could live
better without the limbs of my body than I could without the testimony of the Holy Ghost and
the Spirit of the Lord.
</p><p>
When I returned from my first mission, I was called to speak in my ward. I told the Saints
that the greatest desire I had in my heart was that I might be able so to live now that I was
home that I could enjoy the same spirit I had enjoyed in the mission field. And I added, I
hope the Lord will send me on a mission just often enough so I can keep that spirit. Maybe
that is the reason I filled four missions. I thought when I got in the bishop's office, I would
never get another, but who knows what might happen now?
</p><p>
I have loved my work with the youth of this Church, and with the Aaronic Priesthood, and
for a time we had the girls' program. And we have lived to see some real achievement in the
work with these boys. When we came into the office fourteen years ago, many a ward was
still using the Melchizedek Priesthood in the administration of the sacrament. We tried to get
the Standard Quorum Award going. We could hardly get a quorum to get twenty-five percent
of the boys to attend sacrament meeting. And now the average for the entire Church is
forty-one percent. It is not much to boast about, but it is up a long way to what it was.
</p><p>
And the girls were up to fifty-five percent, so they have to help the boys along a little, or the
boys will not be worth their marrying a little later on when they want companions.
</p><p>
The growth of the Church during these fourteen years has been tremendous. I have been
privileged to travel around the stakes of Zion, and it seems to me that every conference I
attend they say it is the largest crowd they have ever had. The way the brethren have been
dividing the wards and stakes is indicative of the growth of the Church.
</p><p>
In tribute to the faithfulness and the integrity of the Latter-day Saints, I want to give you two
or three figures of what has happened since we came into the Presiding Bishop's office.
</p><p>
The membership of the Church in that time has increased 46.1 percent.
</p><p>
The tithes of the Church have in the same length of time increased 653.3 percent.
</p><p>
Forty-six percent increase in membership, 653.3 percent increase in tithing, and then you say
the Latter-day Saints do not have faith.
</p><p>
And then you add to that what the brethren have already reported during this conference of
the gifts of the Saints that are not counted as tithes, and I say the Saints are wonderful. God
bless them everywhere for their faith and for their integrity.
</p><p>
I never come home from a stake conference but what I say to my wife, "You just have to get
out in this Church to know the power of the Lord that is in it." How anyone in the world
could be familiar with the Church and what it is doing, and the spirit and the power that is in
it, and think that it comes from man! He would have to be a very bright man, wouldn't he?
</p><p>
The fast offerings in that time increased 230 percent. There have been 65 new stakes of Zion
added, 458 wards and 73 new independent branches.
</p><p>
I thought these figures might interest you and show that the Saints are coming along pretty
well.
</p><p>
Now, brothers and sisters, if there is anything that I am sure of, more than anything else in
the world, it is that this work is divine. It is not the work of man. It is the work of God, the
Eternal Father, and his power is in it and I tell you in all sincerity that the Holy Ghost, the
Comforter that the Savior promised to send to guide us in all truth and bring things to our
remembrance, is just as much a reality to me and just as necessary for our well-being as the
sun that shines in the heavens is to the seed that is sown in the ground, and the plants as they
germinate and come forth. I know the power of the Holy Ghost is in this Church.
</p><p>
When the Lord sent his servants out in this day, he told them they were not going to be
taught of men, but to teach that which he would give unto them by the power of the Holy
Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/15#15">D&amp;C 43:15</a>).
I do not know very much about the philosophies of men, but I know that God created
the feelings of the human heart and the human soul, and I know that God has a way of
bringing joy and happiness into the souls of men, when they seek after him, and when they
enjoy the gift of the Holy Ghost, far beyond anything that men can purchase with their
money.
</p><p>
I have been in homes of rich people. I have never seen any tears of joy shed because of
anything they could purchase with their money, but I have been in groups of missionaries and
groups of Saints, when for hours at a time there was not a dry eye there, just because the
spirit of God was there. Like Nephi of old said,
</p><p>
He [the Lord] hath filled me with his love, even unto the consuming of my flesh (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/4/21#21">2 Ne. 4:21</a>).
</p><p>
I feel sorry for Latter-day Saints if they have never felt that power, and that blessing, unto
almost the consumption of their flesh.
</p><p>
That is what Paul meant when he said of those who have tasted of the power of the world to
come, and then fallen away, it is impossible to renew them again to repentance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/6/5-6#5">Heb. 6:5-6</a>), which gave
me to understand that Paul understood that in this life, men could taste of the powers of the
world to come. Surely that was what Paul experienced when he stood before Festus and
Agrippa, there in chains as he was, and bore witness of the ministration and the appearance of
the Savior to him on the way to Damascus, how he had seen the light, and heard the Voice
saying,
</p><p>
. . . Saul, Saul, why persecutest thou me?
</p><p>
. . . it is hard for thee to kick against the pricks
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/4-5#4">Acts 9:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
And after Festus and Agrippa had listened, Festus said,
</p><p>
Paul, thou art beside thyself; much learning doth make thee mad.
</p><p>
But he said, I am not mad, most noble Festus; but speak forth the words of truth and
soberness....
</p><p>
Then Agrippa said unto Paul, Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/24-28#24">Acts 26:24-28</a>).
</p><p>
And there he was in chains, and his reply was something like this, "I would to God, that not
only thou, but all men everywhere were as I am, save these chains that hold me bound" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/29#29">Acts 26:29</a>).
That is what the spirit of the Lord does.
</p><p>
And you remember when Jesus appeared to the people here in America following his
resurrection, and established his Church and ministered among them, the historian says that
the joys that filled their souls no pen could write nor tongue express
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/17/16-17#16">3 Ne. 17:16-17</a>). And that is the thing the
Lord gives to those who serve him, and that is the joy of service there is in this Church.
</p><p>
A few weeks ago I attended a stake conference, and a stake president told me about two visits
he had made to an adult member of the Aaronic Priesthood, to try to induce him to quit his
tobacco so that he might receive the Melchizedek Priesthood and be prepared to go to the
house of the Lord with his family; and he said he had been unsuccessful. So I said to this
stake president, "Did it ever occur to you that you might have been getting the cart before the
horse, so to speak? If you would go to that man and teach him the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ, and he would become converted, you would not need to ask him to quit his tobacco."
</p><p>
I think of the many, many homes into which I went in the mission field. I have in mind one
now. The first night there, because we would not smoke with them, and we could not drink
their coffee with them, the man said, "Well I would never join your Church." Well, we did
not discuss the Word of Wisdom any more for a few weeks, until we got him a little farther
along. And when we got a little farther along, we did not have to ask him to lay away his
coffee; it just disappeared. We did not have to ask him to quit his tobacco; it went out the
window the same way. I remember one man past his eighties who had been in the government
service, walking up and down the streets and lanes in Holland for years and years of his life,
and all he had for a companion and friend was his cigars. He chewed them instead of
smoking them. And when he heard the gospel and became converted, he laid them away; he
used to chew a little licorice root to take the place of the cigars.
</p><p>
I never hear of men like the one the stake president referred to but what I think&mdash;if they
were only converted to the truth, they would not have to be asked to quit their tobacco. I
could not help thinking the other night when we had this demonstration of missionary work,
if every member of the Church could see it and hear it, and all the youth of the Church, we
would not have so much transgression.
</p><p>
I have another thought before I close. You remember what the Lord said to Peter, he said,
</p><p>
. . . Simon, Simon, behold, Satan hath desired to have you, that he may sift you as
wheat.
</p><p>
But I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not: and when thou art converted,
strengthen thy brethren
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/31-32#31">Luke 22:31-32</a>).
</p><p>
I tell you, brothers and sisters, the Latter-day Saints are becoming converted, and they are
strengthening their brethren, but there would not be a man or a woman in all Israel who
would ever buy a pound of tea or coffee or a cigar or a cigarette or tobacco, in any form, if
they were only converted.
</p><p>
You just think of Peter. He said "Though all the world forsake thee, I will not forsake thee."
But the Savior knew that even though he thought he was converted he was not quite
converted (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/33-34#33">Matt. 26:33-34</a>).
And so you remember how the Savior said that ere the cock should crow, he
would deny Jesus thrice, and he did. And he was the first one to say, "I go a fishing" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/3#3">John 21:3</a>)
after the Savior was crucified, but when he had remained at Jerusalem according to the
Savior's command, until he had been endowed with power from on high, the Holy Ghost,
then he went forth fearless as a lion, and when he was commanded that he should no more
preach Christ and him crucified in the streets of Jerusalem, he replied: "Whom shall man
obey? God or man?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/19#19">Acts 4:19</a>).
And you will remember that finally he rejected the privilege of being
crucified with his head up, because he thought he was not worthy to be crucified as was his
Lord.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, if we could just get the Holy Ghost, the testimony of the spirit in the
hearts of all Latter-day Saints, we would not have any of them saying that we harp too much
on the Word of Wisdom. After all, God gave it.
</p><p>
God help us to so live his commandments that we may enjoy his Spirit, that we may ever be
found walking in his ways, and keeping his commandments, I humbly pray, in the name of
the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
