<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Source of Happiness</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 41-44</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I wish to acknowledge all that has been said so far in this conference and ask that I shall also
have a portion of your faith and prayers in my behalf, as has been requested in the prayers of
this conference.
</p><p>
I am sure there is no happier gathering than we have here today, for I don't think there are
any happier people than those who are active, faithful members of the Church. Inasmuch as
we have gathered here together to receive of more encouragement and help in performing our
responsibilities in the work of the Lord, I am sure the Lord will answer that prayer for us.
</p><p>
I am happy in my testimony of the gospel, in the knowledge of the gospel with which the
Lord has blessed me.
</p><p>
GOAL OF HAPPINESS
</p><p>
As has been said, happiness has been the goal of man since the beginning of time, for man is
that he might have joy. When Moses reached the age of 120 and it was time for him to depart
this life, he commanded that all the children of Israel be gathered together that he might speak
to them. He said, "Come, therefore, let me suggest to you by what means you may be happy"
</p><p>
Moses had been an instrument in the hands of the Lord, to bring many blessings to the
children of Israel. Through Moses they had been released from bondage and delivered from
Egypt. He had traveled with them for forty years in the wilderness, teaching them the will of
the Lord. He had gone through many trials and hardships with them and for them. Together
they had suffered hunger, thirst, and had fled before their enemy. Now at the end of his life,
when men are most serious, he called them together to give them instructions. Uppermost in
his mind for the hosts of Israel was their <i>happiness</i>. He continued:
</p><p>
O children of Israel! There is but one source of happiness for all mankind, the favor of God;
for he alone is able to give good things to those that deserve them, and to deprive those of
them that sin against him; towards whom, if you behave yourselves according to his will, and
according to what I, who well understand his mind, do exhort you to, you will both be
esteemed blessed, and will be admired by all men; and will never come into misfortunes, nor
cease to be happy. . . (Josephus, Book 4:8.)
</p><p>
OBEDIENCE INSURES HAPPINESS
</p><p>
After standing the test of thousands of years, it is still just as true today for all mankind; for
true happiness and joy come from the favor of God. How can we obtain the favor of God in
our everyday walks of life? The Lord has given us commandments, obedience to which will
insure our happiness, if we will only heed them. First and foremost, ". . . love the Lord thy
God with all thine heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy might"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/6/5#5">Deut. 6:5</a>). If
our hearts are filled with love for God, then they are also filled with love for our fellow men.
We will be glad to lend a helping hand or give a cheering word to a neighbor. And right here
let me say, that love, like charity, begins at home. If you are fortunate enough to have a home
and a family, your chances for happiness are <i>unlimited</i>. But it takes love&mdash;plenty of love to
make a home happy. The more we give in understanding, sympathy, and service to others, the
happier we are. And love is kind it is ready to overlook failures and try again. If we could
only keep our hearts filled with love, this earth would be a heaven of happiness. Do you
remember the song in our hymn book&mdash;"Love at Home"? It is such a beautiful song. Next
time you are tempted to let something other than love creep into your heart, sing it and see if
it doesn't help. There is a sure method of keeping in the favor of the Lord. When we are in
constant communication, we cannot go far astray. Each morning, throughout the day, and at
night, we ask God to let his Spirit be with us to guide us in all that we do. It is like the beam
that guides the pilot of an airplane. As long as he is on the beam, he knows that everything is
all right, but he must not stray too far or he loses the beam, We have a conscience, each of
us, that will tell us if we are not on the beam. There is no surer way to unhappiness than to
carry a guilty conscience constantly for a companion. Don't do it. Get on the beam. There are
many other things which contribute to our happiness, and God has given us instruction
concerning these things. Our capacity for enjoying life is greater if our health is good. It is
hard to be happy if we are always tired. The Lord told us how to keep from being weary and
keep our minds invigorated. He said:
</p><p>
. . . retire to thy bed early, that ye may not be weary; arise early, that your bodies and your
minds may be invigorated (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/124#124">D&amp;C 88:124</a>).
</p><p>
With every blessing, however, the Lord has put a price or a law upon which each blessing is
predicated. For keeping the Word of Wisdom he promises:
</p><p>
And all saints who remember to keep and do these sayings, walking in obedience to the
commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones;
</p><p>
And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures;
</p><p>
And shall run and not be weary, and shall walk and not faint. And I, the Lord, give unto
them a promise that the destroying angel shall pass by them, as the children of Israel, and not
slay them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-21#18">D&amp;C 89:18-21</a>).
</p><p>
The nineteenth verse is to me most important. They "shall find wisdom and great treasures of
knowledge, even hidden treasures" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>).
Is there any greater happiness that can be given to man
than the testimony of the divinity of this gospel and the plan of life and salvation? That
knowledge comes only from the Holy Ghost. Again the Lord promises, ". . . prove me now
herewith . . . . if I will not open you the windows of heaven, and pour you out a blessing,
that there shall not be room enough to receive it." For the price of this source of happiness,
the Lord says:
</p><p>
Bring ye all the tithes into the storehouse, that there may be meat in mine house . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/10#10">Mal. 3:10</a>).
</p><p>
THE PRICE OF PROSPERITY
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon records the promises of prosperity to those who live in this the
promised land. The price for prosperity is keeping the commandments of the Lord. There
were many times when Israel of old was not in the favor of the Lord. Then the Lord
withdrew his blessings, and they became humbled again, and the blessings of the Lord were
again given to the people. We find the same repetition among the descendants of Lehi on this
continent. What about us? Can we profit by their experience?
</p><p>
The Lord also promised, "All that my Father hath shall be given . . . "
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>). To whom? And why?
</p><p>
And also all they who receive this priesthood receive me, saith the Lord;
</p><p>
For he that receiveth my servants receiveth me; And he that receiveth me receiveth my
Father;
</p><p>
And he that receiveth my Father, receiveth my Father's kingdom; therefore all that my Father
hath shall be given unto him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/35-38#35">D&amp;C 84:35-38</a>).
</p><p>
The reward for keeping the commandments of the Lord is happiness.
</p><p>
Happiness certainly does not come from just idle goodness. The Savior said, "But he that is
greatest among you shall be your servant"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/11#11">Matt. 23:11</a>).
He could have said, "He that is
happiest among you shall be your servant." Active service to others is serving God. That
missionary is happiest who is truly seeking to serve his fellow man by declaring to him the
message of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Active members of the Church everywhere experience
the same happiness. Nor does happiness stop with this life. For those who keep the
commandments of the Lord to the full, and enter into the new and everlasting covenant, and
are sealed together as husband and wife for time and all eternity, shall enjoy the greatest
degree of happiness.
</p><p>
Thus, as Moses declared: "The source of happiness for all mankind," in this life and the life
to come throughout all eternity, "is the favour of God."
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to obtain it, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
