<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Trust the Prophet</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Theodore Moyle Burton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Theodore M. Burton, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 120-122</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I am most grateful for this past year. It has been a marvelous year to
have spent in association with these, my brethren. I have had my eyes opened. I have learned
many things. It has also been a tremendous blessing to me to be able to travel among the
stakes and missions of the Church and see what wonderful strength and leadership we have
where-ever I travel.
</p><p>
I have been greatly impressed by the strength of the Church, for I feel the strength of the
Church is in the hearts of our people who are willing to serve and to sacrifice because of the
testimony they have in their hearts that this is the truth.
</p><p>
Now, as a missionary, how can I teach the things that are in my heart to you, the people?
How can I strengthen the Saints and teach those who are not yet members of the Church?
How can I give confidence to them that God does live and that he does speak in this
generation?
</p><p>
Perhaps I can illustrate this by talking for a moment about some of the problems of
translation. When I worked for the United States government in the foreign agency service of
the Treasury Department, it was my duty to translate some of the customs laws from the
German into the English language. I soon learned that a man in order to translate has to know
much more than just the words of the language. I found that a translator must give a message,
not just a literal translation of the subject word for word.
</p><p>
I found that sentences mean much more than words. I found that paragraphs are much more
important than sentences, and I found that the treatise as a whole must make sense. Otherwise,
the translation is not good. Words have many different meanings, and the meanings of these
words depend upon their usage. The context in which they are used becomes extremely
important.
</p><p>
Let us take as a simple example the word, <i>corn</i>. It is a simple English word, but if you were
to translate this into another language, you would have to understand some of its many
meanings. <i>Corn</i> would mean <i>maize</i> to the Indian. It would mean <i>grain</i> to the Britisher. It
would mean <i>whiskey</i> to the moonshiner. It would mean to <i>granulate</i> to the chemist or to the
munitions manufacturer. It would mean to <i>preserve</i> to the housewife. It would mean to <i>plant</i>
to the farmer. It would mean <i>a horny skin growth</i> to the doctor of medicine.
</p><p>
So, if you were to translate that word you would have to know how it was used. Thus a
translator must understand the meaning of the information he is to present; otherwise, his
translation is impossible. So, if he is to translate, he must become an authority in other fields
much more than just an authority in the language with which he is working. He must
understand something about the subject being translated.
</p><p>
Let us look now at the problem of translating the Bible, particularly in the Old Testament.
Not only must the translator know English, he must also know Hebrew. He must know what
the Hebrew says, and then he must put that understandingly into the English language.
</p><p>
In the Old Testament there are several Hebrew words, "ro'eh," "hozeh," and "nabhi'," all of
which are translated by the translators as <i>prophet</i>. The first two, almost synonymous, from the
roots "ra'ah" and "hazah," both meaning to see suggest the man of vision and should be
properly rendered as <i>seer</i>. The term "nabhi'" from the root "nabha" means <i>to announce</i>. But if
the translator felt that <i>to see</i> and <i>to announce</i> are synonymous and that they refer to the same
thing, then he would so use them. Thus we find that all of these words were used and
translated as <i>prophet</i> and sometimes the word <i>seer</i> was used where <i>prophet</i> should have been
used, and sometimes the word <i>prophet</i> was used where <i>seer</i> should have been used. Confusion
resulted therefrom, because the translators did not understand that these two words <i>seer</i> and
<i>prophet</i> mean different things; that they have different usages.
</p><p>
There is a great difference between these words because a <i>seer</i> is greater than a <i>prophet</i>. King
Limhi, in speaking to the missionary, Ammon, said, ". . . a seer is greater than a prophet"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/8/15#15">Mosiah 8:15</a>).
Then Ammon explained why. He said, ". . . a seer is a revelator and a prophet also; and a gift
which is greater can no man have, except he should possess the power of God, which no man
can; yet a man may have great power given him from God.
</p><p>
"But a seer can know of things which are past, and also things which are to come, and by
them shall all things be revealed, or, rather, shall secret things be made manifest, and hidden
things shall come to light, and things which are not known shall be made known by them, and
also things shall be made known by them which otherwise could not be known"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/8/16-17#16">Mosiah 8:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Life for the ordinary man is ofttimes frightening and bewildering. There is so much that we
mortals fear. There is so much that we do not understand. There is so much that we do not
know. When we talk of knowing, we talk of knowledge, and it would be well to ask ourselves
what we mean by "knowledge." Knowledge is only our interpretation of the evidence before
us. If our interpretation of the evidence is wrong, our knowledge is false.
</p><p>
Sometimes, therefore, we make grave errors, for our interpretation of the evidence is wrong.
What a shock it is for us to realize that what we once thought we knew&mdash;is wrong! This has
occurred many times in the history of the earth. Why, the evidence was so plain to those who
stated that the earth was flat, that when anyone mentioned that the earth is round, it was a
ridiculous thing, and the people just laughed at the idea Yet by the evidence we have today
we interpret this to mean that the earth is round, and we claim that previous persons just
didn't understand the evidence presented to them.
</p><p>
The same thing is true when we talked about the sun revolving around the earth. Why, any
man with eyes to see could actually see the sun revolving around the earth! Yet our
interpretation of the evidence today is just the reverse of this. So, what we say we know is
not always true.
</p><p>
What then can a person cling to? Youth lacks experience, and older people jump at
conclusions also. Knowledge is often based on too little evidence, either by the young or by
the old. Thus, young and old, when they have found themselves questioning, become
skeptical, and they begin to question and doubt everything and have confidence in nothing.
</p><p>
Now to what can a man turn? In what can he place reliance? In whom can we put our
confidence, our trust? Now remember, Ammon said a seer is greater than a prophet. Before he
made this statement he had said ". . . I can assuredly tell thee, O king, of a man that can
translate the records; for he has wherewith that he can look, and translate all records that are
of ancient date; and it is a gift from God. And the things are called interpreters, and no man
can look in them except he be commanded, lest he should look for that he ought not and he
should perish. And whosoever is commanded to look in them, the same is called seer"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/8/13#13">Mosiah 8:13</a>).
</p><p>
Thus one can trust a seer because a seer may see the heavens open. He may see the great
vision of God working in all his majesty. He may see the fulness of truth as
it is revealed to him by God who makes no mistakes. The evidence is clear, therefore, and the
interpretation is clear. The seer can bear personal testimony, not based on books, not based on
scholarship, not based on tradition, but based on the evidence of things that God himself can
reveal to him in an actual experience with Deity. He may receive a revelation from God by
actually seeing and hearing and being instructed in the real truth.
</p><p>
A seer then is one who may see God, who may talk with God, who may receive persona,
instruction from God. Our prophet is a seer and a revelator. I do not know who originally
taught the doctrine. I was told once that it was taught by President Heber J. Grant, but I was
taught this doctrine by Elder Marion G. Romney, who told me that the Lord will never let his
prophet, the seer, lead his people astray. Men in all ranks on this earth and in the Church have
fallen from grace, but the Lord will never permit the great prophet, our seer, and revelator, to
fall or to lead the people astray. Before this could happen God must of necessity remove that
man from the earth.
</p><p>
There must be someone to whom the people can turn and trust, who can speak for God. God
must have someone on earth who can point the way and say, "This is true." How grateful, my
brothers and sisters, we should be that God in the fulness of his grace has given us a living
prophet to guide us to Him even more that God has given us a seer, for this seer and prophet
reveals personal testimony to young and old alike that Jesus is in very deed the risen Savior,
the Living God.
</p><p>
Of this I bear sacred testimony, for under conditions too sacred to mention here God has
given me witness three times in the temples that David O. McKay is truly and indeed a
prophet of God, a seer, and I bear you this testimony that you can trust him and so put your
whole faith in Jesus Christ. We must turn from anything which tears us away from God our
Father and turn to that which will lead us to him through repentance, through our
determination and through our absolute will to do the work of God.
</p><p>
I bear you this testimony in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
