<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Church Is a Stage, Its Members Players</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder William L. Critchlow, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">William L. Critchlow, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 26-29</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my brothers and sisters:
</p><p>
Where could you find sweeter voices than these voices from Ogden and Northern Utah which
have sung for us this day? I have heard them before, I hope to hear them again. I am proud
of them.
</p><p>
"All the world's a stage,<br />
And all the men and women merely players:<br />
They have their exits and their entrances;<br />
And one man in his time plays many parts."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          &mdash;Shakespeare,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          <i>As You Like It</i>, Act II, Scene 7, lines 139-142.
</p><p>
Through the years thousands of our young men and women and many
oldsters, too, have been called to play heroic roles in the great Drama of Life. I have enjoyed
these past two years the privilege of setting apart many of them,&mdash;missionaries of the
Church&mdash;sending them forth to perform on the stage of life with a blessing.
</p><p>
The Drama of Life has many acts. Few of them, however, are as thrilling as the act entitled
"A Mission." Let me sketchily review for you a few scenes in an act which I witnessed, just
to show how exciting this "Mission Act" can really be.
</p><p>
The opening scene was called "Miles Zero." In the missionary's first letter to his folks he
wrote: "Dear Dad: I'm up at Miles Zero on the Alaskan highway in Dawson Creek where it is
costing me one hundred dollars a week for board and room.
</p><p>
His dad replied immediately, "Dear Son: Get off the Alaskan highway! Park Avenue, New
York, should be cheaper. Miles Zero is too rich for my blood."
</p><p>
The dad's letter and another letter from the son crossed in the mail. The son's letter began:
</p><p>
"Dear Dad: The Lord has blessed me already. A man committed suicide in his room. It was
so ghastly that no one would rent it. I offered the landlord forty dollars a month. He took me
up&mdash;so I moved in with my companion who is sharing the forty dollars. All my problems
are solved." Months passed.
</p><p>
Then, in one of his regular letters, the son said, "I have twenty-two prospects about ready to
join up, but no place to baptize them. Peace River will be frozen over till June, and before
then I shall be due for a transfer. Wish I could use a bathtub. They have some large tin ones
up here."
</p><p>
Weeks passed.
</p><p>
In another letter the son wrote: "Lucky me. The Lord has blessed me again. Two of my
choice prospects, the banker and the head of the Masonic Lodge, who is also the president of
the Power Board went six hundred miles down to Edmonton, and I baptized them. That's two
down, only twenty more to go. My president is pleased. He is transferring me to Bella Coula,
wherever that is. Up here, there are two kinds of water&mdash;liquid and frozen, also two kinds of
prospects&mdash;hot and cold. I'm terribly afraid that some of my twenty remaining prospects will
'freeze up' before liquid water and a baptismal font become available. I shall regret losing
them, but I'll pick twenty up in Bella Coula. Wish me luck."
</p><p>
Five years after the curtain fell on this son's "Mission Act," I was sent to a conference in
Calgary, Canada, and in one of the sessions of the conference I listened to the stake president
praise, as he released, his stake mission president who had baptized twenty converts "right
here in Calgary." He called on him to speak. I copied these words from a tape of his talk.
</p><p>
"Seven years ago one Sunday in a converted hut at Miles Zero on the Alaskan highway I met
a young man who was to be instrumental in changing the course of my life. He was big, six
feet. He had a big grin and hands that were always moving. You could tell he had the spirit
of the gospel. I had met many men before, but never had I met a man who could teach the
gospel the way this man did. He would both fast and pray, and I remember that one time he
fasted three days and nights, going without food and water and praying on behalf of the
people he was teaching. He taught the gospel with an inspiration that only one who had the
guidance of his Father in heaven could bring. He baptized me. I have a great love for that
young man. Elder Critchlow, take back to your son a confirmation of the love we have for
him. In a way to pay the debt tell him that many here within the sound of my voice, whom I
have had the privilege of teaching have come into the kingdom of God&mdash;through your son."
</p><p>
Those words "through your son" were ringing pleasantly in my ears&mdash;still I heard the
president who leaned toward me to whisper: "He (the mission president) baptized twenty
people here in Calgary."
</p><p>
Suddenly, my memory was flooded with a maze of words&mdash;words which my son had written
years before. Slowly, they assembled into fragments of broken sentences: "That's two
down&mdash;twenty more to go&mdash;I'm afraid my twenty prospects will freeze up before liquid water
is available .... I regret losing them ....
</p><p>
I'll pick them up in Bella Coula&mdash;Wish me luck."
</p><p>
Well, he didn't pick them up in Bella Coula.
</p><p>
They were picked up in Calgary by one of the "two down" who picked up the "twenty more
to go"&mdash;"through your son."
</p><p>
Families that have never had a missionary in the field have missed one of the grandest
blessings that could come into their homes. Ask the mother who impatiently awaits her
missionary son's letters, who gleefully reads lines in them over the back fence to neighbors
and over the phone to relatives and friends.
</p><p>
Ask the proud father, the brother, or the sister about the sweet feeling they experience when
they kneel together each day in family prayers to ask a blessing for their missionary. Before
Bobby left for his mission the family skipped its prayers occasionally, but while he was in the
field&mdash;so far, far away from home, they skipped fewer prayers because Bobby might need the
protection and the help of a loving Heavenly Father. Never was the family knit more closely
together.
</p><p>
Recently I told a stake president he needed six thousand stake missionaries. "Be reasonable,"
he said, "I've only six thousand members in my stake."
</p><p>
"Right, exactly right," I replied, "and every one of those members is a missionary."
</p><p>
Every member of our Church is a missionary. Without the formality of a setting-apart we
should be so set-apart from the ways of the world that we can teach the gospel, which is our
Father's way of life, by the very lives we live. Without the oral word of mouth preaching, the
example of our living will always be effective teaching. A sermon seen is better than a
sermon heard.
</p><p>
Example has more followers than reason and is more forcible than precept.
</p><p>
Yes, the world's a stage;
</p><p>
So is the Church a stage;
</p><p>
And all its members merely players...
</p><p>
They have their exits and their entrances;
</p><p>
And each member in his time is expected to choose and play a noble part.
</p><p>
Come up here with me on this stage of life and, over the glare of the footlights in this World
Theater let's take a peek at the audience watching us play our parts in the great Drama of
Life.
</p><p>
Down there in the parquet whom do you see? Over the glare of the footlights I quite
distinctly see my wife, my children, my neighbors, my friends across the town and across the
country, my vocational associates, my associates in the Church Offices. All who know me, be
it ever so well or ever so slight, seem to be in this World Theater. And they're watching, oh,
so critically. Yet if I play my role well&mdash;the role of a Latter-day Saint&mdash;I'm sure there will be
some applause. But if I slip out of character&mdash;even for a moment or so&mdash;some of them, like
patrons of any theater, at times, might sneer, perhaps hiss. These translate into one of the
ugliest words in the English dictionary&mdash;"hypocrite."
</p><p>
May our merciful Heavenly Father help me, help you to play our chosen roles so well that we
may deserve the plaudits and the praise, at least the respect of those who watch.
</p><p>
Now look up to the balcony . . . the glare of the footlights, whom do you see there? On the
very first row I see my mother. My father is beside her, my brother beside him. Behind them,
I believe, my grandparents. One man among them with sideburns and a lock of curly brown
hair looks like a picture I've seen of Captain James Brown who led the sick detachment of
the Mormon Battalion into Salt Lake Valley. He's my great-grandfather. These obviously are
the dead. I can almost hear them say:
</p><p>
"We are the dead,<br />
Short years ago we lived, felt dawn, saw Sunshine glow . . .<br />
To you from failing hand the torch we throw<br />
Be yours to hold it high.<br />
If ye break faith with us who die,<br />
We shall not sleep."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          &mdash;adapted&mdash;"In Flanders Fields" McCrea.
</p><p>
I don't really believe, of course, that my father and mother and my grandparents are peeking
through the veil, observing every scene in which I act, but sometimes I wonder. Just in case, I
had better act, I ought to act, yes, I want to act so that they with a feeling of pride will smile
and applaud my scenes.
</p><p>
I love my parents and my grandparents. They are not dead. They live. Sometimes I think I
almost hear, or rather feel, their prayers for me! Surely they must be praying and pulling for
me, otherwise I would not have been so blessed. Again, I ask a merciful Father in heaven to
help me and to help you to play our scenes so well that we may fittingly deserve applause
from the balcony of the dead.
</p><p>
Look again, this tinge to the gallery. Over the glow of the footlights I see faces very
indistinctly. I recognize none of them. These, something tells me, are the spirits yet to come
and be embodied on this earth; they who must come to take our places. I wonder if they do
not watch with interest the Drama of Earth Life, and if they are not earnestly praying that we
will play our roles well, for they must come to dwell in the environment we are creating for
them. Once upon a time our Heavenly Father's children on this earth became so wicked that
he washed them and their wickedness off the stage with a great flood so that these spirits
might inherit a decent environment. This gallery of spirits will certainly applaud if we play
our parts well.
</p><p>
High up above the stage in this World Theater is a box. Look up. The glare of the overhead
floodlights obscures its occupant. This box is reserved for the Author
of the play&mdash;the Drama of Life. He not only is the Author, he is also the Critic and the
Judge. How glorious could be that day if in its morning&mdash;the morning after the curtain
falls&mdash;his press would announce: "Well done, thou good and faithful servant"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/21#21">Matt. 25:21</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, the world's a stage, so is the Church a stage, and you and I are merely players. We've
chosen noble roles in the Drama of Life. Let's play them well.
</p><p>
We can preach a better sermon with our lives than with our lips. We can do more good by
being good than by preaching good. Let us so act that our principle of action shall become a
law, not only for the Church, but also for the whole world. Eventually it will be. May that
time be soon, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
