<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle"><i>This</i> Gospel...Not <i>A</i> Gospel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 107-110</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
An ancient prophet gave the assurance that God would require nothing of his children save he
provided a way for them to carry out his commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/7#7">1 Ne. 3:7</a>). I rely on that promise and pray for
divine guidance.  Speaking of the Lord making provision for the carrying out of his
commandments, I am reminded that in ancient days and in our time he required that the
gospel of the kingdom should be preached to all the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).  When this commandment was
given to the founders of the Church, perhaps it seemed to be an insuperable task, but God has
kept his promise and has made provision whereby we are able to reach more people with the
gospel in a few minutes than our fathers could reach in years.  We are grateful for the
microphone, the radio and television; but these facilities, great as they are, as President Clark
indicated last night, are just in their infancy, and God will, in his own due time, give us such
improvements and amplifications as will enable us to carry out his great commandment.
</p><p>
We greet you, our friends out there in the radio and television audience who are not members
of our Church. We join with Christians everywhere, as has been indicated all through this
conference, in commemorating and giving thanks to God for the resurrection of the Lord. 
The significance of this transcendent event was emphasized by the Apostle Paul in that
matchless sermon recorded in Corinthians, in which, among other things, he said: "And if
Christ be not risen [from the dead], then is our preaching vain, and your faith is also vain"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/14#14">1 Cor. 15:14</a>).
</p><p>
We believe that the greatest story ever told in all the annals of history is the story of the
atonement of Christ. The record of his resurrection and ascension, without which the
atonement would not have been complete, is the climax to that story; and now, two thousand
years after the event, it is still central and pivotal in all true Christian thought.
</p><p>
Christ was both mortal and divine&mdash;mortal through his mother, Mary; divine through his
Father, God&mdash;and because of that unique combination he was able to yield voluntarily to
death in order that through his divinity he might conquer death, break its bands, and make the
resurrection possible to all men.  The resurrection is not for a select few, nor is it alone for
believing Christians; but every man and woman who ever lived upon earth,
or who ever shall live thereon, will be raised from the dead.
</p><p>
Paul, the apostle, epitomized the cause and consequences of the atonement in one sentence . . .
as in Adam all die, even so in Christ shall all be made alive"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/22#22">1 Cor. 15:22</a>). And the Savior
said,
</p><p>
Marvel not at this: for the hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves shall hear his
voice,<br />
And shall come forth; they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that
have done evil, unto the resurrection of damnation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/28-29#28">John 5:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
But we must not assume because of this promise that regardless of what we may do we shall
have exaltation and eternal life.  Those blessings are reserved for those who accept the gospel
of Jesus Christ and observe and keep the commandments of God.
</p><p>
We not only commemorate the resurrection of the Lord as an event in history, but we also
recognize it as a harbinger of things to come. When he gave his life on the cross, he did not
indicate that his interest in his fellow men had ceased. He promised, and his apostles
predicted, as did the prophets of the Old Testament, that there should be a second coming of
the Lord when, as Paul said,
</p><p>
. . . the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the archangel,
and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_thes/4/16#16">1 Thes. 4:16</a>).
</p><p>
But before his coming certain things must happen. Among them, as he said in answer to the
question of his apostles as to what should be the sign of his coming and the end of the world,
". . . this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations;
and then shall the end come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
It is significant that he said "this gospel of the
kingdom," not "a gospel," or "some gospel," but "this gospel." And the Apostle Paul, always
precise and zealous said: 
</p><p>
But though we, or an angel from heaven, preach any other gospel unto you than that which
we have preached unto you, let him be accursed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/1/8#8">Gal. 1:8</a>).
</p><p>
And still there are some who say it matters little or not at all which church one joins, which
gospel one preaches, whether it be the gospel of Luther, Knox, or Calvin, whether one
belongs to the Roman or Greek Catholic Church, to one of the numerous protestant
denominations, or to some group which emphasizes some one aspect of the gospel such as
faith healing, mode of baptism, which day is the Sabbath, etc.  Unfortunately the world is
faced with a variety of religious denominations which in some measure neutralize each others'
influence in the minds of people.
</p><p>
The question then arises, "Where shall we find that gospel?" The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints makes certain definite statements with respect to what the gospel is.  A
commission was appointed in England recently by the Archbishops of Canterbury and York to
make a complete survey of modern evangelism, and they were asked to seek and discover if
they could the causes for the wide and deep gulf that exists between the church and the
people.  This commission in the preamble to their report, emphasized the irrelevance of the
church in the life and thought of the community in general.
</p><p>
The most arresting observation made by the commission was, "We believe that the tendency
to preach another gospel, or a partial gospel, has been the weakness (not to say the sin) of the
church." This observation reminds us of Paul's warning and anathema which for emphasis he
repeated: 
</p><p>
As we said before, so say I now again, If any man preach any other gospel unto you than that
ye have received, let him be accursed (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/1/9#9">Gal. 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
What gospel did Paul preach?  All will agree that he was converted to the gospel of Jesus
Christ as now taught in the New Testament through personal communication and instruction.
He became one of its chief exponents, most effective and fearless defenders, and finally one
of its martyrs.  Many are asking, "Where can one find a church which teaches the gospel as
Paul taught it?" Any search for the true gospel leads at once to the matter of
origin and authority.
</p><p>
In a brief consideration of that subject we shall not challenge the claims of other churches
unless our claim that we have the gospel is taken as a challenge.  The Catholic Church bases
its claims to authority on the long line of apostolic succession.  Many of the other churches
began with a protest against or an attempted reformation of the so-called mother church.  As
the great reformers failed to change or reform the false teachings and undesirable conditions
they claimed to have discovered, and as they were successively excommunicated, some of
them undertook to establish new churches without claiming new revelation or authoritative
ordination.
</p><p>
The restored gospel of Jesus Christ does not base its claim to authority on apostolic
succession, nor did it begin with a protest against or attempt to reform other churches.
Furthermore, this Church did not have its beginning in scholarly analysis of the gospel as
taught in the Bible.  Its founder, at the time of his first vision, did not claim to be a profound
student of theology, and he knew little of the writings of the early church fathers.  His
message came as a direct revelation from heaven.
</p><p>
We say humbly but fearlessly that the restored gospel of Jesus Christ is the divinely inspired
way of life, the plan of salvation.  It is the gospel of the kingdom of which Jesus spoke
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).  It is,
as was its prototype in the Meridian of Time, the fulness of the everlasting and unchangeable
gospel, the very power of God unto salvation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>), the everlasting gospel which, through angelic
ministration in the latter days, was, according to John the beloved, to be carried to every
nation, kindred, tongue, and people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>).
</p><p>
Some express amazement and disbelief when we claim that the restoration began with a vision
of heavenly beings and revelations from God. These claims should not be thought incredible
to anyone who believes in the Holy Bible, for such events were standard procedure in both
the Old and New Testaments.
</p><p>
Mormonism is a message of glad tidings to all people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/10#10">Luke 2:10</a>), a glorious declaration that the
prophecies recorded in both Old and New Testaments concerning the latter days have been
and are being fulfilled.  It is an announcement that the God of heaven has set up a kingdom
as predicted by Daniel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/44#44">Dan. 2:44</a>).
It is a proclamation that the times of refreshing have come from the
presence of the Lord, when there is to be a restitution of all things which God has spoken by
the mouths of all his holy prophets since the world began as predicted by Peter
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/19-21#19">Acts 3:19-21</a>).
We humbly and gratefully announce the opening of the Dispensation of the Fulness
of Times in which, as promised by Paul, all things are to be gathered together in Christ, both
which are in heaven and which are on earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10#10">Eph. 1:10</a>).
</p><p>
The above scriptures concerning the restoration refer to the whole gospel. We think neither
individuals nor groups of men, under whatever title, are justified in their attempts to pick and
choose between particular aspects of the whole gospel.  We profoundly dissent from the
opinion that there is an element in the message which changes with varying conditions.  The
message of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is that there has been a restoration
of the identical gospel which Jesus taught and which the apostles preached at his command. It
is a gospel of glad tidings of great joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/10#10">Luke 2:10</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/3#3">Mosiah 3:3</a>),
a gospel of hope and saving power as was enjoyed by
members of the Church in the days of the Savior and his apostles.
</p><p>
The restored gospel is also a warning of judgment to come, a judgment which is neither
fiction nor superstition but is a tremendous and solemn truth, when all that is found valueless
or out of harmony with the purposes of God must be abolished.
</p><p>
Some may not understand how this message of good news can include a warning of judgment
to come, but judgment is integral to the gospel.  It is the assertion of the final triumph of
good and the abolition of evil.
</p><p>
While the Church, which was organized under divine direction, is the kingdom of God on
earth, its membership consists of men and women who are not yet made perfect. It is a mixed
society with an international complexion, subject in varying degrees to the
weaknesses of humanity. It does not claim to be a picture gallery where every portrait is a
masterpiece; therefore, Church membership requires continued tolerance, charity, and love of
fellow men.
</p><p>
We do not claim to have achieved perfection; we often fall short of our ideals; but with
additional revelations from the Lord, and with the gift of the Holy Ghost to help us, we hope
it may be said of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints what Peter said to the
Church of Jesus Christ of former-day Saints: 
</p><p>
But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye
should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvelous
light (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
We look upon the restoration and the second coming of Christ as sequels to the resurrection. 
We believe that a full understanding of the significance of the resurrection must include
consideration of and belief in his second coming which, as he himself declared, must be
preceded by the preaching of the gospel of the kingdom to all the world.
</p><p>
There are those who wonder at our assurance, and sometimes they say our presumption&mdash;as
we make such positive and definite statements, but we ask you, our friends: If you knew of a
revelation from God, and knew it to be a revelation, would you equivocate or water it down,
or be afraid to defend it, or assert it? In my opinion, no greater message has come to this
world since the angel standing at the open tomb said: "He is not here; he is risen" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/6#6">Mark 16:6</a>).
</p><p>
The announcement of the Church today, and let all people heed as they hear, is that this same
Jesus (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>)
has appeared again, established his kingdom, organized his Church with apostles and
prophets, and set in motion a great missionary system by which the gospel of Jesus Christ
shall be carried to all the world as a witness, and then the end shall come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
Humbly I bear my testimony to you, my friends, and brothers and sisters, that from the center
of my heart to the ends of my fingers and toes I know that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the
Living God. I know that he came forth from the tomb with his body, which he displayed to
his disciples, and invited them to feel of the wounds.  I know that he has spoken again.  I
know that the gospel has been restored to the earth. If this message be true, it should be heard
and heeded by all men everywhere, for it has in it the saving principles of the gospel of the
Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I leave this testimony with you, and thank God that he has given it to me, and pray that I
may be able to live so as to come back into his presence, and I remind all of you that any of
us may come into his presence when our conduct has been such that we can feel at home
there.
</p><p>
God bless us to that end I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
