<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1944, pp. 158-160</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We are all thankful that Brother Rufus K. Hardy has sufficiently recovered from a recent
illness to be in attendance at this conference. It has been deemed inadvisable, however, for
him to assume the responsibility of speaking. That is why you have been denied the privilege
of hearing him and of receiving his message.
</p><p>
Elder Sonne, one of the Assistants to the Twelve, has an appointment which conflicts with
this conference. We shall hear more about that later. He is on a special assignment by the
Church.
</p><p>
The listening audience has heard the message of each member of the General Authorities
except five, who spoke to the Priesthood meeting last evening&mdash;Elder Oscar A. Kirkham,
representing the First Council of the Seventy spoke on the preparation of body and intellect
for our spirituality and greater service. Bishop Marvin O. Ashton of the Presiding Bishopric
emphasized the value of honesty and consistent adherence to all the standards of the Church.
Elder Joseph F. Smith, the Patriarch, gave a talk on the significance of patriarchal blessings
and showed the relation of the Holy Ghost to these blessings. Elder Charles A. Callis, of the
Council of Twelve, spoke on the need of strong, loyal men, and the necessity of all working
together for the establishment of truth and universal brotherhood. President J. Reuben Clark,
Jr., urged the teaching of the simple truths of the Gospel, warned against the teaching of false
doctrine, and untried theories. These messages and those which you have heard over the radio
cover pretty well, I may say comprehensively cover, the teachings of the Church and our
duties therein. It has been a glorious conference. The Spirit of the Lord has been with us; and
now, brethren, as this conference ends, your duties begin. "If to do were as easy as to know
what were good to do, chapels had been churches, and poor men's cottages princes' palaces."
It is one thing to hear, it is another thing to do. The Savior taught that principle when he said:
</p><p>
Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven, but he
that doeth the will of my Father which is in heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/21#21">Matt. 7:21</a>).
</p><p>
Whosoever heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them, I will liken him unto a wise man,
which built his house upon a rock;
</p><p>
And the rain descended and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house;
and it fell not; for it was founded upon a rock.
</p><p>
And every one that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them not, shall be likened unto a
foolish man, which built his house upon the sand;
</p><p>
And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew and beat upon that house;
and it fell; and great was the fall of it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/24-27#24">Matt. 7:24-27</a>).
</p><p>
We have been here during these last few days preparing ourselves for greater work. We have
been as teachers preparing lessons. When a teacher prepares his lesson he receives benefits
from the efforts put forth and from his study. He is personally benefitted, but the preparation
of that lesson is but a means to an end, and that end the instruction of youth&mdash;the inspiring of
young men and women to higher and better living. So we go out now better prepared to teach
the men and women over whom we preside. The scope of that responsibility and that calling
can be well understood by the reference of Paul to the organization of the Church, wherein he
said:
</p><p>
 And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors
and teachers;
</p><p>
For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the body of
Christ.
</p><p>
Till we all come * * * unto a perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of
Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11-13#11">Eph. 4:11-13</a>).
</p><p>
I purposely, in quoting, omitted a phrase, the omission of which you will recognize. Well, we
will put that in and say, "till we all come to a unity of the faith and to a knowledge of the
Son of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/13#13">Eph. 4:13</a>). But I like to think that those are two conditions which lead to the perfect man,
till we all come "in a unity of the faith and a knowledge of the Son of God," unto a perfect
man, unto the measure of the stature of Christ. Unity, knowledge, a willingness to learn, a
willingness to serve.
</p><p>
Officers, leaders, men of the Priesthood, you are chosen of God. Go forth radiating a
testimony that this is God's work. Feel it yourselves and then the men and women in your
wards and stakes will feel it, for you are radiating not just what you say, but what you are
and what you do.
</p><p>
God guide us, and help us, and inspire us in this great work, I pray in the name of Jesus
Christ, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
