<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Principles of the Gospel Are Eternal</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Franklin D. Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Franklin D. Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 140-142</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, I rejoice in being with you this beautiful day in this peaceful
and inspirational environment, knowing that throughout the world there is generally a lack of
peace and men's hearts are failing them.
</p><p>
<b>World needs knowledge that God lives</b>
</p><p>
The great need in the world today is a knowledge that God lives and that he governs the
affairs of this world, that we are his spirit children, and that he is vitally interested in our
welfare. I am grateful for the knowledge I have that God lives and that Jesus is our Savior
and Redeemer. I am thankful for my testimony that Joseph Smith is a prophet of God, the
instrument through which the gospel was restored to earth.
</p><p>
We are blessed beyond measure by having a great prophet who stands at the head of the
Church of Jesus Christ at this time, our beloved David O. McKay. May the Lord bless and
sustain him. Peace will replace fear in men's hearts when they listen to the counsel of God's
Prophet and accept and follow the principles of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Gospel principles eternal</b>
</p><p>
One of the wonderful things about the gospel is that its principles are eternal and unchanging.
It is, therefore, true that as we live in accordance with these principles, we are assured results
consistent with our compliance. The Lord made this clear when he instructed us through the
Prophet Joseph Smith that "all who will have a blessing at my hands shall abide the law
which was appointed for that blessing" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/5#5">D&amp;C 132:5</a>).
</p><p>
Regarding this matter, Elder John A. Widtsoe said: "The great governing principles of truth
are unchanging. But, the conditions brought about by human activity are forever changing . .
. we span changes that in the past seemed impossible. And undoubtedly the future holds
developments that today are equally inconceivable.
</p><p>
"Such changes affect human thinking. New social and economic problems arise. Even the
spiritual outlook is invaded. Then, it becomes the duty of the Prophet to teach how the eternal
laws of the gospel may be applied amidst constant change, for the benefit and blessing of
humanity." (<i>Evidences &amp; Reconciliations</i>, 1960 edition, p. 351.)
</p><p>
With the rapid changes that are taking place today in every phase of our lives, it is very
important that we recognize the eternal nature of principles of truth. Faith in the Lord Jesus
Christ is <i>the first great eternal principle</i> of the gospel and is indeed a very vital factor in our
lives. Time it is one of the most interesting and inspiring principles to contemplate. I would
like to consider with you the principle of faith, together with its corollaries&mdash;work and
progress.
</p><p>
In consideration of this great principle we should recognize that it does not promise something
for nothing. The apostle James asked the question: 
</p><p>
<b>Faith the principle of action</b>
</p><p>
"What doth it profit, my brethren though a man say he hath faith, and have not works? Can
faith save him?
</p><p>
"If a brother or sister be naked, and destitute of daily food, And one of you say unto them,
Depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled; notwithstanding ye give them not those things
which are needful to the body; what doth it profit?
</p><p>
"Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead, being alone" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/14-17#14">James 2:14-17</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph, in speaking on this subject, said: "Let us here observe, that a religion that
does not require the sacrifice of all things never has power sufficient to produce the faith
necessary unto life and salvation . . . and it is through the medium of the sacrifice of all
earthly things that men do actually know that they are doing the things that are well pleasing
in the sight of God."
</p><p>
"And as faith is the moving cause of all action in temporal concerns, so it is in spiritual"
(Lecture 6:7 and Lecture 1:12).
</p><p>
Frequently we refer to the gospel of Jesus Christ as the gospel of work, and the Prophet
Joseph stated in his <i>Lectures on Faith</i> that this means mental as well as physical effort.
</p><p>
Plans are carefully developed before important projects are commenced. All worthwhile
endeavors require mental exertion&mdash;making decisions or the making up of one's
mind&mdash;before physical exertion comes into play.
</p><p>
We should realize that as we develop faith in the Lord Jesus Christ it is possible and natural
for us to develop faith in ourselves; and recognizing the great importance of faith in our lives,
we see the great need of continually building our faith. Among other things, the building of
faith involves a prayerful study of eternal gospel principles and the obtaining of a testimony
that God lives and that Jesus is the Christ. The process also involves making up one's mind to
live the gospel and serve his fellowmen through the sacrifice of earthly things. The Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints offers great opportunities for the building of faith.
</p><p>
Faith, being the moving cause of all action in temporal as well as spiritual concerns, is
evidenced by an affirmative attitude together with a well-developed plan of action. Nephi of
old, when required to go back to Jerusalem to get the record of his forefathers, possessed a
strong affirmative attitude, the evidence of a great faith, when he said: "I will go and do the
things which the Lord hath commanded, for I know that the Lord giveth no commandments
unto the children of men, save he shall prepare a way for them that they may accomplish the
thing which he commandeth them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/7#7">1 Ne. 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
On one occasion at a district conference, I was interviewing a man for ordination to the office
of elder. He was having some difficulty with the Word of Wisdom. I asked him what his
attitude was, and he replied that there was nothing in the world that he would rather do than
stop smoking.
</p><p>
I told him that all he had to do was to make up his mind never to have another cigarette and
that when he did that, 90 percent of his problem would be solved. I would then tell him what
the other ten percent was.
</p><p>
I asked him to make up his mind immediately, look me in the eye, shake my hand firmly, and
tell me that he would never have another cigarette. I extended my hand to him and asked him
if he were ready. He hesitated a moment and said, "No," that he was afraid that if he
promised he would not smoke and then later did so, his conscience would hurt him.
</p><p>
Under these circumstances I could not approve his ordination and so told him, since I felt
there would be many things that he would not do that an elder should do. He left considerably
disturbed.
</p><p>
Later in the day he asked to speak to me again. As he sat down his face lighted up. He said
that he had made up his mind to stop smoking and that he had never experienced such a
wonderful feeling in his whole life. He felt as though a 50-pound weight had been lifted from
his shoulders.
</p><p>
He then asked me what the other ten percent was. I told him that if he had any cigarettes on
him or at home, he should get rid of them immediately so they would not be a temptation.
</p><p>
I also suggested that he discontinue going out with his smoking friends on his breaks. These
and other things that he could do to strengthen himself constituted the other ten percent. Then,
with prayer and fasting by himself and with his family, he could be assured that the Lord
would make him equal to the task of overcoming the smoking habit. This incident occurred
some six years ago. He has never smoked since and is now an honored and respected bishop.
Thus, through his affirmative attitude and works, he manifested his faith; and with the help of
the Lord, he achieved his goal.
</p><p>
<b>Faith, the cause; works, the effect</b>
</p><p>
Effective faith is always connected with works, and it is only through this combination that
we achieve. This is indeed the key to success, happiness, and growth. Keeping in mind that
faith is a gift of God, some of the blessings that come from obedience to the great principle
of faith are: 
</p><p>
A desire to achieve worthwhile objectives.
</p><p>
An affirmative attitude with the capacity to really make up one's mind.
</p><p>
Confidence and power that make the difficult or seemingly hopeless possible of attainment.
</p><p>
Loyalty and steadfastness in service to our fellowmen.
</p><p>
And finally, peace, happiness, and growth resulting from achievement of worthwhile
objectives.
</p><p>
It was necessary for each of us as spirits to leave the spirit world and come to this earth and
learn to walk by faith, that the purposes of this life might be accomplished.
</p><p>
As we enter into each activity of life, both spiritual and temporal, let us apply these great
fundamental and eternal principles of faith and works. By so doing we can be assured like
Nephi of old that the Lord will prepare a way for us to do the things we are assigned to do
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/7#7">1 Ne. 3:7</a>).
Our hearts will not fail us, we will achieve our righteous objectives, and we will have peace
that surpasseth all understanding.
</p><p>
I bear this testimony to you in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
