<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Did Joseph Smith See God?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Merrill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Merrill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1947, pp. 132-137</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren and sisters, listeners here and elsewhere: 
</p><p>
JOSEPH SMITH'S FIRST VISION
</p><p>
Mormonism, as the world generally calls the religious faith taught by the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints, is noted for many characteristic teachings, one of which is that
Joseph Smith was divinely called, beginning with a most wonderful and glorious vision.
Relative to this matter a basic and fundamental question that every member of the Church
may rightfully ask, as well as every honest investigator, is "Did Joseph Smith really see
God?"
</p><p>
As I view it, this is perhaps the most natural and logical question that can be asked
concerning the origin of Mormonism. It is one that might well challenge the attention of
every person who believes in God and in life beyond the grave, whether he is a Mormon or
non-Mormon.
</p><p>
All informed Latter-day Saints know the story of the first vision as related by Joseph Smith.
He was a member of a sincerely religious family but belonged to no church. Though he was
only fourteen years old at the time, this fact of non-church membership worried him. As a
means of helping him to solve his problem, he read the Bible with deep interest, for he
wanted to know which of the contending churches was the right one to join. He therefore
resolved to heed the injunction of James
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5-6#5">James 1:5-6</a>)
and so went into the woods and
prayed that God would give him wisdom that he might know what to do. In answer to the
boy's simple prayer, he related that he was enveloped in a pillar of brilliant light which
descended from above. Looking up he beheld two personages standing above him whose
brightness and glory defied all description. One of them, calling him by name and pointing to
the other said, 'This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>)
and then Joseph heard the voice of Jesus
Christ, the Son, and received instructions from him.
</p><p>
Thus, according to his story, Joseph Smith, the fourteen-year-old lad, saw the Father and the
Son and heard their voices. So far as the records indicate, this was the most glorious vision
ever given to mortal man. Never before had both Father and Son appeared
simultaneously to any mortal man. I have called your attention to Joseph's story
because of its extreme importance to our faith&mdash;to Mormonism, which we testify is the
restored gospel of Jesus Christ. So I ask again, did Joseph Smith really and in fact see God? I
believe all of us can profit by asking ourselves this question, occasionally at least. The correct
answer can be stimulating and satisfying to us.
</p><p>
THE VISION GAVE EVIDENCE OF A PERSONAL GOD
</p><p>
The implications of the affirmative answer are tremendously significant. Through
misunderstanding and wrong interpretations the world had lost the correct conception of the
image and personality of God. To restore the truth, a new revelation was imperative. Though
from the beginning to its end, the Bible, as we understand it, teaches that God is a personal
being in whose image we are made, and that the Father and the Son are two separate and
distinct personalities, alike in image and attributes, yet the modern world, through ignorance
and lack of understanding, denies these fundamental truths. And so important are these truths
to a satisfying faith that, I think, they are absolutely basic. Without any concrete conception
of the image of God, how can one develop the necessary faith of the kind that the Apostle
James asserts is needed to get an answer to prayer. Yes, God the Father and his Son, Jesus
Christ, are personal beings in whose image man himself is made, so declared Joseph Smith.
Hence in this sense we do believe in an anthropomorphic God and take great satisfaction in
this belief.
</p><p>
TRUTHFULNESS OF JOSEPH SMITH'S CLAIMS
</p><p>
In addition to seeing the Father and the Son, Joseph also claimed he was visited, in his
eighteenth year, by the Angel Moroni who among other things told him that his "... name
should be had for good and evil among all nations, kindreds, and tongues, or that it should be
both good and evil spoken of among all people"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/33#33">JS&mdash;H 1:33</a>). This was a very daring
and reckless statement for Joseph to make, unless in very truth it was spoken to him by a
divine messenger; for Joseph was then only seventeen years of age, a very poor and
unschooled lad, living in a frontier village. Humanly speaking, there were no discernible
prospects that he would ever be known beyond the limits of his own backwoods area.
</p><p>
Now, what evidence can we present of the truthfulness of Joseph Smith's claims, one might
ask. Such a question is both natural and reasonable. My time in this meeting will permit of
indicating only a few of the highlights relative to the man, his teachings, and his works. In his
great Sermon on the Mount, Jesus emphasized the principle that a tree is judged by its fruits
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16-20#16">Matt. 7:16-20</a>).
Can there be a more fair, just, and satisfactory basis of judgment than this? All followers of
the Prophet will ask for no other.
</p><p>
JOSEPH SMITH'S ACCOMPLISHMENTS
</p><p>
Then as to the man: He was born of worthy parents who lived in humble circumstances in
one of the rural areas of Vermont. When Joseph was ten years old, the family moved to the
frontiers of western New York where it continued by dint of frugality and hard work to earn a
very modest livelihood. Joseph grew to manhood denied most of the opportunities for even a
common school education, his school training therefore being very limited. Judged by modern
standards, he was practically uneducated and untrained for leadership in any sphere of
intellectual endeavor. Thus handicapped in the eyes of the world, is it any wonder that he was
rejected by people generally and his stories regarded as the product of a wild and foolish
imagination?
</p><p>
But notwithstanding all the severely handicapping conditions from an economic and
educational point of view, what did Joseph Smith become? Let me make a few quotes. First
from John Henry Evans' book entitled, <i>Joseph Smith, An American Prophet</i>, we read:
</p><p>
Here is a man who was born in the stark hills of Vermont; who was reared in the
backwoods of New York; who never looked inside a college or high school; who
lived in six States, no one of which would own him during his lifetime; who spent
months in the vile prisons of the period; who, even when he had his freedom, was
hounded like a fugitive; who was covered once with a coat of tar and feathers, and
left for dead; who, with his following, was driven by irate neighbors from New
York to Ohio, from Ohio to Missouri, and from Missouri to Illinois; and who, at
the unripe age of thirty-eight, was shot to death by a mob with painted faces.
</p><p>
Yet this man became mayor of the biggest town in Illinois and the state's most
prominent citizen, the commander of the largest body of trained soldiers in the
nation outside of the Federal army, the founder of cities and of a university, and
aspired to become President of the United States.
</p><p>
He wrote a book [the Book of Mormon] which has baffled the literary critics for
a hundred years and which is today more widely read than any other volume save
the Bible. On the threshold of an organizing age he established the most nearly
perfect social mechanism in the modern world, and developed a religious
philosophy that challenges anything of the kind in history, for completeness and
cohesion. And he set up the machinery for an economic system that would take
the brood of fears out of the heart of man&mdash;the fear of want through sickness, old
age, unemployment, and poverty.
</p><p>
In thirty nations are men and women who look upon him as a Greater leader than
Moses and a Greater prophet than Isaiah; his disciples now number close to a
million; and already two granite shafts pierce the sky, one over the place where
he was born, and the other over the place where he received the inspiration for his
Book.
</p><p>
JOSIAH QUINCY'S OPINION
</p><p>
Further, you may be interested to hear what a nationally-known writer and publicist and once
mayor of Boston, Josiah Quincy, wrote about Joseph Smith. In May 1844, Mr. Quincy and his
cultured friend, Charles Francis Adams, son and grandson, respectively, of
two United States Presidents, happened to make a two-day visit to Nauvoo. Being
well-known, prominent men they were entertained at the Mansion House, Joseph Smith's
residence. An account of this visit is given by Mr. Quincy, in the last chapter of his book
entitled <i>Figures of the Past</i>, published in 1880. I quote the following from this twenty-four
page chapter:
</p><p>
It is by no means improbable that some future textbook for the use of generations yet unborn,
will contain a question something like this:  What historical American of the nineteenth
century has exerted the most powerful influence upon the destinies of his countrymen? And it
is by no means impossible that the answer to that interrogatory may be thus written: Joseph
Smith, the Mormon Prophet. And the reply, absurd as it doubtless seems to most men now
living, may be an obvious commonplace to their descendants.  History deals in surprises and
paradoxes quite as startling as this. The man who established a religion in this age of free
debate, who was and is today accepted by hundreds of  thousands as a direct emissary from
the Most High,&mdash;such a rare human being is not to be disposed of by pelting his memory with
unsavory epithets. Fanatic, imposter, charlatan, he may have been; but these hard names
furnish no solution to the problem he presents to us. Fanatics and impostors are living and
dying every day, and their memory is buried with them; but the wonderful influence which
this founder of a religion exerted and still exerts throws him into relief before us, not as a
rogue to be criminated, but as a phenomenon to be explained. The most vital questions
Americans are asking each other today have to do with this man and what he has left us  . . .
Joseph Smith claiming to be an inspired teacher, faced adversity such as few men have been
called to meet, enjoyed a brief season of prosperity such as few men have ever attained, and
finally, forty-three days after I saw him, went cheerfully to a martyr's death.
</p><p>
Born in the lowest ranks of poverty, without book-learning, and with the
homeliest of all human names, he had made himself at the age of thirty-nine a power
upon earth. Of the multitudinous family of Smith . . . none had won human hearts
and shaped human lives as this Joseph. His influence, whether for good or evil, is
potent today, and the end is not yet.
</p><p>
Mr. Quincy concludes his chapter with these words: 
</p><p>
I have endeavored to give the details of my visit to the Mormon prophet
absolute accuracy. If the reader does not know just what to make of Joseph
Smith, I cannot help him out of the difficulty. I myself stand helpless before
puzzle.
</p><p>
QUOTATION PROM NEW YORK TIMES
</p><p>
Now I recite one more quotation from an unfriendly writer in the New York <i>Times</i> of
September 4, 1843:
</p><p>
This Joe Smith must be set down as an extraordinary character, a prophet-hero,
as Carlyle might call him. He is one of the great men of this age, and in future
history will rank with those who, in one way or another, have stamped their
impress strongly on society.
</p><p>
It is no small thing, in the blaze of the nineteenth century, to give to men a new
revelation. found a new religion, establish new forms of worship, to build a city
with new laws, institutions, and orders of architecture, to
establish ecclesiastical, civil and military jurisdiction, found colleges, send out
missionaries, and make proselytes on two hemispheres. Yet all this has been done
by Joe Smith, and that against every sort of opposition, ridicule, and persecution.
</p><p>
In the short space of fifteen years, Joseph Smith, unschooled in the learning and the methods
of the world, did all these important things. How was it possible?  Does not the only rational
explanation lie in the claim that he was God-taught and that the statement is literally true
which asserts,
</p><p>
. . . I raised you up, that I might show forth my wisdom through the weak things of the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/1#1">D&amp;C 124:1</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, Joseph Smith was able to confound the wise, to astonish the learned, and to outmarvel
the great.
</p><p>
TRUTHS TAUGHT BY JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
I have briefly indicated who Joseph Smith was and some of the things he accomplished. Now
another important question is what characteristic things did he teach&mdash;things not taught by
other churches. A number of these are mentioned in the thirteen widely used Articles of Faith
of the Church, and written by the Prophet himself. Many of his teachings are not accepted by
the world, but time will permit me to speak of only a few of them. I have already indicated
one such teaching&mdash;a very important and basic one&mdash;the personality and image of
God the Father and of Jesus Christ his Son who redeemed mankind from the bondage of
death, brought about by the fall of Adam. He also taught that we are spirit children of the
Father and had an individual, conscious existence with him and Jesus Christ, our elder spirit
brother, before we were born in mortality. Unquestionably, God created us in the flesh, and
biologists teach that the human family came from the same parents. It follows that the
universal brotherhood of man, both in the spirit and in the flesh, is a divine truth.
</p><p>
Another closely related teaching to the fatherhood of God is the personality and actuality of
Satan, the devil. He is a real person with a spirit body in the image of man. He is here on
earth, accompanied by a multitude of other spirit persons who cooperate with him in his evil
work. This fact should be kept in mind by all who sincerely desire to live righteously and
resist temptations to do wrong. All such temptations stem right back to the devil and his host
of evil spirits, spirit brothers of ours who because of rebellion were cast out of heaven. They
are permitted by the Father to be here as a means of testing us to find if in the exercise of our
free agency we can prove ourselves worthy to return to his presence.
</p><p>
And this suggests a word relative to free agency&mdash;the freedom the Father has given to every
child born in mortality to do as he pleases so long as he does not infringe upon or deny this
freedom to others. Multitudes of people in the world today deny the
existence of a loving and merciful Heavenly Father because he permits war with its associated
terrors and horrors. Such persons do not understand the divine doctrine of free agency, else
they would never hold the Lord responsible for the wickedness, crimes, and horrors in which
his children engage. The Lord is merciful, loving, and good to all his children who will
refrain from doing evil and follow the way of life he has given them. He said to Moses:
</p><p>
. . . this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
And the Lord will not fail in his purpose with those of his children who will render obedience
to, and cooperate with, him.
</p><p>
This leads to a word relative to the beautiful doctrine of salvation for the dead, taught by the
Prophet Joseph Smith. This doctrine, as I understand it, absolutely reveals the Father as a God
of love, mercy, forgiveness, justice, and all other attributes we ascribe to a perfect Father. He
has given his children their free agency. He has prepared for them a plan of eternal
progression. Not one of them will be annihilated&mdash;all will have eternal life, be they saints or
sinners. Every one coming into mortality will in this life or in the life beyond the grave have
the opportunity of hearing and accepting the gospel of Jesus Christ. Those who comply with
all the conditions, which they will have the privilege of doing, will eventually be saved in the
Father's kingdom.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, how beautiful is the way of the Lord! How great his mercy and
forgiveness! How all-embracing his love!
</p><p>
But it is very largely to the teachings and labors of the Prophet Joseph Smith that the modern
world is indebted for a correct interpretation of the plan of life, salvation, and exaltation that
the Lord has provided for his children to follow if they would care to return to his presence.
</p><p>
I close with the thought that Joseph Smith, his claims, his teachings, and his achievements are
so very remarkable in character that they challenge every normal human being able to do so,
to make an honest and thorough investigation of them. A refusal to do this is likely to bring
sometime, somewhere, painful regrets and handicaps as a consequence. Certainly every
member of the Church, in justice to himself, should rouse up to the performance of this
important duty. May every one of us worthily seek the help of the Lord in responding to the
calls of duty I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
