<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bruce R. McConkie</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bruce R. McConkie, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 123-125</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It has been my privilege, for seven years now, to serve on the First Council of the Seventy
with Elder Richard L. Evans, and I think I can certify to you from personal knowledge, born
of that association, that Brother Richard is a man of great ability and devotion to the cause of
Christ. He supports and sustains the brethren and the programs of the Church, and, I am
persuaded, has a great mission to perform in his new and high calling.
</p><p>
I think, perhaps, there is scarcely a name in the Church more widely known
and heralded than his; and in the field of his especial talent and assignment, that of radio, he
approaches as near the indispensable man as any man could. For myself, and I am sure,
speaking also for the other members of the Council, we are pleased with the selection that has
been made and give him, as we do all the brethren who sit on this stand, our united support
and love and affection.
</p><p>
Brother Hugh B. Brown and Brother Marion D. Hanks, as yet, I do not know well, but with
the rest of these brethren, and with all of you, I extend a welcome hand of fellowship.
</p><p>
I have had it in my heart for some time, if the Spirit would give me utterance and direction, to
say a few words in this great conference about that faith which leads to life and salvation and
without which no man can be saved in the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Briefly, speaking in outline form only, I would like to suggest: 
</p><p>
First, what faith is.
</p><p>
Second, how faith may be gained.
</p><p>
And third, the test whereby it may be known whether we have gained faith in sufficient
measure to justify a hope of life and salvation.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith taught, as may be found recorded in the <i>Lectures on Faith</i>&mdash;which
lectures I commend to all men&mdash;that faith is the first principle in revealed religion, that it is
the foundation of all righteousness, that it is a principle of power. He taught that faith is the
assurance which men have of the existence of things which they have not seen, that it is the
moving cause of all action in intelligent beings, and that it is the first great governing
principle which has power, dominion, and authority over all things.
</p><p>
He gave this formula whereby men may exercise faith in God unto life and salvation: 
</p><p>
First, we must believe in God, and that means in the true and living God, the Being who
actually exists and is our Father in heaven, in whose image we are created, and who by his
grace and because of his desire to see his children gain salvation, appeared in our day, with
his beloved Son, to usher in this great work.
</p><p>
It is not sufficient to believe in a god of wood or stone, one that has been created by men, or
to believe in the god described in the creeds that have been created by men. We have to get
to the truth if we are to have faith.
</p><p>
Faith is founded on truth. It was Alma who said that, "... if ye have faith ye hope for things
which are not seen, which are true"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/32/21#21">Alma 32:21</a>),
and so, without truth, there can be no faith.
</p><p>
The second requisite in gaining faith is to have a correct idea of the character, perfections,
and attributes of God. The Prophet summarizes the character of God in these words, and I
think every member of the Church ought to memorize them: 
</p><p>
First, that he was God before the world was created and the same God that he was after it
was created.
</p><p>
Second, that he is merciful and gracious, slow to anger
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/neh/9/17#17">Neh. 9:17</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/103/8#8">Ps. 103:8</a>),
abundant in goodness, and that he
was so from everlasting and will be so to everlasting
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/41/13#13">Ps. 41:13</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/17#17">D&amp;C 20:17</a>).
</p><p>
Third, that he changes not (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/19#19">Morm. 9:19</a>),
neither is there variableness with him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/17#17">James 1:17</a>),
and that his course is one eternal round
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/35/1#1">D&amp;C 35:1</a>).
</p><p>
Fourth, that he is a God of truth and cannot lie
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/titus/1/2#2">Titus 1:2</a>).
</p><p>
Fifth, that he is no respecter of persons
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/34#34">Acts 10:34</a>);
</p><p>
And sixth, that he is love (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/8#8">1 Jn. 4:8</a>).
</p><p>
Then the Prophet gives the attributes of God, also six in number, as follows: knowledge, faith
or power, justice, judgment, mercy, and truth. The perfections of God are given as the
perfections which attach to the attributes of his nature.
</p><p>
Then the third requisite for gaining faith unto life and salvation is so to live that we have the
actual knowledge that the course of life we are pursuing is in harmony with the divine will.
</p><p>
I suppose there are many people in the Church who have a measurable
knowledge of the attributes of God. I think there are even more who have a correct idea of
his character and of his perfections. And I am sure that nearly all, perhaps all in the Church,
believe in him as the personal Being who actually lives. But the place where we fall down in
acquiring faith, faith unto life and salvation, is in that we do not order our lives in such a way
that we have the assurance that our conduct is in harmony with the divine will.
</p><p>
Faith comes by righteousness, and without righteousness and obedience we cannot have the
measure of faith that will save us.
</p><p>
Now the test whereby it may be known whether we do have faith is very simple. It is the
eternal truth proclaimed by the Lord when he said: "And these signs shall follow them that
believe" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/17#17">Mark 16:17</a>).
If we have faith, there will be signs. If there are no signs, there is no
faith. Where there is faith, there will be the gifts of the Spirit; there will be the ministering of
angels and the working of miracles. Where there is faith, there will be apostles and prophets;
there will be the authority of the priesthood; there will be the knowledge of God and the
organization of the kingdom of God on earth.
</p><p>
Now, I suggest to you that faith is the great foundation upon which we must build: faith in
God, faith in Christ, faith in the restored truth and in the living oracles who direct the
kingdom under the Lord in our day.
</p><p>
By faith all things can be done. There is nothing too hard
for the Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/18/14#14">Gen. 18:14</a>),
and if we have faith, we can do whatever is requisite, according to his mind and
will. By faith the worlds were made (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/3#3">Heb. 11:3</a>);
by faith the elements can be controlled, rivers turned out
of their courses, mountains removed. By faith we can have angels minister to us, see our sick
healed, and the dead raised; and what is more important than all this by faith we can live so
as to become the sons of God and be joint heirs with Jesus Christ, entitled to receive and
inherit and possess, as he has done before, the fulness of the kingdom of the Father.
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
