<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Priesthood and Perfecting the Saints</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 86-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
While Elder Lee and the other members of the twelve were presenting the outline of the great
correlation work now in preparation, a passage of scripture came to my mind, which I shall
quote, if I can, which will summarize the purpose of all this work: 
</p><p>
"And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some, pastors
and teachers; "For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying
of the body of Christ: 
</p><p>
"Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a
perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11-13#11">Eph. 4:11-13</a>).
</p><p>
That is what these brethren have in mind. That is what you brethren of the priesthood,
assembled in these vast congregations tonight, have in mind, because you are servants of the
Most High, and he has given you the responsibility of perfecting the Saints, of working in the
ministry, for edifying the Saints of God, and the object is the perfecting of the individual.
</p><p>
There are many who are working tonight in positions who are sometimes discouraged. They
may be in a bishopric, some may be in the presidencies of stakes, some may be in the
presidencies of quorums, some deacons who feel, "Well, I am not doing anything." Teachers
who are asked to go ward teaching sometimes feel they are incompetent, inadequate to teach.
The plans that have been outlined today for you will be an aid no matter what position you
may be holding, and you who feel inadequate, particularly the young boys who hold the
office of teacher, when you go into the home of a man of the priesthood, and you feel
inadequate to do your duty, remember this, given by a nonmember of the Church, but it
contains encouragement: 
</p><p>
"Who does his task from day to day<br />
     And meets whatever comes his way,<br />
     Believing God has willed it so,<br />
     Has found real greatness here below.
</p><p>
"Who guards his post, no matter where,<br />
     Believing God must need him there,<br />
     Although but lowly toil it be,<br />
     Has risen to nobility.
</p><p>
"For great and low there's but one test: <br />
     'Tis that each man shall do his best.<br />
     Who works with all the strength he can<br />
     Shall never die in debt to man."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                    (Edgar A. Guest)
</p><p>
God bless the priesthood of the Church of Jesus Christ throughout the whole world. They are
called to serve; to serve the members of the Church, and to serve the world by preaching the
everlasting gospel. May the Lord guide us, inspire us, never leave us alone, I pray, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
