<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Spirituality in Leading and Teaching the Gospel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">(Read by his son, Robert R. McKay)</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 142-146</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
And now, my brethren and sisters, just a word in parting. This truly has been a glorious and
memorable conference. May our Heavenly Father sanctify the instructions, admonitions, and
testimonies that we have heard throughout the various sessions. May he fill our hearts with
love for one another in the true brotherhood of Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Unity of the brethren</b>
</p><p>
At this time I should like to express gratitude for the support, blessings, and assistance of my
counselors and members of the Council of the Twelve; also, for the help of the Patriarch to
the Church, the Assistants to the Twelve, the members of the First Council of the Seventy,
and the Presiding Bishopric. You can feel radiating from these men that for which Christ
prayed when he offered that great intercessory prayer in which he said, among other things,
"And now I am no more in the world, but these are in the world, and I come to thee. Holy
Father, keep through thine own name those whom thou hast given me, that they may be one,
as we are" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/11#11">John 17:11</a>).
</p><p>
These brethren prove daily, as was particularly evidenced in a sacred pre-conference meeting
of all the General Authorities held in the Salt Lake Temple on Thursday, September 26, 1968,
that they have that spirit of oneness, and we are united in praying that you presidencies of
stakes, bishoprics of wards, presidencies of temples, presidencies of quorums, presidencies and
superintendencies of auxiliaries may be so blessed that you too may say, "We strive to be one,
as the Father and Son are one." God bless you that this may be true.
</p><p>
<b>Gratitude for workers</b>
</p><p>
I am also most grateful for those unsung workers behind the scenes who give of themselves in
rendering service beyond the call of duty to assist in the preparation of the hundreds of details
and important matters that are necessary in order that these conferences may be carried on
efficiently and smoothly.
</p><p>
You know, I am afraid too many of us are like that Scotsman of whom I have told you before
who had lost his wife by death. His neighbor called on him to give comfort to him, saying
what a good neighbor his wife had been, how thoughtful of others she had been, and what a
good wife she had been to Jock, who was mourning her death. Jock answered: "Aye,
Tammas, Janet was a guid woman, a guid neighbor as you say. She was a' you say an mair.
She was, aye, a guid true wifey tae me, and I cam' near tellin' her sae aince or twice."
</p><p>
There come to mind some others to whom I wish to express gratitude. We have not heard
from them. They are the men and women throughout the entire Church who are contributing
of their time and means to the advancement of the truth&mdash;not just in teaching, but in genuine
service in many ways. Some of these are struggling to make their own living. Some of them
are wealthy men and women who have retired and who count their wealth in millions. It
means something when a man of means will give to the Church a contribution of a million
dollars, and then, in addition, say, "All my time is yours, to serve the Church." It means
something to have a man leave his vocation, have his life's work interrupted, and receive a
call to go away from the state, sometimes across the ocean to faraway places, to render
service to the Church, not knowing for sure when he will return. God bless those who are
rendering such service, and bless you all, for I think we can say for the Church, "We are
striving to be one, Father, as thou and thy Son are one."
</p><p>
<b>Divine character of Jesus</b>
</p><p>
Now a word to you officers and leaders in the stakes and wards, in missions, and in temples.
It was the divine character of Jesus that drew the women of Palestine to him, that drew as a
magnet the little children to him. It was that divine personality which attracted men, honest
men, pure men. It was also that divine personality which antagonized the impure, the evil men
and women.
</p><p>
In the realm of personality, and in the kingdom of character, Christ was supreme. By
personality, I mean all that may be, included in individuality. Personality is a gift from God;
it is indeed a "pearl of great price" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/46#46">Matt. 13:46</a>), an eternal blessing.
</p><p>
Fellow workers, you and I cannot hope to exert even to a small degree the personality of our
great teacher, Jesus Christ. Each one's personality may be compared to the Savior's personality
only as one little sunbeam to the mighty sun itself; and yet, though infinitely less in degree,
each leader's, each teacher's personality should be the same in kind. In the realm of character,
each leader and teacher may be superior, and such a magnet as to draw around him or her, in
an indescribable way, those whom he or she would lead or teach. It is the radiation of the
light that attracts.
</p><p>
<b>Teach love of truth</b>
</p><p>
However, no matter how attractive the personality may be, that leader or teacher fails in the
work assigned if the leader or teacher directs the love of the member only to the personality
of the leader or teacher. It is the leader's duty, or the teacher's duty, to teach the member to
love&mdash;not the leader or teacher, but the truth of the gospel. Always, everywhere, we find
Christ losing himself for his Father's will; and so also should our leaders and teachers, so far
as their personalities are concerned, lose themselves for the truth he desires to have them
teach.
</p><p>
When the people came to Jesus and asked for bread, or the truth, he never turned them away
with a stone (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/9#9">Matt. 7:9</a>). He always had truth to give. He understood it. It radiated from his being. He
understood how to use illustrations, the natural things around him, to impress that truth upon
his hearers. In other words, he was filled with his subject and then was enabled to give that
subject to his hearers. It is not always what you say, but what you <i>are</i> that influences children,
the young, or that influences your associates. "What you are," said the alleged wisest of
Americans, "thunders so loud in, my ears I cannot hear what you say."
</p><p>
<b>Characteristics of successful leader</b>
</p><p>
Let me give you briefly five things, among many others, that may characterize the successful
leader or teacher in the Church:
</p><p>
<i>First</i>: Implicit faith in the gospel of Jesus Christ as the light of the world, and a sincere desire
to serve him. This condition of the soul will make for companionship and guidance of the
Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
<i>Second</i>: Unfeigned love for the child, or member. Unfeigned&mdash;remember how the word is
used by the Prophet Joseph Smith in that great revelation in the Doctrine and Covenants: "by
love unfeigned" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41#41">D&amp;C 121:41</a>). Unfeigned love for the children or members, guided by determination to deal
justly and impartially with every member of the Church. Honor the child or member, and the
child or member will honor you.
</p><p>
<i>Third</i>: Thorough preparation. The successful leader knows his duties and responsibilities and
also the members under his direction. The teacher knows his children, as well as the lessons.
</p><p>
<i>Fourth</i>: Cheerfulness&mdash;not forced but natural cheerfulness, springing spontaneously from a
hopeful soul.
</p><p>
<i>Fifth</i>: Power to act nobly.
</p><p>
"If you want to be a teacher or leader<br />
       just watch your acts and walk;<br />
     If you want to be a teacher or leader,<br />
       just be careful how you talk."
</p><p>
<b>Radiate the light</b>
</p><p>
If you want to radiate the light of the gospel, that radiation must first come from the leader
himself. In the Doctrine and Covenants, the Lord says, "If you keep not my commandments,
the love of the Father shall not continue with you, therefore you shall walk in darkness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/95/12#12">D&amp;C 95:12</a>).
</p><p>
That solicitous admonition given by the Savior is as pertinent today as it was when first
expressed. Men and nations, having refused to "walk in the light" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>), as Jesus said, stumble in
darkness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/10#10">John 11:10</a>) and know not whither they go (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/35#35">John 12:35</a>). Motivated for centuries largely by selfish interests,
the human race, judging from present world conditions, is still dangerously near the jungle
where primitive passions dominate and govern.
</p><p>
<b>"We have forgotten God"</b>
</p><p>
Abraham Lincoln, in his day, declared to the people: "We have been the recipients of the
choicest bounties of Heaven; we have been preserved these many years, in peace and
prosperity; we have grown in numbers, wealth, and power as no nation has ever grown. But
we have forgotten God . . . We have vainly imagined, in the deceitfulness of our hearts, that
all these blessings were produced by some superior wisdom and virtue of our own.
Intoxicated by unbroken success, we have become too self-sufficient to feel the necessity of
redeeming and preserving grace, too proud to pray to God who made us.
</p><p>
"It behooves us, then, to humble ourselves before the offended Power, to confess our national
sins, and to pray for clemency and forgiveness . . .
</p><p>
"I still have confidence that the Almighty, the Maker of the Universe, will, through the
instrumentality of this great and intelligent people, bring us through this as he has through all
other difficulties of our country." And we all know how God did guide Abraham Lincoln.
</p><p>
<b>Jesus Christ our head</b>
</p><p>
There are many instances about which I could tell you wherein the hand of the Lord has been
manifest in guiding his servants. I know it is real. I know it as I know that you are assembled
in this conference. I know one's spirit can be in tune, and hear that sweet, still, small voice
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/12#12">1 Kgs. 19:12</a>). I
know he will warn us. I know he will never say anything that is impossible to understand. I
know he is our Father in heaven. He is just as real as my earthly father and mother, whom I
hope to meet over there. The Savior, the Son of God, is at the head of this Church. I am not
the head of this Church&mdash;Jesus Christ is our head! I know that the former Presidents of the
Church knew that, and declared it. Joseph Smith, the Prophet, knew it. This is Christ's
Church, and we are his messengers, his representatives, and it is our duty to keep in touch
with him and know what his wishes are. You and I, and all who have repented of their sins
and have been baptized into this Church, have had hands laid upon our heads and are entitled
to the companionship and inspiration of the Holy Ghost. If we keep in tune with Christ and
his teachings, we are entitled to fellowship with him. He does not love sin, he does not love
lying, nor stealing, misjudging one another, nor condemning others. We have to keep our
hearts pure and clean to be worthy of his fellowship.
</p><p>
God help us so to live that we may be found worthy to hear from him the whisperings of his
Spirit, the whisperings of his voice, as he guides us and warns us and tells us what to do in
order to come back into his presence.
</p><p>
<b>Lose lives in service</b>
</p><p>
Man is not living for himself. His selfish desires should be overcome and controlled, and he
should render service to others. One of the greatest sayings of Jesus, when he was among the
Twelve during his two and one-half years here, was the one that touched upon that same
principle: "He that findeth his life shall lose it [that is the selfish part] and he that loseth his
life for my sake shall find it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/39#39">Matt. 10:39</a>). A paradoxical statement, but oh, how true!
Thousands upon thousands in the Church are willing to lose their lives in service to the
building up of the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
<b>Prayer for God's help</b>
</p><p>
I pray that God will give us strength to continue our mission here in life and, by our actions
and our words, to teach others so that we shall bring the honest in heart to know the truth.
May we show to all that the gospel has been established in this dispensation for happiness and
joy and salvation here in this life, as well as in the life to come.
</p><p>
God keep our young people away from the low, from those who seek to follow the scheming
plans of he who enthrones passion, who decries self-control, who renounces the sacredness of
the family, and who, in the words of Marx himself, would "dethrone God." God inspire our
young men and women to sustain and to fight for, and yes, if necessary, die for the light of
Christ, that they will come to realize the truth of Christ's saying that if they are willing to
lose their lives for his sake, they will find them.
</p><p>
God bless you all in your homes. Husbands, do not be cross when you enter your homes. Let
us be kind, courteous. Have the same courtesy in your homes that you have when you are out
in society. Thank your wives; thank your children; and say, "If you please," "Excuse me."
These little things mean so much and make life so much sweeter.
</p><p>
<b>Defense of the right</b>
</p><p>
Let us be courageous in defense of the right. Be not afraid to speak out for the right. Let us
be true. Let us defend the weak, be charitable to our brothers, render help to the sick and the
afflicted. The gospel is the spirit of kindness. Let us honor and sustain the priesthood in our
homes.
</p><p>
I pray God to sanctify to our good, and the good of all who have listened in this day, and to
the Church membership everywhere, the blessings and testimonies of this great conference. In
this parting, I leave with you, my dear fellow workers, my dear associates, and all members
and friends everywhere, my blessings to each one of you, as God has given me power and
authority to bless, and I do this in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
