<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Sermon on the Mount an Ordination Sermon</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 12-15</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This large group of people assembled to worship our Lord and to give thanks for our
blessings is a beautiful lesson of the meaning of life. You come up to this house of God
obedient to the call. It is obedience that leads us to the knowledge and love of God, and we
conceive God's decrees as eternal truths. It gives us renewed faith and, says Sholem Asch:
</p><p>
It is faith and not wisdom which carrieth the key to the kingdom of heaven.
</p><p>
CONTRIBUTIONS TO PEACE
</p><p>
Among the many questions that we have been asked to answer at the State Capitol through
the Utah State Historical Society is one that I know will impress you, and one, too, we have
tried to answer properly, though briefly. It is a question of great importance. It is:
</p><p>
What contribution has the Latter-day Saint Church made to this darkened world, with the
other Christian churches to bring peace to the world?
</p><p>
As we listen to the Singing Mothers of the Relief Society we recall something that has come
down to us from ancient days. In an old rabbinic code recently discovered is a description of
the duties of women as taught in the synagogue. They were to:
</p><p>
Feed the hungry and give the thirsty to drink.<br />
Clothe the naked, and shelter the homeless.<br />
Visit the sick, bury the dead and comfort the mourner.<br />
Support the widow and instruct the fatherless.<br />
Ransom the captive.<br />
Make garments for the orphan and provide for the betrothed maiden.
</p><p>
When we stop to think that this code is many hundreds of years old and was taught in the
ancient synagogues of Jerusalem, it indicates what a high calling the women of God have
always had.
</p><p>
UNCERTAINTY IN CHRISTIAN WORLD
</p><p>
The modern Christian world is confronted with two conditions which seem to be little
realized. The first is the inner uncertainty of Christianity itself which does not seem to know
its own basic beliefs. The Christian world is confused as to just what Jesus of Nazareth
taught.
</p><p>
Then there is the upsurge of communism, a power that has come into our own midst greater
than we realize.
</p><p>
No movement in history has achieved so sudden an actualization as a world movement.
Systems only grow as they appeal to people. Communism will continue to grow until the
people are confronted with and taught the fundamentals of Christianity which are creatively
worked out in human society.
</p><p>
We know that the gospel of Jesus Christ is comprehensive and all-embracing, including all the
values of religion as they reveal themselves in human experience. It is purifying and refining,
correcting the excesses and rejecting the abuses, which have corrupted the nature and
obstructed the pathway of religion throughout its history. The gospel of Jesus Christ is
distinctively and definitely revelatory, fulfilling the largest meaning and possibility of
revelation. It makes due place for all the human interests that constitute the spiritual life of
man. It is quite true that the Christian world has lost the path. And the reason for this is that
it has not the inner vigor to command a place of commanding power. The religion of Jesus
Christ requires revelation&mdash;revelation to chosen prophets, who teach the principles of the
redemption of mankind. Within the Christian doctrine is the principle and potency of
redemption.
</p><p>
HIGHEST CONCEPTS OF FREEDOM
</p><p>
The faith we have in our government of the United States is of the highest concept, for to us,
it is a sacred institution because of the directive power of God that brought it into existence.
The government of the United States is an outgrowth of the highest concepts of freedom for
mankind that the world has learned in history. Reverting to the simple beginnings of the
founders of America, we know them to have been of the finest blood of England, and other
countries of Europe. They brought hither in their little ships, not money, not merchandise, no
array of armed force, but they came freighted with religion, learning, and law. They stepped
forth upon these shores and a howling wilderness received them. Strong in their faith in God
and their own heroic patience, they began their combat with danger and hardship. Sickness at
times smote them, but they fainted not; famine overtook them, but they feasted on roots with
a patient spirit. They began to build a house for God, and then for themselves. They
established education and the observance of a stern and august morality, then legislated for the
smaller purposes of wealth and convenience. They gave their sons to God, and through virtue
to the state. So they laid their foundations. Villages grew, churches and colleges were built,
and farther into the depths of the wilderness industry multiplied her hands. Civic life and
order completed themselves and swelled into the majesty of states. Herein is a resume of our
own state's history. Utah was founded in sublime hopes and the ideals of a pure morality.
And the higher life was combined with agriculture and all industry&mdash;making the soil bring
forth food for man. Combined with all this was a taste for learning. This state was grounded
in religion, for religion was incorporate in the principles and feelings of the people. This is
what gave us our morals and true public enthusiasms, and our inspired ways of living.
</p><p>
OBEDIENCE TO LAW IS LIBERTY
</p><p>
There is a principle that is often misunderstood, and that is what we call
<i>obedience</i>. It is a principle that makes life happy and creates within us faith in truth and the
results of doing what is right. On the old library of Worcester, Massachusetts, are these
words: Obedience to Law is Liberty.
</p><p>
Obeying laws which we impose upon ourselves, that is, just and righteous laws, laws that are
the expressions of right principles, such as discipline of the intellect, the shame of committing
a wrong, respect for those in authority, consideration for the poor and needy; veneration for
the good; sympathy for the weak: this is true self-discipline. Then one knows what liberty
means. Obedience to the laws that express right principles is what makes it a religious duty. It
leads to faith in the commandments of God.
</p><p>
For forty years, Moses had not been alone. The care and burden of all the people, the weight
of their woe and guilt and death had been upon him continually. He felt at times that the Lord
had forsaken him and he had prayed that he might be slain, that God might not see his
wretchedness. And then when the march to the Promised Land was over, he heard the voice
of the Lord:
</p><p>
Get thee up into this mountain . . . (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/32/49#49">Deut. 32:49</a>)
</p><p>
In his old age the long journey was about to end, and he should see the land that had been his
dream. Moses died. But he had come to know the perfect law of liberty through obedience.
</p><p>
MISSIONARY CALLING OF SEVENTIES
</p><p>
Every generation writes its own history. It is not that the past alters, but that we change, and
our changed present opens new perspectives, and raises new questions. The gospel as revealed
to the servants of God will always remain the same and constant. You seventies who are the
missionaries of the Church, are called to go forth to teach the world as your forebears were
called years ago. The gospel has a worldwide mission. Like Paul, the Church cannot do other
than exclaim:
</p><p>
. . . woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel!
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/9/16#16">1 Cor. 9:16</a>).
</p><p>
I am debtor both to the Greeks, and to the Barbarians; both to the wise, and to the unwise
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/14#14">Rom. 1:14</a>).
</p><p>
You are to give freely that which you have freely received
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/8#8">Matt. 10:8</a>). You have fine ideals; you have
trained yourselves to think and act as your Redeemer would have you think and act.
Remember you are members of a quorum of the priesthood of God, and your organization is a
pure democracy. For this reason alone, you understand the meaning of good government. 
</p><p>
IDEALS OF SERMON ON THE MOUNT
</p><p>
When Jesus called the Twelve and the Seventy to go forth to preach the gospel, he had the
disciples assemble on the shores of the Lake of Galilee, and listen to his
"Sermon on the Mount," which was the Master's ordination sermon. Think of what was
expected of the disciples of Jesus, for the same ideals are expected of us. Standing as
missionaries today, can we not in our imagination hear the Master?
</p><p>
Missionaries go forth with the deep knowledge of the precepts of God, and it is by following
the precepts that belief in God is shown. If we believe in him, we shall keep his
commandments; and the great commandment is that we shall love one another. How simple
are all the doctrines, simple because all great truths are simple. It was the Prophet Isaiah who
wrote:
</p><p>
Wash you, make you clean; put away the evil of your doings from before mine
eyes; cease to do evil; Learn to do well; seek judgment, relieve the oppressed,
judge the fatherless, plead for the widow
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/1/16-17#16">Isa. 1:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
The precepts of the Sermon on the Mount with the words of Isaiah that we should cease to do
evil and learn to do well, not to our brethren and fellow-citizens only, but to all mankind will
ever be a guide to our lives.
</p>
</div>
</div>
