<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Word of God Must Go Forth</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 17-22</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The young men and women in our schools and colleges are confronted with many conflicting
ideas concerning religion and life. They become unsettled in their minds as they study our
present-day problems. Attacks are made on their religious beliefs which have been held sacred
by them ever since they were children in their homes. They often come to wonder about the
teachings of the Holy Bible, particularly the belief in God and the gospel of Jesus Christ.
They often become indifferent to what is right in their daily living. They have just cause to
wonder! The fires of revolution are burning everywhere&mdash;I fear even at our very doors. In
America, and of course in the whole world, we are in need of a spiritual awakening, an
awakening that makes men respect old truths, the finer lessons of history, <i>and the word of God;</i>
a realization that a man owes a lot more to his country, than his country owes him: a
return to the old standards of character that makes it easy for a man to become indignant over
corruption, and to hate sin and wrong. A study of the word of God, faith, and prayer will
bring about a better feeling in the minds of the youth, and it is up to the fathers and mothers
to be patient with their children, for they are living in a new age.
</p><p>
THE DISCOVERY OF AMERICA
</p><p>
Every household should keep in mind the two divinely appointed events in modern history
around which must be centered our future lives as a people. The discovery of America was
for a divine purpose, and the formation of this Republic was an event ordered of God for a
glorious new day. The Prophet Nephi some six centuries before the birth of the Savior wrote:
</p><p>
And I looked and beheld a man among the Gentiles, who was separated from the seed of my
brethren by the many waters; and I beheld the Spirit of God, that it came down and wrought
upon the man; and he went forth upon the many waters, even unto the seed of my brethren,
who were in the promised land.
</p><p>
And it came to pass that I beheld the Spirit of God, that it wrought upon other Gentiles; and
they went forth out of captivity, upon the many waters
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/12-13#12">1 Ne. 13:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
How deeply did Christopher Columbus feel that inspired directive purpose of God when he
wrote of his discovery of America:
</p><p>
But these great and marvelous results are not to be attributed to any merit of mine, but to the
holy Christian faith, for that which the unaided intellect of man could not compass, the Spirit
of God has granted to human exertions. For God is wont to hear the prayers of his servants
who live his precepts even to the performance of apparent impossibilities. . . . Let Christ
rejoice on earth, as he rejoices in heaven in the prospect of the salvation of the souls of so
many nations hitherto lost.
</p><p>
With what inspired knowledge did John Winthrop, one of the old Puritan fathers, write:
</p><p>
It will be a service to the Church of great consequence to carry the gospel into those parts of
the world to help on the coming of the fulness of the Gentiles.
</p><p>
WASHINGTON'S ACKNOWLEDGMENT
</p><p>
In his first inaugural address, Washington said:
</p><p>
Such being the impressions under which I have, in obedience to the public summons, repaired
to the present station, it would be peculiarly improper to omit, <i>in this first official act, my</i>
<i>fervent supplications to that Almighty Being who rules over the universe, who presides in the</i>
<i>councils of nations, and whose providential aids can supply every human defect,</i> that his
benediction may consecrate to the liberties and happiness of the people of the United States a
government instituted by themselves for these essential purposes, and may enable every
instrument employed in its administration to execute with success the functions allotted to his
charge. In tendering this <i>homage to the great Author of every public and private good,</i> I
assure myself that it expresses your sentiments not less than my own; nor those of my
fellow-citizens at large, less than either. No people can be bound to acknowledge and adore
the <i>invisible hand which conducts the affairs of men,</i> more than the people of the United
States.
</p><p>
The people whom Columbus found in America, and to whom Washington was the means of
bringing a knowledge of an Old World, were a deeply religious people. In a recent visit to the
Maricopa Stake, I was impressed with the group of Indians that was present. Noble-looking
people, they were. Some of them were Navajos, some Zunis, and a few Apaches. In speaking
to them, I recalled a visit, made to Boston many years ago, of some Zunis. We are told that
they were taken down the harbor, that they might worship. Landing on an island, the Indians
disappeared for a time, and on their return they walked into the sea, and, with deep solemnity,
sang their mystic chant. They then threw out upon the air from their uplifted hands the grain
they offered to the god of waters, and let it float away as a thanks offering. That was worship
of the Great Spirit.
</p><p>
AMBASSADORS OF TRUTH
</p><p>
When Jesus sent forth the Twelve and Seventy as his ambassadors of the divine truths which
he was teaching, he charged them to reproduce the miracles of his own personal ministry.
Such an extension of his work was a part of his original project of evangelizing the country
roundabout Palestine and eventually the world.
</p><p>
After these things, the Lord appointed other seventy also, and sent them two and two before
his face into every city and place, whither he himself would come.
</p><p>
Therefore said he unto them, the harvest truly is great, but the labourers are few: pray ye
therefore the Lord of the harvest, that he would send forth labourers into his harvest.
</p><p>
Go your ways: behold, I send you forth as lambs among wolves.
</p><p>
And into whatever house ye enter, first say, Peace be to this house
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/1-3,5#1">Luke 10:1-3,5</a>).
</p><p>
Some days afterward, we read in the gospel of St. Luke:
</p><p>
And the seventy returned again with joy, saying, Lord, even the devils are subject unto us
through thy name.
</p><p>
And he turned . . . unto his disciples, and said privately, Blessed are the eyes which see the
things that ye see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/17,23#17">Luke 10:17,23</a>).
</p><p>
To Jesus it was a provocation of purest happiness that God had chosen these men, unlearned
and simple men, in preference to intellectual and aristocratic leaders. Throughout his ministry,
peasants and fishermen, the unlearned and landless were called and he rejoiced that their
mission had been sealed by God: that through the faith of the Twelve and the Seventy they
had been invested with mysterious gifts of his Spirit. Jesus lifted up the ideal of life in the
kingdom of God to inspire his disciples to heightened aspirations and endeavor. He did not
lay down a rigid legalism, but as one English writer, Dr. Church, in his Essays and Reviews
has written:
</p><p>
He wooed his pupils by persuasive ideals. He transferred the source of happiness and the
understanding of the gospel from external circumstances to the inward life of man. Goodness,
morals, ideals depend upon one's attitude toward God. It was fundamental to the ethic of
Jesus. For this reason the Beatitudes are conjoined with purity of heart. It denotes simplicity,
a singleness of aim in allegiance to the divine teachings of the Master. The ethical and
religious teachings pervading Christ's instructions to these first Christian missionaries has
become the foundation of the inner light of the Seventies of today. Their lives exhale the
aroma of complete consecration. They are the salt of the earth, the Light of the world.
</p><p>
GOD'S SERVANTS
</p><p>
God's first demands of his servants are pure hearts, upright lives, truthfulness, mercy, and
honesty. Good manners were regarded as matters of religion and morality. Boasting,
ostentation, conceit, were of old considered the patent evidence of vulgarity. These are
condemned by the scriptures. The Seventies must always keep in mind the grandeur of the
First Article of Faith (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>),
which is the greatest statement of Truth since the days of Christ our
Redeemer. They must keep in mind the supreme test of religion, which is <i>revelation</i>. No
religion can be persuasive unless it relies on the principle of revelation. All true men reveal
God, but the completest carrier of revelation can be no other, or less than a chosen
personality. This is the Christian conception. The nobler the person, the truer the revelation.
</p><p>
It will be a noble resolution for every Seventy to say to himself: "I shall read more diligently
and more deeply the Holy Scriptures than ever before." The Holy Bible, Book of Mormon,
D&amp;C, and Pearl of Great Price are not intended for the few. Their subject-matter constitutes
truth, necessary for us all. Every quorum of seventy will from now on become a study group,
where vital truths are discussed. It is within such a group that men are stimulated to think and
to converse in preparation for the teaching of the gospel. At a time when so much of our
world literature is strangely blind to the glory and excellence of human nature at best, we
should dedicate ourselves again to the study of the truths and the beauties and holiness of the
sacred word of God.
</p><p>
MISSION OF SEVENTIES
</p><p>
The Seventies, because of their calling, have a high mission set before them. They should
resolve that they will develop their mental and spiritual powers toward maturity and learn to
have communion with great souls through the reading of their messages of truth. The habit of
reading must be formed as early in life as possible. A few minutes every day will soon be a
great many hours. Do not miss the thoughts of men who have lived in former times. Broaden
your understanding, enliven your sympathy for other peoples and their ways of living. Make
your own lives richer and deeper by learning other ideas and visions of people. Read good
books. Read them again and again until you have drawn the essence of thought and feeling
from them. These are some of the reasons why the Prophet Joseph Smith wrote:
</p><p>
. . . seek ye diligently and teach one another words of wisdom; yea, seek ye out of the best
books words of wisdom; seek learning, even by study and also by faith
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>).
</p><p>
Joy will be the characteristic of the quorums of Seventy so long as they are growing,
expanding, and creating healthfully. When they cease to grow, they cease to live. God sent us
into the world to create and to enrich our own personality in the process Yet we have to rely
on God's help to make anything worth making. If we devote ourselves to God, we must see
to it that we have <i>ourselves</i> to devote. "Self consecration is not a negative thing: it is a very
positive thing," says a noted evangelist. This leads us to the knowledge that what we are is
more important than what we do or say. If we are really wise in our concepts of God, then
our thoughts lie deeply, though often misunderstood. It takes deep thoughts to understand the
depths of the message of divine truth. For this reason the brethren can hear God speak, and
those whose hearts God has touched can find their way easily to the hearts of others.
</p><p>
TRUE TO REVEALED WORD
</p><p>
In the difficult times that surround us today, the brethren holding the priesthood of God must,
above all things, be true to the word of God as revealed by the Master <i>and as revealed today.</i>
The words of truth are ever the same. Love, joy, peace, faith, humility: these are the
characteristic Christian ideas. How beautiful are the words of the Prophet Joseph Smith when
he said:
</p><p>
. . . O ye that embark in the service of God, see that ye serve him with all your heart, might,
mind, and strength, that ye may stand blameless before God at the last day.
</p><p>
And faith, hope, charity and love, with an eye single to the glory of God, qualify him for the
work.
</p><p>
Remember faith, virtue, knowledge, temperance, patience, brotherly kindness, godliness,
charity, humility, diligence (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/2,5-6#2">D&amp;C 4:2,5-6</a>).
</p><p>
Herein is the Prophet conveying the charm of his teachings and an heroic conception of the
good in life. His concept of the Christian virtues and graces is noble and comprehensive. He
exalted and glorified the principles of morals as given by the Savior of the world, and aroused
the adoration of men for the gospel which is the only road to peace. It is the mission of the
Seventies and all who hold the priesthood to stimulate healthy and majestic ideals through
self-discipline and the knowledge that in "pure religion and undefiled"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>), is life eternal.
</p><p>
A testimony, my brethren, of the truthfulness of the gospel of Jesus Christ is a sacred trust. It
can come only to one who has opened his heart and mind to hallowed living with earnest
prayer and deep faith in the Living God. It is the most divine gift of all. "For it is faith and
not wisdom which carrieth the key to the kingdom of heaven," says Sholem Asch.
</p><p>
Sir Francis Drake in admonishing his men, said:
</p><p>
Men pass away, but people abide. See that ye hold fast the heritage we leave you, yea, and
teach your children its value, that never in the coming centuries their hearts may fail them, or
their hands grow weak. Hitherto we have been too much afraid. Henceforth, we will fear only
God.
</p>
</div>
</div>
