<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1946, pp. 108-111</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, no one can rise on an occasion like this without feeling a thrill of emotion. I
was impressed yesterday when President Clark read the financial and statistical report of the
Church. It was a calm recital of figures, but those figures told a story of growth and progress.
I was deeply stirred a few minutes later when Elder Widtsoe reminded us that just one
hundred years ago the Latter-day Saints were leaving the beautiful city of Nauvoo. They were
then scattered along the fringe of the great desert that extended westward to the slopes of
California. By what combination of circumstances could these men and women hope to
survive? It required a great faith and certainly a great courage to undertake the great task that
lay ahead.
</p><p>
<i>Accomplishments of Church During Last Century</i>
</p><p>
During that century of time, the Church has asserted itself and carried forward the truth
brought to earth by Joseph Smith the Prophet. Since that day the foundation of a great
intermountain empire has been laid. Cities, towns, churches, temples, public buildings have
been built. Deserts have been subdued; schools colleges, seminaries have been established.
Missions have been opened in foreign lands and on the islands of the sea. Branches, wards,
stakes have been organized, and missionary work at home and abroad has gone forward. The
gospel has been explained, and the name of Joseph Smith the Prophet as a restorer of divine
truth has been heralded to all the world. Surely a good beginning has been made in the
"marvelous work and wonder" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/14#14">Isa. 29:14</a>)
spoken of by ancient prophets, and surely the leaders of the
past have made their names secure on the pages of history. These leaders, all of them,
referred to by President S. Dilworth Young, were great in character and in good works. They
were great in their foresight and in their achievement. They were great in their perseverance
and mighty in their faith. "Mormonism," so-called, was not the outgrowth of fraud and
deception. The Latter-day Saints have not been led astray by a wicked pretender or an
unscrupulous imposter. We think of these things whenever the name and character of Joseph
Smith are being assailed. It was Charles Francis Potter who said:
</p><p>
If we are to accept the dictum of Jesus, "By their fruits ye shall know them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16#16">Matt. 7:16</a>), we must rate
Mormonism high.
</p><p>
<i>Faith in God Sustained Pioneers</i>
</p><p>
Reference has been made to the pioneers. How can we account for the constructive faith of
the sturdy, dauntless, courageous pioneers of Utah and neighboring states and for the
unconquerable spirit which possessed them? What motives, what urges actuated them as they
left their homes in the East and moved westward over the trackless waste? These men and
women in the solitudes of the desert had time to think and pray and to ponder and weigh
carefully their responsibilities. What power sustained them in their hardships and in their
difficulties? What prompted each one of them to cast his lot with a persecuted and driven
people? Was it not his faith in God and his conviction that a new dispensation of the gospel
had been committed to man through the divine calling of Joseph Smith? History will one day
deal fairly and intelligently with these questions. The unprejudiced student, the searcher after
truth will see in Mormonism the counterpart of primitive Christianity. His investigations will
discover in it the same spirit, the same energies and fortitudes, the same type of leadership
and the same far-reaching objectives. He will see in Joseph Smith the characteristics of a true
prophet of God like the prophets whose names and deeds glorify the pages of Biblical history.
He will find that Joseph Smith is not easily dislodged from his position as a
prophet of God. The Prophet's claims will never be nullified by the declarations of traitors
and blasphemers.
</p><p>
I read from the Doctrine and Covenants:
</p><p>
The ends of the earth shall inquire after thy name, and fools shall have thee in derision, and
hell shall rage against thee;
</p><p>
While the pure in heart, and the wise, and the noble, and the virtuous, shall seek counsel, and
authority, and blessings constantly from under thy hand.
</p><p>
And thy people shall never be turned against thee by the testimony of traitors
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/122/1-3#1">D&amp;C 122:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
<i>A Good Tree Bears Good Fruit</i>
</p><p>
Those words were reassuring to the Prophet when they were given. They are reassuring to us
today. There is no way to account for Joseph Smith outside of his own explanation. Someone
has said: "Truth is harmonious." It is consistent with itself today and always. Jesus said:
</p><p>
. . . Do men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles? Even so every good tree bringeth
forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit. A good tree cannot bring forth
evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. Every tree that bringeth not forth
good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16-19#16">Matt. 7:16-19</a>).
</p><p>
Wicked and degraded men do not bring light and hope and joy to their fellow men. A mind
darkened by evil could not attract God-fearing men and women of faith, integrity, and
intelligence whose lives have reflected good work and worthy achievements. Would a church
founded on fraud and falsehood go forth with eagerness and determination to uplift humanity?
Would such a church array itself against evil in all of its manifestations? Would it teach faith
in God and repentance of sin as preliminaries to church membership? Would it adopt
doctrines and ordinances and standards established by Jesus Christ and his apostles If so, for
what purpose? We are told that evil begets evil, and good begets good.
</p><p>
<i>Joseph Smith's Work to Stand Forever</i>
</p><p>
Finally, let it be remembered that Joseph Smith and Hyrum Smith, brothers and companions
in the cause of truth, gave their lives as a testimony of their sincerity. Not only they, but
others left a similar testimony, sealed and certified, and therefore binding upon the world.
While he lived, Joseph Smith baffled his fellow men by his teachings, which were so
profoundly creative. The keenest minds were perplexed and puzzled before his demonstration
of power and leadership. But the fury of so many against him is proof even today that he is
not dead in the hearts of men; that he is well-fortified and will continue to stand out boldly
and clearly in the religious world. He will loom bigger and bigger on the human horizon as
the years come and go. The correctness of his views and the soundness of
his principles and doctrines will be vindicated fully and completely. He cannot be removed or
explained away by slander or vilification. He presented a plan which provides for the
exaltation of the individual, the perpetuity and the coherence of the family, and the safety and
security of the nation. He put divine approval upon the establishment of our republic and
proclaimed freedom and equal rights as essential factors in man's progress and advancement.
He declared that America was a land of promise, held in reserve by the Almighty for the
fulfilment and the accomplishments of God's purposes. No one has sounded a higher note of
patriotism than did Joseph Smith. In his veins flowed the blood of the Revolutionary Fathers,
and to him the Constitution was an inspired instrument of government.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith gave to the world a foundation for intelligent faith, and he has also given to
honest, sincere doubters a kindly light to lead them forward and upward to a higher goal and
a more satisfying life. His testimony to the world still stands. God bless his memory. May his
words and teachings be preserved to bless the human family forever, I pray in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
