<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">How Many Apples in a Seed?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 148-153</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It has been a great blessing through this conference to have with us Brother Ivins, our dearly
loved and respected associate. He isn't here at this meeting, but I think it not inappropriate to
tell you that he has been very ill and through the graciousness of the Lord has been restored
marvelously and is able to be with us occasionally. He has been in meetings of this
conference.
</p><p>
I would like to commend also the appointment of President Cullimore, a strong and choice
associate in the missionary course in England&mdash;a man of great substance and faith and
strength.
</p><p>
I was thinking a few moments ago about a meeting in Idaho at which I listened to a speaker
who had waited for a long time to be called on. He commended the people at the meeting for
their graciousness to him, expressed appreciation for their kindness, thanked them for making
him feel at home, and said, "You have really made me feel like one of you. I don't know
which one, but he ought to be about ready to go home&mdash;he's tired!"
</p><p>
As I have listened with you to the great sermons of this conference and to the marvelous
music and have felt the spirit and enjoyed the instructions, like you I have paid many of the
speakers the tribute of divided attention. Their sermons have started me thinking. Two
thoughts in particular have recurred. The repeated references to the modern movement
celebrating the demise of God have recalled a reported exchange between Nietzsche and
another. Nietzsche's message read, "God is dead." Signed "Nietzsche." The answer came back,
"Nietzsche is dead." Signed "God."
</p><p>
The other thought: Someone said that atheists do not find God for the same reason that
thieves do not find policemen.
</p><p>
During these conference sessions I have been thinking of you&mdash;you and your counterparts all
over the Church, all over the world&mdash;you who do so much of the meaningful work of the
Church in your own area and sector. I am sure that you, like I, will go home with the desire
and determination, born of appreciation, to apply and make use of what has been said here.
</p><p>
Perhaps you will go home strengthened in two pivotal principles around which our efforts
revolve.
</p><p>
<b>Great worth of souls</b>
</p><p>
The <i>first</i> is provocatively expressed in a few words shared with me by a choice friend
sometime ago. I suspect you will remember them as I have He said: "You can count the seeds
in an apple, but can you count the apples in a seed?"
</p><p>
". . . the worth of souls is great in the sight of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/10#10">D&amp;C 18:10</a>). The worth of the
<i>individual</i> soul is great in the sight of God and in the lives of those who love God and seek to
express this love through affectionate service to his children.
</p><p>
In order that we might cooperate with our Heavenly Father in his stated purpose to "bring to
pass the immortality and eternal life of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>), we have been blessed with the gospel, the
Church, and the priesthood.
</p><p>
<b>Plan for exalting man</b>
</p><p>
The <i>gospel</i> is God's plan for the exalting of man to an eternal creative opportunity with his
Father through giving him a vision of his great origins and heritage, his purposes and
responsibilities, and his inspiring potential.
</p><p>
The <i>Church</i> is the institutional embodiment of the gospel, the organization through which one
may experience and express the great principles of God's plan.
</p><p>
The <i>priesthood</i> is the power by which God and his sons move in spiritual leadership. And all
of these&mdash;gospel, Church, priesthood&mdash;are designed to bless man and bring about God's
purposes for him.
</p><p>
The earth itself was prepared for man. "Behold, the Lord hath created the earth that it should
be inhabited; and he hath created his children that they should possess it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/36#36">1 Ne. 17:36</a>).
</p><p>
The individual, then, is the focal point of all the programs and performance of the
Church&mdash;not the program itself, not the statistics.
<i>Not institutional expansion but individual exaltation is the purpose of it all.</i>
</p><p>
The implications of the thought are clear: "You can count the seeds in an apple, but can you
count the apples in a seed?"
</p><p>
Every choice child of God is a link in a chain stretching from the past to the future. In the
choice young people of the Church are the seeds of the future.
</p><p>
Do you know four lines that mean much to me?
</p><p>
     "Nobody knows what a boy is worth;<br />
        We'll have to wait and see,<br />
     But every man in a noble place<br />
        A boy once used to be."
</p><p>
Each boy and girl, and every adult also, is infinitely valuable. None is to be rejected, none
written off, none neglected or left without the conscious concern of devoted brothers and
sisters in the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
<b>Responsible for influence</b>
</p><p>
This leads, then, to the <i>second</i> basic conviction of which I have been thinking: Each of us has
a solemn and significant responsibility to others of God's children and the capacity to
wholesomely and favorably influence them for good if we will. We are brothers to all men,
and we have a special responsibility to those of our own household and to those in whose
lives we may, by reason of our church membership and by reason of responsibilities assigned
us in the various organizations and programs of the Church, exert some important influence
through love.
</p><p>
The organization of the Church makes available to every individual, old and young, at every
stage in his life, strong supportive friendships and leadership. From babyhood through the
whole of life every individual should have available always the friendship and sincere concern
of a bishop and his counselors, of priesthood and auxiliary organization leaders and workers,
of interested and loving family and friends and neighbors relating under the special motivation
and inspiration of the Lord through his Church. Every individual all of his life should be
blessed in the Church by a program that involves the consistent concern of teachers&mdash;home
teachers they are now called&mdash;who are assigned to a special relationship of interest and
helpfulness.
</p><p>
<b>Influence of teachers</b>
</p><p>
In preparation for the imminent organization of the Church in 1830, the Lord revealed through
the Prophet Joseph Smith that His representatives holding the priesthood were to visit the
homes of the members of the Church, "exhorting them to pray vocally and in secret and
attend to all family duties.
</p><p>
". . . to watch over the church always, and be with and strengthen them; 
</p><p>
". . . And see that there is no iniquity in the church, neither hardness with each other, neither
lying, backbiting, nor evil speaking; 
</p><p>
"And see that the church meet together often, and also see that all the members do their
duty."
</p><p>
"They are . . . to warn, expound, exhort, and teach, and invite all to come unto Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/51,53-55,59#51">D&amp;C 20:51,53-55,59</a>).
As in the ancient Church, the members of the Church are to be
"remembered and nourished by the good word of God, to keep them in the right way, to keep
them continually watchful unto prayer, relying alone upon the merits of Christ, who was the
author and the finisher of their faith."
</p><p>
And to "meet together oft, to fast and to pray, and to speak one with another concerning the
welfare of their souls" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/6/4-5#4">Moro. 6:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Influence on lives of others</b>
</p><p>
To every person thus blessed by office or assignment or membership in the Church with the
special responsibility of stewardship and concern in the lives of others, the Lord said: 
</p><p>
"Therefore, let every man stand in his own office, and labor in his own calling, and let not
the head say unto the feet it hath no need of the feet; for without the feet how shall the body
be able to stand?
</p><p>
"Also the body hath need of every member, that all may be edified together, that the system
may be kept perfect" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/109-110#109">D&amp;C 84:109-110</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Illustrations:</b>
</p><p>
Let me spend a few minutes illustrating the great importance of our responsibilities to each
other under these sacred assignments from the Lord to be stewards in his kingdom.
</p><p>
In one of the stakes of the Church in another land, a lovely young lady left her home to live
in another city where she had found employment. She was away from family and established
friends and from the Church and its warm involvements. She didn't take occasion to look up
the church organization in the city to which she went, finding it easy for a time to avoid the
customary associations of her church membership. She formed other associations in the new
city, and they were not the kind she had had at home. Gradually she began to become
involved in another kind of attitude and another kind of behavior. She had not made serious
mistakes but had begun a way of living that would not have pleased her parents and that was
not the manner of her former life.
</p><p>
There came a night when, dressed in clothing that she might previously have been
embarrassed to wear in public, perhaps harboring in her mind anticipations of conduct that she
would not ever have considered before, she waited for the arrival of some of her new friends.
It was a critical hour in her life and a critical night in her life, and she knew it. When she
answered the knock at the door, she was surprised to find not those whom she was
anticipating but rather three adults whom she did not know. They identified themselves as the
bishop and his counselor and the president of the Young Women's Mutual Improvement
Association. The bishop had received a letter from the bishop of the girl's home ward
notifying him of the address and circumstance of his ward member in the new city. The
bishop and his associates were calling to express their friendship and concern and to invite the
young lady to the activities and associations of the Church in this town. As she talked with
them she became embarrassed at her clothing, chagrined at the activities of the recent past and
the anticipations of the evening. She wept and rejoiced and responded gratefully to the
friendship of this bishop and his fellow workers. The anticipated events of the evening never
transpired. She formed the warm and wonderful friendships she needed with people of quality
and devotion. She became active in the Church and went on to her happy and wholesome
opportunities.
</p><p>
In another city, long enough ago that the story can now be told without likelihood of the
recognition of the individuals involved, I heard another and different story.
</p><p>
Let's use the name Donna to designate another sweet young lady who left her home for a
nearby bigger city for employment. She had a great desire to attend a church university and
needed funds to help her achieve her ambition. She failed to find work in the big city, and as
time went by she became more and more discouraged. Then, through a series of incidents, she
came into the influence of an unscrupulous and designing person who took advantage of
Donna's loneliness and youthfulness and the discouragement of her inability to find work and
led her into an immoral experience.
</p><p>
The experience was horrifying to Donna, and she returned home with a broken heart to tell
her mother and, after a time, her bishop of the tragedy.
</p><p>
There was counsel and compassion, admonition and direction, prayer and blessing. Donna
went back home to make her adjustments and to begin to learn the sorrow of remorse of
conscience and the blessing of gratitude for the graciousness and goodness and mercy of God.
Then one day she had to counsel again with the bishop, to report to him that through this one
fragmentary, tragic experience it was now apparent that she was with child. Now a different
situation existed, and there was additional counsel and an effort to meet this new situation.
There was consideration of the Relief Society Social Service program, which provides for
such situations, and other possibilities were considered; but the decision was finally made by
Donna that she would remain at home in her small town to wait her time. Some efforts were
made at dissuasion in view of the problems this course involved, but Donna decided that,
under the special circumstances of her widowed mother's illness and otherwise, she would
remain there.
</p><p>
Donna stood up in the next fast and testimony meeting and explained her condition. She
acknowledged her fault and asked the forgiveness of her people. She said to them, "I would
like to walk the streets of this town knowing that you know and that you have compassion on
me and forgive me. But if you cannot forgive me," she said, "please don't blame my
mother&mdash;the Lord knows she taught me anything but this&mdash;and please don't hold it against the baby. It
isn't the baby's fault." She bore testimony of appreciation for her bitterly won but dearly
treasured personal knowledge of the importance of the saving mission of Jesus Christ. Then
she sat down.
</p><p>
The man who told me the story reported the reaction of the congregation to this experience.
There were many tearful eyes and many humble hearts. "There were no stone throwers there"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/7#7">John 8:7</a>),
he said. "We were full of compassion and love, and I found myself wishing that the bishop
would close the meeting and let us leave with this sense of appreciation and concern and
gratitude to God."
</p><p>
The bishop did rise, but he didn't close the meeting. Instead he said, "Brothers and sisters,
Donna's story has saddened and touched us all. She has courageously and humbly accepted
full responsibility for her sorrowful situation. She has, in effect, put a list of sinners on the
wall of the chapel with only her name on the list. I cannot in honesty leave it there alone. At
least one other name must be written&mdash;the name of one who is in part responsible for this
misfortune, though he was far away when the incident occurred. The name is a familiar one
to you. It is the name of your bishop. You see," he said, "had I fully performed the duties of
my calling and accepted the opportunities of my leadership, perhaps I could have prevented
this tragedy."
</p><p>
The bishop then told of his conversation with Donna and her mother before her departure for
the big city. He said that he had talked with some of his associates. He had talked with his
wife, expressing concern for Donna's well-being. He worried about her lack of experience and
her loneliness. He had talked, he said, with the Lord about these things also.
</p><p>
"But then," he said, "I did nothing. I didn't write a note to the bishop or to the brethren in
Salt Lake City. I didn't pick up the telephone. I didn't drive a few miles to the big city. I just
hoped and prayed that Donna would be all right down there all alone. I don't know what I
might have done, but I have the feeling that had I been the kind of bishop I might have been,
this might have been prevented.
</p><p>
"My brothers and sisters," he said, "I don't know how long I am going to be bishop of this
ward. But as long as I am, if there is anything I can do about it, this won't happen again to
one of mine."
</p><p>
The bishop sat down in tears. His counselor stood up and said, "I love the bishop. He is one
of the best and most conscientious human beings I have ever known. I cannot leave his name
there on the list without adding my own. You see, the bishop did talk with his associates. He
talked with me about this matter. I think that he thought that because I travel occasionally in
my business through the big city, I might find a way to check on Donna. I might have done,
but I was hurrying to this meeting or that assignment and I didn't take the time. I too talked
with others. I mentioned my concern to my wife. I am almost ashamed to tell you I talked to
the Lord and asked him to help Donna. And then I did nothing. I don't know what might
have happened had I done what I thought to do, but I have the feeling that I might have
prevented this misfortune.
</p><p>
"Brothers and sisters," he said, "I don't know how long I will be serving in this bishopric, but
I want to tell you that as long as I am, if there is anything I can do about it, this will not
happen again to one of mine."
</p><p>
The president of the YWMIA stood up and told a similar story. The bishop's counselor in
charge of this auxiliary organization had talked with her. She had had some moments of
thought and concern but had done nothing. She added her name to the list.
</p><p>
The last witness was an older man who stood and added two names to the list&mdash;his own and
that of his companion ward teacher. He noted that they were assigned to the home in which
Donna and her mother lived and that they had failed in some visits and made no effective
effort to be the kind of teachers that the revelations of God had contemplated.
</p><p>
"I don't know how longer I will be a ward teacher," he said, "but as long as I am, I will not
miss another home another month, and I will try to be the kind of teacher that the Lord
seemed to have in mind."
</p><p>
The meeting ended, and the wonderful man who shared this great experience with me said,
"Brother Hanks, I think we could not have more clearly understood the importance of the
offices and officers and organizations in the Church if the Lord himself had come down to
teach us. I think that if Paul had come to repeat his instructions to the Corinthians that 'the
eye cannot say unto the hand, I have no need of thee: nor again the head to the feet, I have
no need of you. Nay . . . the members should have the same care one for another. And
whether one member suffer, all the members suffer with it; or one member be honoured, all
the members rejoice with it'
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/21-22,25-26#21">1 Cor. 12:21-22,25-26</a>)&mdash;I think
we could not have understood the point more clearly."
</p><p>
A number of years ago Brother Joseph Anderson and I had the privilege of driving with
President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., to a solemn assembly in St. George. On the way I related to
him this story, it having recently happened then. He thought a long time and had a tear in his
eye as he said "Brother Hanks, that is the most significant story I ever heard to illustrate the
great importance of our filling our individual obligations in the Church. When you have
thought about it long enough, pass it on to others."
</p><p>
I have thought about it long and often. I believe it illustrates powerfully and humblingly the
purposes of the Lord in establishing his kingdom and permitting us the blessing of individual
service therein. I now share it with you and pray God to bless us all to understand its
implications and to act on them, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
