<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1948, pp. 173-177</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
While listening to Bishop Richards I was reminded of an incident in the life of Superintendent
Nelson, formerly Utah State Superintendent of Public Instruction. During the latter part of his
life he was sorely afflicted, and went back East to have performed a very difficult, indeed
dangerous, operation. His affliction was so serious that doctors hesitated about operating on
him. While considering the matter they asked him several questions relating to his private life.
They inquired whether he was addicted to the use of tobacco. He answered: "No." Whether he
indulged in intoxicants. He said: "No." Then they touched more vitally upon his life and
asked him whether he had had any venereal disease. Superintendent Nelson said, "Why no,
doctor, I am a Mormon."
</p><p>
"Well," said the doctor, "what the hell does that matter?"
</p><p>
"Well, that means that we do not indulge in these things. It means that I never have used 
tobacco, that I never have indulged in whiskey, and that I have lived a virtuous life and have
known only one woman and she is my wife."The doctor was surprised. He used the word
astonished and said: "If you have lived that kind of life we are going to operate on you.
</p><p>
They did so, and Superintendent Nelson returned home and continued his service here as
State Superintendent of Public Instruction.
</p><p>
Tonight President Raymond, in his opening prayer, expressed two very important thoughts.
One was an invocation that God would enable us to appreciate our responsibilities; and the
other, an appeal that we may set proper examples, "that we might be a light to others." I
hope the Lord will answer that invocation, and that we as men who hold the priesthood may
realize its value.
</p><p>
THE VALUE OF THE PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
I have told you before of a little incident that happened in front of the Japanese Emperor's
palace in Tokyo. Three or four of us, Mormon missionaries, were there, and with us a
Japanese convert, a carver of ivory, wearing the cloak of the ordinary working man. As we
stood there, I noticed the obeisance this Japanese, though a member of the Church, paid the
grounds and particularly the palace. I turned to him and said: "Do you know, Brother
Watanabe, that you have something which is of more value than all the wealth you are
looking at, and something which the Emperor cannot have unless he follows the same road
that you have followed?"
</p><p>
The man looked up in surprise to think that he, a humble carver, would have something
which was of more value than the Emperor's palace or all his possessions. And through the
interpreter, Brother Stimpson, he said: "What is it?"
</p><p>
"Why," I said, "it is the priesthood of Almighty. You are an Elder in the Church of Christ and
that is of more worth to you than all the wealth you are now looking at."
</p><p>
I pray that we may so sense the value of the priesthood, and that every deacon in this Church
will realize that when he is given the Aaronic Priesthood he is set apart among his fellows,
that he is different from others. He cannot with impunity swear as other boys may swear, he
cannot participate in pranks in the neighborhood as other boys may participate, he stands
apart. That is what it means to a twelve year old boy, and, bishops, that is just what you
should explain to them when you choose them to be deacons. Do not just call them up and
ordain them, but have a talk with them and let them realize what it means to be given the
Aaronic Priesthood. In the boyhood area these boys so chosen and instructed should exert an
influence for good.
</p><p>
OBLIGATION TO SET WORTHY EXAMPLES
</p><p>
The second part was example. It is our obligation when we accept the priesthood to set an
example worthy of imitation by our fellows. It is not what we say that will influence them. It
is what we do. It is what we are. One reputed to be the wisest American said: "What you are
thunders so loud in my ears I cannot hear what you say," referring to the radiation of
character from each of us.
</p><p>
As I have sat here, thrilled with this inspiring audience, and "thrilled" is the word, my mind
wandered out to as many more in our wards, stakes, who never come here, and many who do
not care to come. It is our duty to reach them, kindly, as neighbors, officially, as ward
teachers, officially, as members of quorums and officers in quorums. That is our obligation.
</p><p>
REOPENING OF JAPANESE MISSION
</p><p>
But that is not the message which I have for you tonight. In giving it I am not going to
occupy much time. I have just a few words to say regarding our missionary work. And may I
report for your information and satisfaction, I am sure, that recently five native Japanese
missionaries left Honolulu, properly set apart to go back to Japan and preach the gospel in
their native tongue. We have come some distance, have we not, since that Japanese mission
was opened? And in addition to the elders, two Japanese sisters have accepted their calls and
are going over there to help President Clissold in that great work.
</p><p>
Let me say in passing that Brother Watanabe remained true all through the time that the
Church was absent from there and he died holding his priesthood; and his daughter, I believe
is over there now, active in the Church.
</p><p>
"GO YE THEREFORE AND TEACH ALL NATIONS"
</p><p>
You will be pleased to hear also that we recently received a cable from President Stover in
Germany that we may have a few missionaries now in East Germany. The way is opening up
in all the world and now, as perhaps never before, those who hold the priesthood may fulfill
the injunction given by the Savior to his Twelve when he said: "Go ye therefore and teach all
nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Ghost,
teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you and lo, I am with you
alway, even unto the end of the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
It is most inspiring to see how eagerly our young men and young women are seeking the
opportunity to fulfill that injunction, but brethren, in missionary work the power of example is
most important. It is a glorious thing for a young man to be sent into the mission field. It is a
great opportunity for him. At the dinner table today friends commented upon the number of
our missionaries in different parts of the world. What a culture they bring into our
community! One guest had two sons in Germany. He mentioned another in France, and
another in one of the missions in the United States. Another guest mentioned two in Norway,
one in France, one in Argentine, and so they are in different parts of the world.
</p><p>
WORTHINESS OF MISSIONARIES
</p><p>
What a wonderful thing it is; but, brethren, missionaries are called not for individual
blessings. They are called to preach the gospel, to represent the Church. The blessings come
inevitably as they do their duty, and it is most unfortunate if a young man leaves your ward
to represent the Church who does so unworthily. It injures him, breaks his parents' hearts,
reflects upon the ward, and it might blight some souls who otherwise would come into the
Church.
</p><p>
And so, I am asked tonight to plead with you bishops and presidents of the stakes to be more
careful in your inquiries into the worthiness of the missionaries whom you recommend. Will
you, before calling them or interviewing them, just look over the missionary recommendation
which you are going to sign? Do not just put it in the hand of the missionary and let him fill
the blanks, but you note the significance of these questions. If he is married, please inquire
into the condition of his family. Is he divorced or is she divorced? Please state why and see
whether or not he or she is worthy to go out and preach the sacredness of the marriage
covenant and the ideals of the Church in regard to homebuilding.
</p><p>
STANDARDS OF MORALITY
</p><p>
Under morality, answer sincerely before you put this in the hands of the member of the
Council of the Twelve. Are you satisfied, after thorough investigation, that he or she
conforms to Church standards, aye, in chastity. The world has difficulty in believing that
young men in our Church grow to manhood as chaste and pure as virgins. I have had them
say they did not believe it; they did not believe that any young men could do that. But I tell
them such is the fact, and that it is the standard of the Church for young men as well as for
young women to keep themselves unspotted from the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>). In the Church there is but the
single standard of morality and that applies to young men as well as to young women. See to
it that prospective missionaries realize what this means, no matter what false teaching they
have had in psychology or in other classes about "inhibitions" and so on. The standard of the
Church is right; it is divine; it contributes to manhood and virtuous womanhood, happy
homes, perpetuity of the nation.
</p><p>
Are you satisfied through investigation that he or she conforms to the Church in the
observance of the Word of Wisdom? And note this, in integrity. Is there anybody in the ward
who will say: "Well, he has cheated me. He is not worthy. If that is the kind of men they
have to send out, well then, I am done with the Church."
</p><p>
These pointed questions are put in the recommend purposely, and they mean something,
because those who go out to represent the Church are chosen. They are set apart. They are
leaders. They are teachers. They are ambassadors of truth. Please, when you bring these
young men and young women to the members of the Council of the Twelve and place in the
hands of the Council of the Twelve this written recommendation with your signature, be sure
that you have made a thorough investigation, because it is embarrassing, very embarrassing, to
the young man to be rejected as a representative.
</p><p>
SELECTIVE SERVICE REQUIREMENTS
</p><p>
Another point. From questions received in person and in writing it is evident that there are
some problems in the minds of bishops and the stake presidents as to whom they should
recommend for missionary service in the light of the recent selective service. In answer to
these inquiries we offer the following suggestions, without going into many details. Young
men may continue to be recommended for missionary service as follows:
</p><p>
Those who have reached the age of twenty years, or approximately that age, or, young men
under twenty years of age who have had either previous military service or two years of
college.
</p><p>
If a young man receives his notice of induction from the selective service before he enters the
missionary home, the Church will excuse him from missionary service. In other words, if the
young man receives his call in November to enter the missionary home, let us say, in the
following May, if he will register in his regular vocation as a mechanic, a student, a farmer,
or whatever it may be, and if, during that interim, between the time of his call and his
entrance into the home, he is selected in the draft, he is to respond. If, however, he enters the
missionary home before he is drafted his status changes. He is then recognized as being an
ordained minister and the government will excuse him. He will be deferred by the Selective
board for military service for the duration of the term he is to serve as an ordained minister.
Following his release, I believe it is within five days after he is home, he is to report to his
local draft board.
</p><p>
For the present bishops and presidents of stakes will govern themselves accordingly.
</p><p>
REQUIREMENTS FOR YOUNG WOMEN MISSIONARIES
</p><p>
The age of young women is set at twenty-three. Young women under twenty-three years of
age, preferably twenty-one, who are engaged to young men who are in the field, may be
considered as prospective missionaries, provided they can go and serve a regular term mission
and be home in time to meet their sweethearts. Some requests are made that they may go out
and spend a few months, some a year. Now, it is evident, if you give that a thought, this
cannot be done for the good of the service. Presidents of missions will make certain
appointments, assignments. Those assignments will be broken up and it is not advantageous to
send young missionaries out for less than the regular term missions.
</p><p>
Brethren, "Go into all the world and preach the gospel to every creature"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19#19">Matt. 28:19</a>). We are heeding that
call.
</p><p>
God bless the young men and the young women who are responding, and God bless the
parents, the fathers and mothers, who in pride are sacrificing where necessary to pay the
expenses of these choice young men and women.
</p><p>
That the blessings of the Lord may continue to be poured out upon the priesthood of this
Church, that we may in every way be honorable representatives of the Master, I pray, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
