<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">If the Gift of Faith Is There</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Clifford E. Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Clifford E. Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 102-104</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I feel as if I had run through a red light!
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters: I join you this beautiful Sabbath morning in expressing gratitude for
a testimony of the divinity of this work.  As I drove up this morning from my home in Utah
County, I could not help feeling grateful that I had a father and a mother who believed.  My
father, it is his 117th anniversary today, knew the Prophet Joseph, only as a boy, however, but
his family knew the Prophet intimately, and they loved him.  My father loved him.  My
mother loved his name.  They have instilled in the hearts of us children an appreciation of
this great work.  They went through times that were rough.  Father knew the criticisms that
had been heaped against the Prophet, but he knew they were not true, and he
knew in very deed that Joseph was all that he pretended to be.
</p><p>
I tried to think this morning, as I was driving along, what I would have thought, had I lived
in the little village of Palmyra in 1820, when a young boy was to return to his home and tell
his parents of the great manifestation that had come to him.  I am wondering what I would
have thought, had I even been a brother, as was Hyrum, six years older than the Prophet.
Would I have believed him or would I have thought that there was something wrong with the
boy?  But I am sure if I had come under that parental influence and had felt the faith and
warmth of those parents who knew, I, too, would have subscribed to his great message and
would have believed.
</p><p>
A mother knows the weakness of her children; she knows those weaknesses before anyone
else.  She does not parade them, for which we are grateful, but she knows the weaknesses,
and Lucy Smith would have known whether or not the Prophet, the boy, was telling the truth. 
She would have known whether his message was one of truth or one of error, and she did
know it and she never wavered throughout her life; neither did the father, who stood loyally
and truly by the side of the young Prophet.  It was a fantastic message.  It was not easy to
believe. And I try to picture the Prophet as we picture the Savior as he stood before Pilate,
alone; his disciples had left him, even Peter had said that he did not know him when he was
pressed by some of the rabble (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/69-74#69">Matt. 26:69-74</a>);
so Jesus stood alone. In that early day in the history of the
Church, the Prophet stood alone, and yet think of this great work today.  One and a quarter
centuries have passed and here we have the evidence of the leaven that was referred to by
Brother Morris, small as it was, leavening the lump; and this message of the restored gospel is
spreading throughout the land.
</p><p>
I thought of these things as I drove along, and then I thought of Oliver Cowdery.  Oliver
Cowdery at one time lost the gift of faith. He was like many of us today!  Some little thing
had cankered his soul. We sometimes let little things canker our souls, and we lose the great
values and blessings that come through faithful service in this Church.  Oliver had let little
things canker his soul.  Phineas Young who was very close to my father's family, and who
was a brother-in-law of Oliver Cowdery, labored with Oliver, wrote him letter after letter,
telling him never to mind the little things but to remember that the truth had been restored
and that he, Oliver, knew it and that he should come back in the Church.
</p><p>
In this very pulpit a number of years ago, Brother Alonzo Hinckley read a letter that Oliver
Cowdery had written to Phineas Young, in which he set forth some of his grievances, feeling
that he had been injured by some of his friends, and Phineas Young wrote back to him and
said, "Never mind all that; suppose there was some grievance. You know the gospel is true;
you know your testimony; you know where you belong." Following this, Oliver finally came
up to Council Bluffs, and you know the rest of the story. He appeared before the people and
then before the high council, and humbly he said to the high council, substantially as follows,
"I do not ask to be restored to my former position" . . . the gift of faith had come back in his
soul . . . "but all I ask is that I may come back into the Church, because I know it is true."
</p><p>
It is a marvelous testimony, my brothers and sisters.  He had been out of the Church ten
years.  It was nearly twenty years since he had written the Book of Mormon, as it fell from
the lips of the Prophet Joseph, as he Joseph, translated.  He could easily have wavered; he
could have said, "We were mistaken.  It was all a mistake. Joseph made us believe we saw
the plates.  We imagined we heard a voice, and somehow or another we thought we saw an
angel." But he did not say that.  He said, "The Book of Mormon is true.  It was translated by
the gift and power of God.  We saw the angel, and we heard his voice as he declared the
truthfulness of this sacred record."
</p><p>
So, my brethren and sisters, with a heart full of gratitude and a testimony in
my soul of the divinity of this work, I stand before you acknowledging the goodness of God
to me, and to my family, for the gift of faith, realizing that no matter what comes in one's
life, if the gift of faith is there, one may safely walk without wavering and without complaint. 
I feel that in my soul today, as I bear you this testimony, in the name of the Lord Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
