<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">For Time and Eternity</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1955, pp. 114-116</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: I sincerely seek an interest in your faith and prayers, that what I shall
undertake to say in the next few minutes may be directed by the Spirit of our Heavenly
Father and may be delivered in a spirit of love and fellowship, for I love the work of the
Lord, and I love his people; I love to work with them.
</p><p>
I have been interested in this conference, especially interested in the many references that
have been made to the foreign missionary work and to the newly completed temple in
Switzerland. Those references have caused me to reflect upon the purposes of temples. We
have had some instruction already as to why we build them.  It seems to me that so far as a
newly erected temple is concerned, perhaps its major purpose would be to take care of the
living, because I believe the accommodations of those already existent would take care of the
vicarious work that we have available at the present time.  So this newly erected temple is
likely to be most beneficial for the living people of Europe.  They who have never had the
experience of an endowment in the temple before, will receive a wonderful uplift in their
spirituality as they enjoy this rare and wonderful privilege which is given to us in the temples
of God.
</p><p>
The priesthood has for its purpose integrating into the lives of people the ordinances and the
benefits of the gospel of Jesus Christ.  The greatest and most supreme of all of these blessings
comes to us through the administration of the priesthood in the temples of God and in no
other place and were this new temple limited to the benefits the people receive in mortality,
its erection and administration would be amply justified, but the benefits of these ordinances
when they are carried through to their ultimate end, are not limited to mortality.  They
penetrate the veil between mortality and eternity, giving people advantages which are past our
understanding.  Really, they are so sublime and wonderful that they stagger our imagination.
</p><p>
In the Doctrine and Covenants we are told that any man who can attain to the magnification
of all of his duties in the Melchizedek Priesthood would and will ultimately attain to the
powers of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33-34#33">D&amp;C 84:33-34</a>).
</p><p>
No man who goes into a temple and is content with receiving his own endowments realizes
the full possibilities that the temple offers him.  He only who takes a wife into the temple and
is sealed to her for time and all eternity can ultimately attain to the tremendous and wonderful
blessings that are held out as an inducement for righteous living.  That seems to me to be the
sublime and supreme distinction between the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints and
all other religious denominations.
</p><p>
During the last year, 1954, and this year up to the present, as we have ministered among the
stakes of Zion, there has been placed in our hands an item, a statistical item relative to the
numbers of people who avail themselves of this grand and glorious privilege. I have kept
account of the stakes I visited last year and this.  Last year there were reported 1811
marriages in the stakes that I visited, and I was surprised to learn that less than half of them
were consummated in the temple, a fifth of them involving people who were not members of
the Church.
</p><p>
It is an astonishing thing.  I rather feel to regard that as an unsatisfactory percentage.  There
may be people who think it is perhaps all that could be expected, but I do not.  I think that
we ought to strive to increase that percentage, and then once you make up your mind that that
should be an incentive and an objective, the question then is: Where are you going to start to
bring about an improvement?
</p><p>
It seems to me that the duty of teaching people who are approaching marriageable age, the
advantages of celestial and eternal marriage, first, and always, is with the parents.  Then I
wonder how parents who have not availed themselves of that privilege and who hardly live so
as to impress their children with the desirability of perpetuating the marriage relationship, can
expect so to impress their children.  I have come to decide, brethren and sisters, that the place
to start is not with the young folk, but with the old folk, to get the fathers and mothers of
young people fully to appreciate the advantages, the wonderful advantages of celestial
marriage, and then to present to their growing children an example which will make marriage,
a marriage for eternity, attractive to them.
</p><p>
If the parents do not do it, where can we lay the responsibility for it? We have a good many
agencies that are supposed to supplement the efforts of the parents, brethren and sisters, but it
seems to me that fathers and mothers can never escape the responsibility for this instruction.
</p><p>
So it behooves us to live to be worthy of it.  If we have not already availed ourselves of the
opportunity to bring our lives into conformity with the standards of the gospel so that we can
avail ourselves of that privilege, what example do we set as a lesson to our children?  Words
fall flat when they do not show in the example of the parents the value of the teaching.
</p><p>
So I believe that is where we ought to begin, brethren and sisters, and there are many of us
who can take it to heart.  I am sure there is a wonderful percentage of people who make
every possible effort to magnify their calling and obligation, but there are many others of us
who do not.  We let jealousy and hatred and other things enter into family relationships which
disrupt them and disturb them, resulting too frequently in the dissolution of the union, and all
of that is not right, brethren and sisters.  It is not right, and it behooves us as fathers and
mothers to set the example and then give the instruction. That instruction should be subtle.  It
should be attractive.  It should be convincing.
</p><p>
Then to supplement the efforts of the father and the mother, we have the bishopric of the
ward.  We had a wonderful film on the responsibility of a bishop the other night.  There have
been bishops in the Church who have seen and used the opportunity that is theirs to instruct
their young people when they approach marriageable age in the advantages of celestial and
eternal marriage.  There, again, is the closest contact I believe that we have in the Church to
supplement the efforts of the fathers and the mothers.  And if fathers and mothers and bishops
and auxiliary associations should combine in a serious effort to teach this truth, I believe we
could make it so attractive that the evils which befall many of our young people would cease
to be attractive to them, and they would develop a strength in their youth which would carry
them through all their future lives in honorable service to God, our Heavenly Father, and in
righteous living.
</p><p>
Now what will we do about it? We cannot dream ourselves into it, brethren and sisters, and if
any single one who is here today finds opportunity, he should start action at once to correct
his life and make it appropriate for the realization of these grand and glorious principles and
privileges.
</p><p>
The greatest result of such living is the union of a man and a woman for time and eternity,
sealed by the Holy Spirit of Promise, with the power of eternal increase, an attribute of
Godhood.  "...all that my Father hath shall be given unto him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>) is the
promise made to the man who receives and magnifies the priesthood. God bless you.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
