<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Some Problems and Principles</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1948, pp. 63-67</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Somehow or other, this task never seems to become any easier. In fact at times I feel that it
becomes more difficult, and I earnestly hope that you will sustain me with your thoughts and
prayers and that my Father in heaven will give me utterance.
</p><p>
TESTIMONY OF INFORMED WITNESS
</p><p>
I was struck by a thought that Dr. Merrill presented in the opening paragraphs of his talk, that
the testimony of one informed witness is worth infinitely more than the testimony of many
who don't know, I have often made the observation that an idiotic opinion multiplied by fifty
million is still an idiotic opinion. Sometimes our children endeavor to induce us to give them
permission to do things we know they shouldn't do, with the well-worn phrase that
"everybody is doing them."
</p><p>
But no matter what everybody does, an error is still an error even though it is multiplied
millions of times. So is an evil, and it doesn't matter how popular or how glamorous or how
universal evils become, they are still evils. Some evils have been made very glamorous, very
appealing and very popular, but we must be aware of the fact that they are still what they are,
regardless of who partakes of them or what they are called, or what appearance they assume.
History has proved many times over that the opinion of one man who knows and who knows
that he knows, the opinion of one man who has the truth and proclaims it, is much more
important than the opinions of many millions who don't know.
</p><p>
EVENTS OF A CENTURY AGO
</p><p>
I can't look at this audience this morning without thinking of another audience that gathered
on Temple Square a hundred years ago. It is one hundred years this month since the first
general conference was held on Temple Square. A bowery was built here in 1847. A special
conference was held in that year, in August, I believe, and the two general conferences
following that one, one on Christmas day, 1847, and one in April 1848, were held back in
Kanesville, Iowa. The first general conference of the Church on this square was one hundred
years ago now, and what has happened since then, here and elsewhere, is almost beyond
belief.
</p><p>
The picture of those people comes before us&mdash;men and women who faced the harsh realities of
physical existence, who had been, that summer and that spring, through the ordeal of seeing
their crops threatened by complete destruction, and many of whom had witnessed the
deliverance through their Father in heaven by the episode of the seagulls, which is now
immortalized in stone on this block.
</p><p>
With what little they had, ragged, I am sure, many of them, and worn and weary, nevertheless
they continued to consult their convictions rather than their convenience, and the fact that they
did so accounts for what we have here today, physically and tangibly, as well as the greater
spiritual and intangible values that have so blessed our lives and the lives of our children.
May God bless their memories and help us to be worthy of the heritage they gave us.
</p><p>
FAME OF TEMPLE SQUARE
</p><p>
This square has since become one of the most visited and most talked-of ten acres in the
world, I am sure. President Smith told you yesterday that we had had more than eight
hundred forty thousand visitors up to this time this year. About a million people a year are
coming here currently, a little more or less. There are still many people who come here from
all parts of the country who remember and who speak feelingly of their visits in decades gone
by, when they met such men as Joseph Peery who so greatly influenced what went on, on this
block, for so many years.
</p><p>
But we are facing new circumstances so far as the operation of this square is concerned. It
was only fifteen years ago, in 1933, that there were about one hundred thousand people who
visited this place, and I rather think that that figure might have included the general
conference visitors. We have about ten times that number now, excluding general conference
visitors. It was only three years ago, 1945, that we had about a third as many people come
here as we have now, three hundred seventy-seven thousand in 1945. You can see that we are
facing new problems of organization and administration, and if the activities on these grounds
continue to multiply in the next ten or fifteen years as they have in the past, these ten acres
literally will not accommodate them.
</p><p>
TEMPLE SQUARE GUIDES
</p><p>
We have some seventy-five guides functioning now on these grounds, faithful men and
women who take time from their businesses and their professions and their homes at a
moment's notice to come here and render such service as is needed. We have about eight
lawyers, three or four doctors, and many successful businessmen, who leave their clients,
their patients, and their customers waiting in their offices while they come here to conduct
strangers about these grounds. There are many times when we have five or six groups moving
on the grounds at once, and if one building is tied up, it means that there are many times
when we have no place to take these people who come. They come at their convenience, not
at ours, and we have to take care of them when they come or not see them at all.
</p><p>
These grounds are open about fourteen hours a day at the present time, and they are open
almost every day of the year, seven days a week. The only day we have been closed in my
experience here is Christmas Day, and I am sure we could have conducted some people about
the grounds even on that day. This is our window to the world, and I want to express my
appreciation to the Presiding Bishopric for their most helpful and sympathetic cooperation in
maintaining the personnel and the physical appearance of these grounds, and to the First
Presidency, President Smith and President Clark, and President McKay, in helping us to get
the help we need and in helping us with many of our problems and in acquiring the physical
facilities we need here. I almost believe at times, without being able to prove it, that not only
do we see more people here than anywhere else in the Church, but that more strangers see us
here than in all the rest of the Church put together.
</p><p>
TEACHINGS OF KARL G. MAESER
</p><p>
I am grateful to Brother Frank Otterstrom for inviting again my attention a few sentences
from the mind and heart and experience of Brother Karl G. Maeser who had such an
influence on this Church and its educational policies in his generation, and on the lives of
those who have succeeded his generation.
</p><p>
Here is one which we may all have heard many times over but repetition of which is well
worthwhile:
</p><p>
The Lord has unconditionally declared the triumph of his Church, but his promises to me are
all conditional. My concern, therefore is about myself.
</p><p>
I have no fear, and I know you haven't, as to the ultimate destiny of this Church, and of the
Lord's work in the earth. But many individuals fall by the wayside, and in the 
Doctrine and Covenants the Lord
has in a number of places distinguished between his pleasure with the Church collectively and
his pleasure with people individually, or displeasure as it may be. One such utterance is in the
first section, where he declares that he is pleased with the Church speaking collectively but
not individually (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30#30">D&amp;C 1:30</a>).
Regardless of the great strides the Church has made, in the words of Karl G.
Maeser, "my concern . . . is about myself" and my own
part and contribution to it. I commend to you the beautiful and profound thought of President
Ivins yesterday: "Serving for the sheer joy of service, without thought of self."
</p><p>
Another sentence from Brother Maeser:
</p><p>
No man shall be more exacting of me or of my conduct than I am of myself.
</p><p>
And another one:
</p><p>
I would rather trust my child to a serpent than to a teacher who does not believe in God.
</p><p>
Here is another:
</p><p>
The Lord never gets in debt to any man.
</p><p>
I am reminded of Bishop Richards' remarks here yesterday.
</p><p>
And here is another sentence from Karl G. Maeser that is pertinent to our present problems:
</p><p>
Youth demands recreation, and if it is not provided in high places they will seek it in low
places.
</p><p>
Brother Moyle touched on that yesterday: Spending time with our children regardless of our
other pressing professional and business pursuits. These children of ours are going to grow up.
What we have said about the visitors who come here, that they come at their convenience and
not at ours, is true of children. They grow up at their convenience, or at Nature's
convenience, and not at ours, and we had better touch their lives while they are with us and
while we have the opportunity. They are going to find companionship somewhere, and if it
isn't our companionship, it will be the companionship of someone else. If it isn't our
influence, it will be some other influence that shapes and molds them, because they are not
going to be isolated from outside influences, and we shall have no cause for complaint about
the influences that do mold their lives unless we do our best to see that ours is dominant in
the shaping and molding of their characters.
</p><p>
A final sentence from Brother Maeser:
</p><p>
If you want excuses, go to the devil&mdash;he can give you any number. We can go to the devil for
a good many things, and sometimes, in some instances, I'm afraid that is the source of too
much that is plentiful in the world. The law of supply and demand does not
seem to work as well as it should in this instance.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE AND FORGIVENESS
</p><p>
I am grateful, however, as Bishop Isaacson expressed yesterday, that this is a Church that
proclaims the principles of repentance and forgiveness. If it weren't for repentance and
forgiveness, life would be hopeless for most of us, if not for all of us.
</p><p>
I was talking a day or two ago with two of our brethren who are attorneys, and we were
speaking of some of our penal practices and problems, about life imprisonment, for example.
A man who is imprisoned for life, and who knows that there is no hope for him, hasn't much
inducement, perhaps, to be on his good behavior. I recall a scene to which I was a witness not
long ago, which involved a small boy who had been invited to stay in the house for the rest
of the day because he needed some disciplining. He was rather obstreperous during the day
and said, "Why should I be good? I can't go out anyway."
</p><p>
Well, he had to be reminded that there was another day coming. If there isn't another day
coming, there isn't much inducement, and I am grateful for the principle of repentance and
forgiveness. There is another day coming for all men, with some rare exceptions, on terms of
repentance and forgiveness, and obedience. "Go thy way, and sin no more"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/11#11">John 8:11</a>). There are two
parts to that equation and they involve both forgiveness and sincere repentance.
</p><p>
I am grateful for my fellowship with you, my brothers and sisters, more than I can speak.
And I am grateful that the mysteries of the kingdom have never troubled me much. I think
that the simple truths of the gospel are so plain and so beautiful that I don't worry much
about the things that no man can explain; and I am sure in my own heart that if we will just
live as well as we know how to live, we will be all right here and hereafter. It won't be the
things that we don't know that will give us trouble. It will be the things that we do know and
fail to abide by.
</p><p>
May God help us to go forth and live our lives and meet our problems and counsel our
families and render service in his Church and be accepted into the kingdom of our Father in
heaven, with his approbation, when that time shall come, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
