<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 183-187</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Smith has requested that I speak next. I rather feel that perhaps, if we were to
adjourn now, after the powerful and inspired utterances of President McKay, we would be
better off than perhaps to have me try to say something, but obedient to the request of the
President I shall do the best I can.
</p><p>
I do pray that the Lord will bless me and that you will be good enough to ask him in my
behalf that he will grant the blessing, in order that you may be edified, strengthened, and built
up.
</p><p>
Over the last year I have been doing considerable reading of a more intensive kind than I
have before done, on the matters I have been reading about, and I have been impressed with
certain historical facts to which I wish briefly to allude.
</p><p>
EARLY CHRISTIAN HISTORY
</p><p>
For some reason, which is not clear, either from history or from scriptures, it does not appear
that Peter, James and John, who were left as the First Presidency of the primitive church, ever
appointed any successors to themselves. The result was what might have been expected. There
grew up certain great centers, Alexandria, Rome, Carthage, Caesarea, and so on. As time went
on, each of these was presided over by a bishop. They had no central guiding hand, and the
result was they began to dispute about doctrine, and about rites and ceremonies. Cults grew
up, one cult here, another there. These various units, headed by bishops, drifted off into
contrary or divergent directions. They called councils from time to time to settle their
disputes. The great council of Nicaea about 325 after Christ was the first great ecumenical
council. There they tried to settle certain matters of doctrine.
</p><p>
There was no unity in the church; there was no unifying direction. They were as lost sheep.
</p><p>
The church moved fairly well while the apostles still lived. Then followed a secondary period
when, the apostles having died, there still lived those who had known the apostles, and who
had received from them instructions. This kept the church from wandering too far and too
fast. Then the third church generation came, and not having the anchorage that was given by
the apostles first, and next, by those who had known the apostles, they drifted and drifted
rapidly, until by the middle of the third century, they had lost the priesthood, indeed they no
longer pretended actually to confer it. Their ordinals merely prayed that the Lord would give
the powers, the priesthood powers which Christ had conferred upon his apostles and which
they, in turn, had, according to the sacred record, conferred upon a very few individuals.
</p><p>
IMPORTANCE OF UNITY
</p><p>
I have never permitted an opportunity of this kind to go by without speaking on this question
of unity. I have said to you brethren, over and over again, and I repeat it tonight, that if we
were really united, if we really saw eye to eye, and then would move in unison, there is
nothing in the world, in righteousness, that we might not do in accordance with the will of the
Lord and not to defeat his purposes. But there comes to us as we get farther-flung in the
world, there comes constantly back to the First Presidency, signs that if we did not have the
priesthood, if it had been lost to us as it was lost to the primitive church, we would be
marching along the same roads that they marched to complete apostasy.
</p><p>
Now brethren, there is only one way to be united, and that is to be united. The Lord has set
up amongst us, with our priesthood and with our auxiliaries, as nearly a perfect organization
as we mortals, in our present condition, can carry on. Just so soon as we undertake, by
ourselves and of our own thought and volition, of our own wisdom, to set up other
organizations than those set up by the Presidency of the Church, under the direction of the
President of the Church, the presiding High Priest of the Church, just so soon as we undertake
to do that then we are on a detour. We are no longer going down the middle of the road. We
are on a road that could lead to apostasy.
</p><p>
I think perhaps that even now there are evidences that those in the outlying areas farthest
away from the central organization of the Church, are feeling, perhaps, the absence of controls
a little more keenly than they who are nearer in; and yet I would like to say here that my
observation is that among those who are farther away from us, who do not see us every day,
there is a higher regard for the General Authorities than there is among those who are around
here. Yet there is that seemingly inevitable drawing away tendency in the remoter areas, to this time
in details that leave us still strong. But we must be always alert.
</p><p>
The Lord gave us our free agency, as you know, and we may think and we may talk as we
wish, but we may not teach false doctrine for that is no part of free agency. In the spiritual
domain false doctrine is the equivalent of libel, and slander in the civil domain. Those things
we may not do.
</p><p>
PLANS OF MEN
</p><p>
This is an age, a period, when everybody has a new idea as to what to do to cure the ills of
society. There are almost as many plans as there are people, plans usually developed by men
of no experience no training, no thought, and the plans gain currency among those who are
equally untrained, inexperienced and ill taught.
</p><p>
Amongst us, it is quite a common thing for us to look about and see something that needs to
be corrected, and so we start a movement to correct it. We see something that should be done,
some opportunity we think we see that has not been embraced, and so we form a plan to meet
that opportunity as we see it. I think perhaps I might say that not always have our auxiliary
organizations brought themselves under restraint, the restraint of the discipline of doing
primarily the things that they were set up to do. But whether that be true or not, it is certainly
true that here and there somebody gets an idea of what he ought to do and so starts out to do
it.
</p><p>
There was handed to us tonight a plan to satisfy all the needs of the members of a proposed
group, from an economic, social, physical, spiritual and educational standpoint. Well, that is
quite a program, just to start out with right from scratch. They have several hundred members
they say.
THE LORD'S PLAN
</p><p>
Now brethren, the Lord has set up, as I said to begin with, an organization that is as nearly
perfect as we mortals can live, and the only safety we shall have will be in following that
plan and that program.
</p><p>
I sometimes think that maybe we take to our souls a little more unction than we should over
the thought that the Lord has set up his work never more to be thrown down or taken away
and given to another people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/44#44">Dan. 2:44</a>).
I believe that as I believe I am looking at you, as I know I am
looking at you. But that does not say that all of us are going to be among those who stand
firm by the plan which the Lord has given. Let us be sure that we do not get away from the
Lord's plan.
</p><p>
You Elders quorum men, Seventies, High Priests, all of you brethren of the Aaronic
priesthood, cling by what the Lord has given to you. There is opportunity for all of the
activity that you can possibly participate in and as it is under a divine plan there will be
nothing in it that is not profitable for you. Do not go off and try to reform the Church. Let us
reform ourselves, and the Church will take care of itself.
</p><p>
DIRECTION OF HOLY GHOST
</p><p>
Sometimes people get to preaching, preaching false doctrines. Sometimes the Elders get to
telling their own ideas about what the Gospel is, making their own explanations. The Prophet
records that on one occasion a man came to him and was very much surprised when the
Prophet told him that a prophet was not always a prophet. He was a prophet only when he
spoke with the spirit of prophecy.
</p><p>
On two occasions today that passage of the scripture has been quoted and referred to, which
was really directed to Orson Hyde, but it is applicable to all of us, that whatever the servants
of the Lord say shall be scripture, the mind of the Lord, the will of the Lord, the voice of the
Lord, the power of God unto salvation. Sometimes we overlook the beginning, "what ye say
under the direction of the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/34#34">D&amp;C 68:34</a>).
</p><p>
You remember that Paul and Barnabas had a little trouble in their time
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/15/36-41#36">Acts 15:36-41</a>). One of them at that
particular occasion did not have the direction of the Holy Ghost, the inspiration of it. Peter
and Paul had their troubles
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/3/15-17#15">2 Pet. 3:15-17</a>).
They were not then both being moved by the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
The Prophet tells&mdash;you will find it in his works&mdash;that some of the brethren in the early days
early days got very much interested in the book of revelation, a pregnant source of
speculation, and he rebuked them for it.
</p><p>
I would like to urge you brethren to read the scriptures yourselves. We have had some
wonderful talks today about reading the Book of Mormon. I subscribe to all of it. And the
other books were mentioned at the same time, the Bible, the D&amp;C and the Pearl of Great
Price. But read the scriptures and get your own ideas about them.
</p><p>
In speaking about Brother Hezekiah Brown the Prophet Joseph said he was so happy that
men could read and think and speculate; we were not cramped like the sectarians were, but
he cautioned the brethren that they should be careful about what they taught. There is only
one source on the earth that has any right to change or modify or extend any revelation of the
Lord, and that is the President of the Church, the Prophet, Seer, and Revelator, the presiding
High Priest. He alone, through the inspiration and revelation of the Lord, can change the
revelations already given. All the rest of us can think about them, talk about them, speculate
about them, but we cannot change them, and until he speaks the revelations stand as is. We
ought not, therefore, to get discouraged because somebody sees a revelation in a different
light from the way in which we see it. We are entitled to our opinion; the other man is
entitled to his opinion, but the revelation stands until God changes it in the regular way.
</p><p>
APPEAL FOR UNITY
</p><p>
Brethren, I return again to this question of unity. Can we not forget our little troubles, our
little disagreements? Can we not unify on the words of the Lord, even as He spoke them; and
having unified in our belief, can we not unify ourselves in our observance? I am talking, I
know, to brethren who are the stalwarts of the Church, the brethren to whom the Lord looks,
and President Smith as the Lord's representative looks, to carry on the work of the Church.
You must do it. President Smith cannot be everywhere. And you have done a great job. But
we are in perilous times, economic, political and spiritual, and if you will just harken to what
the Prophet of the Lord says and be guided by the revelations which God has given through
his prophets in ancient times and modern times, all will be well.
</p><p>
I pledge you that I will try, with all my mind and soul and heart, to do the things which our
leader wishes us to do. I wish that you brethren, each and all of you would follow me in that
pledge, and if we shall do that, we shall be nearer heaven, this great priesthood body of the
Church, we shall be nearer heaven than we have yet been in this dispensation.
</p><p>
I bear my testimony that I know that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ and the firstfruits of
the resurrection (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/20#20">1 Cor. 15:20</a>).
I know that the gospel and the Priesthood were restored through the Prophet
Joseph. I have the testimony of the Spirit to that and the testimony of the Spirit seems to me
far greater than the testimony of the senses.
</p><p>
May God be with all of us, at all times, and may we so live that he can be with us under all
circumstances, which means that we live pure lives, that we keep away from sin and the
places of sin, and that we go to no place where we might not ask our Heavenly Father to go
with us, may we so live that we may be saved and exalted in his presence, I humbly pray, in
the name of Jesus, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
