<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Concluding Address</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President George Albert Smith</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Albert Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1946, pp. 181-186</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is just five minutes to three&mdash;in San Francisco. (Laughter.) This has been a very delightful
experience for me to be at this conference, notwithstanding the fact that some of the dearest
friends I have ever had, who were here a year ago, are not here today. We have listened to
the members of the Quorum of the Twelve, and I realize that for every one now in that
quorum, a very dear friend of mine and member of that group has passed away. Their places
have been well filled. These brethren are really servants of the Lord, but I miss the men who
are gone. Aunt Augusta Grant has sat through this conference attending most of the meetings.
That blessed woman sat by the side of President Grant, helped him rear his family, and
blessed this community. I am grateful to see her here today. I am sure that quite a number of
elderly people are here that some of us do not know about. I mention Aunt Augusta Grant
because President Grant stood here not long ago. Aunt Mary, wife of President Joseph F.
Smith, is here also and is always at our meetings, and many others whom we love. I am sure
they are blessed by being here, and we are blessed by their presence. It will not be long
before many of us will pass on. We will not all leave as fine a record as some of those I have
referred to, probably, but it is a wonderful thing to have that kind of companionship
throughout life.
</p><p>
Just to look into your faces and see the earnestness of your lives is a joy, because that
earnestness is written in your faces. I want to say to many of you that I know personally, I
can never repay your kindness and helpfulness to me in many ways. I say never&mdash;I'll say I
can't do it in this life, but I believe that we are living eternal lives, and perhaps some of these
failures here may be remedied hereafter.
</p><p>
LASTING GREATNESS OF THE PROPHET JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
Much has been said in this conference about the Prophet Joseph Smith. There isn't much that
I could say, except that which is good. Many of the benefits and blessings that have come to
me have come through that man who gave his life for the gospel of Jesus Christ. There have
been some who have belittled him, but I would like to say that those who have done so will
be forgotten and their remains will go back to mother earth, if they have not already gone,
and the odor of their infamy will never die, while the glory and honor and
majesty and courage and fidelity manifested by the Prophet Joseph Smith will attach to his
name forever. So we have no apologies to make.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing to live in an age like this when so many problems are being solved. It
is also a disquieting age to live in when people find pleasure in harshness and unkindness
toward those who are seeking to bless mankind.
</p><p>
CHOICE ASSOCIATIONS IN THE CHURCH
</p><p>
I am glad that I belong to a Church that has produced such men and women as this Church
has produced. I have traveled approximately a million miles in the world in the interest of the
gospel of Jesus Christ. I have been in many climes and in many lands and in many nations,
and I have never seen any place that I thought was as rich in the sweet companionships of life
as I have found in the valleys of these grand mountains and in the organizations of the
Church established in other parts of the world. It is a wonderful thing to have such friendships
of good, true, honorable, sweet, faithful men and women. I have often said no man in the
world has been more blessed than I. From my childhood, ever since I can remember, I have
never been compelled to associate with evil individuals. I have been fortunate in having my
life so adjusted that I could choose the very finest men and women that could be found in the
world to be my companions. This has enriched my life, and I am grateful.
</p><p>
THE PRIMARY ASSOCIATION
</p><p>
I think of my early experiences in the Primary Association. Mentioning the Primary calls to
my attention the fact that it is a marvelous institution. It was the Savior of the world who
said: ". . . Suffer the little children to come unto me, and forbid them not: for of such is the
kingdom of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/14#14">Mark 10:14</a>).
In this organization there is a program to develop little
children and to give them the advantage of education, refinement, and culture equal, if not
superior, to any other in the world. Personally I feel today to thank the general officers and
the stake and ward officers of this organization who give their time to developing these little
children. I am reminded of it because yesterday and today I see quite a number of these
children sitting in the aisles, on the steps, and elsewhere, paying attention and listening to
what has been going on. It is lovely to have so many little children here, and it makes me feel
comfortable to have them in the audience. The Lord loves them, and I am sure we love them.
</p><p>
THE SUNDAY SCHOOL
</p><p>
And we have our great Sunday School organization. There is no such Sabbath School group
in all the world as we have in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. It is marvelous
what has been accomplished, and its teaching has been so adjusted that
anybody, old or young, may find development and uplift in it. So I would like to thank those
who have made it possible for me, in the Primary and in the Sunday School, to associate with
men and women whose ideals are real Christian ideals, not make-believe, and who train those
under their watchcare to walk uprightly before the Lord, to honor father and mother, to love
one another, to be honest and true and chaste and benevolent. These are great organizations.
</p><p>
MUTUAL IMPROVEMENT ASSOCIATIONS
</p><p>
I think of what the Mutual Improvement Association has done for me. It is one of the most
remarkable organizations in all the world, prepared and adjusted for those above twelve years
of age. It has given me the companionship, as the other organizations did, of a little older
group, but a group of the same fine quality, having faith in God, love for their fathers and
their mothers, and honor and respect for those who preside over them in the Church and state
and nation. What a wonderful help the Mutual Improvement Association has been to me. I
feel to thank and bless whose who made it possible for me to have those companionships.
There are in this audience today men and women with whom I have associated in that great
group for many, many years, and I would like them to know that I appreciate their love and
their kindness.
</p><p>
THE RELIEF SOCIETY
</p><p>
There is another fine organization in the Church, the Relief Society, organized under the
direction of a prophet of God, for the development of women. This organization is
unsurpassed by any woman's organization in all the world. What a wonderful thing it is to
have in each of our wards and branches, these mothers of men and women, who give their
lives to uplift and bless the communities in which they live. What a blessing they are and
have been to this Church and will continue to be!
</p><p>
THE GENEALOGICAL SOCIETY
</p><p>
The Genealogical Society is another marvelous organization. It has the task of gathering the
names of those who have passed on, generations ago, bringing them into a great depository
where they may be sorted over and classified, so that we may trace our ancestry. I said to a
man one day. "You can find out all about your ancestors if you will go with me to the
Genealogical Library." He said, "I don't want to know anything about them." I wouldn't
either if I thought my ancestors could be traced back to an orangutan or a baboon. But like
William Jennings Bryan, those who have any pride in that kind of ancestry will not connect
me with their family tree. I want to say that we don't appreciate what this great organization
has done in gathering our genealogy and in tying together all the family lines that have been
broken and lost.
</p><p>
CHURCH WELFARE PROGRAM
</p><p>
We have our welfare program. It has been organized only a short time, and yet today is in a
position to ship carloads of food, clothing, bedding, and other materials, to men and women
and children on the other side of the sea, who are starving and freezing to death for the
various things that we have in abundance, gathered by that great organization.
</p><p>
This Church and its organization prepare us for the kingdom of heaven if anything does that
is in this world. So today, as I stand here and look into your faces, I realize what the gospel
of Jesus Christ has done for me. I have no words to express my gratitude to God for the
ministry of this Church and the blessings of its members to me as an individual; then multiply
that by what it has done for all the rest of you.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing to go through life, hand in hand with the Master of heaven and earth,
and this Church comes as near giving me this privilege as anything can do in mortality. I am
grateful as I look around this group and see what God hath wrought for us, and I thank these
elderly men and women who have borne the burden in the heat of the day and carried on, that
we who have come on might have the blessing of a knowledge of the purpose of life to
prepare us for eternal happiness.
</p><p>
CHURCH SCHOOL SYSTEM
</p><p>
We have our great educational institutions, our schools and seminaries, where our sons and
daughters may not only be taught the rudiments of education but may be taught the
fundamentals of eternal happiness. I am thankful that Karl G. Maeser, when I was only a
child, put into my life a part of that which goes to make up the organization of the great
Church school system of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. There are many
things that I might mention, but these are just some that come to my mind as I stand here.
</p><p>
OUR MISSIONARY OPPORTUNITIES
</p><p>
As we approach the conclusion of this great conference I have only good will in my heart for
mankind. I haven't any animosity in my heart toward any living human being. I know some
that I wish would behave themselves a little better than they do, but that is their loss, not
mine. If I can get my arm around them and help them back on the highway of happiness by
teaching them the gospel of Jesus Christ, my happiness will be increased thereby. That is the
purpose of the missionary work of this great Church. I would like to say to the brethren who
are mission presidents, you have a real responsibility in your various fields. You do not have
very many missionaries from Zion as yet, but they are coming. I want to say that you will
have all you can do to take care of them and train and develop them, as well
as to assist the local people who have been so faithful and helpful during these long trying
times. The letter we read from Brother Benson today indicates that many of the people over
there are nearly starving and freezing to death, but the thing they are thinking about
apparently, as indicated by his letter, is not how they may have a palace on earth, but how
they may help other people to enjoy a mansion on high. That is what the gospel does for us.
It is not what we have that makes us happy; it is not the material things of life that enrich our
lives; but it is what we are. The nearer we are like our Heavenly Father and his beloved Son
Jesus Christ, the happier we are. Surely, therefore, not any man or woman under the sound of
my voice, or in the world who understands, will hesitate to go out and teach these people who
do not understand, and radiate sunshine. You cannot drive people to do things which are right,
but you can love them into doing them, if your example is of such a character that they can
see you mean what you say.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR HELPFULNESS OF ASSOCIATES
</p><p>
I thank my brethren and my associates for their help and their kindness. When I think of what
a weak, frail individual I am to be called to stand in the midst of this great Church, I realize
how much I need the help of every soul that is in it, if I am to succeed; so I thank my
brethren, my faithful counselors, who have helped me in the unusual experience of becoming
accustomed to a great responsibility. I am grateful to my brethren of the Quorum of the
Twelve, the Patriarch, the Assistants to the Twelve, the First Council of the Seventy, the
Presiding Bishopric&mdash;all these men who are servants of the Lord and who are seeking to keep
his commandments and teach us the way of eternal life. I am grateful to them, and I invoke
upon them, and upon all of you, my Father's children, here or wherever you may be, the
blessings of peace and love and joy, and the companionship of the Spirit of God, and in the
end eternal life in the celestial kingdom. I pray that that may be our privilege. When the
Lamb's book of life is opened and the names of those are recorded who are to inherit the
celestial kingdom, I hope and pray that you and all those you love, all these sons and
daughters of our Heavenly Father who are associated with you here, may have their names
recorded there&mdash;not one missing. If that is the case, how happy we will be throughout the ages
of eternity. Thanks to the prophets of old, to our Heavenly Father who sent them, thanks to
his beloved Son Jesus Christ who died that we might live again, thanks to Joseph Smith
whose name has been belittled by some ignoramuses in the world, that is, they have sought to
belittle him, but they cannot. Thanks to him who was willing to lay down his life and seal his
testimony with his blood as evidence of the fact that he knew whereof he had spoken. God
bless you, my brethren and sisters; may peace abide with you in your hearts and in your
homes. Love one another; love mankind; reach out to those who need you. If
we do that happiness such as can be found in no other way will be our portion.
</p><p>
God grant that it may be, I humbly ask in the name of Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
