<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Liquor Advertising</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Merrill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Merrill, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 32-37</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
During the few minutes allotted to me in this conference, I desire to give brief consideration
to a problem that is arousing more and more attention among those thinking people of
America who are deeply concerned with their moral and spiritual welfare. I refer to the liquor
problem&mdash;one of the most challenging and difficult of all unsolved internal problems that face
the country today, a problem of major importance. Of course the point of view from which I
shall look at this problem is that given me by the moral teachings and standards of the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Yet I hasten to say that in respect to the liquor problem
the teachings and standards of multitudes of people in other churches and organizations are
similar to our own. Some of them recognize as clearly and keenly as we do that drinking is
an evil that all good, right-thinking people should unite to eliminate.
</p><p>
USE OF ALCOHOL DESTRUCTIVE
</p><p>
I use the word "drinking," as meaning the imbibing of a liquid containing <i>alcohol</i>, which is a
definite chemical compound, once described by the <i>Journal</i> of the American Medical
Association as
</p><p>
. . . a poison inherently, absolutely, essentially; in a drop or in a gallon, in all
quantities and in every quantity. Plainly its quantity cannot affect its chemical
constitution.
</p><p>
And when drunk, what does alcohol do? In the language of the late Robert G. Ingersoll:
</p><p>
. . . alcohol burns up men, consumes women, destroys life, curses God, and
despises heaven. It suborns witnesses, defiles the jury box, and stains the judicial
ermine. It bribes voters, corrupts elections, endangers the government, degrades
the citizen, debases the legislature, dishonors the statesman. It brings shame, not
honor; terror, not safety; despair, not hope; misery, not happiness. It destroys
peace and ruins morals; it murders the soul; it is the father of all crime, the mother
of all abominations, the devil's best friend.
</p><p>
In the language of the First Presidency of the Church:
</p><p>
Drink brings cruelty into the home; it walks arm in arm with poverty; its
companions are disease and plague; it puts chastity to flight; it knows neither
honor nor fair dealing; it is a total stranger to truth; it drowns conscience; it is the
bodyguard of evil; it curses all who touch it. Drink has brought more woe and
misery, broken more hearts, wrecked more homes, committed more crimes, filled
more coffins than all the wars the world has suffered.
</p><p>
It is involved in more traffic accidents and fatalities, and sends more patients to mental
hospitals than any other single factor.
</p><p>
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS WASTED
</p><p>
Yet notwithstanding these facts, which warrant a bitter arraignment of alcohol, there are an
estimated one hundred million Americans over fifteen years of age, fifty million of whom
drink more or less regularly. According to the United States Department of Commerce these
people spent for alcoholic beverages during 1946 nearly nine billion dollars ($8,770,000,000).
This is more than was spent during the same period for all types of public and private schools
including school and university libraries, and for state and federal government services in the
fields of health, welfare, old age assistance, etc.
</p><p>
Of the fifty million drinkers, it is estimated that three million drink excessively, that is, are
alcoholics&mdash;people who have measurably lost control of their drinking. They have acquired the
disease of alcoholism, as it is termed by the experts. One who suffered from this
disease&mdash;Mrs. Marty Mann, now executive director of the National Committee for Education
on Alcoholism&mdash;said in her Columbia Broadcasting System broadcast last December:
</p><p>
These were the most painful years of my life. I suffered constantly, not just one
kind of pain, but all kinds of pain. I suffered physically, mentally, emotionally,
financially, and socially&mdash;in every department of my life. I tell you, honestly, and
on behalf of those three million human beings, that alcoholism is the most
<i>painful disease</i> known to man.
</p><p>
LECTURES ON "YOU AND ALCOHOL"
</p><p>
Some of you may remember that several months ago the Columbia Broadcasting System
carried over its network thirteen lectures entitled "You and Alcohol," described as
</p><p>
A series of broadcasts examining the problem of alcoholic consumption in the
United States and its effect upon our people and our institutions, delivered on
Tuesday nights, beginning November 12, 1946.
</p><p>
The preface to these lectures said:
</p><p>
Since alcohol touches the lives of large numbers of people, it seemed logical to
Columbia to consider it a problem in which radio's special and unique functions
could be usefully employed to translate the problem into plain, arresting terms and
to bring it directly to the attention of millions of listeners.
</p><p>
Each of the thirteen speakers was considered an expert on the phase of the subject of which
he spoke. I have just quoted one of the speakers. Nine of the others were doctors in various
fields of research&mdash;medicine, neurology, psychology, sociology, psychiatry. Seemingly they all
agreed with Mrs. Mann&mdash;as do medical experts generally&mdash;that alcoholism is a disease, as
certainly as pneumonia, tuberculosis, and cancer are diseases, and should be treated as such.
One of these speakers, Dr. Lyman C. Duryea, wrote:
</p><p>
As a physician, I am concerned about those people who drink to excess and cannot
control their drinking [alcoholics]. These people need medical care. They are sick
people.
</p><p>
ALCOHOLISM A DISEASE
</p><p>
The alcoholic (compulsive drinker, Dr. Duryea calls him) finds it absolutely impossible to
drink in moderation. This means all alcoholic beverages, as well as medicines, or anything
else containing alcohol. Complete abstinence is his only salvation. The person with an alcohol
problem must remember that he is a sick person and that never again can he take a drink "of
anything that contains alcohol." So, let us admit that alcoholism is a disease. However, there
is one peculiarity about the disease&mdash;it is <i>never</i> acquired by anyone who does not take his first
drink. This is a fact. Let everyone remember it.
</p><p>
As just stated, according to accepted figures, fifty million Americans drink. Of this number,
three million, one in sixteen&mdash;six percent acquire the disease of alcoholism, become sick and
in need of treatment. This is more than twice the number afflicted with tuberculosis, we are
told. These figures indicate the magnitude of the problem. (I divert to express the opinion that
the most certain and by all odds the least expensive treatment for alcoholism is that given by
Alcoholics Anonymous, groups of which exist all over America.) I stated that no one ever
becomes an alcoholic who does not take his first glass.
</p><p>
But something more can be said. According to the experts on alcohol, no one who begins to
drink be he rich or poor, master or servant, learned or ignorant, can ever know until it is too
late, if he continues to drink, whether or not he will get the alcoholic disease. No medical
examination can determine this. The change from controlled to uncontrolled drinking occurs
suddenly and without warning, so the experts tell us. Thus there are two things to be
remembered about this disease of alcoholism: It costs nothing to avoid getting it, and nothing
to avoid its recurrence, if once rid of it. Total abstinence is the certain remedy both before
and after.
</p><p>
BILL TO PROTECT ADVERTISING OF LIQUOR
</p><p>
And now let us go to another phase of the alcohol problem&mdash;that of advertising. On May 12
and 13 of this year (1947) the committee on interstate and foreign commerce
of the United States Senate gave a public hearing in Washington, D.C., on Senate Bill 265, by
Senator Arthur Capper of Kansas, which would prohibit all types of advertising of any kind
of alcoholic beverage. The proponents of the bill were able and well prepared and backed by
many resolutions of church and other organizations, as well as by thousands of petitions,
numerously signed. In supporting the bill Senator Capper said:
</p><p>
The growth and extent of the liquor habit in the United States in the last few years
alarms me. We were told preceding repeal, by the advocates of repeal, that the
manufacturers and dealers of alcoholic beverages would discourage excessive
drinking. Yet in 1946 the national drink bill was nearly nine billion dollars,
eighty-nine dollars for every person in the United States over eighteen years
old&mdash;about one-fourth of the federal budget for the coming year. Now, Mr.
Chairman, I believe that the tremendous amount of advertising seeking to whet the
appetite for drinking, seeking to create new customers, especially among women
and children, has much to do with the greatly increased amount of alcoholic
consumption during recent years.
</p><p>
Bishop Wilbur E. Hammaker, of the Methodist Temperance Board, in his testimony said:
</p><p>
Our judges all the way up through the Supreme Court have decided again and
again that the liquor business is hurtful to life, is an enemy of the well-being of
society and lives only by sufferance. It has no inherent or inalienable rights.
Tragedy stalks the liquor business; it is constantly violating the very laws that
permit its presence in our midst. Its history is sordid, shameful, slimy, scrofulous,
rather than glad, noble, and fine as its ads try to tell us.
</p><p>
In his statement before the committee, Mr. O. G. Christgau, superintendent of the Iowa
Ant-Saloon League, among other things, related that Mr. P. S. Dupont, president of the
Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, wrote two years prior to repeal the
following:
</p><p>
Advertising is one of the most fruitful means of increasing business and of
promoting sales. As it is the policy of this country to reduce sales of liquor, no
advertising of any kind should be permitted manufacturers or sellers.
</p><p>
President Roosevelt in proclaiming the repeal of the Eighteenth Amendment declared:
</p><p>
The objective we seek through the national policy is the education of every citizen toward a
greater temperance throughout the nation.
</p><p>
Compare these statements with the fact that during 1946 more than one hundred million
dollars was spent in advertising alcoholic beverages.
</p><p>
Dr. Glen Cunningham, internationally famous some years ago as an athlete and now a
university professor, was a witness before the committee. Among his statements were these:
</p><p>
In my work with thousands of young people during the past fifteen years, I have
noticed an alarming increase in the number who use alcoholic beverages. Every
person, conscious of the startling increase in delinquency among youths, in deaths
and injuries from accidents, in murder and rape, in impoverished and broken
homes, and in the number of mental diseases, realizes the urgent need for the
passage by Congress of Senator Capper's bill. The cost in human misery, maimed
bodies and minds, the lost lives, makes it inestimably more important that the
advertising of alcoholic beverages which contribute so heavily to these great
tragedies, be brought under control.
</p><p>
SUPPORT OF CAPPER BILL URGED
</p><p>
In view of the results that follow the consumption of beverage alcohol, why do the American
people tolerate it? I leave the answer to them. In any case, the vast sums spent for
widespread, alluring, deceptive advertising have had much to do with it and with greatly
increased consumption, especially among women and teenagers. But may I ask you, the
Mormon people, why do you tolerate it? You accept and teach the Word of Wisdom as a
divine revelation in which alcoholic drinks are proscribed. Thus it logically follows that
Latter-day Saints, if true to their faith, cannot conscientiously indulge in drinking; the
informal world knows this. Church members cannot indulge without displeasing God and
without losing more or less the respect of their non-Mormon friends, many of whom look
upon Mormon drinkers as weaklings or hypocrites.
</p><p>
But may we not with perfect propriety and expectation of favorable response ask all Church
and non-Church members who love their fellow men and will work for their best good to do
whatever in their power is feasible to reduce the consumption of alcoholic beverages to the
smallest attainable limits? As one means to this end let us actively support the Capper Bill
and pray that it will become law, thus going far to eliminate every type of beverage alcohol
advertising. But this bill will not become law except over the strenuous opposition of the
financially powerful liquor industry&mdash;an industry that has spent hundreds of millions of dollars
and continues to spend vast sums in advertising.
</p><p>
Representative Joseph R. Bryson said at the Senate committee hearing the following:
</p><p>
Advertising shapes our lives and molds the rising generation. We eat, drink, dress,
and think according to advertising. Immature youths are particularly
impressionable. This advertising comes to us, mainly by press and radio. If the
artificially stimulated demand for intoxicants is to be checked, the advertising of
liquor must stop. Liquor advertising negates the educational efforts of the home,
the school and the church on the dangers of alcohol. How foolish it is to teach
youth the dangers of liquor while allowing the stuff to be advertised in the most
alluring of terms.
</p><p>
CHURCH FOR TOTAL ABSTINENCE
</p><p>
Again I ask: Why do the Mormon people tolerate the drinking of alcoholic
beverages by their members? They all know the Church stands irrevocably for total
abstinence. Many answers are given, but, perhaps one of the most frequent and basic is that
no one may be denied his "free agency"&mdash;his right to drink. But I ask, may one be permitted
to indulge his free agency when to do so endangers the safety, peace, good, and happiness of
others? The answer of our civil laws is <i>no</i>.
</p><p>
Satan the devil, a personal being, is abroad in the land with a multitude of helpers. Back to
him stems the source of all sins, crimes, wickedness, and troubles of the human family.
Satan's ambition is to handicap the Lord's work. This he tries to do by leading away and
using the Father's children in any and every way that brings misery, distress, and destruction
to them. Let us resolve to resist him wherever his influence is manifested, as it certainly is in
all phases of the liquor problem.
</p><p>
LIQUOR ADVERTISING UNMORAL
</p><p>
In the light of all that can be truthfully said of the effects of consumed alcohol are we not
amply justified in declaring that liquor advertising is unmoral and wrong? To encourage and
induce human beings, particularly the youth and immature, to destroy themselves is wicked in
the sight of God and criminal in the sight of man. As I see it nothing more mild can in truth
be said of the vast alcoholic beverage promotion business. Back of it all may be found some
of the keenest and ablest minds working, planning, and scheming how to get more and more
people to drinking.
</p><p>
Behold, verily, thus saith the Lord unto you: In consequence of evils and designs
which do and will exist in the hearts of conspiring men in the last days, I have
warned you, and forewarn you, by giving unto you this word of wisdom by
revelation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>).
</p><p>
Surely Satan is working through these men to the injury and destruction of our fellow men.
</p><p>
Of course many of these people move in respectable and so-called high grade society. But this
does not change the fact that their business is damnable and should not be advertised. Traffic
in morphine, marijuana, stealing, gambling, prostitution, and many other evils, is not
permitted to be advertised. Yet in its evil results does not the liquor traffic outrank any one of
these wicked businesses? In justice to youth, the unwary, and people generally, is not the
elimination of every variety of liquor advertising the very least we can do in this matter. Let
us sincerely and wholeheartedly support the Capper Bill $265.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters of this Church, by promise and covenant we are obligated to serve God
and work for the good of our fellow men. May we be faithful to our obligations, I pray in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
