<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...When Mankind Will Listen"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1955, pp. 35-37</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brethren and sisters; I sincerely trust that the Lord may bless
me in the endeavor to express to you one or two thoughts that I have in connection with my
belief that we are in the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ established through the Prophet
Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
In thinking of the Prophet Joseph Smith, there comes to mind a great statement made in the
Doctrine and Covenants, section four, wherein the Lord said this to the Prophet: 
</p><p>
Now behold, a marvelous work is about to come forth among the children of men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/1#1">D&amp;C 4:1</a>).
</p><p>
That was given to the Prophet in 1829.  In 1830, the Church was organized with but six
members.  The Prophet lost his life in 1844, at which time there were in the Church
approximately forty to forty-five thousand members, an indication to me, and I am sure to
you, that when the Lord said to the Prophet, "Now behold, a marvelous work is about to
come forth among the children of men"&mdash;the men who heard of that great revelation accepted it,
and the result, as I said, was that there were between forty and forty-five thousand who were
members of the Church when the Prophet lost his life.
</p><p>
It is most inspiring to me to know that the Church was in existence for fourteen years when
the Prophet died, and when you think of the accomplishment in that period of time, there is
no question but what the Prophet Joseph was being inspired by the Lord in building up the
kingdom.
</p><p>
From that time on, after the death of the Prophet, it was necessary for the Church to leave
Nauvoo and come into the tops of these mountains where we now exist.  Brigham Young
became the President, and during his period there were approximately 150,000 members; in
the time of President John Taylor, approximately 200,000; in the time of President Wilford
Woodruff, approximately 250,000; in the days of President Lorenzo Snow, approximately
278,645; in the days of President Joseph F. Smith, approximately 495,960; in the days of
President Heber J. Grant, approximately 979,454; and in the days of President George Albert
Smith, approximately 1,111,314 members. Today, in the day of President David O. McKay,
there are approximately, in 1954, 1,302,240.
</p><p>
This again proves to us, as the Lord said through the Prophet Joseph, "Now behold, a
marvelous work is about to come forth among the children of men." And the children of men
have accepted it from that day until this day and are accepting it as it is being taught to them
by missionaries and others who are bringing to them the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I think of the great work of President David O. McKay.  In 1952, President McKay visited
eleven nations.  In 1953, President McKay selected sites for two new temples&mdash;one of which,
of course, has already been dedicated, you know, in far-off Switzerland, and another one soon
is to be built in Great Britain.  In addition, in 1954, President David O. McKay covered
50,000 air miles, visiting eight nations in Europe, South Africa, and South America.  In 1955,
President McKay visited seven nations in the South Pacific, including Hawaii, Samoa,
Australia, and New Zealand, and at the same time selected a site for a temple in New
Zealand; all of which again is evidence of the fact that the Lord did reveal to the Prophet
Joseph that a great and a marvelous work was about to be taught and sent forth among men.
</p><p>
In 1893, President Woodruff made this statement as he dedicated the Salt Lake Temple, "That
from this time on, the power of the evil one would be broken and that the enemy would have
less power over the Saints." How true that is! When we go back into the history of this great
Church, from 1893 until now, we find that the power of the evil one has become weak; and
therefore, it has been possible to go out and preach the gospel in the world. When you stop to
think, the Prophet Joseph lost his life through the power of Satan; and the Saints were driven
from Nauvoo to this country because of the power of the evil one; and from that time until
1893, there was difficulty and suffering for our people; nevertheless, as the Lord said to the
Prophet Joseph, "Now behold, a marvelous work is about to come forth among the children of
men." And the children of men have accepted the same, even though the Prophet was
murdered; and the Church has grown and exists to the point now to where we have, as I said,
over 1,302,000 members.
</p><p>
It is marvelous to know that in this day and age we have more missionaries out in the world
than ever before, preaching the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.  There will be more, and the
time will come when mankind will listen to what the Prophet said in the establishment of the
Church of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I also, brethren and sisters, would like to say this, that each and every one of us has great
responsibilities because we belong to the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ, and the Lord said
this through the Prophet Joseph to us: 
</p><p>
Therefore, O ye that embark in the service of God, see that ye serve him with all your
heart, might, mind and strength, that ye may stand blameless before God at the last
day.
</p><p>
Therefore, if ye have desires to serve God ye are called to the work; 
</p><p>
For behold the field is white already to harvest; and lo, he that thrusteth in his sickle
with his might, the same layeth up in store that he perisheth not, but bringeth salvation
to his soul (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/2-4#2">D&amp;C 4:2-4</a>).
</p><p>
Actually, if we have the faith in our hearts that this is the work of the Lord Jesus Christ and
desire to serve the Lord, we can only do it through the work&mdash;through the results of our
efforts in building up the kingdom and making it strong, so strong that the world will accept
the great truths as they are being forwarded to them through our missionaries, and as has been
done through our President in the last two or three years.
</p><p>
I accept what the Lord said through the Prophet to us, in speaking about what we should do,
and what our attitude should be: 
</p><p>
And faith, hope, charity and love, with an eye single to the glory of God, qualify him
for the work.
</p><p>
Then he went on to say: 
</p><p>
Remember faith, virtue, knowledge, temperance, patience, brotherly kindness,
godliness, charity, humility, diligence.
</p><p>
Ask, and ye shall receive; knock, and it shall be opened unto you.  Amen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/5-7#5">D&amp;C 4:5-7</a>).
</p><p>
There is no question in my mind that when an individual who, in his heart, desires to serve
God and live the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and prays to the Lord, he will receive the
blessings of the Lord according to what his needs are.  I think of the words of the Lord, too,
wherein he said this: "The glory of God is intelligence"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
</p><p>
What a marvelous opportunity we all have in this great Church where the apostles of the Lord
Jesus Christ teach us the gospel!  Therein we do receive the knowledge of the glory of God.
"The glory of God is intelligence"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>),
which intelligence we can use in our lives
from day to day. Surely it becomes the glory of God unto us.
</p><p>
In my testimony I feel as did the apostle of old, when Paul said: 
</p><p>
For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto
salvation to every one that believeth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
I would make one addition, and I might not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, for it is the
power of God unto salvation revealed to us and given to us through the Prophet Joseph and
every one of the Apostles who has lived from that day until this time.
</p><p>
I am grateful for the testimony I have that this is the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ.  I am
grateful for the testimony that I know that Joseph Smith was a Prophet of God, and every
President of the Church has been a prophet of God&mdash;has been an apostle.  I am grateful for
the opportunity of the services that are rendered through the power of the priesthood, for with
our priesthood, brethren and sisters, we have many responsibilities and many opportunities to
help build up the kingdom. I leave you my humble testimony that this is the Church of the
Lord Jesus Christ, that Joseph Smith was indeed a Prophet of God.  There is no question
about it: This is the work of God. May we do all within our power to continue to build it up,
and therein enjoy all of the blessings that the Lord will give us as we go forward in his
behalf, I humbly ask, in the name of Jesus.  Amen
</p>
</div>
</div>
