<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Fulfilment of Prophecy</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">President of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1952, pp. 26-28</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am very grateful for the meeting that was held this morning and for the good counsel that
was given to the members of the Church. I pray that we will heed it and remember that we
are living in a wicked world where men's hearts have turned from truth to untruth, from
righteousness to wickedness; when men are unrighteously ambitious, seeking for power; when
the liberties of the people are in danger. It behooves us as members of the Church to heed the
counsels that are given by those who stand as our leaders under Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I am grateful for the gospel, for all the privileges which are mine to give service, for the
privilege that is mine to honor my Maker and be a true servant to our Master, the Savior and
Redeemer of the world.
</p><p>
We are all aware that we are in imminent danger&mdash;danger because Satan rages in the hearts
of the people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/20#20">2 Ne. 28:20</a>).
This has all been predicted, and the predictions are coming true. Antichrist is
gaining power, and Satan has put into the hearts of the people&mdash;the majority of
them&mdash;greed, and the desire to dominate and take advantage of those who are weak.
</p><p>
Our duty is to keep the commandments of the Lord, to walk uprightly, to defend every
principle of truth, to sustain and uphold the Constitution of this great country, to remember
the Declaration of Independence, for, as we heard this morning from our President, upon
these principles our country was based. They stand at the foundation, the cornerstones of the
liberty that our fathers fought for, and which brought to pass according to the word of the
Lord, the redemption of this land by the shedding of blood.
</p><p>
There is no other course for us to take but the course of righteousness and truth. An ancient
prophet on this continent said, ". . . the natural man is an enemy to God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/19#19">Mosiah 3:19</a>).
The world today has become carnal, as much so now as in the beginning when Adam
attempted to teach his children the principles of eternal truth, and Satan came among them
and commanded them to believe it not.
</p><p>
And we read, "From that time forth man became carnal, sensual, and devilish"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/13#13">Moses 5:13</a>).
</p><p>
Surely we see these indications prevalent in our own land and in foreign lands. Men have
become carnal. They have become enemies to God. They are seeking for their own
advancement and not for the advancement of the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Let me call your attention to this fact which you, of course, all know that we are living in the
last days, the days of trouble, days of wickedness, spoken of as days of wickedness several
hundred years before the coming of Christ by Nephi, as it is recorded in the twenty-seventh
chapter of Second Nephi.
</p><p>
But, behold, in the last days, or in the days of the Gentiles&mdash;yea, behold all the nations of
the Gentiles and also the Jews both those who shall come upon this land and those who shall
be upon other lands yea, even upon all the lands of the earth, behold, they will be drunken
with iniquity and all manner of abominations.
</p><p>
And when that day shall come they shall be visited of the Lord of Hosts, with thunder and
with earthquake, and with a great noise, and with storm, and with tempest and with the flame
of devouring fire (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/27/1-2#1">2 Ne. 27:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
That was said many hundreds of years before the birth of Christ. We are living in the days of
the Gentiles when this prediction was to be fulfilled. We see it being fulfilled, and we must
remember, my good brethren and sisters, that members of the Church are not members of,
and do not belong to the world.
</p><p>
In the wonderful prayer of our Redeemer, as recorded in the seventeenth chapter of John&mdash;I
can hardly read this chapter without tears coming to my eyes&mdash;wherein our Lord, in praying
to his Father in the tenderness of all his soul because he knew the hour had come for him to
offer himself as a sacrifice, prayed for his disciples. In that prayer he said,
</p><p>
I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them
from the evil.
</p><p>
They are not of the world, even as I am not of the world.
</p><p>
Sanctify them through thy truth: thy word is truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/15-17#15">John 17:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
If we are living the religion which the Lord has revealed and which we have received, we do
not belong to the world. We should have no part in all its foolishness. We should not partake
of its sins and its errors&mdash;errors of philosophy and errors of doctrine, errors in regard to
government, or whatever those errors may be&mdash;we have no part in it.
</p><p>
The only part we have is the keeping of the commandments of God. That is all, being true to
every covenant and every obligation that we have entered into and taken upon ourselves.
</p><p>
Brother Kimball in his remarks this morning spoke of a man who could not quite understand
when he paid his tithing and kept the Word of Wisdom, was prayerful, and tried to be
obedient to all the commandments the Lord had given him, and yet he had to struggle to
make a living; while his neighbor violated the Sabbath day, I suppose he smoked and drank;
he had what the world would call a good time, he paid no attention to the teachings of our
Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, and yet he prospered.
</p><p>
You know, we have a great many members of the Church that ponder that over in their hearts
and wonder why. Why this man seems to be blessed with all the good things of the
earth&mdash;incidentally, many of the bad things that he thinks are good&mdash;and yet so many members of
the Church are struggling, laboring diligently to try to make their way through the world.
</p><p>
The answer is a simple thing. If I sometimes, and once in a while I do, go to a football game
or a baseball game or some other place of amusement, invariably I will be surrounded by men
and women who are puffing on cigarettes or cigars or dirty pipes. It gets very annoying, and I
get a little disturbed. I will turn to Sister Smith, and I will say something to her, and she will
say, "Well, now, you know what you have taught me. You are in <i>their</i> world. This is their
world." And that sort of brings me back to my senses. Yes, we are in their world, but we do
not have to be of it.
</p><p>
So, as this is their world we are living in, they prosper, but, my good brethren and sisters,
their world is coming to its end. It will not be many years. I can say that. I do not know how
many years, but Elijah said when he bestowed his keys: ". . . by this ye may know that the
great and dreadful day of the Lord is near even at the doors"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/16#16">D&amp;C 110:16</a>). I am sure that
over a hundred years later I can say that the end of this world is drawing to its end.
</p><p>
The day will come when we will not have <i>this</i> world. It will be changed. We will get a better
world. We will get one that is righteous, because when Christ comes, he will cleanse the
earth.
</p><p>
Read what is written in our scriptures. Read what he himself has said. When he comes, he
will cleanse this earth from all its wickedness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/48#48">Moses 7:48</a>),
and, speaking of the Church, he has said that
he would send his angels and they would gather out of his kingdom, which is the Church, all
things that offend (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/41#41">Matt. 13:41</a>).
Then we are going to have a new earth, a new heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/23-24#23">D&amp;C 29:23-24</a>). The earth will be
renewed for a thousand years, and there shall be peace, and Christ, whose right it is, shall
reign (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/11#11">D&amp;C 29:11</a>).
Afterwards will come the death of the earth, its resurrection, its glorification, as the
abode of the righteous (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/25-26#25">D&amp;C 88:25-26</a>)
or they who belong to the celestial kingdom, and they only shall dwell
upon the face of it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/9#9">D&amp;C 130:9</a>).
</p><p>
Let us be true and faithful, keep our covenants, be true to every obligation the Lord has given
us. I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
