<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Gratitude for the Restoration of the Truth</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 6-9</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am very grateful for the message from President McKay and pray that the blessings of the
Spirit of the Lord may continue with him that he may be raised and be able to meet with us
again.
</p><p>
<b>Father Asked Me to Read The Book of Mormon</b>
</p><p>
When I was a small boy, too young to hold the Aaronic Priesthood, my father placed a copy
of the Book of Mormon in my hands with the request that I read it. I received this Nephite
record with thanksgiving and applied myself to the task which had been assigned to me.
There are certain passages that have been stamped upon my mind, and I have never forgotten
them. One of these is in the 27th chapter of 3rd Nephi, verses 19 and 20. It is the word of
our Redeemer to the Nephites as he taught them after his resurrection. It is as follows:
</p><p>
"And no unclean thing can enter into his kingdom; therefore nothing entereth into his rest
save it be those who have washed their garments in my blood, because of their faith, and the
repentance of all their sins, and their faithfulness unto the end.
</p><p>
"Now this is the commandment: Repent, all ye ends of the earth, and come unto me and be
baptized in my name, that ye may be sanctified by the reception of the Holy Ghost, that ye
may stand spotless before me at the last day"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/19-20#19">3 Ne. 27:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
The other passage is in the 10th verse of chapter 41 in the book of Alma and is as follows:
</p><p>
"Do not suppose, because it has been spoken concerning restoration, that ye shall be restored
from sin to happiness. Behold, I say unto you, wickedness never was happiness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/41/10#10">Alma 41:10</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Fundamental Teachings of the Prophets</b>
</p><p>
These two passages I have tried to follow all the days of my life, and I have felt to thank the
Lord for this counsel and guidance, and I have endeavored to stamp these sayings on the
minds of many others. What a wonderful guide these teachings can be to us if we can get
them firmly fixed in our minds! These thoughts are of course not peculiar to the Book of
Mormon. They are fundamental teachings of the gospel of Jesus Christ and have been
expressed many times by the prophets of old and our Redeemer when they were upon the
earth. It is a fact beyond successful dispute that no unclean thing can inherit the kingdom of
God and obtain what is known as eternal life. This is to say that the Redeemer of this world,
through the great sacrifice which he made, opened the graves and restored all mortal things,
both mankind, fowls of the air, fishes of the sea, and every creature that partook of death
through the "fall" of Adam. In the 5th chapter of John, verses 28 and 29, we have the definite
statement of our Redeemer proclaiming this truth as follows:
</p><p>
"Marvel not at this: for the hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves shall hear
his voice,
</p><p>
"And shall come forth; they that have done good, unto the resurrection of life; and they that
have done evil, unto the resurrection of damnation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/28-29#28">John 5:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Old Things Shall Pass Away"</b>
</p><p>
Permit me to quote some other passages of scripture from the revelations that have come to us
by divine decree in this dispensation. This is from the Doctrine and Covenants, section 29,
verses 22 to 25:
</p><p>
"And again verily, verily, I say unto you that when the thousand years are ended, and men
again begin to deny their God, then will I spare the earth but for a little season;
</p><p>
"And the end shall come, and the heaven and the earth shall be consumed and pass away, and
there shall be a new heaven and a new earth.
</p><p>
"For all old things shall pass away, and all things shall become new, even the heaven and the
earth, and all the fulness thereof, both men and beasts, the fowls of the air, and the fishes of
the sea;
</p><p>
"And not one hair, neither mote, shall be lost, for it is the workmanship of mine hand"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/22-25#22">D&amp;C 29:22-25</a>).
</p><p>
Again the Lord spoke to the Prophet Joseph Smith in a revelation in answer to the question:
</p><p>
"Q. What are we to understand by the four beasts, spoken of in the same verse (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/4/6#6">Rev. 4:6</a>)?
</p><p>
"A. They are figurative expressions, used by the Revelator, John, in describing heaven, the
paradise of God, the happiness of man, and of beasts, and of creeping things, and of the fowls
of the air; that which is spiritual being in the likeness of that which is temporal; and that
which is temporal in the likeness of that which is spiritual; the spirit of man in the likeness of
his person, as also the spirit of the beast, and every other creature which God has created"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/2#2">D&amp;C 77:2</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Resurrection A Complete Restoration</b>
</p><p>
There is a strange doctrine in the world concerning the resurrection even among those who
believe there will be a reuniting of the spirit and body, which is to the effect that only the
righteous will come forth to receive rewards of exaltation. This, however, is a
misunderstanding. Through the atonement wrought by the Son of God, our Savior, the
resurrection is a complete restoration of all things mortal, even of this earth itself on which
we stand. The earth is to be purified and become the abode of the righteous. Peter understood
this doctrine and in his second epistle made the following statement:
</p><p>
"But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night; in the which the heavens shall pass
away with a great noise, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat, the earth also and the
works that are therein shall be burned up.
</p><p>
"Seeing then that all these things shall be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in
all holy conversation and godliness,
</p><p>
"Looking for and hastening unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens being on
fire shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat?
</p><p>
"Nevertheless we, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein
dwelleth righteousness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/3/10-13#10">2 Pet. 3:10-13</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Earth to Receive Resurrection from Mortality</b>
</p><p>
Let us not misunderstand this expression. The new heaven and new earth will be the same
heaven and the same earth on which we now sojourn, for this earth is to receive the
resurrection after this day of mortality and be the abode of the righteous in eternity. Without
the revelations of the Lord given to men, this truth would not be made known. Neither would
we have knowledge of the final glory to which this earth will be assigned. Even now, where
men are without divine guidance and revelation, this truth is unknown.
</p><p>
<b>Darkness Covered the Earth</b>
</p><p>
I am very grateful to my Father in heaven for the privilege that has been granted to me to
come into this world in this dispensation when once again the fulness of the gospel has been
revealed. I have been grateful and have thanked the Lord many times for the privilege which
came to me to live in the present dispensation and that I was not born two or three hundred
years ago during the great period when the fulness of the gospel was not had among men and
they were running, as the scriptures say, "to and fro" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/8/12#12">Amos 8:12</a>)
seeking for the truth which could not be
found because of the deep spiritual darkness which covered the entire earth. This condition
was not the fault of the Lord but the fault of mankind, for they had been offered the fulness
of the gospel, but in course of time they refused to have it, and their teachers turned away
and caused to enter into the Church false doctrines and false ordinances and, worse than all, a
false conception in relation to God our Eternal Father and his Son Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
It was a day when there was not one left in mortality with the divine power to officiate in the
vital and saving ordinances of the gospel&mdash;a day when false teachings, false ordinances, and
false instructors came upon the scene. This condition left the entire Christian world in a state
of confusion, without divine inspiration, so that the notion prevailed universally that the
heavens were closed. Contact with the Father and his Beloved Son had ceased, and the angels
for a long, long past had ceased to visit mortal man on the face of the earth. Under such
conditions it was a natural thought encouraged by clergy that our Eternal Father had ceased to
commune with his children on the earth. Moreover, the false notion became prevalent that
mortal man was left with the teachings of the Bible and that it contained all of the revelation
that mankind needed to insure his salvation in the kingdom of God. Under such conditions
and practice no doubt Satan rejoiced; false teachers arose, and the people, no matter how
devout they were, found themselves in spiritual darkness. Moreover, for a long time the edict
went forth that mortal men who had not been prepared for the clergy should not seek for
knowledge or search the scriptures, for this was the sole responsibility of the clergy.
Therefore I am exceedingly grateful for the Prophet Joseph Smith and the coming of the
Father and the Son to him and their directing him in the course he should take. Moreover, I
am thankful that the time came for the restoration of divine truth and the power of the Holy
Priesthood so that the inhabitants of the world could find the path to eternal life, and the
ordinances of the Holy Priesthood could again be exercised in behalf of the salvation of all
mankind.
</p><p>
<b>The Plan of Salvation Heaven's Gift to Mankind</b>
</p><p>
On January 22, 1834, the Prophet Joseph Smith said:
</p><p>
"The great plan of salvation is a theme which ought to occupy our strict attention, and be
regarded as one of heaven's best gifts to mankind. No consideration whatever ought to deter
us from showing ourselves approved in the sight of God, according to His divine requirement.
Men not infrequently forget that they are dependent upon heaven for every blessing which
they are permitted to enjoy, and that for every opportunity granted them they are to give an
account. You know, brethren, that when the Master in the Savior's parable of the stewards
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/14-30#14">Matt. 25:14-30</a>)
called his servants before him he gave them several talents to improve on while he should
tarry abroad for a little season, and when he returned he called for an accounting. So it is
now. Our Master is absent only for a little season, and at the end of it He will call each to
render an account; and where the five talents were bestowed, ten will be required; and he that
has made no improvement will be cast out as an unprofitable servant, while the faithful will
enjoy everlasting honors. Therefore we earnestly implore the grace of our Father to rest upon
you, through Jesus Christ His Son, that you may not faint in the hour of temptation, nor be
overcome in the time of persecution." (<i>DHC</i> 2, 23-24.)
</p><p>
I would like to quote a few remarks of divine truth from the lips of President David O.
McKay, taken from <i>Gospel Ideals</i>, p. 383.
</p><p>
"No man can disobey the word of God and not suffer for so doing. No sin, however secret,
can escape retribution. True, you may lie and not be detected; you may violate virtue without
it being known by any who would scandalize you; yet you cannot escape the judgment that
follows such transgression. The lie is lodged in the recesses of your mind, an impairment of
your character that will reflect sometime, somehow in your countenance or bearing. Your
moral turpitude, though only you, your accomplice, and God may ever know it, will canker
your soul."
</p><p>
I will close my remarks by reading a poem which I think is very appropriate, entitled "The
Guy in the Mirror."
</p><p>
When you get what you want in your
       struggle for self,<br />
    And the world makes you king for a day,<br />
    Then go to the mirror and look at
       yourself<br />
    And see what that guy has to say.
</p><p>
For it isn't a man's father, or mother,
       or wife,<br />
    Whose judgment upon him must pass;<br />
    The feller whose verdict counts most in
      his life<br />
    Is the guy staring back from the glass.
</p><p>
He's the feller to please, never mind all
       the rest<br />
    For he's with you clear up to the end.<br />
    And you've passed your most dangerous,
       difficult test,<br />
    If the guy in the glass is your friend.
</p><p>
You may be like Jack Horner and
       'chisel' a plum,<br />
    And think you're a wonderful guy,<br />
    But the man in the glass says you're only
       a bum,<br />
    If you can't look him straight in the eye.
</p><p>
You can fool the whole world down the
       pathway of years,<br />
    And get pats on the back as you pass,<br />
    But your final reward will be heartaches
       or tears<br />
    If you've cheated the guy in the glass.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless you, my good brethren and sisters, and all, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
