<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Visit to the Holy Land</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 40-43</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Richards, President Clark, my beloved brothers and sisters, and
friends: I humbly pray that the Lord will help me as I speak to you today.  I shall be grateful
because I know that that will give me more strength than anything I could do.
</p><p>
I wonder if you have ever asked yourself how you would feel if you were occupying this
position.  If you will answer that, then I am sure that is the way you will feel for me.
</p><p>
I am thankful that we can attend these great conferences of the Church. We are all spiritually
strengthened and built up in our faith. I do not know what we would do without our general
conferences.  I hope and pray that each person in the radio and television audience may be
able to partake of the spirit of the conference with us.
</p><p>
You who may have problems&mdash;there may be someone in the radio or television audience
who has a problem&mdash;I hope you can get great comfort from these conferences.  I have come to
the conclusion that no matter what our problems may be, we can find an answer in the gospel
of Jesus Christ.  To those who may be discouraged or to those who may be worried, I would
plead with you that we try to understand the gospel and adopt its principles in our lives, and I believe we
will solve our problems and be able to put discouragement aside.
</p><p>
Some weeks ago it was my privilege to receive an invitation from the United
States Administration of Foreign Operations to fulfil an assignment in far-off Iran.  I am
grateful for that experience. On my way I stopped at Paris and Rome.  I will not say anything
about those European countries except to say that I was rather disturbed and concerned over
their attitude toward, and their criticism of, this great government and this great country.  I
was worried! I wondered if it were possible for us to purchase friends with money.
</p><p>
After I left Rome, I flew into the city of Damascus, and as I entered that ancient city, I could
not help thinking of Paul the Apostle&mdash;how he had persecuted the Saints, how he had been
stricken blind, and of his repentance.  Then I thought of how he was blessed and healed and
became a great Apostle of the Lord, Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
From Damascus I flew into the city of Tehran, the capital of Iran.  My heart went out to that
little nation, only 150 miles from Russia, living in constant fear of that great Soviet power.
There I met a people who love freedom and who would not sacrifice that freedom even if it
meant the loss of their own lives.  My sympathy  and interest, and my heart went out to that people.
If we believe anything in the brotherhood of men, then I do not see how we can deny helping
that people, not with money&mdash;they do not seek money or grants or a dole&mdash;but they like some assistance in
learning how they can better take care of themselves.
</p><p>
While I was in Iran, I heard great tributes paid to one of our own brethren, one of our own
fine men in the Church.  I have never heard finer tributes paid to a man than I heard paid to
Dr. Franklin S. Harris who went there, when he was president of the Utah State Agricultural
College, to render that country assistance.   From the Prime Minister to the Minister of
Agriculture and the Minister of Education and government officials, how they praised the
work and the inspiration and the guidance of that great teacher and that great scientist.  He
brought great credit to this nation, to this state and to this Church.  He is a great and fine man.
</p><p>
After I finished my assignment in Iran, I flew to the country of Lebanon. Then I arranged for
a trip down into a country where I have always wanted to go, down into the country of
Jerusalem.  Before I left here, President McKay said to me, "You will get out of Jerusalem
about what you look for and about what you take in." As we flew over that beautiful blue Sea
of Galilee, I could not help thinking of the miracles that had been performed there&mdash;the
feeding of the five thousand, the healing of the sick, the blessing of the blind that they could
see and the crippled that they could walk.  I could not help thinking of that beautiful song we
sing, "O Galilee! sweet Galilee! Where Jesus loved so much to be."
</p><p>
I think I was never so impressed as I was when viewing that country from the sky, realizing
that those rugged mountains were the wilderness we have read and heard so much about.  Jesus
loved his life in Galilee, and the people loved him.  Yes, he went about doing good in
Galilee. Then we followed the River Jordan on its way to the Dead Sea. We landed in the
Arab section of Jerusalem.  Now there are two sections of that city, the Jewish section and the
Arab section. There is great hatred there.  I feel sorry for the city of  Jerusalem.  You cannot
cross over from one side to the other, so we landed on the side where we desired to go.
</p><p>
Soon after our arrival we were assigned a very high type Arab Christian guide; he spoke
English well.  The first place he took us was the approximate location&mdash;I do not know whether
he was entirely accurate or not&mdash;but the approximate place, said he, where Christ was arrested
and his mockery trial was held.  He was never convicted.  Then the guide described the
judge, Pontius Pilate, the trial, the charges, the attitude of Pontius Pilate and the mob.  Jesus
the Savior was never condemned. He was never guilty, but Pontius Pilate did not have the
courage to release him, because in the face of that trial, mobs were calling, "Crucify Jesus"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/21#21">Luke 23:21</a>).
</p><p>
As he led us over those narrow cobblestone streets, up toward the Hill of Calvary, I thought
of the song that Sister Jessie Evans Smith sings so beautifully, "I Walked Today Where Jesus
Walked." As we came near the Hill of Calvary, the guide said, "About here
was where the cross was so heavy that Jesus could not carry it any longer.  He fell to the
ground because of his great suffering, his abuse, and his torture when he was stripped to the
waist, whipped with a heavy whip until his flesh lay open. Here he fell, and he was forced to
arise and continue." As Jesus was suffering such agony, his mother Mary, seeing him, broke
through the crowd to embrace him, but she was not permitted to do so.
</p><p>
As the daughters of Jerusalem were weeping, Jesus told them, ". . . weep not for me, but
weep for ourselves, and for your children"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/28#28">Luke 23:28</a>).
That remark was not a rebuke, but
was a warning which was prompted by his great love for mankind.  He knew of the later
destruction of Jerusalem.  A terrible disaster awaited a city steeped in iniquity.
</p><p>
Then as we reached the Hill of Calvary and the guide described the crucifixion, I was
severely touched to think that that suffering which we have heard here expressed by President
Clark and others today was for us that we might live again.  He had told his disciples that he
would be crucified in Jerusalem, but they did not realize the intenseness of the suffering he
was willing and anxious&mdash;and would have to&mdash;endure to accomplish his mission.  But what
a lesson he had taught us prior to that when he went into the Garden of Gethsemane, and as
we walked into the Garden of Gethsemane, I bowed my head in thankfulness to the Savior.
</p><p>
Before his crucifixion, he, too, sought strength from his Father that he could meet that test,
and how he met it! Others who had been tortured would scream and condemn and curse, but
he had taught the spirit of love all his life, and now he was faced with that test, and how he
measured up to it in the face of all that suffering we probably cannot understand.  Then from
his lips burst forth those great words, "Father, forgive them; for they know not what they do"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/34#34">Luke 23:34</a>),
and I thought then and there if Jesus the Christ, the Savior of the world, could
say and feel that way after all the torture, agony, and suffering which he had received, surely
he taught us the great lesson of love and forgiveness, and I pledged that I would never hold
hatred or bitterness or jealousy or anything like that in my heart toward anyone again.  What
a lesson Jesus had taught the world!
</p><p>
Before his crucifixion, as President Clark just stated, he told his disciples that he would come
forth on the third day (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/21#21">Matt. 16:21</a>),
and that word soon spread among the people, and a strong guard was
then placed over the tomb to see that his not stolen by his friends. No, his body was not
stolen. An angel from heaven came down and rolled the stone away
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/2#2">Matt. 28:2</a>),
and Jesus came forth
from the tomb on the third day as he had said he would, and even then, those close to him
could not believe.  You remember the story of Thomas.  He had to see and feel before he
could understand that the Savior had risen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/25#25">John 20:25</a>).
Here was the mission of Jesus, death and resurrection.
</p><p>
Then as the guide took us back into the Garden of Gethsemane&mdash;that is the place where
Jesus loved to go and pray&mdash;the guide said of all places which brought comfort to the Savior,
it was the Garden of Gethsemane.  Here he sought strength and wanted God's help in facing
such an ordeal.  Yes, he enjoyed having his disciples go with him. Some of them could not
understand and did not quite recognize his purposes, but he did not go there to ask the Lord
to save his life or to spare his life.  He was not afraid to die. That was part of his mission,
and he so regarded it.  No, he prayed to his Father to give him sustaining patience and power
of decision to meet that test as he would be called upon to meet it.
</p><p>
No wonder he was calm; no wonder he was lovable and kind.  Even in the face of that torture
and suffering.  God had prepared him to meet this crisis.
</p><p>
Then the guide took us upon the Mount of Olives; some would say that the Sermon on the
Mount was given there, but others would not agree; regardless, that great preachment,
probably the greatest preachment of all time, the Sermon on the Mount, should be our guide
today, in business, in education, in religion, in all of our phases of life.  Oh, it will do us
good to read the Sermon on the Mount, and it will make us better people if we will practice
its teachings.
</p><p>
Then, as the guide said, "From this spot Jesus ascended to heaven, and that is the last that we
have any record of the Savior of the world, the Redeemer of mankind," I felt more grateful
than ever in my life that I could carry that story a little farther. I said to the guide, "No, this
was not the end of Jesus the Christ, the Redeemer of the world, the Savior of mankind," and I
know the guide was sincere when he said, "No, we have no other record of anything on Jesus
since he ascended from this place to be with his Father."
</p><p>
Then I told him as best I could in the little time I had that he did reappear again with God the
Father to the boy Prophet, Joseph Smith, in another wooded area.  He was interested, but I
am sure he could not accept this on that first interview, but I only hope and pray that this
intelligent guide will read and study so that he can carry that story on to the time when the
gospel was restored again.  When I went back to my room, I locked my door and knelt down
and thanked God more humbly, I think, than I have ever done before in my life for the
teachings, the mission, the resurrection, of the Lord Jesus and the restored gospel of Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
Some would say he was a great teacher.  Some of the world like to leave it at that.  Oh, no,
he was more than just a great teacher.  He was the Son of God.  He was the Redeemer of the
world, and he did appear just as surely to the Prophet Joseph in the Sacred Grove as he
appeared to his disciples in Jerusalem.
</p><p>
May God bless us that we may appreciate these blessings that have come to us, I humbly pray
in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
