<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Blind Obedience or Obedience of Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 50-55</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brothers and sisters and friends, I approach this opportunity with fear and
trembling, humility, and fasting and prayer.
</p><p>
It was my privilege in the month of August to attend the great pageant at Palmyra, and I sat
entranced with some forty thousand others at the Hill Cumorah, looking up at that dark hill as
the night came on. I heard the voices of those who took the parts of many prophets, Nephi,
Jacob, Alma, Amulek, Ammon, and finally the prophet, Samuel the Lamanite, all prophesying
as to the coming of the Savior of the world to them here on this continent.
</p><p>
It was inspirational as the program progressed to its conclusion, to see the beautiful picture as
a Personage came above the hill. Because of the blackness under him, it appeared as though
he stood in mid-air, with long white robes flowing in the breeze that blew from the top of the
hill.  I was inspired, and that inspiration has remained with me ever since.  There was being
portrayed the story of the coming of the Savior to this land when these
thousands of people gathered at the temple, and were looking intently up toward heaven. 
They heard the voice, neither loud nor harsh, but a penetrating one, and it pierced their very
souls (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/3-6#3">3 Ne. 11:3-6</a>).
The third time they could understand, and they heard the voice say: 
</p><p>
Behold my Beloved Son in whom I am well pleased, in whom I have glorified my name&mdash;
hear ye him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/7#7">3 Ne. 11:7</a>).
</p><p>
Then came the voice of him who had appeared to these Nephite people saying: . . . I am
Jesus Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/10#10">3 Ne. 11:10</a>).
His message then and before and since always to his people has been: 
</p><p>
. . . <i>to obey is better than sacrifice and to hearken than the fat of rams</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/22#22">1 Sam. 15:22</a>).
</p><p>
So said the Prophet Samuel to the disobedient King Saul who lost his kingdom because of
rebellion.  The prophet warned Saul that he should discomfit his enemies but that he should
not retain the spoils of war.  But the bleating of the sheep and the lowing of the oxen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/14#14">1 Sam. 15:14</a>)
revealed that Saul and his people had disobeyed the simple command of the Lord.  Samuel
chastised: 
</p><p>
Hath the lord as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the
lord?
</p><p>
. . . rebellion is as the sin of witchcraft, and stubbornness is as iniquity and idolatry
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/22-23#22">1 Sam. 15:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
Saul asked forgiveness, but the prophet replied: 
</p><p>
. . . thou hast rejected the word of the lord, and the lord hath rejected thee from being king
over Israel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/26#26">1 Sam. 15:26</a>).
</p><p>
In his arrogant and haughty state he took things in his own hands wholly disregarding the
commandments of the Lord.
</p><p>
Samuel scolded: 
</p><p>
. . . When thou wast little in thine own sight, wast thou not made the head of the tribes of
Israel, and the lord anointed thee king over Israel?
</p><p>
Wherefore then didst thou not obey the voice of the lord, but didst fly upon the spoil, and
didst evil in the sight of the Lord?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/17,19#17">1 Sam. 15:17,19</a>).
</p><p>
Saul rationalized.  It was easy for him to obey as to the disposition of the kings, for what use
were conquered kings? But why not keep the fat sheep and cattle?  Was not his royal
judgment superior to that of lowly Samuel?  Who was Samuel that his words should be
obeyed implicitly, and who would know anyway?
</p><p>
How like Saul are many in Israel today. 
One will live some of the Lord's revelation on health
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/1-21#1">D&amp;C 89:1-21</a>) except that he must have his occasional
cup of coffee; she will not use tobacco nor liquor for which she has no yearning anyway but
must have the comforting cup of tea.
</p><p>
He will serve in a Church position, for here is activity which he likes and honor which he
craves, or contribute to a chapel where his donation will be known, but rationalization is easy
as to tithepaying which he finds so difficult.  He cannot afford it&mdash;sickness or death has laid
a heavy hand&mdash;he is not sure it is always distributed as he would have it done, and who knows
anyway of his failure?
</p><p>
Another will attend some meetings but Saul-like rationalize as to the rest of the day.  Why
should he not see a ball game, a show, do his necessary yard work, or carry on business as
usual?
</p><p>
Another would religiously attend his outward Church duties but resist any suggestions as to
family frictions in his home life or family prayers when the family is so hard to assemble?
</p><p>
Saul was like that.  He could do the expedient things but could find alibis as to the things
which countered his own desires.
</p><p>
To obey! To hearken! What a difficult requirement!  Often we hear: "Nobody can tell me
what clothes to wear, what I shall eat or drink.  No one can outline my Sabbaths, appropriate
my earnings, nor in any way limit my personal freedoms!  I do as I please!  I give no <i>blind obedience!</i>"
</p><p>
Blind obedience!  How little they understand!  The Lord said through Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
Whatever God requires is right, no matter what it is, although we may not see the reason
thereof until long after the events transpire
(<i>Scrapbook of Mormon Literature</i>, vol. 2, p. 173).
</p><p>
When men obey commands of a creator, it is not blind obedience.  How different is the
cowering of a subject to his totalitarian monarch and the dignified, willing obedience one
gives to his God.  The dictator is ambitious, selfish, and has ulterior motives.  God's every
command is righteous, every directive purposeful, and all for the good of the governed.  The
first may be blind obedience, but the latter is certainly faith obedience.
</p><p>
The Patriarch Abraham, sorely tried, obeyed faithfully when commanded by the Lord to offer
his son Isaac upon the altar (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/22/1-2#1">Gen. 22:1-2</a>).
Blind obedience?  No.  He knew that God would require nothing
of him which was not for his ultimate good.  How that good could be accomplished he did
not understand.  He knew that he had been promised that through the seed of the miracle son
Isaac should all the multitude of nations be blessed, and God having promised, it would be
fulfilled. Undoubtedly questions arose in his mind as to how these things could be if Isaac
were liquidated, but he knew that the Lord was just and would provide a way.  Had not the
Lord fulfilled the promise made wherein this very son was to be conceived when Abraham
was old and Sarah far past the normal bearing period
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/17/15-22#15">Gen. 17:15-22</a>)?  In Hebrews, we read: 
</p><p>
Therefore sprang there even of one, and him as good as dead, so many as the stars of the sky
in multitude and as the sand which is by the sea shore innumerable
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/12#12">Heb. 11:12</a>).
</p><p>
Abraham was now called upon to sacrifice this beloved son who as yet had no posterity.  But
with faith supreme, Abraham: 
</p><p>
. . . offered up Isaac . . . accounting that God was able to raise him up, even from the dead
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/17,19#17">Heb. 11:17,19</a>).
</p><p>
Knowing that God would make no capricious nor unnecessary demands, that the lad could be
raised even from death if necessary, Abraham obeyed. A ram was provided.
</p><p>
Perhaps the criminal in the penitentiary obeys blindly, for here is compulsion. Most of his
decisions are made for him.  Somewhat comparable are dictator's subjects whose work,
recreation, religion, and other activity are controlled and regimented.  Here <i>is blind</i> obedience.
</p><p>
It was not blind faith when the patriarch Noah built an ark some forty-two centuries ago or
when the prophet Nephi built a boat about twenty-five centuries ago.  Each was commanded
by the Lord to construct a seaworthy vessel.  An unprecedented total flood was to envelop the
earth in the one case and the greatest ocean to be crossed by the other.  No experience of
either builder could give guidance in these new adventures&mdash;no previous flood or ocean
crossing had ever come in the life of either&mdash;there was nothing on which to base construction
except directions from the Lord.  Here was no blind obedience.  Each knew the goodness of
God and that he had purpose in his strange commands.  And so each with eyes wide open,
with absolute freedom of choice, built by faith. Noah's family was saved from physical
drowning and spiritual decadence, and Nephi's people were saved likewise.
</p><p>
No swords nor bayonets, no famine nor pestilence drove the Lehites from the lush shores of
Bountiful, but seeing obedience led them across uncharted oceans.  The Lord had promised: 
</p><p>
. . .  inasmuch as ye shall keep my commandments, ye shall prosper, and shall be led to . . .
a land which is choice above all other lands
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>).
</p><p>
And with compliance born of faith and confidence, the vessel was finished, loaded, and
launched.
</p><p>
There was no compulsion in Noah's movements&mdash;no blind obedience.  It was not raining
when this man of God made the craft which was to save his family.  After its completion, a
full week of dry weather preceded the storm. Here was obedience born in testimony of the
power, sureness, justice And Noah's trust was justified, and a race was perpetuated.
</p><p>
When men speak of <i>all faith</i> and <i>all obedience</i> as blind, are they not covering their own
weaknesses?  Are they not seeking an alibi to justify their own failure to
hearken?
</p><p>
A man obeys strictly the income tax law and pays fully and before due date his property taxes
but justifies himself in disregarding the law of the Sabbath or the payment of tithes on time,
if at all.  In the one case he may suffer only deprivation of freedom or resources or lose his
home or personal property, but in the other he opens doors to the loss of a soul. The spiritual
as truly brings penalties as the temporal, the principal difference is the swiftness of
punishment, the Lord being so long-suffering.
</p><p>
One would hardly call the first blind obedience, yet he sometimes regards the spiritual
commands as such.
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when the student pays his tuition, reads his text assignments, attends
classes, and thus qualifies for his eventual degrees?  Perhaps he himself might set different
and easier standards for graduation, but he obeys every requirement of the catalog whether or
not he understands its total implication.
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when one regards the sign "High Voltage&mdash;Keep Away" or is it the
obedience of faith in the judgment of experts who know the hazard?
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when the air traveler fastens his seat belt as that sign flashes or is it
confidence in the experience and wisdom of those who know more of hazards and dangers?
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when the little child gleefully jumps from the table into the strong arms
of its smiling father, or is this implicit trust in loving parent who feels sure of his catch who
loves the child better than life itself?
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when an afflicted one takes vile-tasting medicine prescribed by his
physician or yields his own precious body to the scalpel of the surgeon or is this the
obedience of faith in one in whom confidence may safely be imposed?
</p><p>
Is it blind obedience when the pilot guides his ship between the buoys which mark the reefs
and thus keeps his vessel in deep water or is it confidence in the integrity of those who have
set up protective devices?
</p><p>
Is it then blind obedience when we, with our limited vision, elementary knowledge, selfish
desires, ulterior motives, and carnal urges, accept and follow the guidance and obey the
commands of our loving Father who begot us, created a world for us, loves us, and has
planned a constructive program for us, wholly without ulterior motive, whose greatest joy and
glory is to "bring to pass the immortality and eternal life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>) of all his children?
</p><p>
Blind obedience it might be when no agency exists, when there is regimentation, but in all of
the commands of the Lord given through his servants, there is total agency free of
compulsion. Some remonstrate that agency is lacking where penalties are imposed and
condemnations threatened&mdash;to be damned for rejecting the gospel seems harsh to some and to
take away free agency.  This is not true, for the decision is ours&mdash;we may accept or reject,
comply or ignore.
</p><p>
In all of our life activities it is the same&mdash;we may attend college or stay away from the
campus; we may apply ourselves to our studies or waste our time; we may fulfil all
requirements or ignore them. The decision is ours; the agency is free.
</p><p>
We may take the medicine or secretly pour it down the drain; we may yield our bodies to the
surgeon's knife or refuse his service; we may follow paths or get lost in the jungle; but we
cannot avoid the penalties of disobedience to law.
</p><p>
We may speed one hundred miles an hour, park our car against fireplugs, drive on the wrong
side of the road, resist arrest, rob a bank, but we will pay penalties sooner or later, even the
utmost farthing.  No soul is clever enough to evade penalties indefinitely or to counter this
extensive and basic law of retribution.  Without free agency men would be lifeless, limp
weaklings, and worthless to themselves and to the world.
</p><p>
Our heavenly Father, knowing all things, gave us this fundamental law of free agency.  He
could force our obedience, compel our goodness, regiment our acts, but that would make of
us spineless creatures without will or purpose, or destiny.
</p><p>
Our Lord wept bitterly (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/28#28">Moses 7:28</a>)
when he saw his creatures breaking his commandments in the
pre-deluge days, but he refrained from force.  They must have their agency: 
</p><p>
The Lord said unto Enoch: Behold these thy brethren; they are the workmanship of mine own
hands, and I gave unto them their knowledge, in the day I created them; and in the Garden of
Eden, gave I unto man his agency
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/32#32">Moses 7:32</a>).
</p><p>
They were permitted to ignore the warnings of the prophets till their cup of iniquity was full,
ran over, and flooded the world and drowned its inhabitants.
</p><p>
Rewards for faithfulness and penalties for disobedience are certain.  God is longsuffering,
patient, and kind, where as men and natural laws are often swift and cruel.
</p><p>
Our righteous and wise parents, Adam and Eve, were exemplary in the matter of obedience
born of childlike faith: 
</p><p>
. . . And Adam was obedient unto the commandments of the Lord.
</p><p>
And after many days an angel of the Lord appeared unto Adam, saying: Why dost thou offer
sacrifices unto the Lord? And Adam said unto him: I know not save the Lord commanded
me.
</p><p>
And then the angel spake, saying: This thing is a similitude of the sacrifice of the Only
Begotten of the Father, which is full of grace and truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/5-7#5">Moses 5:5-7</a>).
</p><p>
Blind obedience?  Assuredly not. They had known Jehovah, heard his voice, walked with him
in the Garden of Eden, and knew of his goodness, justice, and understanding.  And so for
"many days" they killed the blemishless lambs and offered them without knowing why, but in
total confidence that there was righteous purpose in the law and that the reason would unfold
later after compliance.
</p><p>
Obedience was paramount in the healing of the lepers.  They cried: 
</p><p>
Jesus, Master, have mercy on us.
And when he saw them, he said unto them,
Go shew yourselves unto the priests.
And it came to pass, that, as they went, they were cleansed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/13-14#13">Luke 17:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
It is certain that the priests made no contribution to the healing.  The ten had probably lived
all their lives in the jurisdiction of the priests who are not own ever to have healed lepers.
The miracle happened when, but not until, they obeyed in every detail.  No blind obedience
here.  These lepers knew Christ would not fail them.  They had faith not only in his power
but also in his goodness and integrity.
</p><p>
So also did the man born blind move toward wholeness of sight, yet he obeyed the voice of
authority.  Questioned by the skeptical Pharisees as to his unparalleled sight recovery, he
stoutly maintained,
</p><p>
He put clay upon mine eyes, and I washed, and do see.
</p><p>
. . . He is a prophet.
</p><p>
. . . one thing I know, that, whereas I was blind, now I see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/15,17,25#15">John 9:15,17,25</a>).
</p><p>
A simple little formula it was.  A little spittle, a little clay, a simple anointing, a simple
command, and an act of faith obedience; and darkness was replaced with light.  "Lord, I
believe" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/38#38">John 9:38</a>),
he said as he worshiped in gratitude. Blind obedience, would you say?  It was a
blind man, but a seeing obedience. The Savior had: 
</p><p>
. . . spat on the ground, and made clay of the spittle, and he anointed the eyes of the blind
man with the clay.
</p><p>
And said unto him, Go, wash in the pool of Siloam . . . He went his way therefore, and
washed, and came seeing (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/6-7#6">John 9:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
How simple the process!  How gentle the command!  How faithful the obedience!  How
glorious the reward!
</p><p>
Strange&mdash;we provide pure, sterile tissue for spittle and forbid expectorating even on
sidewalks.
</p><p>
We bathe with soap, scrub with disinfectants, and scald dishes, pots, and pans with boiling
water to kill the germs from the filth of clay.
</p><p>
We use for culinary purposes and especially in hospitals and sickrooms only water purified by
chemical processes.
</p><p>
But here the Master disregarded all our rules of sanitation and prescribed spittle, germ-ridden
clay, and impure water from the contaminated pool of Siloam which bathed the sweaty bodies
of laborers and the sore bodies of the sick and diseased.
</p><p>
Is there healing in mere clay to make eyes see? Is there medicinal value in the spittle to cure
infirmities?  Are there curative properties in the waters of Siloam to open eyes of congenital
blind?  The answer is obvious.  The miracle was conceived in the womb of faith and born
and matured in the act of obedience.
</p><p>
Had the command involved oil instead of spittle, herbs instead of clay, and waters of a pure
bubbling spring instead of filthy Siloam, the result would have been the same.  But some
would have said that oil and herbs and pure water had healed the eyes, but even the untrained
must know that these could not cure one. Consequently, only one conclusion could be drawn:
The unparalleled miracle was positively the result of faith obedience.  But had the sightless
one disobeyed any of the phases of the command, he would indubitably have suffered till
death with continued blindness.
</p><p>
Though there is no compulsion, the spiritual laws of today must also be obeyed if blessings
are to be realized, for as the Lord has said: 
</p><p>
I, the lord, am bound when ye do what I say; but when ye do not what I say, ye have no
promise (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
And: 
</p><p>
Mine arm is kindled against the rebellious
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/1#1">D&amp;C 56:1</a>).
</p><p>
And: 
</p><p>
And the rebellious shall be pierced with much sorrow; for their iniquities shall be spoken
upon the housetops, and their secret acts shall be revealed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/3#3">D&amp;C 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
And: 
</p><p>
Behold, I, the lord, utter my voice, and it shall be obeyed.
</p><p>
Wherefore, verily I say, let the wicked take heed, and let the rebellious fear and tremble; and
let the unbelieving hold their lips, for the day of wrath shall come upon them as a whirlwind,
and all flesh shall know that I am God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/5-6#5">D&amp;C 63:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
And my people must needs be chastened until they learn obedience, if it must needs be, by
the things which they suffer (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/6#6">D&amp;C 105:6</a>).
</p><p>
And when we obtain any blessing from God, it is by obedience to that law upon which it is
predicated (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/21#21">D&amp;C 130:21</a>).
</p><p>
And so we render intelligent, constructive obedience when we voluntarily, humbly, and
happily obey the commands of our Lord: 
</p><p>
1. Be ye clean who bear the vessels of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/52/11#11">Isa. 52:11</a>).
</p><p>
2. Thou shalt go to the house of prayer upon my holy day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/9#9">D&amp;C 59:9</a>).
</p><p>
3. Bring all the tithes into the storehouse
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/10#10">Mal. 3:10</a>).
</p><p>
4. Honor the Sabbath Day to keep it holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>).
</p><p>
5. Ye are the temple of God&mdash;defile it not with liquor, tobacco, tea, and coffee
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
6. Repent or suffer (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/4#4">D&amp;C 19:4</a>).
</p><p>
7. Bow down upon thy knees before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/10-11#10">Philip. 2:10-11</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/104#104">D&amp;C 88:104</a>).
</p><p>
8. Judge not that ye be not judged
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/1#1">Matt. 7:1</a>).
</p><p>
9. Except a man be born of the water and of the spirit he cannot enter into the kingdom of
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
10. A man must enter into the new and everlasting covenant to be exalted
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/2#2">D&amp;C 131:2</a>).
</p><p>
11. Woe unto those who come not unto this priesthood
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/42#42">D&amp;C 84:42</a>).
</p><p>
May God bless all of us, members of his Church, and all others, in the great world which he
has created and peopled to live and obey his commandments, I pray in the name of Jesus
Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
