<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Keep Faith with Your Family</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Nathan Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 133-137</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is with a feeling of humility and a prayer in my heart
that I accept this assignment to speak to you at this time.
I have chosen as my subject, "Keep Faith With Your Family."
</p><p>
As a school teacher, scoutmaster and bishop, and as I have
traveled from place to place and talked to different people,
I find that many are worried about their children, their
youth, are criticizing the youth of other families, blaming
all kinds of conditions for their problems, and are
wondering just what can be done or should be done to
improve these conditions. On the other hand, I find many of
our youth who are frustrated, who would really like to
choose and do the right and be accepted, but who wonder just
what it is all about, and what is important, and why so
little emphasis is placed on the Gospel of Jesus Christ. It is true
that nothing brings greater joy and satisfaction and comfort
to a parent than to see a child really develop into an
honorable, respected, righteous citizen. The youth who
develops into that kind of citizen is loved, respected and
admired by all. How can this be accomplished?
</p><p>
I have always been impressed with the admonition of Joshua
to his people when he said, "Choose you this day whom ye
will serve, but as for me and my house we will serve the
Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
Then we have the promise made by the
Saviour when he said, "Seek ye first the Kingdom of God and
his righteousness and all these things shall be added unto
you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
The other day I reread an article by J. Edgar Hoover
entitled "Should I Force My Child" which reads:
</p><p>
"Shall I make my child go to Sunday School and Church? Yes!
And with no further discussion about the matter. Startled?
Why? How do you answer Junior when he comes to breakfast on
Monday morning and announces to you that he is not going to
school any more? You know! Junior goes.
</p><p>
"How do you answer when junior comes in very much besmudged
and says, 'I'm not going to take a bath.' Junior bathes,
doesn't he?
</p><p>
"Why all this timidity, then, in the realm of his spiritual
guidance and growth? Going to let him wait and decide what
Church he'll go to when he's old enough? Quit your kidding!
You didn't wait until you were old enough. You don't wait
until he is old enough to decide whether he wants to go to
school or not to start his education. You don't wait until
he is old enough to decide whether he wants to be clean or
dirty do you? Do you wait until he is old enough to decide
if he wants to take his medicine when he is sick, do you?
</p><p>
"What shall we say when junior announces he doesn't like to
go to Sunday School and Church? That's an easy one to
answer. Just be consistent. Tell him, 'Junior, in our house
we all go to Church and to Sunday School, and that includes
you.' Your firmness and example will furnish a bridge over
which youthful rebellion may travel into rich and satisfying
experience in personal religious living. The parents of
America can strike a telling blow against the forces that
contribute to our juvenile delinquency, if our mothers and
fathers will take their children to Sunday School and Church
regularly."
</p><p>
In my opinion, Mr. Hoover answers the question in the last
paragraph wherein he says, "<i>Tell him, in our house we all go</i>
<i>to Sunday School and Church</i>." And then again in the last
sentence, "The parents of America can strike a telling blow
against the forces that contribute to our juvenile
delinquency if our mothers and fathers will <i>take</i> their
children to Sunday School
and Church <i>regularly</i>." There would be no need of forcing our
children to attend Sunday School and Church if we as parents
attend regularly, because that would just be a part of their
lives and children like to be with their parents. It is
difficult for children to understand why they should go to
Sunday School or Church when their parents feel it is more
important or more interesting for them to go fishing or
golfing. Our Lord and Master has said, "Thou shalt go to the
house of prayer and offer up thy sacraments upon my holy
day" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/9#9">D&amp;C 59:9</a>).
</p><p>
I thought a friend of mine showed a good example of this
when his son came to him and said, "Dad, I don't want to go
to Church today." His dad replied, "My son, you have your
free agency, you better hurry and get your coat or we'll be
late." You notice, <i>we'll</i> be late&mdash;not <i>you'll</i> be late.
</p><p>
How fortunate is the boy or girl who lives in a home where
the parents believe in God, the Eternal Father, and his
Son, Jesus Christ, and know within their hearts that the
Savior came and brought the Gospel of peace and good will
and gave the plan of life and salvation whereby all mankind
may be saved; and who set about to so order their lives as
to keep his commandments. We have been admonished, "Counsel
with the Lord in all thy doings and he will direct thee for
good" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/37#37">Alma 37:37</a>).
To join with the family in prayer every day, and to
talk to our Father in Heaven, to seek his blessing, and
express our gratitude, will have a profound influence not
only on the life of the child, but on the lives of the
family as a whole. A feeling of love, unity, and of being in
tune will be experienced by all. Encourage them to go
privately to the Lord in thanksgiving and supplication.
</p><p>
What strength and courage it gives a young man as he goes
out into the world when he comes from a home where there is
no question in his mind that his parents feel and always act
as Paul when he says, "I am not ashamed of the Gospel of
Christ for it is the power of God unto salvation to
everyone that believeth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
There are too many people in the world
today who are like the chief rulers as recorded in these
words, "Nevertheless, among the chief rulers also many
believed on him, but because of the Pharisees they did not
confess him lest they should be put out of the synagogue
<i>for they loved the praise of men more than they loved the</i>
<i>praise of God</i>" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/42-43#42">John 12:42-43</a>).
</p><p>
Great doubt is raised in the mind of a child whose parents
profess one thing and do another; where they profess to be
Christians and believe in God, but do nothing about it. As
Elijah came unto all the people and said, "How long halt ye
between two opinions. If the Lord be God, follow him; but if
Baal, then follow him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/18/21#21">1 Kgs. 18:21</a>).
The Lord has said,
"If you love me you will keep my commandments"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/15#15">John 14:15</a>).
</p><p>
Every day is full of choices. Our choices today determine
our future and the future of our children. Such little
questions as: Will I be honest? Will I keep my pledge or
commitment or promise? Will I prove dependable? Will I go
to Church or will I go fishing? We cannot be <i>nearly</i>
dependable, we cannot be <i>reasonably</i> honest, we cannot be
diligent <i>sometimes</i>, we cannot <i>nearly</i> catch a plane and be
where or what we wish to be.
</p><p>
Let us always remember and determine that the things which
matter most must not he at the mercy of things which matter
least. First, we must choose what we want out of life, and
then if we wish to achieve it, we must abide by the rules
whether it be to gain a university degree, to become an
American citizen or to reach the Celestial Kingdom.
</p><p>
As one of our poets wrote so well:
</p><p>
"Know this, that every soul is free<br />
To choose his life and what he'll be;<br />
For this eternal truth is given<br />
That God will force no man to heaven.
</p><p>
"He'll call, persuade, direct aright<br />
And bless with wisdom, love, and light;<br />
In nameless ways be good and kind<br />
But never force the human mind.
</p><p>
"Freedom and reason make us men<br />
Take this away and what are we then<br />
Mere animals, and just as well<br />
The beasts may think of heaven or hell."
</p><p>
Let each of us check and determine whether our innermost
thoughts are holding us on the animal plane or whether they
tend to lift us into the mental, moral, and spiritual realm.
We become slaves as we break the laws of nature, as we
become addicted to bad habits, or, we remain free as we
choose the right. The Lord has said, "Thou shalt have no
other Gods before me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3#3">Ex. 20:3</a>).
Some have as their Gods
money, political power, fame, false ideologies, idols, and
even unknown Gods. Two or three years ago, while traveling
with Lord Rowallan, Chief Scout of the British Commonwealth,
I was thrilled with his comment as he led in the Scout
promise. As he said, "On my honor I promise to do my duty to
God," he stopped and said to the Scouters who were present,
"As I make this promise I think of a God who can hear and
answer prayers, who is interested in what we are doing, and
who will guide us and bless us according to our needs and
our faith." And then he said, "If any of you do not believe
in such a God, you can serve better some place else." "For
God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son
that whosoever believeth in him shall not perish but have
everlasting life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
Selfishness, murder, hatred, and conquest are rampant
throughout the so-called civilized world today. If each and
every man could say and do as Joshua admonished, "as for me
and my house we will serve the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>),
and keep his
commandments, we would have peace in the world. Yes, if the
people in the world would today "love" God and keep his
commandments, we would have peace overnight. As someone has
so aptly said, "Righteousness in the individual makes for
harmony in the home, harmony in the home makes for order in
the nation, and order in the nation results in peace in the
world."
</p><p>
It would be most helpful if parents would sit down with the
whole family and discuss what they want out of life, what
they want to accomplish, and how they can help one another
in doing
it. After this decision is made, it will be necessary for
all of them to answer the questions: Is it worth the effort,
or am I prepared to do my part? Can I discipline myself, or
have I the will power? Then, each and every one must make up
his mind, accept his obligations, and go forward with
determination realizing that it will bring the greatest joy
and satisfaction and success in life. When one begins to
rationalize, or try to explain why he does this or that
which he knows is wrong, he is actually bringing his ideals
down to his actions. Where, on the other hand, if one
repents and sets about to improve himself and keep the
commandments, he is raising his standards or his actions up
to his ideals.
</p><p>
What a marvelous thing it would be if we and our children
could learn early in life the joy and satisfaction that
comes from living good, clean, honest, and upright lives all
the time and that there is no joy or satisfaction in sin. It
is so important that we all try to enjoy living and that our
young people have a good time. However, this good time
should be such that in the future, whether it be a month, a
year, or ten years from now they can always look back on
this as "a good time," realizing that a man of honor does
not change his code of honor with passing circumstances.
The greatest joy and happiness one can get out of living is
to know that he has done and is doing right, and to be in
the service of the Lord.
</p><p>
We have the old commandment, "Honor thy father and thy
mother that thy days may be long upon the land which the
Lord thy God giveth thee"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/12#12">Ex. 20:12</a>).
Children should be taught and
trained to honor their father and their mother. Their
parents gave them life and cared for them when they could
not care for themselves. Every child of every age should
love and honor his parents. It is much easier, however, for
children to do this if the parents live worthy of the honor
of their children and are always an example to them, where
they wield a real influence for good in their lives.
</p><p>
There is no responsibility greater than that of teaching and
training a child
to be an honest, honorable, and righteous citizen; and
there is no stronger, more effective way of doing it than
for the parent to be what he would like his son to be. What
a great day it will be for the world and the Church when
every father and son will do and be what he would like the
other to think he is. In other words, father should always
try to put himself in the position where he would be glad
to have his son say, "I do nothing save that which I have
seen my father do." It is the manner of our living and not
the words we use to explain it that makes up the moral fiber
of the children God has given to us. We should never be
surprised if our children grow up to be like us. Therefore, we
must take the time to be the kind of people we would like
our children to be. It is so important that the rush of the
world and the pressure of business do not make fathers and
sons strangers. When we say with a shrug of the shoulder,
"Boys will be boys," maybe we should remember that boys
will soon be men and set about to help make them men. There
is a point at which sympathy becomes coddling and kindness
becomes indulgence and they who are too busy, too lazy, or
too softhearted to give children the example and discipline
they need are being unfair to everyone and particularly to
the children. It is most difficult for parents to discipline
their children and expect them to do those things which are
not important enough for parents to do themselves.
</p><p>
We are all the children of God and he wants us to succeed
and stands ready to answer a call. Let us never forget that
the Lord has said, "This is my work and my glory to bring to
pass the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
Satan has pledged himself to destroy man. We should always
thank our Heavenly Father that Satan cannot force us to do
wrong; and also, realize and be thankful for the fact that
the Lord will not force us to do right. We have our free
agency and we can choose to do right or wrong, to be a
failure or success, to serve the Lord or Baal.
</p><p>
Let us not forget that a young man
or a young woman of character, industry, faith,
intelligence and loyalty will always be at a premium and
will always be able to find a place or make one when he can
truthfully say, "As for me and my house we will serve the
Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>)
and truly seek first the Kingdom of God and his
righteousness, knowing that all things for his good will be
added unto him.
</p>
</div>
</div>
