<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">God's Abundant Blessings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Clifford E. Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Clifford E. Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1950, pp. 137-141</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
As we go out to the stakes of Zion and the wards of the Church, we feel the warmth and the
friendliness of the good people who always makes us so welcome, and as we come into your
assemblies, there is a friendliness, and we are made to feel at home. But as we meet here in
the Tabernacle with all of you together, it becomes a real challenge, and I sincerely trust that
while I stand here I may have an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
COST OF MISSIONARY SERVICE
</p><p>
The other day at the opening session of conference some rather imposing figures were
presented. Among them was the cost of our missionary service, a cost amounting to over four
million dollars, which comes from the general funds of the Church. To that should be added
the contributions of the families that make possible the boys and girls called to the mission
field.
</p><p>
We have nearly five thousand missionaries. The average cost for each
missionary a month is about fifty-three dollars. That alone would amount to three million
dollars a year. Then add to that the equipment, clothing, and other personal accessories, and
railroad fares for the missionaries to reach their fields of labor, which costs are largely borne
by the families of the Church, and it would probably amount to another million dollars; so
that we have something like four million dollars cost in the sending of our five thousand
missionaries to the nations of the earth. I doubt that that figure would cover the entire
expense. Then, as has been suggested here the money that these boys could earn were they to
remain at home represents another imposing figure.
</p><p>
Brother Sonne remarked the other day that the Bishop of York, who spoke from this pulpit a
year or more ago, on his return to England had been quite complimentary to the Church.
Among other things he had said that the Mormon Church must be a very wealthy institution
to maintain such an impressive missionary service.
</p><p>
The funds for that service come from all the people, rich and poor alike, and if the truth were
known, it would be found that most of these funds come from the very humble of the
Church&mdash;those of very limited means. So this does represent a great contribution on the part of
Church members, and it brings home to us what it costs to be a Latter-day Saint.
</p><p>
SACRIFICES OF CONVERTS
</p><p>
But there is another phase to it that transcends all the material costs. I have reference to those
who have made great sacrifices in coming into the Church. Brother Widtsoe touched on it
briefly this morning when he mentioned the immigrants who come here many learning a new
language, making new adjustments, the conditions altogether different from those they left in
the Old Country. Many of them have had to sacrifice their own kindred and loved ones, being
told in some instances that they had to choose between this new religion and their own
families, and their new-found religion has been their choice. This has been a common
experience in this Church from the beginning.
</p><p>
CONVERSION OF GRANDMOTHER
</p><p>
I remember my worthy grandmother, a Quaker, who was converted in Pennsylvania through
the coming of some of the missionaries in the days of the Prophet Joseph. My mother at one
time had a great decision to make, one that was to try her to the very depths. Grandmother
said to her in her typical Quaker style, "Thee will find that it is not always easy to live the
truth, but thee will also find that there is joy and peace that comes in thus living." This
grandmother and her people, including her mother and seven daughters, had had the restored
gospel presented to them by the missionaries, and they accepted it. They found the witness;
they believed. The father in that home was to say to them (a witness of the
truth had not come to him), "You can either choose this so-called religion or me." The
witness had come to them, and with that witness there always comes a responsibility. The
Savior said: 
</p><p>
And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto
all nations; and then shall the end come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
When that witness comes into the human heart, it brings, I repeat, a responsibility&mdash;a
responsibility that we cannot escape. And this good Quaker grandmother felt that she could
not escape it.
</p><p>
She did not believe the Book of Mormon when it was first presented to her. She read it and
read it again and she could not get away from it. Finally the witness came, and that's when
she made her decision. She had no other choice, and finally she said to her husband, "If that's
it, then it must be." So she, with her seven daughters and some of their families, started for
Nauvoo.
</p><p>
There was nothing inviting when they arrived in Nauvoo. Nauvoo had been built up and was
now a lovely city, but persecution was rampant. The economic conditions of the people were
not good; apostasy prevailed; the Prophet was being undermined on every hand; and into this
influence came this good family. I wonder sometimes what some of us would do under
similar circumstances; and yet they never wavered; they never failed.
</p><p>
President Grant's mother had to face the same problem. She was told that it was either her
new-found religion or her inheritance and her family. She chose her religion because she, too,
had received the witness.
</p><p>
I have always been thrilled in reading the story of Brother Widtsoe's mother. She may be no
different from hundreds of Scandinavian mothers who have come here. They had to make
decisions. They had to decide whether it was their relatives, their friends, or this unpopular
religion. So I repeat, my brethren and sisters, the foundation of this Church has been laid at a
great cost.
</p><p>
BLESSINGS RECEIVED
</p><p>
The cost we pay today is minor&mdash;comparable to the great blessings received, it amounts to
nothing. The Lord has blessed us abundantly, has given us of his substance that we might use
it to build up the Church and kingdom, so that we need have no anxiety about any of these
costs. I repeat, they are minor.
</p><p>
But the greatest cost of all is that cost we pay which gives strength and character to our
people, a cost that has built a foundation against which the gates of hell cannot prevail.
</p><p>
Now today what does it all mean to us? What did it mean to these good people? I could name
many more who made great sacrifices, and we have them today. We have our modern
pioneers out in the world who are giving up their all because of the witness
they have in their souls. And that will always be. But what does it do? I repeat again what my
worthy grandmother said to my mother, that it brings peace and joy to the human heart.
</p><p>
JESUS THE CHRIST
</p><p>
That is why Easter means so much to the Latter-day Saints. It isn't the symbolism, the
pageantry, that we are conscious of today. It is the fundamental truth that Jesus is the Christ,
that he lives, and what he appeared in this day to the Prophet Joseph.
</p><p>
When I say "in this day," have you ever stopped to think how close that is? There are men
sitting on this stand whose fathers knew the man who communed with Jehovah. The man to
whom God the Father, and Jesus Christ, the Son, appeared and bore witness again of the
reality of the life of Jesus Christ, that the resurrection is true, the literal resurrection as
President Clark explained to us this morning in his impressive address. That is how close it is.
</p><p>
STATEMENT OF LOUIS PASTEUR
</p><p>
A consciousness of this truth brings peace to your soul and mine. I read recently a statement
by one of the French scientists, Louis Pasteur, who lived about eighty years ago, at a time
when skepticism prevailed throughout France. He was trying to prove before the French
Academy that the theory of spontaneous generation was not true. When he was chided by his
associates for only accepting that which he could prove, he said: 
</p><p>
This is not to be taken to mean that, in my beliefs and in the conduct of my life, I
only take account of acquired science: if I would, I could not do so, for I should then
have to strip myself of a part of myself. There are two men in each one of us: the
scientist, he who starts with a clear field and desires to rise to the knowledge of Nature
through observation, experimentation, and reasoning, and the man of sentiment, the
man of belief, the man who mourns his dead children (he had just lost a son in the
Franco-Prussian War), and who cannot, alas, prove that he will see them again, but
who believes that he will and lives in that hope, the man who will not die like a
vibrio, but who feels that the force that is within him cannot die. The two domains are
distinct, and woe to him who tries to let them trespass on each other in the so
imperfect state of human knowledge.
</p><p>
He was deeply religious. He had a spiritual concept. Most men of science have that deep
concept and a deep humility in their search for truth. He said: 
</p><p>
I see everywhere the inevitable expression of the Infinite in the world; through it, the
supernatural is at the bottom of every heart. The idea of God is a form of the idea of
the Infinite.
</p><p>
In other words, the spiritual is just as real as is the side of a test tube. The spiritual is just as
real as the physical. That was the fundamental doctrine of the Prophet Joseph.
</p><p>
And so today, Easter means something to you and me. It is worth while&mdash;this great cost. It
was worth while to our forebears, my brethren and sisters, and it is worth
while to us. I join with you and with my associates in expressing the gratitude of my heart for
the peace that has come to my soul and comes every day, in the confidence and the
knowledge that I have of the divinity of this great work.
</p><p>
God help us to be true to it, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
