<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Principle with a Promise</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Boyd K. Packer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Boyd K. Packer, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 106-109</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
In 1833 a revelation was given by the Lord to the Prophet Joseph Smith known as the Word
of Wisdom, given as a principle with a promise
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/3#3">D&amp;C 89:3</a>). This principle has not been neglected by the
leaders of the Church nor abandoned by them. It has been reaffirmed vigorously, as one theme
of this conference, for we have learned that however much a generation of people learn a
truth, it must be rediscovered by each succeeding generation.
</p><p>
It is to the young people of our generation that I speak. Some may regard as trivial the
assignment to speak to young people. I consider it otherwise and sense the meaning of an
appeal made by the late President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., in speaking to the teachers of the
Church. "May he," President Clark said, "give you entrance to the hearts of those you teach
and then make you know that as you enter there you stand in holy places."
</p><p>
Some young people, not members of the Church, may not be acquainted with the revelation
known as the Word of Wisdom. It is simply this, a law of temperance. In it we are counseled
by the Lord to refrain from: the use of alcoholic beverages&mdash;any of them, tobacco in any
form, and from hot drinks&mdash;understood by the Church to mean those with habit-forming
potential, specifically coffee and tea.
</p><p>
Members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints are expected to live this
principle.
</p><p>
The Lord has directed that observance of this principle is a condition of membership for one
seeking baptism into his Church. For the member of the Church, compliance with this law is a
prerequisite for the bestowal of the priesthood, for a call to missionary service, for temple
endowments or temple marriage.
</p><p>
You who are young members of the Church full well know that preliminary to such a call
you will be interviewed, and the question will be put to you directly, "Do you keep the Word
of Wisdom?" If you must confess that you do not, and if there is reasonable doubt that you
can honor a commitment to live the principle, your opportunity may be withheld from you.
</p><p>
You may have difficulty, my young friends, understanding why the Lord should require his
servants to hold so stedfastly to this rule, particularly when the use of alcohol, tobacco, and
hot drinks is practised so commonly in the world, and when we seem to run the risk of
driving many fine young people from activity in the Church. Some say we are too persistent
in stressing this principle&mdash;that indeed it has been over-stressed.
</p><p>
A principle with a promise such as this could hardly be over-stressed. It may well have been
stressed in a negative way, emphasizing only the "Don't."
</p><p>
A father, censuring his little son for some mischief, demanded an explanation from the boy.
"Why," he said with exasperation, "did you <i>do</i> such a thing?" The little lad was thoughtful for
a moment, then, "If I'd had a 'why,' Daddy, I wouldn't have done it."
</p><p>
It isn't always easy to give you a "why" for everything. But we owe it to you of the coming
generation to do more than just say, "Don't!" There are several "whys" for the Word of
Wisdom.
</p><p>
The first "why" concerns the effect upon your body. The case against tobacco as the killer in
lung cancer, and the indictment for accident, death, and moral mischief returned against alcohol
are so well substantiated that hardly anyone would wish to act as attorney for the defense
when these two malefactors are brought to trial.
</p><p>
The Word of Wisdom offers protection to your body. Part of the promise reads: "And all
saints who remember to keep and do these sayings, walking in obedience to the
commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones; 
</p><p>
"And shall run and not be weary, and shall walk and not faint"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18,20#18">D&amp;C 89:18,20</a>).
</p><p>
But the greatest loss in failing to observe the Word of Wisdom is not what may happen to
your lungs or to your brain or to your coordination. There is another "why" much more
important even than this.
</p><p>
No doubt you have noticed that some, who have achieved so-called success, have not kept the
Word of Wisdom; for instance, you may know a businessman who provides generously for
his family, and you know that he does not. Or you may know of a political figure who seems
to command the vote of the people in spite of known intemperance. You could hardly escape
the example of the movie queen&mdash;fair in face and figure&mdash;who makes no effort to hide her
dissipation. Or the athlete who has run up impressive records, yet openly endorses one brand
or another of these injurious agents.
</p><p>
He seems to run without fainting, you reason, and bewildered you may wonder "Why?" How
can this principle be so intensely important when so many people&mdash;some of them who have
been taught otherwise&mdash;abuse the principle and yet seem immune from any penalties? You,
my young friends, have a greater calling than that in the business world, or
as a political figure, or as an athlete. Your opportunity is not so much in what you will
contribute materially but in the influence that you may have spiritually.
</p><p>
To those who keep the Word of Wisdom the promise is given of ". . . wisdom and great
treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>). Our spiritual senses are
more delicately balanced than any of our physical senses. Like a fine radio receiver with a
sensitive tuning mechanism, they can easily be thrown off channel or even jammed by
corrosive influences introduced into our minds and bodies.
</p><p>
You, my young friends, can be sensitive to inspiration and spiritual guidance. To do this you
need the wisdom and treasures of knowledge&mdash;they constitute a spiritual confirmation, your
testimony of the truth. To have this witness fulfills the promise of the Lord. To be denied it is
the penalty.
</p><p>
There is yet another "why"&mdash;perhaps the most important of all. In the fourth verse of the
revelation we read: "Behold, verily, thus saith the Lord unto you: In consequence of evils and
designs which do and will exist in the hearts of conspiring men in the last days, I have named
you, and forewarn you, by giving unto you this word of wisdom by revelation&mdash;"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>).
This is a solemn&mdash;even frightening warning. But in the promise we are offered protection.
To understand, we turn in the Old Testament to the account of the ten plagues of Egypt.
</p><p>
Moses and Aaron were negotiating for the release of the Israelites from bondage. Nine
plagues were called forth upon Egypt, but none of them softened the Pharaoh's heart. The
Lord said then unto Moses: ". . . Yet will I bring one plague more upon Pharaoh, and upon
Egypt; afterwards he will let you go hence . . .
</p><p>
"For I will pass through the land of Egypt this night, and will smite all the firstborn in the
land of Egypt . . . and against all the gods of Egypt I will execute judgment: I am the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/11/1#1">Ex. 11:1</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/12/12#12">Ex. 12:12</a>).
</p><p>
Under a strange requirement, Israel was to escape this judgment. They were instructed to take
a lamb, a male of the first year, without blemish. It was to be slain and prepared as a feast.
They were instructed to take of the blood of the lamb and strike it upon the doorposts of the
houses, "And the blood shall be to you for a token upon the houses where ye are: and when I
see the blood, I will pass over you, and the plague shall not be upon you to destroy you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/12/13#13">Ex. 12:13</a>).
And it is recorded that the plague of death was visited upon Egypt from ". . .
the firstborn of Pharaoh that sat on his throne unto the firstborn of the captive that was in the
dungeon" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/12/29#29">Ex. 12:29</a>).
But Israel, because of the blood of the lamb, was spared, for the
plague of death passed over them and did not slay them.
</p><p>
Remarkable, is it not, that in addition to the other promises offered to those who observe the
Word of Wisdom, we find in the last verses of the revelation this additional promise: "And I,
the Lord, give unto them a promise, that the destroying angel shall pass by them, as the
children of Israel, and not slay them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/21#21">D&amp;C 89:21</a>).
</p><p>
Can you understand now, my young friends, why we stress so strongly this principle? It is
not, certainly not, to drive any of you from activity in the Church, but that your blessings
may be full. Some have said of you who are young that you are attracted to the low standard,
to the easy course, to the careless way. I say they who would sell youth so cheaply do not
know you.
</p><p>
Some of you who are young, and many perhaps who are older, have unwittingly been
tampering with, or have become addicted to, the use of alcohol, tobacco, or hot drinks.
Probably you feel estranged, even rejected, by the Lord and by his Church.
</p><p>
If you only knew how he yearns to open the flood gates of blessings. How he cries for you as
did David for Absalom, ". . . my son, my son!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_sam/18/33#33">2 Sam. 18:33</a>).
</p><p>
We make no apologies for holding to a standard that the Lord has set. In this ominous day
when spiritual strength is so desperately needed, we invite all youth to come where a
standard is kept, where the challenge is great, where much is required, where
the gospel is lived.
</p><p>
I bear witness that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, that he is the Lamb of God, crucified
that men might live. Though we suffer mortal death, through the blood of the Lamb we have
amnesty from spiritual death if we keep the commandments of the Lord, for it shall pass over
us and not slay us. This witness may come to you even in your youth. On the basis of this
personal testimony I commend to you the Word of Wisdom, which is not only a code of
health, but quite as much a key to spiritual wisdom&mdash;a principle with a promise&mdash;in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
