<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Family and the Restored Gospel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 56-59</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I stand before you this morning to make a few remarks with a hope
in my heart that the Lord will bless me and direct me in what I shall say and that I may be
aided by your faith and prayers. With those prayers coming to me in my behalf, I shall be
blessed, and you also.
</p><p>
ABSENCE NOTED
</p><p>
I think I would like to begin by noting the absence of a man who was with us for forty-seven
years as an Apostle, as President of the Quorum, and as President of the Church; a man who
had as great love for his fellow men as any man I have ever met; a man who left with us, or
left with me, two great sayings&mdash;"We are all children of our Heavenly Father," and "Keep out
of the devil's territory"&mdash;fundamental principles. I am referring, of course, to President
George Albert Smith.
</p><p>
In this Church there never is an interregnum. So soon as one President dies, the Twelve take
over; then, on their proposal, a President of the Church is chosen and sustained. And always,
the powers and authorities, the prerogatives of the one who has passed descend to the one
who comes. Those powers and authorities, responsibilities, have descended upon our present
President, David O. McKay, who is administering the affairs of the Church with wisdom, with
understanding, and inspired by the revelations of the Lord's mind and will.
</p><p>
THE FAMILY RELATIONSHIP
</p><p>
During this conference much has been said about a subject that has been running in my mind
for several months, and notwithstanding that it has been discussed so much, I should like to
add a few words during the time I shall address you, of my own feeling about it. I am
referring to the home and the family relationship.
</p><p>
The family, looked at broadly, is as nearly basic to the principles and plan of the restored
gospel as any principle of which I know. We have a Heavenly Father and Mother, the eternal
parents of the spirits of us who are here. And those spirits were created that they might come
to this earth and receive mortal tabernacles, so that in the due time of the Lord we shall lay
away the mortal tabernacle; then in due time we shall resume it and become the perfect soul,
the body and the spirit reunited.
</p><p>
The Lord has created, so he has told us, worlds without number
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33#33">Moses 1:33</a>), and I am sure for this same
purpose.
</p><p>
That, I repeat, that family relationship is fundamental, because without it we cannot reach out
to the destiny which our Heavenly Father has provided for us. When Adam came, he was
alone. And the Lord said, "It is not good that the man should be alone"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>). He said to Adam,
"Multiply, and replenish the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
Eve came, then the command was given that
a man "shall cleave unto his wife," leaving father and mother, "and they twain shall be one
flesh" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/5#5">Matt. 19:5</a>).
That was reiterated by the Savior replying to the query of the taunting
Pharisees. And out of that union came ourselves, our mortal tabernacles. In our day the Lord
has revealed another element, and that is the sealing of man and wife for time and for all
eternity (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/7#7">D&amp;C 132:7</a>),
and out of that union they twain beget blood and flesh.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY OF PARENTS
</p><p>
And I would like you to reflect upon the fact that our children came to us with spirits that did
not ask us to bring them, but with spirits, through some operation of which I am not aware,
that are assigned to us; and they come to us as our guests. We are responsible for the mortal
tabernacling of that spirit; and I should like each and every Latter-day Saint to get that fact
into his heart, that the child which is his, or hers, comes at the invitation, virtually, of them
who beget it, and then I would like you to reflect upon the responsibility which that brings
home to each and every man and woman who is a parent. Yours is the responsibility to see
that this tabernacled spirit loses no opportunity, through you, to prove his worthiness and
righteousness in living through his second estate
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/26#26">Abr. 3:26</a>).
</p><p>
Now the point that I wish particularly to emphasize is this&mdash;you parents cannot shift that
responsibility to anyone else. It is yours; you cannot divest yourselves of it.
</p><p>
You cannot give it to the state, and you ought not to give it to the state, for when the state
takes over the direction, instruction, and rearing of its youth, then passes out, as the whole
history of the world shows, the great principle of free agency, and not only that, but all the
sacred principles of chastity and morality, with a host of other virtues which belong to a free
society and are inherent in the governing principles of the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
You cannot entrust your children, in the sense of having them take over your responsibility, to
our schools. They cannot do your work. They may aid, and, sometimes, they may detract and
defeat. I have referred before to pernicious doctrines which are appearing in our schools, not
only political doctrines, which I would like you to note, but moral. The doctrine that the sex
urge is like the urge for food and drink, is born of Satan, and the man or woman who teaches
it, is Satan-inspired. Every effort you can make to prevent the spread of this doctrine, you
should make.
</p><p>
You cannot entrust your children to society. That will never do. Society is too tolerant of
wrong, too ignorant of matters of right living, too easy to betray and debauch.
</p><p>
And lastly, the Church cannot take over the responsibility which is yours to train your
children. The Church can aid, and should be the greatest aid; and we are derelict if we do not,
as Church members and as Church organizations, provide that assistance. But beyond the
Church Sunday Schools, the Mutual Improvement Associations, the Primary, the Relief
Society, and all the priesthood organizations and that is the family, and it is our responsibility
as parents to see to it that we fully perform our duties in this respect.
</p><p>
THE MOTHER'S PART
</p><p>
Now, brethren, at best we are somewhat clumsy at leading and directing our children. We are
away from home, of necessity, a great part of the time, our thoughts are along other lines, we
have to battle for our existence, for the livelihood of our families. Those of us who hold
Church positions are absent in the evenings, in addition to the days that we spend getting our
livelihood. I repeat, we are a little bit clumsy. And so to the sisters of the Church, the
mothers of the Church, they whom the Lord has designed and planned should be the
immediate instrumentality of perpetuating the race and of bringing spirits to this earth,
providing bodies for them, to them we must primarily look for the rearing of our children.
</p><p>
Sisters, when you think of what a child is, the mortal tabernacle of a spirit created by our
Heavenly Father, a mortal tabernacle which you, with all the sacrifice that it has entailed, with
all the danger that has been involved of going down into the valley of the shadow of death to
bring the child forth, when you think of that, do you not sense how urgent, how immediate,
how great is the responsibility which you have assumed? And, oh, how well the great bulk of
the sisters, the mothers of the Latter-day Saints are performing that, going on through their
whole lives sacrificing for their children, for their grandchildren, and sometimes for their
great-grandchildren! The Lord will bless you sisters, out of the abundance of his blessings, for
every sacrifice which you make for these children. And do keep close to them! And above all,
you, yourselves, lead lives that will be an example to these little ones that you have brought
into the world. After all, perhaps that is your greatest responsibility&mdash;to live righteously
before the Lord.
</p><p>
NOT BEYOND TEMPTATION
</p><p>
One thing other I would like to mention for a moment, and that is&mdash;I hope that none of you
will feel that your children are beyond the reach of temptation or transgression. The more
firmly you feel that, the greater the danger to your family. No one is safe from the wiles and
the persuasions of Satan. He reached Adam and Eve before mortality came. He reached into
the family of Adam, and Adam's family produced the first murderer. All down through
history he has reached into the families and to the persons of those who are in high and
responsible positions. Satan reached David, a man after the Lord's own heart
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/13/14#14">1 Sam. 13:14</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/13/22#22">Acts 13:22</a>), who committed
the great sin which he committed; the great Solomon, and stole his heart away. And in
modern times we have too many illustrations of where children of our leaders do not live just
as we would wish. So I beg of you do not assume, my dear brothers and sisters, that your
children are beyond the reach of Satan, but always go forward, always conduct your family
life, always be parents, fathers and mothers acting on the fact that Satan stands at the elbow
of your dear one to lead him astray. Never forget that, my brothers and sisters.
</p><p>
A LIGHT TO GUIDE
</p><p>
Now, in conclusion, I am reminded that Moses, herding his father-in-law's sheep at Mount
Horeb, saw one day a flaming bush, and the flame did not consume. Being curious, he started
to walk toward this flaming bush, and the voice of the Lord came out of the bush forbidding
him to come farther, for, said the Lord, ". . . the place whereon thou standest is holy ground"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/3/5#5">Ex. 3:5</a>).
So I think that in every Latter-day Saint home the Spirit of the Lord is a flaming,
non-consuming fire, there to light our way, to guide us, to protect us, and to help us do our
duty, and every inch of space in that home is holy ground. We should never forget it. Always
remember, and always live so that we shall not defile in any way the holiness of the home
which should be ours.
</p><p>
May God bless the Saints in their trials and in their tribulations may he help them to guide
and direct their children, may he give them the power to rear their children in righteousness,
so that this work of ours shall fulfil its destiny and roll forth and fill the earth; this blessing I
ask in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
