<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Keep Mothers in the Home</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 34-40</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brothers and sisters and friends of the air audience:
</p><p>
Today we remember with deep affection our beloved leader Henry D. Moyle, and from his
stirring sermon last April conference, we can still hear his earnest voice saying:
</p><p>
"I believe with all my heart and soul that the solution to our problems here upon this earth
today and tomorrow is to be found in the knowledge and appreciation of man's relationship to
God, his dependence upon God, and his obedience to God's laws.
</p><p>
"There is absolutely nothing of such great worth to man as to know God."
</p><p>
In my childhood, we had mottoes hanging on our walls sometimes embroidered, sometimes
painted, these for decoration and for inspiration. One I remember read: "What is home
without a mother." From my infancy, every time I entered the house, I
called, "Mama," over and over until I found her. Totally satisfied in the security her presence
afforded, I ran again to play. Just to know she was there! That was all.
</p><p>
When I was eleven, Mother passed away and from my aching heart came numerous times,
"Mama," as I entered the house, but there were only mocking echoes of emptiness. Later the
void was filled when our stepmother gave presence to the home and again through my youth,
I called and found my security in the welcome answer, "I am here, son."
</p><p>
It was the same red brick house through the days of security and the days of desolation, the
same shelf-filled pantry, the same wood stove and water tank, the same parlor with its rag
carpet and the same old clock ticking away the hours and days and years, but stability and
sureness and peace were there, for Mother was there, and security was there, and the house
breathed belongingness.
</p><p>
On Labor Day 2,000 young people converged on the little resort town of Seaside, Oregon,
repeating their last year's devastation, smashing windows, ripping street and shop signs down,
and requiring 100 police plus National Guardsmen to quell the rioting, and I wondered if
these 2,000 homes from which they came were normal ones with a mother at home who
could answer, "Yes, dear, I am here."
</p><p>
Again, the news reported 30,000 teenagers rioting on a California beach, filling beer cans and
bottles with sand and throwing them at police, boys stripping girls and sex indulgence
common and unabashed. And we wondered how many of these 30,000 fathers were furnishing
cars and money for their children to vacation at resorts; for beer and brutishness, and who
provided the gasoline, and who paid the fines?
</p><p>
And, we wondered how many of the 30,000 mothers were making homes and how many
making money. How can mothers justify their abandonment of home when they are needed so
much by their offspring? Rationalization must take over as they justify themselves in leaving
home and children.
</p><p>
Of course, there are <i>some</i> mothers who <i>must</i> work out to support their children, but let every
working mother honestly weigh the matter and be sure the Lord approves before she rushes
her babies off to the nursery, her children off to school, her husband off to work, and herself
off to her employment. Let her be certain that she is not rationalizing herself away from her
children merely to provide for them greater material things. Let her analyze well before she
permits her precious ones to come home to an empty house where their plaintive cry,
"Mother," finds no loving answer.
</p><p>
Do not these absentee mothers and millions of approving fathers know that basic attitudes
towards standards, morality, the Church, and God are developed in the family circle and are
quite well set while they are still small children?
</p><p>
It is said: "Give me a child until he is seven and then do with him what you will." These first
years are so vital.
</p><p>
The Lord said: "My sheep hear my voice" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/27#27">John 10:27</a>).
So do the little ones respond to
their own mothers. The maid, the neighbor, the sister, the grandmother may clothe and feed
and diaper the child, but no one can take the place of mother. This is impressed upon us by
the story of the six-year-old who got lost from his mother in a large supermarket and began to
call frantically, "Martha, Martha."
</p><p>
When the mother was found and they were reunited, she said: "Honey, you should not call me
Martha, I am 'mother' to you."
</p><p>
To which the little fellow rejoined: "Yes, I know, but the store was full of mothers, and I
wanted mine."
</p><p>
Children need security, special love, and to be wanted.
</p><p>
At a distant conference, my plane brought me to the city many hours early. The stake
president met me at the airport and took me to his home and, having important work to do,
excused himself and returned to his work. With the freedom of the house, I spread my papers
on the kitchen table and began my work. His wife was upstairs sewing. In mid-afternoon,
there came an abrupt entry from the front door, and a little fellow came running in, surprised
to see me, but we became friends. Then he ran through the rooms calling,
"Mother," and she answered from upstairs, "What is it, darling?" and his answer was, "Oh,
nothing." He went out to play.
</p><p>
A little later another voice came in the front door calling, "Mother, Mother." He put his
schoolbooks on the table and explored the house until the reassuring answer came from
upstairs again, "Here I am, darling," and the second one was satisfied and said, "OK" and
went to play. Another half hour and the door opened again and a young teenager moved in,
dropped her books and called, "Mother." And the answer from upstairs, "Yes, darling,"
seemed to satisfy, and the young girl became acquainted with me, then began practicing her
music lesson. None of the three had gone upstairs.
</p><p>
Still another voice later called, "Mother," as she unloaded her high school books. And, again
the sweet answer, "I am up here sewing, darling," seemed to reassure her. We became
acquainted, and she tripped up the stairs to tell her mother the happenings of the day in a
sweet mother-daughter relationship. Home! Mother! Security! Just to know Mother was home.
All was well.
</p><p>
A child is happy if he feels that he is wanted and enjoyed by his parents. He needs to feel
that his parents will be there, especially in a crisis.
</p><p>
This mother, too, could have had a job. Her children also could use more things her wages
could provide. She also could have rationalized that two salaries could give her children more
advantages, more outings, travel, and vacations, more clothes, gifts, and luxuries. But, this
mother knew well that a child needs a mother available more than all the things which money
can buy.
</p><p>
The <i>Parents</i> Magazine says: "The feeling of security is the core and foundation for good
mental health.
</p><p>
"Most of the married women over 35 in the labor force (says this authority) are working not
because their families really 'need the money,' but in order to maintain a higher standard of
living, get away from some housework, and lead, as they suppose, a more interesting and
richer life."
</p><p>
A prominent judge listed the causes of juvenile delinquency:
</p><p>
First, destructive toys and games such as guns and other symbols of violence. Second,
<i>working mothers</i>; and third, fathers who <i>work two shifts</i>, absenting themselves from the home
except to eat and sleep.
</p><p>
His long list of causes ended with this: Lack of religious training and discipline in the home
and schools, and lack or love in the home. My reference is Judge Jacob M. Braude of the
Circuit Court of Cook County (Chicago), Illinois.
</p><p>
These lacks were inherent in the parents, but it was the children who suffered.
</p><p>
Twenty-four million women in the United States work outside the home. This is one-third of
all in the total labor force, and 80% of them have living husbands.
</p><p>
In 1890, only 5.5% of the wives under 35 and living with husbands were working. By 1957,
it was 27.7% and now it is about a third of those wives between 18 and 24.
</p><p>
In the labor force are about 2.5 million women whose children are under six, and 5.4 million
with children under twelve years of age. Think of it: a possible twelve to fifteen million
children without a mother through crucial hours! Of these about 400,000 children under
twelve years of age must care for themselves entirely while their mothers work. One-third of
all mothers with children under eighteen are in paid employment. My statistics come from the
Children's Bureau of the US Department of Health Education and Welfare and other
dependable sources. This means that in this country, one child in 13 under 12 must look out
for himself. In the 10-11 year old group, the ratio is one in five <i>without care</i> while the mother
is at work.
</p><p>
It is shocking! Nearly one-third of all our young matrons, 18 to 24, are breaking the law of
God in not bearing children, or if they are having children, are they neglecting the helpless
little ones?
</p><p>
President McKay said, "The more woman becomes like man, the less he will
respect her. Civilization weakens as man's estimate of woman lessens."
</p><p>
We are told that the average age when women cease bearing children is about 26; yet in these
vital years, nearly one of every three is working outside her home. When such masses of
mothers are employed out, what may we expect from the offspring?
</p><p>
How nearly perfect can a mother be who rushes in the morning to get everybody off and
settled for the day, herself included, then returns weary after a hard day of employment to a
tired husband who has had a hard day and to children and youth with problems, and then to
her homemaking, cooking, cleaning, and then to a full social calendar. From such homes come
many conflicts, marital problems, and divorces, and delinquent children. Few people in
trouble ever ascribe their marital conflicts to these first causes, but blame each other for the
problems which were born and nurtured in strained environments. Certainly the harmonious
relationship of father and mother and the emotional climate prevailing between parents give
soundness and security to children.
</p><p>
President Belle S. Spafford speaking to her world of Relief Society mothers said:
</p><p>
"Children should be cherished with the strongest bonds of affection . . . No effort should be
too much, no sacrifice too great to protect them from evil and preserve them in righteousness.
. . The love and the sanctity of the home should be zealously safeguarded."
</p><p>
And she speaks of mothers' obligations&mdash;
</p><p>
". . . to make all else in life subservient to the well-being of our homes and families.
</p><p>
* * * * *
</p><p>
"Always in the Church, people have been admonished to marry in the House of the Lord, to
establish homes, and bear and rear children in righteousness."
</p><p>
Brigham Young says:
</p><p>
"It is the calling of the wife and mother . . . (to tie) her offspring to herself with a love that is
stronger death for an everlasting inheritance" (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, p. 198).
</p><p>
In this important city crime has increased three times faster than it did in the nation during
1962, said our local newspaper. And crime in the past five years increased four times faster
than population, four serious crimes per minute recorded on the crime clock.
</p><p>
One authority gave us: "The more the parents approve of each other, the more the child will
be welcome,&mdash;the most important single factor in the development of the child is the
emotional climate prevailing between his parents."
</p><p>
Are music and dancing lessons and camps and clothes justified when it may mean the
sacrifice of the home and mother on the altar of employment?
</p><p>
One girl said, "I really don't want to go to the girls' camp. I'd rather stay home with Mother,
but Mother is not home to stay with." Are we glamorizing out-of-home activities for our
children when they should be home helping or off to work themselves?
</p><p>
Absenteeism of mothers is often linked with idle youth&mdash;delinquent youth. When we read of
the recent Labor Day escapades by tens of thousands of high school and college young people
on their mass invasions of resort towns, we wonder again: Why are they permitted leisure till
they become sick with boredom? Home is drab so they resort to destructiveness and
immorality.
</p><p>
One judge said: "These mad vacations make their biggest appeal to youngsters who have too
little to do . . . We never have any trouble with kids who have real interests, real hobbies, a
radio ham, or a real athlete."
</p><p>
The idle generation! Hours each day and nothing to do. Saturdays and nothing to do. Three
long months of school vacation and nothing to do. No one has found a truer adage than: "The
idle brain is the devil's workshop."
</p><p>
Another judge states that, "Too many kids are loafing. Parents do not make children get jobs.
And, this helps them into trouble . . . there is an alarming lack of employment among our
young people . . . and idleness among those who come before me."
</p><p>
He is not talking about the pallid, spindly urchin, working twelve hours a
day in coal mines but of the hulking youth sitting around while his hardworking, doting
parents support him.
</p><p>
It is foolish to expect an energetic exuberant youth to live normally when he has his free time
largely to himself including three idle months of summer vacation. I quote him further,
</p><p>
"As I see young people of what I consider an employable age sitting around drive-ins or malt
shops, on park benches, or at the beaches, cruising around in cars or hanging around on the
street corners at all hours of the day and the night, I am amazed at their ability to stay out of
trouble as well as they do . . . idleness is a prime factor in most juvenile misbehavior."
</p><p>
He continues: "I find the average parent of the average employable but unemployed youngster
to be weak, overprotective, and overindulgent. Both he and his wife work to afford their child
the niceties of life which they now consider necessities. All the comforts of home plus a car
and a gasoline credit card."
</p><p>
This judge says these parents are a generation of well-intentioned ones rearing a generation of
sloths&mdash;Judge Robert Gardner of the Juvenile Court of Santa Ana, California.
</p><p>
A woman who had not been able to hold a job in spite of the fact that she was well-trained
and highly educated explained: "Oh, it's not odd at all. My parents never expected me to
work, and for that reason I never expected to either." She seemed to feel unabashed, and that
such was reason enough.
</p><p>
The judge proceeds: "This type of parent blindly accepts Junior's plaint: 'I can't find a job.'
</p><p>
"Can't find a job! Well, Junior. I have news for you ! These are boom times. A whole
generation of us grew up during the depression when there were no jobs, but we found jobs
anyway. Oh, they weren't good jobs, but they were jobs. There were always jobs&mdash;mean,
disagreeable, back-breaking jobs. And many of these jobs didn't pay very much and they were
hard and they were long hours and they were not desirable."
</p><p>
Do youth look for work in the cotton fields, in the beet fields, in the hay fields, the jobs that
are taken by itinerant workers brought from Mexico and other foreign lands?
</p><p>
Some judges give arrested youth a choice to get a job within thirty days or be locked up, and
seldom have had to lock up any. If the alternative is unpleasant enough, somehow Junior finds
employment.
</p><p>
To this philosophy, there are rejoinders from many sources which cry there are not enough
jobs to go around and that a job for a youngster means a job lost to the head of a family. And
the answer of the judge to this is, "Get women out of the factories and put them back into the
home where they belong . . . cooking, sewing, cleaning house and doing the traditional
woman's work. It would do both for them and their neglected youngsters a world of good."
</p><p>
If a few million of the working mothers who need not work were to go home to their
families, there might be employment for men now unemployed and part and full-time work
for youth who ought to help in family finances and who need occupation for their abundant
energy.
</p><p>
How many children today contribute toward the family living? Parents permit the youth to
idle away their time.
</p><p>
"Can't get a job," they say. Why, bless your souls, the world is crying for helpers. Have we
spoiled our children paving them for every effort? I heard a fifteen-year-old complaining
because he received only sixty cents an hour.
</p><p>
"What can we do?" they cry, "Where can we go?" Listen, youth, go home, roll up your
sleeves; pick cotton, hoe the corn, thin the beets. Yes, before and after school and Saturdays
and vacation days! It won't hurt you to store your ball and bat and hiking togs. Hang the
storm windows, paint the fence, wash the car, pick the fruit, mow the lawn, repair the screen,
plant a garden, cultivate flowers, trim the trees.
</p><p>
As we read of delinquency and crime, 2,000,000 serious crimes in this land in a year, and as
we note many are committed by girls and boys, we ask ourselves what is the cause and what
are the cures? In an adequate survey it was learned that a majority of youth
wish responsibility and will thrive on it.
</p><p>
"What can we do?" they ask again.
</p><p>
Do the shopping, work in the hospital, help the neighbors and the church custodian, wash
dishes, vacuum the floors, make the beds, get the meals, learn to sew.
</p><p>
Read good books, repair the furniture, make something needed in the home, clean the house,
press your clothes, rake the leaves, shovel the snow, peddle papers, do "baby sitting" free for
neighbor mothers who must work, become an apprentice.
</p><p>
J. Edgar Hoover of the FBI said, "Our youthful delinquency is a problem which strikes
practically every home in America. It is something to which every parent should give the
deepest consideration and the said responsibility for youth law infraction today lies more on
the doorstep of the adult than it does on the youth. In the majority of instances the story of
juvenile delinquency is the story of shattered homes where parents are neglectful, indifferent,
and fail to exercise the proper degree of discipline."
</p><p>
One parent wrote to youth: "Your parents do not owe you entertainment; your villages do not
owe you recreation facilities; the world does not owe you a living; you owe the world; you
owe it your time, your energy, your talents, yourself. In plain simple words, grow up, get out
of your dream world; develop your backbone, a backbone not a wishbone, and start acting
like a man or a lady."
</p><p>
Lawmakers in their over-eagerness to protect the child have legislated until the pendulum has
swung to the other extreme. But no law prohibits most work suggested above, and parents can
make work.
</p><p>
President David O. McKay said: "We are living in an age of gadgetry which threatens to
produce a future generation of softness. Flabbiness of character more than flabbiness of
muscle lies at the root of most of the problems facing our American youth."
</p><p>
Are these iconoclasts from normal homes with normal fathers and mothers? Or, are those
parents income producers who satisfy their every selfish desire for social life, comforts, golf,
parties, travel, drinking at the expense of their children?
</p><p>
Do the families of these window smashers kneel in prayer night and morning before these
depredations? Do they have family evenings, family picnics, vacations, and entertainment
together? Do these parents of such hoodlums exercise discipline in the home or are the
children emancipated from restraint, from duties, and from controls?
</p><p>
To slow down this ever-increasing rate of juvenile delinquency, there is a growing cry: "We
must have more detention homes and reformatories. We need more public money appropriated
for better facilities, more highly trained specialists, social workers, psychologists and
psychiatrists. We need larger jails, more police."
</p><p>
Certainly, it must be apparent that all this is
but an attempted control of a malady of epidemic proportions. Have the experts failed? Isn't it
time to come back to fundamentals? "We need more money," they say, but we have spent in
the last decade $78 billion on elementary and high schools for the children, yet delinquency
increases; $110 billion on cars; $127 billion for recreation, and still immorality, hoodlumism,
sadism, and vandalism grow apace, and to make it worse, $180 billion in cosmetics, tobacco,
and alcohol. No&mdash;money is not the answer! Surely we must realize that an ounce of
prevention is worth tons of cure.
</p><p>
The Lord has indicated long ago the perfect pattern of prevention. He has organized the
family in a home with unified pursuits. It takes no magician nor social authority to know
where the error lies, and that the cure is prevention. With the home a sweet religious one with
discipline and love and parental bliss and sweet parent-child relationships, there would be few,
if any, prodigals. Reformatories and correction institutions could close; social agencies could
lock their doors; jails would have few prisoners, and war be outlawed.
</p><p>
All this could come by the building of the homes of the people into spiritual
fortresses. If fathers would give themselves to their families and mothers come home from
employment and high society to conserve the smaller incomes and to be real mothers, then the
word <i>delinquency</i> would cease to terrify us.
</p><p>
May we organize our homes, discipline our children, and create nations of homes such as our
Heavenly Father has planned, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
