<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Gratitude</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Theodore M. Burton</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Theodore M. Burton, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 48-50</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Clark, if he were here, President Moyle, members of the General
Authorities, my dear brothers and sisters, this is a humbling experience.
</p><p>
When President McKay called me this morning into his office and asked me how I felt, I told
him I was frightened. I am frightened, but only to this extent&mdash;frightened that I might not
measure up to the responsibility that has been given me. President McKay told me that my
responsibility would be to principally bear witness to the divinity of Jesus Christ, and this I
can do from the bottom of my heart. I do know that Jesus is the Christ. I have covenanted
with him to be his son. I have covenanted to bear that name, and I pray that I might always
bear it honorably, that I might never do anything to bring dishonor to that glorious name.
</p><p>
I have wondered since the call was given me why I was called to this position. I do not stand
here alone. This call has come to a great many people, people who have influenced my life,
even before I was born. As the other brethren have said, I, too, come from a long line of
forebears who bore responsible positions in this Church. My great-grandfather Burton was a
member of the Church and came into the Church with his wife and one of his daughters. My
grandfather Burton was a young man only fifteen years of age, who had heard about the
Mormons in Canada, and he said that he would disown his parents if they joined the Church.
So he left them and went down into Ohio, and there the missionaries contacted him and
brought him into the Church. He then went back, and on his knees apologized to his father
and mother for his lack of insight, for his lack of understanding, and asked their forgiveness.
</p><p>
Grandfather Burton came here with some of the very earliest pioneers as a bugler to
Brigham Young, and he became one of Brigham Young's constant companions, along with
Brother Lot Smith and Brother Porter Rockwell. I have read Grandfather's journals; I know
how devoted he was to the Church. He was a member of the Presiding Bishopric for many,
many years.
</p><p>
He married my grandmother, whose maiden name was Garr. The Garrs, too, are wonderful
people of whom I am very proud. They were among the very first who came into the Church,
and Great-grandfather Fielding Garr was one of those seven men chosen to perform that very
special burial mission when the Prophet was assassinated, so I have been told. Grandmother
walked across the plains as a young girl eight years of age, and said how happy she was when
she got a thorn in her foot because that was the only time she was able to ride on the tailgate
of the wagon until they got the thorn out of her foot. So she was one of those early pioneers
who helped establish and build this country.
</p><p>
The Moyles have been in the Church for many years. My mother was Florence Moyle. I am
proud of the Moyles. Great-grandfather Moyle and Grandfather Moyle helped build the Salt
Lake Temple, and when you see the carving on the east side of the temple, "Holiness to the
Lord," Great-grandfather did that as a missionary called to work on the temple.
</p><p>
I am proud of the Cannels. They, too, came into the Church early. Great-grandfather came
here to Utah to protect his daughter from the Mormons, and when he got here he joined the
Church and was grateful that his daughter found such an outstanding man as Grandfather
James Moyle.
</p><p>
So I am proud of all of these people who have made it possible for me to be here. I am
grateful to my Sunday School teachers. I am grateful to my Primary teachers. In my day we
had Religion Class. I am grateful to those sisters who labored with us when we caused them
many hours of trouble and concern, I am sure, but they taught me the divinity of Jesus Christ,
for which I will always be grateful.
</p><p>
I came of goodly parents (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/1/1#1">1 Ne. 1:1</a>).
My father and mother are people of whom I am very proud. I am
grateful for the association I have had with my wife. She, too, comes from a long line of
people who have been in this Church for many generations. Her father, who is still living,
over ninety years of age, is still president of his high priests quorum. I am grateful to her, for
she has stood by me from the time we were married and has been loyal and faithful in every
respect.
</p><p>
I am proud of my son. I only have one son, and so I have to make up in quality what I lack
in quantity. I am proud of him. When my great-uncle Henry Moyle was patriarch of Alpine
Stake, he gave me my patriarchal blessing. He told me that we would have responsibilities to
take upon us. He told me that my children would have to bear part of that responsibility, too.
So I pray that my son will live close to the Lord and be able to accept his share of
responsibility when that comes.
</p><p>
I have just returned from the West German Mission, and I bring you all the love of those
wonderful people. I have spent just about one-fifth of my life among German-speaking
people. I love the Swiss people; I love the Austrian people; I love those German people with
whom I have been working. They are simply marvelous Saints, strong and stalwart, loyal and
true, and they are about to strengthen the Church in that mighty nation so that we will have
stakes of Zion there, too. I am hoping and praying that I shall also be present when that
glorious day comes, when we can establish on the continent of Europe, among
foreign-speaking peoples, stakes of Zion. I know that their hearts are filled with love of God
as yours are, and I bring you their greetings and their love, and I am proud to be associated
with a Church so international in its character that we can love people regardless of what
language they speak, what color they may be, or what nation they represent. We have
covenanted to be brothers and sisters, and this love that was spoken of
before is the love that exists in this Church today.
</p><p>
Without multiplying words, then, President McKay, I accept this calling with humility and
pray for your help and for your instruction.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, I will rise and do better than my best, because I know that I have
been called to this position by a Prophet of God who speaks in the name of Jesus Christ. I
bear you my testimony that he is a prophet of God. I bear you my testimony that Joseph
Smith is a prophet of God. I bear you my testimony that these men with whom I have
associated in the mission field, and these authorities who are sitting before you today, are
prophets, seers, and revelators, for I have seen prophecies fulfilled that they have made. I bear
testimony that Jesus is the Christ, that this is the Church of Jesus Christ, possessing all the
authority that is necessary to establish and maintain it upon the face of the earth today. I
know it will grow until all people can recognize and bow their knee and confess that Jesus is
the Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/10-11#10">Philip. 2:10-11</a>),
and that his kingdom is upon the earth. This testimony I give you in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
