<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Order and Diligence</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Franklin D. Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Franklin D. Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 75-78</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, I appear before you today with a humble heart and rejoice with
you in the spirit and proceedings of this great conference. I have recently returned from an
assignment to the stakes and missions in Samoa, Fiji, New Zealand, and Australia, and I bring
you the greetings and the love of the Saints and missionaries in these wonderful areas.
</p><p>
<b>The Prophet Leads Us</b>
</p><p>
I am grateful for the privilege I have had of meeting with the people of the South Pacific and
bearing to them, as I do to you today, my testimony that God lives and is mindful of all of
his children; that Jesus is the Christ, our Redeemer and Savior, the Only Begotten of the
Father in the flesh; that Joseph Smith was a prophet, commissioned to be the instrument
through which the fulness of the gospel and authority to act for God has been restored to the
earth in this dispensation. I always rejoice in bearing witness that we are led and guided by a
great prophet today, our beloved President David O. McKay; and may the Lord bless and
sustain him and strengthen him.
</p><p>
The work of the Lord is progressing in the South Pacific areas at an accelerated rate. I found
the same wonderful spirit and the same problems facing the people and the Church there as
elsewhere. We can be grateful, however, that throughout the ages God has
counseled his people and helped them to solve their problems.
</p><p>
<b>Order and Diligence</b>
</p><p>
It is interesting to note that as God has admonished his people through his  prophets, two
words have frequently appeared&mdash;<i>order</i> and <i>diligence</i>.
</p><p>
King Benjamin, in concluding a great address to his people, said, "And see that all these
things are done in wisdom and order; for it is not requisite that a man should run faster than
he has strength . . . it is expedient that he should be diligent, that thereby he might win the
prize; therefore, all things must be done in order" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/27#27">Mosiah 4:27</a>).
</p><p>
In this dispensation through the Prophet Joseph Smith the Lord has told us that his ". . . house
is a house of order . . . and not a house of confusion"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/8#8">D&amp;C 132:8</a>), and that every man
should learn his duty, and ". . . act in the office in which he is appointed, in all diligence"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>).
</p><p>
When called upon to accept an assignment in the Church which is an important part of
building the kingdom of God, many people wonder how they can give the time and attention
necessary to fulfil the assignment properly and also meet their family obligations.
</p><p>
Today there are so many things to do so many things crowding us. In this environment the
words <i>order</i> and <i>diligence</i> are key words to success and happiness regardless of the activity
we are engaged in.
</p><p>
In meeting with stake and mission leaders and other individuals, I frequently ask them what
their greatest needs are. Almost invariably they reply that among their greatest needs is "better
organization of their time and work"&mdash;or in effect more order and diligence.
</p><p>
And it is not infrequent that many ask the question, "How does one develop the traits of order
and diligence?" President McKay has given us some good advice in this connection. He said,
"Don't be too busy to meditate, and when the answer comes have the courage to execute it."
</p><p>
Order commences with meditation; and meditation includes thinking, analyzing, prayer,
fasting if needs be, and always planning. Meditating requires that time be regularly set aside
to consider the things that you think you have to do. Many times you find you have more to
do than you can do in the time available.
</p><p>
To develop an orderly pattern you must consider the things facing you, analyze their
importance, and list them in the order of their importance. After the things of prime
importance are selected, develop a plan to accomplish these more important matters.
</p><p>
Planning involves further analysis and developing of effective ways which will save time and
simplify the operation involved. Prayer is always desirable in planning the effective use of
time.
</p><p>
Many are prone to do the easy things and give those matters attention that seem to be the
most pressing regardless of whether they are the most important or not, but through
meditation, prayer, and planning you can select what might be called the first things to do and
work out effective ways to do them.
</p><p>
<b>First Things</b>
</p><p>
Undoubtedly the two most important first things for us to do in this life are to provide for our
families and to assist in building the kingdom of God. As we select first things and put them
in preferred positions and work out a plan to accomplish them, we are developing orderly
habits which will make it possible to serve in the Church and properly care for our families.
</p><p>
In building the kingdom of God the Lord has said that we should first learn our duty (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>).
He has counseled us to seek out of the best books words of wisdom and to
seek learning even by study and by faith (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>). Study should be rated among
those things of first importance. In organizing our time and work, time should be regularly
allotted for personal study as well as study with our families.
</p><p>
In any successful endeavor we learn our duty by having a clear understanding of our
responsibilities. Moses in speaking to his people charged them, "And thou shalt write upon the
stones all the words of this law very plainly" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/27/8#8">Deut. 27:8</a>).
In this manner Israel could learn
its duties. Instructions from leaders should be, as Moses said, plain, in order
that those affected might easily learn their duties. Plainness generally incorporates simplicity.
Simple things are readily understood. The gospel is simple and was taught by the Savior in a
simple and beautiful way. Simplification brings better understanding and provides more time
by eliminating unessentials.
</p><p>
We must provide time to be with our families and to do things together. In planning the use
of your time, I counsel you to spend as much time as possible regularly with your
families&mdash;say at least two nights each week. As parents our obligation to our families not only includes
seeing that they are fed, clothed, and educated, but that their spiritual needs are taken care of
as well. Certainly a good part of this must be done personally, such as having a weekly
family night, taking vacations together, and going to Sacrament meeting as a family.
</p><p>
<b>Diligence</b>
</p><p>
By selecting first things to do and working out a plan to do them first, we have taken an
important step toward accomplishing them. This is where diligence plays a big part. When the
Lord counseled us to perform our assignments in all diligence, he meant whether it was
convenient or not.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith said, "that a religion that does not require the sacrifice of all
earthly things never has power sufficient to produce the faith necessary unto life and
salvation" (Sixth Lecture on Faith).
</p><p>
To perform our assignments diligently, sacrifice of our time, talents, and means is frequently
required, but we know that sacrifice brings forth the blessings of heaven. We are entitled to
the blessings which are predicated upon obedience to this principle of sacrifice. The Lord has
said, "I, the Lord, am bound when ye do what I say; but when ye do not what I say, ye have
no promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
To be diligent in our work also means to be effective and not just busy. The Lord recognized
this difference between just being busy and being effective when in 1831 the elders were
traveling down the Missouri River in canoes. The Lord said at that time, ". . . it is not needful
for this whole company of mine elders to be moving swiftly upon the waters, whilst the
inhabitants on either side are perishing in unbelief"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/3#3">D&amp;C 61:3</a>). Just as it was unnecessary
for all of the elders to be moving swiftly upon the waters, so it is with us&mdash;it is not
necessary to do many unessential things that keep us busy but result in little or no real benefit
to anyone.
</p><p>
Being diligent also requires faith in the Lord Jesus Christ and in ourselves, and making up our
minds to be orderly and diligent is a good part of having faith in ourselves. Even though our
assignments seem difficult, as we develop our faith and persevere, we are able to achieve our
righteous objectives.
</p><p>
President Heber J. Grant frequently quoted from Emerson: "That which we persist in doing
becomes easy to do, not that the nature of the thing has changed but that our power to do has
increased."
</p><p>
To be diligent one must learn to persevere&mdash;yes, to endure to the end. But we might ask, to
the end of what? Can we endure to the end of a day with the same dedication and enthusiasm
we had at the beginning of the day even though faced with frustrations and problems. Each
year has 365 days, and each day has twenty-four hours, each requiring enduring to the end.
However, remember what King Benjamin said: ". . . it is not requisite that a man should run
faster than he has strength" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/27#27">Mosiah 4:27</a>).
He undoubtedly meant mental, physical, financial,
or spiritual strength, or all combined.
</p><p>
<b>Survey Large Fields; Cultivate Small</b>
</p><p>
In all phases of my personal experience I have found it wise to survey large fields but
cultivate small ones. In surveying large fields one in effect makes a master plan which he
later develops in orderly stages. This is a sound way to build and avoid many disappointments
which can result from overextending oneself. Surveying large fields and cultivating small ones
involves the principles of order and diligence and results in growth and development. These
are basic principles of eternal progression.
</p><p>
As we increase our personal effectiveness, we increase our effectiveness in our
church assignments, and one of the great needs today in building the
kingdom of God is effective leaders. The Savior has told us that "Not every one that saith
unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my
Father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/21#21">Matt. 7:21</a>).
Note the words ". . . doeth the will of my Father."
</p><p>
Finally, again I cite the words of King Benjamin, ". . . it is expedient that he should be
diligent, that thereby he might win the prize; therefore, all things must be done in order"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/27#27">Mosiah 4:27</a>).
</p><p>
I bear witness, and I know that the witness I bear is true, that through order and diligence we
can work in the Church and properly take care of our families and win the prize of eternal
life&mdash;of peace, happiness, and success through eternal progress.
</p><p>
May we this day resolve to apply these basic principles of order and diligence in our lives and
win the most worthwhile prize of all&mdash;eternal life&mdash;I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
