<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Need for Inspired Leadership</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 115-117</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have learned a little more realistically what is meant by the scripture, "he that endureth to
the end." Brother Hinckley says it is "the survival of the fittest." I do not know what that
means but I do know this, that what has been said at this conference has greatly increased my
faith and testimony and desire to serve the Lord.
</p><p>
In the few minutes that I shall occupy I should like to testify of the prophets and read to you
from section one of the Doctrine and Covenants these words: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
I had an experience some few months before I left the mission field, of a ministerial
association from one of the states in our mission, writing a letter and saying that they were
receiving ever-increasing inquiries about the Mormon Church and would we please supply
them with literature and information. We did this, and I had occasion also to visit the
headquarters of this association. And there in the presence of a number of these men, and
some of them were ministers, had the opportunity of explaining to them the premise under
which the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints had been organized.
</p><p>
I took occasion at that time to read to them from section twenty of the Doctrine and
Covenants, and I would like to read to you what I read to them, beginning with verse 7: 
</p><p>
"And gave unto him [meaning Joseph Smith] commandments which inspired him;<br />
"And gave him power from on high, by the means which were before prepared, to translate
the Book of Mormon;<br />
"Which contains a record of a fallen people, and the fulness of the gospel of Jesus Christ to
the Gentiles and to the Jews also;<br />
"Which was given by inspiration, and is confirmed to others by the ministering of angels, and
is declared unto the world by them&mdash;<br />
"Proving to the world that the holy scriptures are true, and that God does inspire men and call
them to his holy work in this age and generation, as well as in generations of old;<br />
"Thereby showing that he is the same God yesterday, today, and forever. Amen.<br />
"Therefore, having so great witnesses, by them shall the world be judged, even as many as
shall hereafter come to a knowledge of this work.<br />
"And those who receive it in faith, and work righteousness, shall receive a crown of eternal
life; <br />
"But those who harden their hearts in unbelief, and reject it, it shall turn to their own
condemnation&mdash;<br />
"For the Lord God has spoken it; and we, the elders of the church, have heard and bear
witness to the words of the glorious Majesty on high, to whom be glory forever and ever.
Amen" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/7-16#7">D&amp;C 20:7-16</a>).
</p><p>
This had a profound effect upon these men, and I was grateful to leave my witness with them
as to the premise for the organization of God's Church upon the earth in this day and time.
</p><p>
Some years ago there appeared an article in <i>Fortune</i> magazine, which had to do with the
failure, according to the editors and authors of this article, of the Christian churches of
America to supply the needed inspiration for the direction of the Christian churches in this
land. This article has very recently been referred to by one of our noted educators from the
West Coast, Dr. Robert Gordon Sproul, president of the University of California. I read from
this article, which stresses the need of divine direction in the Christian churches of America. I
quote: 
</p><p>
"We have the peculiar spectacle of a nation which, to a limited extent, practices Christianity
without actively believing in Christianity. We are asked to turn to the Church for our
enlightenment, but when we do this we find that the voice of the Church is not inspired. The
voice of the Church today is the echo of our own voices. And the result of this experience,
already manifest is disillusionment . . .
</p><p>
"The way out," continues Dr. Sproul, "is the sound of a voice, not our voice, but a voice
coming from somewhere not ourselves, in the existence of which we cannot disbelieve.
</p><p>
"It is the task of the pastors to hear this voice, cause us to hear it, and to tell us what it says.
If they cannot hear it, or if they fail to tell us what it says, we, as laymen, are wholly lost.
</p><p>
"Without it we are no more capable of saving the world, than we were capable of creating it
in the first place."
</p><p>
I think one of the great messages of this Church is to declare unto the world that God has
raised up a prophet and that there is a need for a prophet of God in this day and age. We go
to the ends of the earth to proclaim this unto the children of men and if they will but listen to
the direction and the inspiration of the prophets of God we could be led from our dilemma
and from the disillusionment that settles over the earth today.
</p><p>
I read recently of a statement of Winston Churchill which gives some evidence of the need of
inspired direction in the earth today, for said he "As the years go by, the process of
government&mdash;I suppose in every modern country and certainly in our own&mdash;grows ever more
complicated and burdensome.
</p><p>
"I have perhaps a longer experience than almost anyone, and I have never brooded over a
situation which demanded more patience, composure, courage and perseverance than that
which unfolds itself before us today."
</p><p>
Is there a need for a prophet of God? The answer is yes. Look at the evidences of this. The
world of politics and relationships between nations is not improving since that statement was
made, in fact they have grown worse. There is a worldwide lack of trust between peoples.
We stand each dawn, as it were, on the brink of open hostilities.
</p><p>
Atomic and hydrogen power, with their many implements of destruction serve only to add to
the menace of our way of living. The pressure conditions under which we live today are
taking a tremendous toll in heart and mental disturbances. The status of home life, spiraling
trends of drunkenness, surging infidelity in the home of husband and wife, with an over-all
laxity of morals among both young and old, increased personal and community delinquencies
all pointing to a growing disregard for the worth of the individual. One would have to be
blind not to recognize these disastrous trends and the need of divine direction
to save those who will hear, understand, and follow the truth. The ancient Prophet Amos
declared, that God would do nothing, save he reveal his mind and will to his servants the
prophets (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>).
The need of the mind and will of our Heavenly Father, through his
servant, a prophet, is greatly in evidence.
</p><p>
I want to leave my testimony, my brethren and sisters, that God does live and that he and his
Son, Jesus Christ, are at the helm, and that prophets have been raised up from the very
inception of this Church, commencing with Joseph Smith and others who have followed him,
and that we are blessed to have standing at the head of the Church today and directing us, a
prophet of God, and if the children of men would but listen to the voice of that prophet we
all could be led away from the difficulties that are oppressing us this very day. I bear this
record in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
