<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">America: Land of the Blessed</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 82-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I pray for the inspiration of the Lord as I address you for the next few moments. I have been
thrilled with the testimonies that have been borne in this conference. I love this work in which
we are engaged.
</p><p>
I am grateful, my brethren and sisters, for this land in which we live. I never return from
foreign shores but what I have a feeling of gratitude for the prophetic mission of America. I
love Zion, both as a place and as a condition.
</p><p>
THE FREEDOM TRAIN
</p><p>
During the last few weeks there has traveled from one end of the country to the other a
so-called Freedom Train, the purpose of which has been to direct our attention and focus our
interest upon our heritage and blessings as American citizens, and to call our attention to
those foundation principles upon which this great country has been established as a Christian
nation.
</p><p>
It has been an attempt to call to our attention sacred documents which mark the origin and
development of our liberties and to reawaken in us an appreciation of the American way of
life. We have had called to our notice important things that we must do if we are to continue
to enjoy and pass on to coming generations the priceless blessings which are ours. Embodied
in these sacred documents are eternal principles&mdash;God given&mdash;and of the utmost
importance to all of us.
</p><p>
Now, while the world is literally in a mess, is a good time to take stock. We are inclined so
much to take our blessings for granted. We are five generations&mdash;170 years&mdash;removed
from the founding of this great nation.
</p><p>
We are living in a critical period of the world's history. We note, on every side, the spread of
coercive systems, the increased power of dictators, and the influence of state control and its
power over the individual. Recently, we have witnessed nations which have succumbed to the
onslaught of these coercive systems. I am sure it has caused deep reflection upon the part of
all of us who enjoy the blessings of freedom in this blessed land of America.
</p><p>
MISSION OF AMERICA
</p><p>
I am grateful for the prophetic mission of this nation as it has been proclaimed by prophets,
ancient and modern. I have before me, this morning, some of those prophecies made by Book
of Mormon prophets which I should like to refer to briefly.
</p><p>
I have always been grateful that the Lord saw fit to hold this nation, as it were, in the hollow
of his hand in preparation for its great mission as the cradle of liberty and the cradle for the
Church and kingdom of God that was to be established, and now has been established, in this
the last dispensation.
</p><p>
The prophet of the Jaredite colony, Mahonri Moriancumer, commonly referred to as the
brother of Jared, spoke of this land as a choice land, a land choice above all other lands. He
indicated that those people who live here should worship the God of this land if they were to
enjoy the blessings of freedom and liberty and be free from bondage. Otherwise, if they
failed, they were to be swept off. And he proclaimed that this is the everlasting decree of
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/7-12#7">Ether 2:7-12</a>).
</p><p>
Sixteen hundred years later the Prophet Nephi was privileged to see a large part of the history
of the establishment of this great nation. He spoke in no uncertain terms regarding its mission.
He told that the Spirit of the Lord came down and wrought upon a man upon foreign shores,
and that he went forth and discovered this land. He also saw other gentiles follow to these
shores under the influence of that same Spirit. And he saw that the Spirit of the Lord was
here and that multitudes of people came to these shores and that God prospered them because
they humbled themselves before him; that he was with them and that his power was here, and
that during times of struggle and conflict&mdash;referring to the Revolutionary War&mdash;that the Lord
was with them and sustained them and bore them off victorious
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/12-19#12">1 Ne. 13:12-19</a>). He further saw that this land
was consecrated to those whom the Lord should bring and who would serve him and keep his
commandments; that it should be a land of liberty; that it should never be brought down into
captivity unless it be because of the iniquity of the people.
</p><p>
The Lord promised through Nephi that the power of God would be with the gentiles whom he
should bring to this land and that the wrath of God would be "upon all those that were
gathered against them to battle" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/18#18">1 Ne. 13:18</a>).
</p><p>
Later, after the colony, which came to be called Nephites, arrived on the western hemisphere,
their prophet-leader Lehi declared:
</p><p>
Wherefore, this land is consecrated unto him whom he shall bring. And if it so be that they
shall serve him according to the commandments which he hath given, it shall be a land of
liberty unto them; wherefore, they shall never be brought down into captivity; if so, it shall be
because of iniquity; for if iniquity shall abound cursed shall be the land for their sakes, but
unto the righteous it shall be blessed forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/1/7#7">2 Ne. 1:7</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Jacob, a brother of Nephi, twenty-five years later was privileged also to see into
the future regarding this land and to proclaim that God would fortify the land against other
nations; that he that fought against Zion would perish; that no king would ever be raised on
these shores; that God would forever here be a light unto the people who accepted and
listened to his words (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/11-14#11">2 Ne. 10:11-14</a>).
</p><p>
And so this great nation, my brothers and sisters, has come into being under the inspiration of
the Almighty to accomplish his purposes. Through modern revelation we have had made very
plain to us something of the mission of America and the establishment of our national
Constitution in this dispensation.
</p><p>
THE CONSTITUTION A GLORIOUS STANDARD
</p><p>
During the dark days of Missouri when the Saints were being persecuted and driven, and their
lives threatened, and their property taken from them, the Lord commanded the Saints, through
the Prophet Joseph, to continue to importune for redress. He said:
</p><p>
According to the laws and constitution of the people, which I have suffered to be established
.... for the rights and protection of all flesh, according to just and holy principles.
</p><p>
He proclaimed, at that time, that it is not right for men to be in bondage one to another. Then
he said:
</p><p>
And for this purpose have I established the Constitution of this land, by the hands of wise
men whom I raised up unto this very purpose, and redeemed the land by the shedding of
blood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/77,80#77">D&amp;C 101:77,80</a>).
</p><p>
Earlier, the Lord had said:
</p><p>
. . . verily I say unto you, my law shall be kept on this land .... Let no man break the laws of
the land (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/19,21#19">D&amp;C 58:19,21</a>).
</p><p>
He commanded the people to be subject to the powers that existed.
</p><p>
In the Kirtland Temple, in that glorious dedicatory prayer which, according to the Prophet,
was given by revelation, we find this significant verse:
</p><p>
Have mercy, O Lord, upon all the nations of the earth; have mercy upon the rulers of our
land; may those principles, which were so honorably and nobly defended, namely, the
Constitution of our land, by our fathers, be established forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/54#54">D&amp;C 109:54</a>).
</p><p>
And so, every true Latter-day Saint has a deep love and respect for the Constitution of this
land.
</p><p>
It is no wonder that the Prophet Joseph said&mdash;even though he knew he would suffer
martyrdom in this land&mdash;"The Constitution of the United States is a glorious standard; it is
founded in the wisdom of God. It is a heavenly banner."
</p><p>
Yet, according to his contemporaries, he foresaw the time when the destiny of the nation
would be in danger and would hang as by a thread. Thank God he did not see the thread
break. He also indicated the important part that this people should yet play in standing for the
principles embodied in these sacred documents&mdash;the Declaration of Independence and the
Constitution.
</p><p>
SPREAD OF COERCIVE SYSTEMS
</p><p>
We see abroad today on every hand, and to some degree in our own land, the spread of
coercive man-made systems, which are contrary to eternal principles and which strike at the
very foundation of all we hold dear as American citizens. These programs would take from us
our liberty and freedom, and those opportunities for achievement which the Lord has
promised for this nation in order that it might perpetuate those eternal principles so that a
haven might be established here where men from all lands might come and enjoy the glorious
blessings of freedom and liberty.
</p><p>
We see abroad in the world an increase in these coercive systems. We witness millions of
God's children in bondage, who have had their blessings of liberty and freedom taken from
them. Great numbers of liberty-loving people no longer have their free agency, no longer have
freedom of choice such as we enjoy here. They no longer have the privilege of living where
they wish, taking advantage of any educational or work opportunity, but on the contrary they
are under the power of these coercive systems and have lost completely their God-given free
agency.
</p><p>
The impelling force in the hearts of the founding fathers as also in the hearts of the pioneers
of these valleys was their love of truth and virtue and their belief in the overruling power of
Almighty God. They believed in the existence of eternal laws and principles in both the
physical and spiritual realms. These, they believed, never change but are eternal and are
embodied in the gospel of Jesus Christ. It was their conviction that there are certain
inalienable rights which are God-ordained and that no man, group of men, or nation has the
right to withhold these blessings from others of their fellow men. To them, governments
should be the servants and not the masters of the people. There was no place in their hearts
for the principles of communism, fascism, or any other coercive system which endangers the
enjoyment of freedom.
</p><p>
WARNING AGAINST COMMUNISM
</p><p>
One of the greatest conflicts ever known to man is rapidly spreading throughout the world.
Eternal principles of right and wrong are involved. Communism, to my mind, is not merely
an economic program. It is a total philosophy of life utterly atheistic and utterly opposed to
all we hold dear as a great Christian nation. There should be no place in the heart of any true
Latter-day Saint for the principles enunciated by the leaders of these coercive systems such as
communism, fascism, or any form of state control.
</p><p>
I am pleased to quote to you a part of a statement which was made by the First Presidency of
the Church in 1936, and reaffirmed later, regarding this problem of communism which has
been referred to. It reads as follows:
</p><p>
Communism being thus hostile to loyal American citizenship and incompatible with true
Church membership of necessity no loyal American citizen and no faithful Church member
can be a communist.
</p><p>
We call upon all Church members completely to eschew communism. The safety of our
divinely inspired Constitutional government and the welfare of our Church imperatively
demand that communism shall have no place in America.
</p><p>
A MESSAGE OF PEACE
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, our message to the world is, of course, first of all, a message of
peace, a message of love, a message of the restored gospel. At the same time we stand firmly
in support of the principles enunciated in the Constitution and the Declaration of
Independence, and every Latter-day Saint would defend to the last those eternal principles.
We should measure every coercive system, every program that might be offered, by the
standards of those principles set forth in these sacred documents. At the same time, as we face
the spread of communism and the spread of other coercive forces in the world, we must keep
our hearts free from hatred and remember ever that we should carry with us always a love for
the children of men. We should renounce war and declare peace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/16#16">D&amp;C 98:16</a>). The Lord has commanded us
so to do. Our message is a message of peace. We are followers of the Prince of Peace, and
we should rededicate our lives to the spread of truth and righteousness and the preservation of
the liberty and freedom, which have been vouchsafed to us as American citizens and as
Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
SECURITY BASED ON RIGHTEOUSNESS
</p><p>
This nation rests upon a solid spiritual foundation, established by the Lord of heaven, and I
hope and pray that the nation may go forward to accomplish its great mission. There is no
security except upon the basis of righteousness. The prophets, ancient and modern, have so
declared. And so may we value these spiritual principles and keep them close to our hearts
and preserve this land as a land of liberty and freedom, that this, his Church, which has been
established by the hand of the Lord, might go forward and accomplish its great mission.
</p><p>
I leave my testimony with you, my brothers and sisters, that God has again spoken from the
heavens, that he has raised up a prophet as he said in the first section of the D&amp;C, in
preparation for the calamites which will follow:
</p><p>
Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
Zion is intended to be a place of refuge, a defense
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/6#6">D&amp;C 115:6</a>) from the storm that is to come, from the
wrath which shall be poured out upon the entire earth. God help us to be true and to live the
gospel and do all in our power to promote righteousness in this great land. This is God's
work, and I testify to you that God lives, that Jesus Christ is the Redeemer of the world, that
Joseph Smith is his Prophet, raised up to establish this work in these, the last days, in
preparation for the second coming of the Master. I leave this testimony with you in all
humility, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
