<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Joy of Missionary Service</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Clifford E. Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Clifford E. Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 20-23</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: It seems to me that every time I stand in this position I feel less sure
of myself. I recognize that as we go out in the stakes, there is a warmth of feeling between
the congregation of the Saints and those who visit their conferences from time to time, and
there should be no difference in this meeting, because that same spirit of warmth and
fellowship is multiplied by the increased numbers that are here, and yet notwithstanding that,
this vast congregation, and consciousness of the fact that there are so many listening in on the
outside, presents a challenge indeed.
</p><p>
I have undertaken today to write what I would like to say in the interest of time, and I
sincerely hope that the Lord will be with all of us, that what I shall say may be of benefit to
you and to me, and give us increased faith.
</p><p>
Since our last conference it has been my privilege to visit two of the missions of the Church,
one in southern California and one in eastern Canada. I have been thrilled with the splendid
work that is being done by our missionaries. It seems to me they are doing more effective
work than ever in our history. They do not go out with a spirit of antagonism toward any
church or any people, but rather in the spirit of the counsel that was given in the early history
of the Church by the Prophet Joseph when he said that we should contend against no church,
save it be the church of the evil one
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/20-22#20">D&amp;C 18:20-22</a>),
that we should take upon ourselves the name of Christ,
and speak the truth in soberness, and that as many as repented and were baptized in his name,
which is Jesus Christ, and endured to the end, should be saved. He also said that we should
declare glad tidings, publish them upon the mountains and upon every high place and among
every people that we should be permitted to see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/29-31#29">D&amp;C 19:29-31</a>). We should do it with all humility, trusting in
him, reviling not the revilers, and of tenets we should not talk, but should declare repentance
and faith on the Savior, and the remission of sins by baptism and by fire, yea, even the Holy
Ghost. It is in this spirit that our missionaries are counseled to go from house to house,
preaching and bearing witness of the restored gospel of Christ. We recognize the fact that the
world is full of good people, that they have their religious convictions and traditions,
traditions that are deeply rooted from ages past. We do not ask them to give up any truths
that they have, but we do ask that they re-appraise their faith and their religion, their church,
to see if they harmonize with that which was taught by our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.
Our missionaries do not present a message of a new church; it is a message of the restored
Church. We do not have a new gospel. It is the gospel that was preached by Jesus Christ, the
same yesterday, today, and forever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/13/8#8">Heb. 13:8</a>).
Our position as Latter-day Saints is that we are entrusted
with the responsibility of establishing the kingdom of God in the earth, that it may prepare
mankind for the kingdom of heaven that is to come. We feel that there is no greater message
that can be brought to the children of men than one that will make men conscious of error
and turn them to the truth. Repentance is a grand Christian act. It is not only Christian, but it
is also divine.
</p><p>
This missionary activity is a great contribution to our missionary's life whether he be young
or old. For two or more years, he is in the field of a spiritual uplift. He
learns to pray as he never did before. He learns to draw near to God, and he finds that God
draws near to him. He learns that there is only one way to every human heart, and that is
through humility and prayer. He learns to be tolerant with his fellow men. Through study he
learns to enrich his mind, enlarge his soul with the thoughts of great men, men of God,
prophets of God, and thus he grows in knowledge and wisdom.
</p><p>
In the mission field a missionary is often tempted, but he does not yield. Thus he becomes
brave and strong, physically, mentally, morally, and above all, spiritually. A missionary often
has great decisions to make, decisions that many times are beyond the wisdom of his youth.
</p><p>
I recall an experience that was related by President J. Robert Price, former president of the
Central Atlantic States Mission, as he met with us on one occasion in the temple, telling of
two young missionaries who had just recently come into the field, neither of whom had had
much experience. Brother Price had received a message that one the families was having some
difficulty, marital trouble as I remember, and so these two young, inexperienced missionaries
were sent to this home. On entering the home, one of the elders asked if it would be in order
with the family that they first kneel in prayer. And so they all knelt down, and the young
elder who led asked that the Lord would guide in the proceedings that should follow, that the
differences would be composed in that home, and that peace could be established. And he
prayed for the home, and in the sincerity of his heart he brought conviction to those who
listened. And when they all arose from their knees the father, who seemingly had been the
leader, who had been the source of the trouble, approached the missionary; taking him by the
hand, he said, "We do not need you longer. You have touched our hearts, and we will
compose our differences, and you can depend upon it that we will not fail." And Brother
Price in reporting it said "Surely, out of the mouths of babes and sucklings hath the Lord
ordained strength" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/2#2">Ps. 8:2</a>).
</p><p>
And so it is in this spirit that our missionaries go forth, and they have great decisions to
make, and they are equal to them.
</p><p>
The missionaries also learn the injunction that was given by Isaiah the prophet, that they
should seek the Lord while he may be found: 
</p><p>
. . . call ye upon him while he is near: 
</p><p>
Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts: and let him return unto
the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/55/6-7#6">Isa. 55:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
Our missionaries learn to love their contacts, the people whom they meet, although they do
not always see alike in matters of religion and do not always agree, yet they recognize that
the world is full of good people. Many honest-hearted and upright men and women have not
accepted and do not accept Mormonism because they cannot comprehend it. As the Savior
said to Nicodemus, "They cannot see" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/3#3">John 3:3</a>).
And yet through the fine work that they are doing, our
missionaries are gradually breaking down prejudices. They are being invited into homes that
are blessed because of the faith and the testimony that they bring to them. There is no greater
joy that can come to the human heart than to bring this message of eternal truth to those who
do not have it. And so our missionary service becomes a great spiritual factor in the lives of
those who have this unusual experience. There is nothing equal to it anywhere. Our boys
come home filled with a testimony of the truth, acknowledging the goodness of the Lord to
them and conscious of the fact that they have been able to do some good, not only to
themselves but also to those with whom they have come in contact.
</p><p>
Thus has been laid a foundation of faith and spirituality and strength of character in our
young people that has contributed greatly to the growth and the strength of
this Church. It is no wonder the Bishop of York was led to say after his visit to Salt Lake
City, on his return to England, as reported, I think, by Brother Sonne on his return from
Europe, "The Mormon Church must be a wealthy Church, for it maintains so many
missionaries in the world." At that time I think there were five thousand missionaries, and at
an average cost of sixty dollars a month for each, you can see that would amount to
$300,000.00 a month, or over $3,500,000.00 a year, and so the Bishop of York was
calculating it in dollars and cents. He did not understand that the wealth that maintains these
missionaries is not gold and silver, but faith, sacrifice, devotion on the part of parents in most
cases, parents of limited means, not of wealth, but rich in faith and in a confidence in this
great work. It is not gold that has built our temples and our meetinghouses, but the same faith
and devotion to the Lord on the part of those who also support the great missionary system of
the Church.
</p><p>
In conclusion, my brethren and sisters, may I read an extract from a sermon delivered in this
pulpit many years ago by President George Q. Cannon. I think it was in 1871. It was
subsequently reported in the Church Section of the <i>Deseret News</i>. For some of you who are
younger, President Cannon served as counselor in the First Presidency from the time of
President John Taylor on to the time of President Snow. I think it was during President
Snow's administration that President Cannon passed away. He was one of the great leaders of
this Church&mdash;a brilliant mind. He knew the Prophet Joseph. His father had come from the
Isle of Man with his family. They had become converted to Mormonism, and had settled in
Nauvoo, and were there at the time of the martyrdom. I think I may safely say that President
Cannon's tribute to the Prophet Joseph in his biography is one of the finest that has ever been
written regarding the Prophet Joseph. It was written from an intimate touch that the Cannon
family had with the Prophet, and George Q. Cannon as a lad fourteen years of age
remembered the great leadership and the spiritual power that characterized the Prophet of
God, to whom the Lord had revealed his great work. And so I quote in conclusion some
remarks from President Cannon: 
</p><p>
The Latter-day Saints are not so uncharitable as to imagine that they are the only ones with
whom God is dealing, or are they the only people over whom and toward whom his
providences are being exercised. Such a thought has never entered into the hearts of those
who are intelligent and reflecting in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. It is true
that we believe and testify that we have been called to proclaim the everlasting gospel in its
ancient purity and simplicity, with the plenitude of its gifts and graces, as enjoyed in ancient
days, that we have been called to lay the foundation of that work which is destined to grow
and increase and spread until it fills the whole earth from north to south and from east to
west. Yet we do not on this account arrogate to ourselves all the kindness, all the mercy, care
and goodness which God dispenses to his creatures here on the earth, but we firmly believe in
every nation and among every kindred, tongue, and people, and in fact in every creed on the
face of the earth, there are those whom God watches with particular care, and to whom his
blessings are extended, and we believe that his providences are over all the works of his
hands, and that none is so remote, friendless, or isolated that he is not the object of his care,
his mercy and his love. This is our belief, and when we see the events which are taking place
at the present time [and this sounds almost prophetic], when we hear of revolutions and wars,
of nation rising against nation, of the various judgments and calamities, as well as the various
kindnesses and mercies, that are bestowed upon and extended to the inhabitants of the earth,
and to the various nationalities into which they are divided, we see in all these things the hand
of our kind and beneficent Creator. We see his providences. We behold his going forth, and
we acknowledge his goodness, and we also think that we can discern his overruling care and
providence for the bringing to pass the great events of which he has spoken, which will
eventually result in the emancipation of our race from the thralldom of evil,
under which it now groans.
</p><p>
It is in this spirit, my brethren and sisters, that our missionaries go out into the world to
proclaim the restored gospel, and I have nothing but commendation for these fine men and
women who are sent out, and for the splendid men and women who preside over them. These
mission presidents and their wives, outstanding in their faith and in their devotion to the work
of the Lord give these missionaries proper direction, and inspire them in the great work to
which they are called. I am grateful to stand here today for the privileges and blessings that
were mine over forty years ago to be called to the mission field to preach the gospel. I am
grateful for the foundation of faith that was established in my soul because of this unusual
experience, and I humbly acknowledge on this occasion these blessings, and also the goodness
of my parents in making such an experience possible. I express my gratitude to my heavenly
Father, and I bear my testimony of the divinity of this great work in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
