<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Knock, and It shall Be Opened unto You&mdash;"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 57-59</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I feel humble, and also I feel the loss of our beloved President, just as you who are assembled
here feel that loss. With the help of the Lord, I shall bear my testimony. I am very grateful to
the Lord for the knowledge that I have of the truth of this divine work. I was baptized when I
was eight years old. It was impressed upon me at that time that through baptism I had
received the remission of sins and stood pure, clean, before the Lord. I had a sister who was
very kind, as all my sisters were, who impressed upon my mind the need of keeping myself
unspotted from the world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>).
Her teachings to me the day I was baptized have stayed with me all
the days of my life, and I honor her memory.
</p><p>
DIVINE MISSION OF PROPHET
</p><p>
I have a perfect knowledge of the divine mission of the Prophet Joseph Smith. There is no
doubt in my mind that the Lord raised him up and gave him revelation, commandment,
opened the heavens to him, and called upon him to stand at the head of this glorious
dispensation. I am just as satisfied in my mind that in his youth when he went out to pray he
beheld the actual presence, stood in the actual presence, of God the Father and his son, Jesus
Christ; in my mind there is no doubt; I know this to be true. I know that he received later the
visitations from Moroni, the Aaronic Priesthood under the hands of John the Baptist, the
Melchizedek Priesthood under the hands of Peter, James, and John, and that the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints was organized on the sixth day of April 1830 by divine
command. These things I know. The Lord has revealed them to me, and this knowledge I
have had since the day I was baptized. I know that the power of the Almighty is guiding this
people, that we are under covenant to keep his commandments to walk in light and truth. It is
my firm conviction that every member of this Church should be able to bear witness and
declare by words of soberness that these things are true, that the Book of Mormon is true, that
the revelations given to the Prophet Joseph Smith are true, that the destiny of this latter-day
work is true, and according to the revelations, must and will be fulfilled.
</p><p>
SECOND COMING
</p><p>
I believe that the coming of the Son of God is not far away, how far I do not know, but I do
know that it is over one hundred years nearer than it was when Elijah the prophet came to the
Prophet Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery in the Kirtland Temple on the third day of April,
1836. Elijah's words point to the fact that we are that much nearer. And this ancient prophet
declared that by the restoration of those keys we should know that the great and dreadful day
of the Lord is near, even at our doors
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/13-16#13">D&amp;C 110:13-16</a>).
I have opened these scriptures to the seventh chapter of
Matthew, and I want to read the seventh and eighth verses: 
</p><p>
Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened
unto you: 
</p><p>
For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth, and to him that
knocketh it shall be opened (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7-8#7">Matt. 7:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
ALL MAY KNOW THE TRUTH
</p><p>
Is there any good reason why every living soul cannot know the truth and where it can be
found? Is there any reason that any members of this Church can give why he does not know
that Jesus Christ is the Son of God, that Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of God, and that
this is his work? If we lack that understanding, we have no one to blame but ourselves. I had
perfect confidence in the sayings of the Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ; and when he says,
"Ask and it shall be given you; seek and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto
you: For everyone that asketh receiveth," I am just as sure that every member of this Church
may know within himself or herself that God lives, Jesus Christ is the Son of God, and that
this is his work which he has established. We have no excuse whatever for not knowing and
having the absolute faith and confidence in this restored gospel of Jesus Christ. It is our duty
to know. In a revelation given to the Church many years ago, that is, in the days of the
Prophet, he warned the members of the Church against false prophets, false spirits
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/1-3#1">D&amp;C 50:1-3</a>), against
those who lie in wait to deceive. He gave us a key then by which we may know, but I repeat,
this key, given by our Savior in his Sermon on the Mount is just as true today as it was
nearly two thousand years ago. It's his word and can be accepted, can be proved today just as
well as it could by his disciples as he spoke to them in this Sermon on the Mount. In
interviewing missionaries I frequently ask them, nearly always do, if they have a testimony of
the truth. Some of them say, "No, I do not. I think it is true, but I do not know, but I have
the assurance that if I go on this mission I will learn that it is true." Down in their hearts they
give an honest answer, but I think they know better than they say. However, it is the right of
every baptized member in this Church to know for himself by the revelations of the Spirit of
the Lord that all that I have said in regard to the establishment of this work is absolutely true.
There is no reason in the world why any soul should not know where to find the truth. If he
will only humble himself and seek in the spirit of humility and faith, going to the Lord just as
the Prophet Joseph Smith went to the Lord to find the truth, he will find it. There's no doubt
about it. There is no reason in the world, if men would only harken to the whisperings of the
Spirit of the Lord and seek as he would have them seek for the knowledge and understanding
of the gospel of Jesus Christ, for them not to find it&mdash;no reason, except the hardness of their
hearts and their love of the world. "Knock, and it shall be opened unto you." This is my
testimony, I know it is true. I know that just as well as I know I stand here. The Lord has
revealed it to me as he has to my brethren. The Lord bless you all, I pray in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
