<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"How Often Would I Have Gathered Thee..."</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1947, pp. 77-79</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I trust that the sweet influence of the Spirit of the Lord which has
been with us thus far in this conference and in this session will continue with us while I stand
before you.
</p><p>
TRIBUTE TO CHARLES A. CALLIS AND MARVIN O. ASHTON
</p><p>
We miss this morning from our presence two great men, Apostle Callis, whose greatest love
was his fellow men and his desire and purpose to spread among them the truths of the
revealed gospel of this last dispensation: the other, Bishop Ashton, who loved men as much as
did Apostle Callis, whose troubles, the troubles of men and women, appealed to him, and
always he did all that he could do, that lay within his power to do, to alleviate those troubles.
They were great men. They have gone to a great reward that will take them to a place in the
celestial kingdom of God.
</p><p>
THE SAVIOR'S MOURNING OVER JERUSALEM
</p><p>
When the Savior was just leaving Trans-Jordan to come into Jerusalem to be crucified, the
Pharisees came to him and told him that Herod was seeking to kill him. And speaking of
Herod as "that fox" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/13/32#32">Luke 13:32</a>)
the Savior said: Tell him that the sick are healed and that the blind see.
Tell him that I must travel today, tomorrow, and the next day, "for it cannot be that a prophet
perish out of Jerusalem" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/13/33#33">Luke 13:33</a>).
</p><p>
And the mention of Jerusalem seemed to have awakened in his mind all that had gone before
since the world was, particularly since Jerusalem was built, and he said:
</p><p>
O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, which killest the prophets, and stonest them that are sent unto thee;
how often would I have gathered thy children together, as a hen doth gather her brood under
her wings, and ye would not! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/13/34#34">Luke 13:34</a>).
</p><p>
When he came to Jerusalem on that last mission and while preaching in the temple, he uttered
that fierce denunciation against the Pharisees and the Scribes, the fiercest that I know of in all
history, called attention to the fact that they had persecuted and martyred the righteous
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/13-36#13">Matt. 23:13-36</a>), and
then again broke forth in the same lament:
</p><p>
O Jerusalem, Jerusalem, thou that killest the prophets, and stonest them which are sent unto
thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together, even as a hen gathereth her
chickens under her wings, and ye would not!
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/37#37">Matt. 23:37</a>).
</p><p>
That is the motif of all of God's dealings with mankind, always forgiving, always ready to
accept us if we will but put ourselves where we may be accepted. His expression was an
expression of divine love, and it is not without interest that in making his comparison he
spoke of the love of the mother hen, mother love, the nearest thing we know to divine love.
</p><p>
LOVE AND FORGIVENESS MANIFESTED BY JESUS
</p><p>
Ever since the world was, he has offered us opportunities to serve him. He has tried to have
us live righteously. He has forgiven, over and over again. He has tried to bring us back to
him. Enoch, Noah, Moses&mdash;think of how patient he was with Israel, the destruction of the
firstborn of Egypt, the crossing of the Red Sea, the providing of the manna, the striking of
the rock in the wilderness. When it came to the time of the Savior himself, think how he tried
to lead them to repentance, forgiving wherever he found people worthy of forgiveness. All
through the history of Israel there has run that one sentiment:
</p><p>
How often would I have gathered thee but thou wouldst not.
</p><p>
In our day the same thing is true. Time and time and time again he has called us to serve
him, and has given us mighty promises as to what he would do if we would but do our part.
The Church had scarcely organized when he gave the great law of temporal and spiritual
salvation, the United Order. And remember, that the Lord very early said that to him all
things were spiritual, that he never had given a law which was temporal
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/34#34">D&amp;C 29:34</a>). He tried to get us to
live the commandments that he had given in the matter of the United Order that none might
suffer, that all who needed might be provided for, that all might be his people, happy, one
with another, because of no jealousies of excess in one and deficiency in another. But the
people could not live it. After three years and four months he was forced to take it away,
suspend it, and if you want to know why it was suspended I refer you to the fifty-sixth
section of the Doctrine and Covenants, beginning with the fourteenth verse
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/14-20#14">D&amp;C 56:14-20</a>). There is crystallized his
denunciation of selfishness and greed against us of this dispensation. We tried other measures
when we came here to the valleys, but they were no more successful. Here
in the last few years we have set up another plan, temporal yet spiritual. He is again trying us.
"How often would I have gathered thee together as a hen gathers her chickens under her
wings"&mdash;that is the issue, my brothers and sisters.
</p><p>
TIMELY ADVICE
</p><p>
I do not need to belabor the need we have or that we are likely to see grow greater,
particularly in this country with unemployment coming on. We shall all need help, even those,
perhaps, with the most. Yesterday's sermons told of the needs of our brothers and sisters who
are in foreign lands. Are we going to meet this challenge and provide for those who are in
need of help or are we going to let matters go and take up our time complaining?
</p><p>
I want to repeat the suggestion I have made before, the thought was inspired by the reports
that came that some of the brethren were counting out what a terrible load they had in dollars
and cents. Their computations surely made it big enough. If I remember rightly, the Lord
commanded Israel that she should not take a census, should not count her men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_chr/21/1-8#1">1 Chr. 21:1-8</a>). I do not know
why the command was given, but I suspect it was because if they counted and saw how few
they were, they would lose all heart to right the battle which they had to fight. And the record
is that when they did not count, God blessed them. If I were you presidents of stakes,
chairmen of regions, I do not believe I would spend too much time figuring out how much
money I had to raise but go to work and raise it.
</p><p>
I repeat, as I see it, we are again on trial. The Lord is giving us a continuing opportunity to
serve him, to work out his plan, the plan which he gave certainly as far back as Sinai.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us, give us the power to hold fast to the eternal truths he has revealed.
May he open our vision that we may see our duty to our fellow citizens, to our fellow
members of the Church wherever they are. May he take out of our hearts all feelings of hate
and leave there only love for those who belong to us and to our Heavenly Father, I humbly
pray in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
