<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Dynamics of Testimony</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 80-83</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I am very grateful for the privilege of once again bearing
witness to the restored gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
On a certain occasion I had a conversation with Dr. Frederick L. Paxson, chairman of the
History Department at the University of California and one of America's outstanding
historians. This conversation suggests God's method of transmitting light and knowledge to
his children here on earth, and so I shall use it as the basis of my talk today.
</p><p>
<b>Historian Appraises Brigham Young</b>
</p><p>
Dr. Paxson stated that it was his opinion that Brigham Young was perhaps the greatest
colonizer that the world had ever known. He explained that after founding Salt Lake City,
Brigham Young sent settlers in every direction from that center, resulting in colonizing an
expansive desert country. Dr. Paxson stressed the point that wherever President Young told
his followers to go, they went without any hesitation. Then he gave his reasons to account for
Brigham's outstanding success as a colonizer.
</p><p>
"Brigham Young," so he explained, "was one of those rare individuals blessed with an
exceedingly forceful personality. He was a man naturally endowed with unusual powers of
leadership. Through those natural powers of leadership and as a result of his unusual forceful
personality, he was able to completely dominate the lives of the Latter-day Saints. Thus his
followers always did Brigham's biddings."
</p><p>
After completing his explanation, Dr. Paxson said to me, "Am I not correct, Mr. Hunter, in
my appraisal of Brigham Young, and are not these the reasons why he was so successful in
colonizing such a vast empire in the great West?"
</p><p>
I replied: "No, Dr. Paxson, in my opinion the reasons you gave are not the most vital factors
which caused the Mormon leader to do such an outstanding job as a colonizer. I do agree that
he possessed the powers of personality and leadership that you described, but there is another
factor far more important than anything that you mentioned which completely dominated the
lives of Brigham Young and his people.
</p><p>
<b>Basis of Brigham Young's Power</b>
</p><p>
"The supreme reason Brigham Young and all the Saints migrated to Utah was that each of
them had in his heart a burning testimony of the truthfulness of the restored gospel of Jesus
Christ. Each one accepted without any mental reservation the reality of the existence of God
the Father and Christ the Son and felt a close personal relationship to them. It was a positive
fact to each Latter-day Saint that the Eternal Father and his Only Begotten Son had appeared
to Joseph Smith in the Sacred Grove, and also that other heavenly beings had appeared to the
Prophet and given to him the priesthood through which he had organized the true Church of
Jesus Christ. They firmly maintained that all the principles and ordinances of the gospel
which had been on earth in former dispensations were revealed from heaven to the Prophet
Joseph. Thus, Brigham Young and his followers maintained that Joseph had been God's
mouthpiece here upon the earth&mdash;his holy prophet, seer, and revelator&mdash;just as literally as
had any of the Old Testament prophets.
</p><p>
"Following the martyrdom of Joseph Smith, the members of the Church who migrated to Utah
maintained that all the power and authority from God which had been brought by heavenly
beings to Joseph had been bestowed upon his successor, Brigham Young. The Saints were
positive that their pioneer leader was now God's holy anointed prophet, seer, and revelator.
His word was accepted, therefore, as the word and the will of the Lord. The Saints firmly
believed that they with Brigham were building the kingdom of God under divine direction
from heaven.
</p><p>
"Thus, Dr. Paxson," I concluded, "an individual testimony of the gospel of Jesus Christ
possessed by each Latter-day Saint was actually the dynamic force which caused Brigham
Young and his followers to withstand mob violence and terrible persecutions in the East, to
leave their homes and comforts of life, and to willingly suffer untold hardships, hunger,
disease, and&mdash;for many of them&mdash;death and endure numerous other difficulties encountered
in making more than a thousand miles' trek through the wilderness to their promised land.
Their positive, dynamic testimonies caused thousands of people to follow Brigham Young's
suggestions, obey his instructions and commands, and successfully make the desert . . .
blossom as the rose'" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/1#1">Isa. 35:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Testimony of the Gospel</b>
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, this power, known as testimony of the gospel, is one of the most
dynamic forces in the world when it comes into a person's heart. It is that divine power
which lights up men's souls and gives them deep feelings, indescribable inward peace,
unbounded joy, and great understanding. Yes, it endows them even with hidden treasures of
knowledge. It guides them back to God. Paul, the ancient apostle, tells us from what source
mortals get their testimonies. He wrote: 
</p><p>
"For what man knoweth the things of man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so
the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God . . .
</p><p>
"But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness
unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11,14#11">1 Cor. 2:11,14</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Spiritual, Not Physical, Senses</b>
</p><p>
From Paul's statement it is evident that people do not obtain their testimonies through their
physical senses but through their spiritual senses. Thus Brigham Young and his people
obtained their knowledge directly from God, receiving it through their spiritual senses, and so
a testimony can be termed spiritual knowledge. Those who have received strong testimonies
feel that spiritual knowledge may be even more real than knowledge gained through the
physical senses. A statement made by Brigham Young illustrates his personal conviction
regarding this matter. To quote:
</p><p>
"Men talk about what has been accomplished under my
direction, and attribute it to my wisdom and ability; but it is all by the power of God, and by
intelligence received from him . . .What I know concerning God, concerning the earth,
concerning government, I received from the heavens, not alone through my natural ability and
I give God the glory and the praise." (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, 1926 ed., p. 664.)
</p><p>
<b>Channel of Spiritual Gifts</b>
</p><p>
The Holy Ghost is the medium through which God operates in giving to men revelations,
testimonies of the gospel, and all other spiritual gifts. Perhaps you recall that shortly before
his death, Jesus said to his apostles: 
</p><p>
"If ye love me, keep my commandments.
</p><p>
"And I will pray the Father, and he will give you another Comforter, that he may abide with
you forever . . .
</p><p>
"But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he
shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said
unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/15-16,26#15">John 14:15-16,26</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord declared that ". . . the Comforter, the Holy Ghost . . . knoweth all things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/35/19#19">D&amp;C 35:19</a>).
His principal function is to bear witness, or testimony, to the hearts of righteous
people. Throughout all ages the Holy Ghost has borne witness of ". . . the Eternal God, and
the Messiah who is the Lamb of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/12/18#18">1 Ne. 12:18</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/27#27">D&amp;C 20:27</a>). It is a fact of special
significance that the Holy Ghost bears testimony to the hearts of men that Jesus is the Christ,
the Savior of the world. Paul definitely declared that ". . . no man can say that Jesus is the
Lord, but by the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/3#3">1 Cor. 12:3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Holy Ghost</b>
</p><p>
The Holy Ghost is the member of the Godhead through which both prophecy and revelation
operate. For example, Peter wrote: ". . . prophecy came not in old time by the will of man:
but holy men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21#21">2 Pet. 1:21</a>). John the
Revelator declared that ". . . the testimony of Jesus is the spirit of prophecy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/10#10">Rev. 19:10</a>). In
the words of the Prophet Joseph Smith, "No man can receive the Holy Ghost without
receiving revelations. The Holy Ghost is a revelator." (<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>,
p. 328.) The Lord has declared that ". . . the Holy Ghost . . . manifesteth all things which are
expedient unto the children of men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/18#18">D&amp;C 18:18</a>).
In fact, ". . . the Holy Ghost, even the
Comforter . . . showeth all things, and teacheth the peaceable things of the kingdom"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/6#6">D&amp;C 39:6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/8/2#2">D&amp;C 8:2</a>).
</p><p>
It is a fact that the gift of the Holy Ghost is bestowed upon each baptized person when he is
confirmed a member of the Church of Jesus Christ, but the Holy Ghost will not abide with
that person if he is not righteous and pure in heart. A person who has a powerful
testimony&mdash;even a dynamic, compelling testimony&mdash;can easily lose it. How? Through committing sins
and not repenting. Then ". . . the heavens withdraw themselves; [and] the Spirit of the Lord is
grieved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/37#37">D&amp;C 121:37</a>).
"And he that repents not, from him shall be taken even the light
which he has received; for my Spirit shall not always strive with man, saith the Lord of
Hosts" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/33#33">D&amp;C 1:33</a>).
</p><p>
On the other hand, a testimony grows through a person's humility, willingness to submit to
God's will, and continuous obedience. The more completely one conforms his life to the
teachings of the Master, the greater will be his testimony and the manifestations of the gift of
the Spirit. Jesus declared: 
</p><p>
"And whoso cometh unto me with a broken heart and a contrite spirit, him will I baptize with
fire and with the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/20#20">3 Ne. 9:20</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Factors of Testimony</b>
</p><p>
The Savior has proclaimed what we might regard as a scientific pattern which must be
followed if one attains a testimony and retains it. First, he must have a strong desire to gain a
testimony. Second, he must study the holy scriptures prayerfully and with an open mind. You
recall that the Master declared: "Search the scriptures; for in them ye think ye have eternal
life: and they are they which testify of me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/39#39">John 5:39</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/37#37">D&amp;C 1:37</a>).
Third, a person must
render obedience to God's commandments. Jesus made this fact clear. He said: "My doctrine
is not mine, but his that sent me.
</p><p>
"If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether
I speak of myself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/16-17#16">John 7:16-17</a>).
And fourth, he must pray to God the Father in the name
of Jesus Christ and sincerely ask for a testimony. By doing these things a person receives a
testimony that the restored gospel of Jesus Christ is true.
</p><p>
In order to gain a thorough understanding of what it means to have the Holy Ghost bear
witness to one's heart, a person must have that experience. One who has done so knows that
the power of the Holy Ghost may come to an individual in varying degrees. On most
occasions it bears witness to one quite gently, but there may be a few occasions in one's life
when that divine power enters his body with such overwhelming force that he feels as if it
might consume his flesh, such as was experienced by the ancient apostles on the day of
Pentecost and by Heber C. Kimball at his baptism and confirmation. Brother Kimball wrote:
". . . I received the Holy Ghost, as the disciples did in ancient days, which was like
consuming fire . . . it seemed as though my body would consume away." (<i>Life of Heber C. Kimball</i>, 1945 ed., p. 22.)
</p><p>
On these rare and marvelous occasions, one feels the power of the Holy Ghost enter his body
as if it were a wave of electricity. While he is under that spiritual influence, he experiences an
indescribable joy throughout his whole being. Yes, he feels a love for everybody and
everything far surpassing his natural ability to feel love and joy on other occasions. An
experience of this kind is more dynamic, more powerful, and more awe-inspiring than any
sensation that could be received through the physical senses. Such a dynamic experience
leaves a lasting impression on the recipient that time does not dim and that he can never deny.
</p><p>
For example, if this powerful witness from the Holy Ghost comes to bear testimony of the
divine nature and truthfulness of the Book of Mormon, the person who has had that witness
borne to his heart will know beyond a shadow of doubt, just as surely as he knows that he is
alive, that the Book of Mormon is true&mdash;that it is the word of God.
</p><p>
<b>Moroni's Promise</b>
</p><p>
When Moroni was finishing the Nephite records preparatory to hiding them for future
generations, he gave us the key to receiving a testimony. He wrote: 
</p><p>
"And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the
Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true, and if ye shall ask with a
sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you,
by the power of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
"And by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4-5#4">Moro. 10:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
This dynamic witness has come to me, as it has to thousands of other people who have
followed Moroni's injunction. As a result of a gift from God through the power of the Holy
Ghost, I know as positively as I know any other fact with which I am thoroughly acquainted
that the Book of Mormon is true. It is a divine and sacred record of the history and religion
of the ancient Americans. This knowledge is so thoroughly entrenched in my entire being that
with all my heart, strength, and might I bear testimony to the divine authenticity of this holy
book.
</p><p>
Members of the Church of Jesus Christ, let us build, sustain, and retain our testimonies by
living ". . . by every word that proceedeth forth from the mouth of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/44#44">D&amp;C 84:44</a>). And
then our names shall be ". . . written in the Lamb's book of life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/27#27">Rev. 21:27</a>), and we shall
be ". . . sealed by the Holy Spirit of promise"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/26#26">D&amp;C 132:26</a>)
to rise in the resurrection of
the just to be crowned with glory, exaltation, and eternal life.
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
