<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Demand for Proper Respect of Human Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1946, pp. 84-89</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters: In humility I ask for your help that what I may say today may be in
that same sweet spirit which has been with us during this conference until the present time.
</p><p>
As the Savior and the apostles were on the shores of the Sea of Galilee on that early morning,
Jesus asked Peter:
</p><p>
. . . lovest thou me more than these? . . . Yea, Lord; thou knowest that I love thee. . . . Feed
my sheep (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/21/15-16#15">John 21:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
And the only excuse and likewise the only reason that any of us have for standing before you
in this conference is that we shall feed you.
</p><p>
Brother Widtsoe yesterday made allusion to a principle, spoke somewhat about it, to which I
wish now to refer. He spoke of our duties and our obligations as those who held the truth. It
is a very great blessing, not only, to have the truth, but it imposes likewise a great
responsibility. We of this Church are possessors of the truth in so far as it has been revealed,
the ultimate truth, and we are the possessors and custodians of the power of the Holy
Priesthood.
</p><p>
MORE BLESSED TO GIVE THAN TO RECEIVE
</p><p>
We speak often, and properly, of the great blessings which we have, the blessings that are
given to us by the Lord. But sometimes I wonder if our thought may not be mostly concerned
with what we get instead of what we give. In that great sermon of Paul to the elders of
Ephesus, he said Jesus had declared:
</p><p>
. . . It is more blessed to give than to receive
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/20/35#35">Acts 20:35</a>).
</p><p>
There is something very remarkable about what we have to give under the gospel plan. No
matter how much we give of truth, of good example, of righteous living, our stores, our
blessings increase, not decrease, by that which we give away. There are two or three miracles
in the Bible that impress me in this connection. One was the barrel of meal which Elijah
blessed after the good woman who owned it said that if she gave it to him it would take all
she had. That barrel of meal, blessed by Elijah, did not thereafter fail
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/17/12-16#12">1 Kgs. 17:12-16</a>). The more she took
from it, the more she had to give. Elisha blessed that cruse of oil for the widow who was in
dire debt and about to lose her sons as bondmen, so that she filled from that cruse not alone
the utensils which she herself had, but those which, pursuant to the prophet's orders, she went
out and borrowed. All were filled that she could obtain
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/4/1-7#1">2 Kgs. 4:1-7</a>). The Savior on the banks of the Sea
of Galilee fed five thousand with five loaves and two little fishes, yet when they had finished
they gathered up twelve baskets full of what was left
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/16-21#16">Matt. 14:16-21</a>). So when on the plain he fed the four
thousand, from seven loaves and a few little fishes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/32-38#32">Matt. 15:32-38</a>).
</p><p>
And so it is with God's spiritual blessings to us. We have the truth; we possess the
priesthood; both are given into our care. We are responsible for the use we make of them. We
are expected to give out of our store all that we possibly can give away, and in proportion as
we give unto others, we become thereby more and more enriched ourselves. "It is more
blessed to give than to receive"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/20/35#35">Acts 20:35</a>).
I repeat, as possessors of truth, our mission is to minister
therefrom to others. And the more of truth we give away, the more we shall have. The more
we righteously use the priesthood, the greater its powers will grow in us.
</p><p>
PRINCIPLES GOVERNING IN TIMES OF WAR
</p><p>
As all of you were, I am sure, I, too, was much impressed yesterday by the talk which
Brother Bower gave. As he proceeded, I thought perhaps it might be useful (and if I did not
think it would, I would not proceed) if I were to trace out very briefly and imperfectly some
of the principles governing the intercourse of nations in times of war. We have fallen just as
far in our concepts there, as in the respects to which Brother Bower referred. Brother Romney
this morning referred to one of the terrible incidents in the Old Testament history where the
Lord, not man, commanded the imposition by Israel of a penalty of the extermination of a
people. In the early history of the world, wars of extermination or enslavement were more or
less the rule. However, when the Roman Empire became all powerful, it adopted more
temperate rules; it had more humane feelings about war, its deceits, stratagems, and artifices.
A certain honor was observed towards enemies, so much so, indeed, that it is said that on one
occasion the Romans declined to recognize one of their generals in a victory he had won by
using bribery. On another occasion they declined to take advantage of an offer made to them
that by the use of poison they could accomplish the destruction of certain of their enemies.
</p><p>
HUGO GROTIUS' WORK ON INTERNATIONAL LAW
</p><p>
However, after the fall of the Roman Empire, the world fell into the Dark Ages, and then
apparently every excess that could be invented by man was practiced as nations went to war.
Things became so bad that finally at about the period of the Reformation, men's consciences
became shocked at man's inhumanity to man, and they began to try to see if something could
not be done to bring more humanity into the conduct of war. Along in the late fifteen
hundreds a very great Dutchman was born, Hugo Grotius, who, in the course of his life,
prepared the first great work on international law. In the preface to that monumental work
which has stood as the great classic from that time until this (and you cannot reach much
farther back when you go into international law of the modern time, than Grotius), as I say, in
his preface, he made this statement of the reasons why he wrote this treatise:
</p><p>
I saw prevailing throughout the Christian world a license in making war of which even
barbarous nations would have been ashamed; recourse being had to arms for slight reasons or
no reasons; and when arms were once taken up, all reverence for divine and human law was
thrown away, just as if men were thenceforth authorized to commit all crimes without
restraint.
</p><p>
Because of this condition Grotius wrote his work <i>De Jure Belli et Pacis</i>, which was the
beginning of the bringing into war of something of humanity, if humanity may be properly
spoken of in connection with war.
</p><p>
First, an effort was made to draw the distinction between combatants and non-combatants.
War was to be waged between armies and not between civilian peoples. Statesmen and
nations sought to relieve non-combatants from the woes, cruelties, and horrors of war. Old
men, women, children, the decrepit and infirm were to be protected, not slaughtered. Many
other humanizing elements came in, relating to prisoners of war and the treatment of
wounded.
</p><p>
PRINCIPLE OF NEUTRALITY
</p><p>
When our nation was formed, we contributed to the world some great principles, among the
greatest being that of neutrality, the intent thereof being to confine the war conflagration in as
narrow a space as possible with the purpose of providing that the peoples of the nations that
were not fighting might conduct their intercourse as usual. The miseries and woes of war
were not to be inflicted upon innocent, disinterested peoples. We came to the brink of war in
the last years of the eighteenth century to maintain this principle as applied to ourselves. The
effort was to make it impossible to have what we have now come to glorify as "global war"
and "total war." We then knew such a war was a curse.
</p><p>
RULES GOVERNING CIVIL WAR
</p><p>
Then came our own Civil War. Up until that time there never had been a written code of
rules governing war between nations; and up until that time civil war was a war by traitors;
those who were taken as prisoners of war were treated as traitors. But Francis Lieber, a
political refugee from Germany, drew up for Lincoln what were known as "General Orders
100," which went out to the Federal armies in the field, and thereafter governed the conduct
of our armies in the Civil War. These rules went further than any practice of nations up until
that time in international war. These rules forbade the bombardment, without notice, of places
where there were civilian peoples. It provided for the protection of museums, of libraries, of
scientific institutions. These were to be saved from the ravages and destruction of war.
Undefended towns were not to be attacked. Civilians were to be spared. Old men, women,
and children, the wounded, all were to receive the maximum possible protection. As time
went on and as a result of that code, other codes were framed by various international
conferences, notably The Hague conferences of 1899 and 1907. Furthermore, they provided
certain inhibitions on the waging of war which I think you might be interested in hearing me
name. They adopted a declaration prohibiting the dropping of projectiles from balloons; they
provided that poison gases should not be used; that poison itself should not be used. They
repeated the prohibitions that undefended towns should not be bombarded. Family honor was
to be respected; pillage and rape and arson and the whole train of like crimes
that we read so much about today were forbidden.
</p><p>
WORLD WARS I AND II
</p><p>
Then came World War I, and we began to sag back into barbarism. World War II followed.
All distinctions between combatants and non-combatants disappeared. This was inevitably so,
if they used the kind of weapons they employed. So we had destroyed in England many
towns, some of those suffering most being Sheffield, Hull, Manchester, Coventry, and
London. There were many towns in Germany equally destroyed, including Berlin, and
particularly Dresden, and as to this last city, some of our people, Americans, are affirming
that the bombardment of Dresden (where it is said we killed in two nights more than two
hundred fifty thousand people, men, women and children, including wounded who had been
collected there) was in violation of a tacit understanding that if Germany would leave Oxford
and Cambridge alone, we would not touch Dresden. I do not know how true this report is; but
we know the result.
</p><p>
TRAGEDY OF USE OF ATOM BOMB
</p><p>
Now do not forget that all of the nations had prepared before World War II to use aircraft;
they had already used submarines in World War I; and we in this area know we were
prepared to use poison gases. Then as the crowning savagery of the war, we Americans wiped
out hundreds of thousands of civilian population with the atom bomb in Japan, few if any of
the ordinary civilians being any more responsible for the war than were we, and perhaps most
of them no more aiding Japan in the war than we were aiding America. Military men are now
saying that the atom bomb was a mistake. It was more than that: it was a world tragedy. Thus
we have lost all that we gained during the years from Grotius (1625) to 1912. And the worst
of this atomic bomb tragedy is not that not only did the people of the United States not rise
up in protest against this savagery, not only did it not shock us to read of this wholesale
destruction of men, women, and children, and cripples, but that it actually drew from the
nation at large a general approval of this fiendish butchery.
</p><p>
The other day there appeared in the New York <i>Times</i>, it may have appeared here, too, but I
have it from the New York <i>Times</i>, an article which I shall read to you.
</p><p>
A new super-deadly poison, the most potent known to man, has been developed by the special
projects division of the United States Chemical Warfare Service. [That is, it is officially
developed.]
</p><p>
An innocent-looking crystalline toxin, the poison is so powerful that an inch-cube size of it,
roughly an ounce, could kill every person living in the United States and Canada, silently and
swiftly.
</p><p>
"If World War III comes, which we pray will never happen, it will be a war
in which most people may die from silent, insidious, anti-human weapons that make no
sound, give no warning, destroy no forts or ships or cities, but can wipe out human beings by
the millions," Dr. Gerald Wendt of New York City, editorial director of <i>Science Illustrated</i>
magazine, declared in a General Electric Science Forum address.
</p><p>
Dr. Wendt said: "The United States has already spent $50,000,000 in research off it, a small
sum compared with the cost of radar and the atomic bomb. Most startling are two facts: These
killers are invisible, microscopic in size, capable of spreading to reach every living enemy"; [I
wonder how we are going to direct these killers so that they will work only on the enemy.]
"and they can be easily and cheaply prepared by any belligerent who has as much as a
brewery and the skill to operate it.
</p><p>
"If any small nation is competent in biological warfare, a large nation, even with atomic
bombs, may be helpless against it."
</p><p>
There are other new biological weapons, Dr. Wendt asserted, that "operate through the slow
agony of starvation. It is the attack on plants and animals."
</p><p>
PROTEST AGAINST SAVAGE METHODS
</p><p>
Thus we in America are now deliberately searching out and developing the most savage,
murderous means of exterminating peoples that Satan can plant in our minds. We do it not
only shamelessly, but with a boast. God will not forgive us for this.
</p><p>
If we are to avoid extermination, if the world is not to be wiped out, we must find some way
to curb the fiendish ingenuity of men who have apparently no fear of God, man, or the devil,
and who are willing to plot and plan and invent instrumentalities that will wipe out all the
flesh of the earth. And, as one American citizen of one hundred thirty millions, as one in one
billion population of the world, I protest with all of the energy I possess against this fiendish
activity, and as an American citizen, I call upon our government and its agencies to see that
these unholy experimentations are stopped, and that somehow we get into the minds of our
war-minded general staff and its satellites, and into the general staffs of all the world, a
proper respect for human life.
</p><p>
May God give us the strength to stand in these times of stress and trial and crisis. May he
give us the wisdom and the inspiration to put hate out of our hearts, a hate that is consuming
us. May he give us the power as a people so to bring our influence to bear that men,
mankind, may be saved, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
