<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Great and Marvelous Work</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 82-84</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The Lord spoke from heaven to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery 140 years ago and said: 
</p><p>
"A great and marvelous work is about to come forth unto the children of men . . .
</p><p>
"Behold, I am Jesus Christ, the Son of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/1,21#1">D&amp;C 6:1,21</a>).
</p><p>
<b>A great and marvelous work</b>
</p><p>
And then he commissioned Oliver Cowdery to assist Joseph Smith in translating the Book of
Mormon. This book was designed to play a prominent role in this "great and marvelous
work."
</p><p>
Jesus Christ had already chosen Joseph Smith to be his prophet, seer, and revelator, and had
announced that his gospel would be restored from heaven through that prophet, and also that
he had been selected to establish the true Church of Jesus Christ upon earth once again.
Accompanied by God the Father, the Savior had appeared to that prophet in what is known as
"The First Vision" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-20#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-20</a>).
</p><p>
This "great and marvelous work" that Jesus Christ declared to Joseph Smith and Oliver
Cowdery was about to come forth among, the children of men was the "restitution of all
things, which God hath spoken by the mouth of all his holy prophets since the world began"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>),
with all the gifts, powers, and priesthoods, and gospel ordinances requisite for the
exaltation of the human family possessed by any and all former gospel dispensations. This
was to be the last dispensation, the dispensation of the fulness of times.
</p><p>
Accordingly, numerous ancient prophets brought to Joseph Smith the priesthoods, keys, and
powers of their dispensations. Through direct revelation from the Savior, Joseph Smith
established the Church and officially named it the Church of Jesus Christ. This church was
endowed with power from God to carry forth the work of the Master and build a kingdom to
which the Savior will eventually come to reign.
</p><p>
<b>The Book of Mormon</b>
</p><p>
Jehovah, or Jesus Christ, began making preparations 2,500 years ago for this "great and
marvelous work" in the latter days by initiating a project to produce a holy scripture to testify
to his divinity. Also, the scripture was destined to play a prominent role in helping to give the
gospel of Jesus Christ to the honest in heart and bring them into his Church in the latter days.
This holy scripture is known as the Book of Mormon. Therefore, the Book of Mormon is the
voice of God to our generation.
</p><p>
No holy scripture in the world is unique in as many ways as is the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
First, Jesus Christ initiated its writing and through numerous revelations supervised its
production, which is unique.
</p><p>
Second, as early as 600 B.C. the Master proclaimed that this record would play a unique role
in the latter days in testifying that he was the Christ, the Savior of the world, thereby
sustaining the testimony of the Jews, the Holy Bible.
</p><p>
Third, through 1,000 years' time the prophets who wrote the book did so under the divine
guidance of our Savior.
</p><p>
Fourth, acting in accordance with revelation from Jesus Christ, the last two Nephite
prophets&mdash;Mormon and Moroni&mdash;abridged the ancient records, making them suitable for use in our
day. We know of no other similar occurrence in history; hence, unique.
</p><p>
Fifth, the Book of Mormon is unique in its being translated from records of which an angel
was the custodian for 1,400 years before they were brought forth in a book.
</p><p>
Sixth, the Book of Mormon stands alone in being the only book known to have been
translated from ancient records delivered to an unlearned young man by an angel.
</p><p>
Seventh, the feat of translating the ancient record was also an unheard of achievement. Joseph
Smith, assisted by Oliver Cowdery, translated the entire Book of Mormon of 522 printed
pages in approximately sixty days. The writing on the plates was in an ancient script called
"reformed Egyptian" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/32#32">Morm. 9:32</a>),
a language that no mortal man through his own power
could decipher. Then how did Joseph Smith accomplish such a mammoth job in such a short
time? He has told us that he translated the Book of Mormon "through the gift and power of
God and through the Urim and Thummim."
</p><p>
Eighth, no other book in the world has been testified to as to its truthfulness and divinity by
the voice of an angel and by the voice of Jesus Christ other than the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
<b>Testimonies of divinity</b>
</p><p>
Let us now pay particular attention to some remarkable testimonies regarding the truthfulness
and divinity of the Book of Mormon. One of the strongest testimonies came directly from the
mouth of Jesus Christ himself. In June 1829, the Savior spoke from heaven and declared: 
</p><p>
". . . as your Lord and your God liveth it [the Book of Mormon] is true"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/17/6#6">D&amp;C 17:6</a>). I am
positive that my Lord and God liveth&mdash;and so I am also positive that the Book of Mormon is
true.
</p><p>
No other book in the world has ever had a witness borne to it as dynamic and powerful as the
one the Master provided to sustain the Book of Mormon in what is known as "The Testimony
of Three Witnesses." The ancient American prophets had predicted that through the power of
the Lord the plates would be shown to three others
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/27/12#12">2 Ne. 27:12</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/5/2-4#2">Ether 5:2-4</a>)
besides the prophet to whom the records
would be given for the purpose of their bearing witness. Oliver Cowdery, David Whitmer,
and Martin Harris asked for that privilege.
</p><p>
<b>The Three Witnesses</b>
</p><p>
In June 1829, Jesus Christ spoke from heaven to the three men through the Prophet Joseph
Smith, declaring: 
</p><p>
". . . you shall have a view of the plates, and also of the breastplate, the sword of Laban,
[and] the Urim and Thummim"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/17/1#1">D&amp;C 17:1</a>).
Thereupon the four men went into the
woods and kneeled down and prayed. In response, the Angel Moroni came down from heaven
and showed these sacred objects to them.  He turned the sheets of the gold plates leaf by leaf
and let them examine the inscriptions thereon. He described Joseph Smith's work in
translating the Book of Mormon records. As he was doing so, the voice of Jesus Christ spoke
from heaven and said: 
</p><p>
"These plates have been revealed by the power of God, and they have been translated by the
power of God. The translation of them which you have seen is correct, and I command you to
bear record of what you now see and hear" (Cited in Preston Nibley,
<i>The Witnesses of the Book of Mormon</i>, p. 8).
</p><p>
After the Angel Moroni left with the gold plates, the three men wrote their testimony, which
is known as "The Testimony of Three Witnesses"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/thrwtnss">BM Three Wit.</a>). Their testimony states: 
</p><p>
". . . we declare with words of soberness, that an angel of God came down from heaven, and
he brought and laid before our eyes, that we beheld and saw the plates, and the engravings
thereon . . . the voice of the Lord commanded us that we should bear record of it."
</p><p>
In no other time in history has such an astounding event occurred. Never before nor since
have three men received their testimonies directly from an angel and from Jesus Christ, as did
these three men.
</p><p>
<b>Believers and nonbelievers</b>
</p><p>
Since the coming forth of the Book of Mormon is so astounding, it has divided all people
who have come into contact with it into two definitely separate groups&mdash;believers and
nonbelievers. Those who believe love it, enthusiastically testify to its divinity, and proclaim
its great worth to humanity. Those who disbelieve it hate it. Many brilliant men have written
viciously against it. No book has had as many attacks made upon it as has the Book of
Mormon.
</p><p>
One may wonder why so many intelligent people have rejected the Book of Mormon. Perhaps
it is because there is so much that they would call miraculous connected with its origin,
preservation, coming forth, and translation.
</p><p>
Apostle Paul explained that it is only through the operation of the Holy Spirit of God that
spiritual things can be understood and received by man. Paul declared that "the things of God
knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.
</p><p>
"But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness
unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11,14#11">1 Cor. 2:11,14</a>).
</p><p>
Thus the ordinary man whose heart is not moved upon by the Holy Ghost regards the Book of
Mormon and all of the great and marvelous things that Jesus Christ did in its preparation and
bringing forth as being fantastic, fabricated, and untrue. On the other hand, when the Holy
Ghost bears testimony to the heart and soul of a man of the divine nature of the Book of
Mormon, the spiritual-minded man knows the reality of the divine authenticity of that book,
and this reality becomes very important in his whole being. He feels impelled continuously to
testify.
</p><p>
<b>Formula of Moroni</b>
</p><p>
Any person in the world can know for sure that the Book of Mormon is true, that it is the
word of God, if he will in all sincerity, humility, and faith follow the formula laid down in
the last chapter of Moroni: 
</p><p>
"And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the
Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a
sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you,
by the power of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
"And by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4-5#4">Moro. 10:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
I bear my testimony that I know positively that the Book of Mormon is true. It is the word of
God. I am as sure of it as I am sure that I am alive, or as I am sure that I am speaking unto
you today. The Holy Ghost has borne powerful witness to my heart and mind of the
truthfulness of this divine book, and has filled my heart with a powerful love for it and an
exceedingly great love for my Savior. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
