<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Loyalty Among All Nations</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, p. 37-39</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Most persons in the world today are striving for recognition. They want to be respected and
have the world look up to them. They would like to feel that they are wanted and needed.
They wish to be loved. As strong as this desire is, President McKay has emphasized that there
is a virtue that exceeds being loved, when he taught: "To be trusted is a greater compliment
than to be loved."
</p><p>
<b>Attributes of trustworthiness</b>
</p><p>
A person in whom trust can be placed is one who must be loyal, steadfast, and dependable.
Before he can be loyal to others, he must first be loyal to himself.
</p><p>
Our Heavenly Father has granted man the privilege of making decisions, the right to choose
between good and evil; the glorious principle of free  agency. A person living
a wholesome, clean life may have the Spirit of the Lord in making his choices and decisions.
He must remain firm, steadfast, and unwavering in the decisions he has made and considers to
be right, if he would have peace within himself and be loyal to himself. The wise man
Shakespeare expressed the thought in these words: 
</p><p>
"To thine own self be true,<br />
         And it must follow, as the night the day,<br />
         Thou canst not then be false to any man."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;         (<i>Hamlet</i>, Act I, sc. 3.)
</p><p>
Many centuries ago the Lord taught the children of Israel through Moses that if they wished
to have their days prolonged upon the earth, they would honor their father and their mother.
That was wise counsel, and still applies to us today. In honoring our parents, it is
contemplated that we will be obedient and loyal to them.
</p><p>
As the Lord made known to the Church through revelation in the year 1831, he charged the
brethren to be loyal to their wives. These are his words: "Thou shalt love thy wife with all
thy heart, and shalt cleave unto her and none else" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/22#22">D&amp;C 42:22</a>). Yet there are some who
have not followed the counsel of the Lord and who have allowed their affections and loyalties
to stray into forbidden paths. Separation, divorce, and heartache have been the result of such
disobedience.
</p><p>
Through obedience, we have been privileged to come to this earth and to enjoy the many
wonderful opportunities and blessings that come to us here in mortal life. People are born and
live in many different lands and countries. The Lord has decreed that we shall be loyal to the
country in which we dwell and will abide by the laws of the land, as long as those laws are
founded upon just principles. Loyalty to country is an admirable quality.
</p><p>
<b>Loyalty and its fruits</b>
</p><p>
Upon man has been placed the responsibility of preparing himself, so that he can earn a
livelihood for his wife and his family. He may establish his own business and provide work
for himself, or he may seek and secure employment from others. As he works he comes to
realize the satisfaction and happiness that comes from useful and productive labor. Loyalty to
his employer is fundamental to his conscience and peace of mind. One has aptly pointed out:
"Loyalty consists in giving faithful allegiance and untiring service to the concern that
furnishes you with bread and butter. It consists in working during business hours and after
business hours and before business hours for the best interests of your concern. It consists in
doing everything within your power to figure out some new method that will advance the
interests of your employer." Knox 117
</p><p>
A feeling of loyalty may not be apparent immediately. It may take time to develop and strive
for, through experiences, the necessary courage to display the kind of loyalty we would hope
for.
</p><p>
When the Savior told Peter, one of his beloved associates and companions, that before the
night was ended and the cock would crow, he would deny Christ three times, Peter was
astonished, and inwardly might have been indignant, as he cried out: "Though I should die
with thee, yet will I not deny thee" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/35#35">Matt. 26:35</a>). Nevertheless, three times during the long
night, as different individuals confronted Peter with the accusation that he was an associate of
Jesus, he loudly and emphatically denied any acquaintance with Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/69-74#69">Matt. 26:69-74</a>). Just as he uttered his
final denial, the cock crowed. Peter then remorsefully recalled the words of Jesus "And he
went out, and wept bitterly" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/75#75">Matt. 26:75</a>).
</p><p>
From this experience, sad to Peter, he gained courage and throughout the remainder of his
life, in spite of persecution and even torture, he was loyal to the memory of the Savior and
his teachings.
</p><p>
Judas Iscariot learned through torment and remorse the bitter lesson that can come from
disloyalty, when he betrayed the Master for 30 pieces of silver (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/14-16#14">Matt. 26:14-16</a>). Disloyalty to righteousness
results in unhappiness.
</p><p>
If loyalty is misapplied, or even if it is given to an evil cause or person, the
result will be evil. Satan and his rebellious hosts are zealous and loyal, but to an evil cause.
Ungodlike and unchristianlike communistic forces are active in the world today, attempting to
impose their will on others, which is an unrighteous cause. To follow them can bring only
sorrow and disaster.
</p><p>
There is also a danger in being over loyal to an individual, rather than to the cause such a one
represents. Lyman Wight was a devoted friend and associate of the Prophet Joseph Smith, and
when the Prophet was unjustly placed in the dungeon at Liberty Jail, Wight in company with
other close friends accompanied Joseph. Following the Prophet's martyrdom, Wight declared:
"The only man who can handle me is dead." He became rebellious and unmanageable and
refused to follow the leadership of Brigham Young and the Twelve. Finally he led a group of
his followers to Texas, where he sank into obscurity and oblivion, while the faithful followers
of the Prophet Joseph, who believed in him, not only as a man and a Prophet, and in the
gospel principles he taught, followed his successors, Brigham Young and the Twelve,
westward, where Brigham Young and the brethren rose to fame and founded a great
commonwealth.
</p><p>
<b>Loyalty to the prophet</b>
</p><p>
When Joseph was thrust in prison at Carthage, at his side was his ever-loyal and faithful elder
brother, Hyrum. Joseph knew and had predicted that his life would not be spared. He had
attempted to dissuade Hyrum from accompanying him. But Hyrum, with a strong conviction
in his heart that his brother was the Prophet, called by the Lord, loyally insisted on sharing the
trials and dangers, even though it would mean the giving of his own life. His love for and
allegiance to his younger brother is a heartwarming example of true loyalty. In a tribute paid
to them by their associated, it was said: "In life they were not divided, and in death they were
not separated" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3#3">D&amp;C 135:3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Loyalty a principle of action</b>
</p><p>
Loyalty is a principle of action. One must be loyal to something, a cause, a person, a
principle; one must give one's best for that to which one is loyal. But, if one is satisfied to do
one's duty only, one is but half loyal. When one, however, is willing to go beyond the call of
duty, to go the "second mile" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/41#41">Matt. 5:41</a>), to do more than that for which duty calls, then one is truly
loyal.
</p><p>
<b>Loyalty, a manifestation of faith</b>
</p><p>
As Latter-day Saints we have in the gospel the greatest cause in all the world to which to be
loyal. We also have true prophets of God to lead and guide us, and a country that guarantees
us the right to be loyal to all of them. Shall we not be true to our sacred trust?
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us as individuals with powers of discernment, that we may make proper
decisions, righteous decisions: then, with a display of will power and courage, be loyal to
those convictions.
</p><p>
May we be loyal to the country in which we live, to the Church in which we enjoy
membership, its teachings and its leaders. May we love and be loyal to our parents, our
husbands, wives, and families. May we be loyal and true to ourselves and the trusts that are
placed in us, so that when the question is raised: "Who's on the Lord's side?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/32/26#26">Ex. 32:26</a>) we can step
forward with confidence, knowing that we have kept the faith, have justified the confidence
and trust placed in us, to the end that we will realize the truth and significance of great
teaching that "to be trusted is a greater compliment than to be loved," for which I pray in the
name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
