<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Indian Traditions of the Book of Mormon</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 102-107</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I humbly ask an interest in your faith prayers and that the Spirit
of God may direct what I may say today. I would like to speak briefly on the subject of
"Indian Traditions of the Book of Mormon."
</p><p>
Since the publishing of that sacred scripture on March 26, 1830, a number of missionaries
have been informed by various Indians that according to their traditions their progenitors in
the distant past had possessed a sacred, religious book, which volume had disappeared; and a
prominent factor in those traditions is the claim that that sacred record would be possessed
again by the American Indians. On a number of occasions these people have identified the
Book of Mormon as the record of their ancestors for which, in accordance with their
traditions, they had been waiting and seeking.
</p><p>
Elder Glen G. Fisher, former president of the Western Canadian Mission, wrote an article
which was published in THE IMPROVEMENT ERA in March 1952, in which he graphically
described the experiences had in 1908 by Chief Yellow Face and his Cree Indians in their
search for the sacred book of their ancestors. (Glen G. Fisher, "Chief Yellow Face,"
IMPROVEMENT ERA, (Salt City, March 1952), pp. 148-150, 180-184.)  They came from
northern Canada to southern Alberta, camped on the Mormon ranch, and during several
months' time patiently waited for an opportunity to get a copy of the Book of Mormon and
be taught its contents, because they knew that this book was the record of their ancestors. 
After they had learned of the purpose of the sojourn of Chief Yellow Face and members of
his tribe, some of the Latter-day Saints who worked on the Mormon ranch spent evening after
evening teaching the Indians the contents of the Book of Mormon.  The Indian chief and his
followers expressed much joy and deep satisfaction regarding what they were taught, declaring 
that the Book of Mormon was truly the sacred record of their ancestors which had been
preserved for their enlightenment.
</p><p>
In the April issue of THE IMPROVEMENT ERA, Elder Golden R. Buchanan, president of
the Southwest Indian Mission, described some of the traditions of the Indians with whom he
has been working.  He wrote: "The people lost their records and their 'books.'" But as the
Hopis say,
</p><p>
We were not left without hope; we were told some day young white men with blue
eyes would come knocking at Hopi doors and would bring back to us our records and
our true story. They would come from the east and that we would know them by their
outstretched hands, and they would call us my brother" and "my sister." (Golden R.
Buchanan, "Indian Traditions," ibid., (Salt City, April 1955), p. 285.)
</p><p>
There may be people who would question the validity of the evidences in the examples I have
given of Indian traditions of the Book of Mormon, maintaining that these evidences have all
come forth since the publishing of that book and may have been  instigated by it or by the
Mormon missionaries.  Be that as it may!
</p><p>
The important question for our consideration, however, is: Are there any important documents
available which were written by the Indians prior to the publishing of the Book of Mormon
which furnish evidence that these people had traditions which came down from their ancestors
to the effect that their progenitors at a certain time in the distant past had possessed an
important, sacred, religious book, which book could be identified as the Book of Mormon?
</p><p>
I shall answer that question in the affirmative.  Yes, we do have some very important
documents which were written between two and three hundred years prior to the publishing of
the Book of Mormon which make the claim that many years ago the ancestors of the
American Indians possessed an important, sacred book.  These writings are so explicit that
one could easily believe that the ancient records spoken of by the Indian writers are the same
records as the ones from which the Book of Mormon was translated by the Prophet.
</p><p>
The first of these Indian writings of great significance which shall be referred to is the
<i>Works of Ixtlilxochitl</i>, written by an Indian of the royal family in Mexico approximately 1600 A.D.
In these writings he accounts the history, traditions, and religious beliefs of his people from
the time of the migration of the first group from the Tower of Babel&mdash;continuing with the
emigrations from over the sea of two other groups&mdash;and on down to the Spanish conquest.
</p><p>
The most pertinent portion of his book in relationship to our subject today deals with a very
important character called Hueman.  He and his work are described at great length in several
different places in the <i>Works of Ixtlilxochitl</i>, his unusual accomplishments being highly
extolled.  If one was to study thoughtfully Ixtlilxochitl's account of Hueman and compare it
with the portrayal of the character, personality, activities, and various accomplishments of
Mormon as described in the Nephite record, one could easily identify the two men as being
the same individual (<i>Works of Ixtlilxochitl</i>, cited in, Milton R. Hunter and Thomas Stuart
Ferguson, Ancient America and the Book of Mormon (Oakland, California, 1950), pp.
337-316).  For example, their names are quite similar&mdash;the one in the Indian manuscript
being called Hueman and the other in the Nephite account being called Mormon. Each is
claimed to have been a great prophet of God.  Each is claimed to have been the head general
of the army.(Ibid., pp. 342-354.) Each is claimed to have been instrumental in bringing about
a treaty of peace in 350 A.D., which treaty is claimed to have lasted for ten years. (Ibid., pp.
349-370.) And the last comparison which shall make, and probably the most pertinent one to
our subject today is: Each is claimed to have been the compiler of a very important religious
record which delineated the religious beliefs and history of the inhabitants of ancient
America. (Ibid., pp. 337-338, 341-342.)
</p><p>
Since each of us is more or less acquainted with the account given in the Nephite record of
Mormon's activities, under the direction of the Lord, in taking a thousand years accumulation
of records and from them compiling and abridging in one book the story of his people, which
momentous task was completed by his son Moroni and brought forth in the latter days under
the title of the Book of Mormon, I shall not spend time to discuss that point further. I would
like, however, to quote directly from the <i>Works of Ixtlilxochitl</i> wherein he described Hueman
as a collector and compiler of the sacred records of his people.  While meditating on this
particular quotation, the thought came to me that upon reading this quotation one could easily
imagine that he was reading the Nephite account of Mormon's activities as a writer and
keeper of records. To quote from the sixteenth century Indian document: 
</p><p>
And before going on I want to make an account of Hueman, the astrologer.  Before
dying he gathered together all the histories the Tultecas had from the creation of the
world up to that [his] time and had them pictured in a very large book, where were
pictured all their persecutions and hardships, prosperities and good happenings, kings
and lords, laws and good government of their ancestors, old sayings and good
examples, temples, idols, sacrifices, rites and ceremonies that they had, astrology,
philosophy, architecture, and the other arts, good as well as bad, and a resume of all
the things of science, knowledge, prosperous and adverse battles, an other things; and
he entitled his book calling it <i>Teoamaxtli</i>, which, well interpreted means
<i>Various Things of God and Divine Book:</i> The natives now call the Holy Scriptures [meaning
the Bible] Teoamoxtli because it is almost the same, . . .(Ibid., pp. 337-338.) This
marvelous quotation describing the activities of Hueman in writing or compiling a very
important book is so similar to the Nephites' account of Mormon's activities that such
a quotation constitutes a noteworthy Book of Mormon evidence.
</p><p>
The second example which I shall give of an early Indian document which contains
numerous, marvelous evidences sustaining the claims made by the Book of Mormon is known
today as the <i>Popol Vuh</i>. (<i>Popol Vuh</i>, The Sacred Book of the Ancient Quiché-Maya, (Eng. tr.
by Delia Goetz and Sylvan G. Morley, Norman, Oklahoma, 1950), pp.  1-767.)  The original
manuscript was written in the Quiché language by a Quiché-Maya Indian in faraway
Guatemala, Central America, nearly three hundred years before the Prophet Joseph Smith
published the account translated from the Nephites' records.  Between the years 1554 and 1558
A.D., an Indian at Chichicastenango, Guatemala wrote what has become accepted by scholars
as a very important and unusual document in which he delineated the mythology, beliefs, and
traditions of his people. (To quote the late Dr. Morley: "This manuscript is, without doubt, the
most vigorous, literary, and significant effort achieved by the American Indian in the field of
mythology and history." Ibid., p. 75.)  The Quiché-Maya Indian author claimed that there was
a prevalent tradition among his people that his ancestors in the distant past had at one time
possessed an important, religious, sacred book which had disappeared, being had no more by
his people, and so he wrote his manuscript to replace that lost book.
</p><p>
Father Francisco Ximenez, a Catholic priest who officiated in the St. Tomas church at
Chichicastenango, obtained the manuscript from the Quiché-Maya Indians approximately 1600
A.D.  No doubt he had won their good will and thereby was able to borrow this manuscript
for the purpose of translating it from Quiché into the Spanish language. After his work was
completed, Father Ximenez's translation of the Indian document remained in manuscript form
for approximately two hundred fifty years before it was discovered and published in the
Spanish language.  Since that time it has appeared in several Spanish editions, as well as in
French and German.  It was not until five years ago (1950), however, that it was translated
and published for the first time in English, the translation being made by Delia Goetz and the
famous Mayan scholar, Sylvanus G. Morley.
</p><p>
When the Quiché-Maya manuscript was first written, it had no title.  The Indian writer
claimed that the lost Quiché book was called the <i>Popol Vuh</i>, and so it was natural for the
publisher of this sixteenth century document to call it the <i>Popol Vuh</i> after the name of the
lost Quiché-Maya book.  The meaning of <i>Popol Vuh</i>, according to the sixteenth century
document, is <i>The Book of the People</i>, or <i>The Book of the Princes</i>, or
<i>The Book of the Community</i>. It seems that those titles, according to the content of the Book of Mormon,
would also be very fitting for the Nephite records.
</p><p>
I shall now quote directly from the <i>Popol Vuh</i> and let each one evaluate in his mind the
possibility of this record referring to the Book of Mormon records as they were when
possessed by the people of ancient America: 
</p><p>
This we shall write now under the Law of God and Christianity; we shall bring it to
life because now the <i>Popol Vuh</i>, as it was called, cannot be seen any more, in which
was clearly seen the coming from the other side of the sea and the narration of our
obscurity, and our life was clearly seen. The original book written long ago, existed,
but its sight is hidden to the searcher and to the thinker. Great were the descriptions
and the account of how all the sky and the earth were formed . . . (Ibid., pp. 79-80.)
</p><p>
In speaking of the original <i>Popol Vuh</i> which the ancestors of the Quiché-Maya Indians had
possessed in the distant past, the late Dr. Sylvanus G. Morley, possibly the greatest of the
Mayan Scholars, wrote as follows: 
</p><p>
The <i>Popol Vuh</i> was also the book of prophecy and the oracle of the kings and lords,
[Certainly that is exactly what the Book of Mormon was. Then he continues:]
according to a reference which the author of the Manuscript makes in another passage,
where he states that [Morley quoting directly from the sixteenth century document]
"Great lords and wonderful men were the marvelous kings . . . They knew if there
would be war, and everything was clear before their eyes; they saw if there would be
death and hunger, if there would be strife. They well knew that there was a place
where it could be seen, that there was a book which they called the <i>Popol Vuh</i>." (Ibid.,
pp. 19, 225.)
</p><p>
This quotation reminds one of King Mosiah and King Benjamin, great Nephite prophets,
seers, and revelators.
</p><p>
The late Dr. Morley adds the following interesting comment: 
</p><p>
And in the final paragraph, the Quiché chronicler adds with a melancholic accent that
what he has said in his works is all that has been preserved of the ancient Quiché,
"because no longer can be seen (the book of the <i>Popol Vuh</i>) which the kings had in
olden times, for it had disappeared." (Ibid., pp 19. 234-235.)
</p><p>
Since the time that Father Francisco Ximenez translated the sixteenth century <i>Popol Vuh</i> from
Quiché into Spanish, scholars have done much speculating regarding this lost Indian book.
They have made guesses regarding its authorship, the language in which it was written, the
writing materials used, its probable contents, and numerous other things.  For example, as
early as 1600 A.D. Father Ximenez wrote: 
</p><p>
The truth is that such a book never appeared nor has been seen, and thus it is not
known if this way of writing was by painting, as those of Mexico, or by knotting
string as the Peruvians; you may believe that it was by painting on woven white cloth.
(Ibid., p. 18.)
</p><p>
Probably one of the most intriguing subjects regarding the lost book of the Quiché-Maya on
which scholars have speculated is: "What has become of the original <i>Popol Vuh?</i>" Of course
none of them has known the answer to that question any more than they have known the
answers to the other questions on this subject on which they have speculated.  It is my firm
opinion that we as members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints have a far
better chance to know the answers to such questions than do the scholars because of the
restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the numerous appearances of the Angel Moroni, and
the coming forth of the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
Since I firmly believe that the Quiché-Maya Indians of Guatemala are descendants of the
Book of Mormon peoples of ancient America, as I believe also that other Indians trace back
to the same ancestry, it is but natural for me to regard the lost Quiché-Maya <i>Popol Vuh</i>,
which disappeared from among the ancestors of the Quichés many, many years ago, to be the
Book of Mormon records.  It is evident that they were lost or disappeared when Moroni, the
last historian of the Nephite race, hid them in the Hill Cumorah in 421 A.D.  A knowledge of
the activities of the compilers of the ancient records, their contents, and finally their sudden
disappearance was carried down from age to age by the Indians through tradition to the
sixteenth century, when at that time a Quiché-Mayan recorded the traditions of his people,
according to the late Dr. Morley,
</p><p>
. . . as a substitute for the <i>Libro Nacional</i> [original <i>Popol Vuh</i> or lost book from which
"the kings used to read"], as a revision and a new version of the accounts which had
been preserved in the venerable book which had already disappeared. (Ibid., p. 61.)
</p><p>
In our present discussion, I have purposely presented Indian traditions of the Book of
Mormon from four widely separated sections of the country: the first from Canada; the second
from Arizona; the third from Mexico; and the fourth from Guatemala.  My purpose was to
show that traditions prevailed somewhat universally among the various American Indian tribes
to the effect that their ancestors in the distant past had possessed an important, sacred,
religious book, which volume had disappeared  but, according to many of the traditions,
would be mysteriously preserved and eventually brought again to the descendants of the
inhabitants of ancient America.  It is obvious that these traditions fit well with what has
actually happened in regard to the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
Why should not the Indians have received through tradition the knowledge of the fact that
their progenitors in ancient America had had a sacred book written for them, since evidence is
abundant in the Book of Mormon which shows clearly that the Lamanites were well aware of
the fact that their rivals were record keepers and that the prophets had predicted the eventual
destruction of the Nephite nation and the preservation of the records for the Lamanites'
descendants?  For example, Enos, the Son of Jacob and a record keeper, knowing that the
Lamanites had
</p><p>
. . . swore in their wrath that, if it were possible, they would destroy our [the
Nephites'] records and us, and also all the traditions of our fathers.  [praying gently,
asking] . . . that the Lord God would preserve a record of my people, the Nephites. . .
that it might be brought forth at some future day unto the Lamanites. . .
</p><p>
. . . and he covenanted with me that he would bring them [the records] forth unto the
Lamanites in his own due time . . .
</p><p>
And the Lord said unto me: Thy fathers have also required of me this thing; and it
shall be done unto them according to their faith . . .
</p><p>
. . . I Enos went about among the people of Nephi . . . testifying of the things I had
heard and seen (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/enos/1/13-19#13">Enos 1:13-19</a>).
</p><p>
The latter two historians of the Nephite nation, like the prophets during the early period, had
firm convictions that the records would be preserved and brought forth in the latter days to
thee descendants of the Lamanites.  Shortly before his death, Mormon recorded in the records
a sermon to the descendants' of the Lamanites in which he said: 
</p><p>
. . . I would speak somewhat unto the remnant of this people who are spared . . . For
behold, this is written for the intent that ye . . . will know concerning your fathers, and
also the marvelous works which were wrought by the power of God among them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/7/1,9#1">Morm. 7:1,9</a>).
</p><p>
Following Mormon's death and after Moroni had completed the abridgment of the Jaredite
records, he wrote: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, I write a few more things contrary to that which I had supposed; . . . that
perhaps they may be of worth to my brethren, the Lamanites, in some future day,
according to the will of the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/1/4#4">Moro. 1:4</a>).
</p><p>
I bear witness that the Book of Mormon contains the word of God and that it was written
originally by holy prophets with the knowledge that it would be preserved to be brought forth
in the latter days for the benefit of the descendants of the Lamanites&mdash;the American Indians. 
In fact, one of the declared purposes of writing and preserving that sacred book is proclaimed
in its preface, which declares that it was ". . . written to the Lamanites"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>).
</p><p>
Since the knowledge of all the things of which I have spoken was so widely had by the
Nephites, it is my firm conviction that the Lamanites were also fully aware of the records and
the promises contained therein to their posterity. Following the close of Nephite history,
certainly the Lamanites and their Indian descendants would hand such knowledge down from
age to age by tradition to the present time, which has actually happened; and so it is easily
understandable why the Indians who live in various parts of the Americas have similar
traditions of the Book of Mormon.  These Indian traditions, to my way of thinking, provide
important evidences sustaining the claims made by the writers&mdash;thereby constituting
additional important Book of Mormon evidences.
</p><p>
I bear witness to these things, and I do so in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
