<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Obedience&mdash;the First Law of Heaven</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder S. Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 26-28</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Many years ago President Charles W. Penrose of the First Presidency attended a sacrament
meeting in Richards Ward in Salt Lake City. Just before the meeting commenced President
Penrose walked down the aisle toward the pulpit, accompanied by the bishop. About halfway
down he stopped, turned to the bishop, and inquired of him, "Who put that sign there?" "That
sign" was a placard that was attached to the front of the pulpit and that read: 
</p><p>
"Order is the first law of heaven"
</p><p>
The bishop didn't know but supposed that the sign had been installed by one of the
auxiliaries. Nothing more was said. The march down the aisle continued, and the meeting
duly commenced.
</p><p>
<b>"Obedience, the first law of heaven"</b>
</p><p>
I do not know what subject President Penrose intended to speak on when he arrived at the
chapel, but when he arose to speak, he said that order is not the first law of heaven, but that
obedience is. He spent the next 45 minutes marshalling instances and scripture to prove his
thesis. The main point that impressed me, a boy at the time at the time, was that by obedience
order may be established and that without obedience there will be no order, but chaos.
</p><p>
We are all familiar with the revelation given to Abraham concerning the purpose of the Lord
God: 
</p><p>
"And there stood one among them that was like unto God, and he said unto those who were
with him: We will go down, for there is space there, and we will take of these materials, and
we will make an earth whereon these may dwell; 
</p><p>
"And we will prove them herewith, to see if they will do all things whatsoever the Lord their
God shall command them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/24-25#24">Abr. 3:24-25</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Obedience, principle of the Gospel</b>
</p><p>
We have learned that in order to obey the Lord we must obey his servants. Each presiding
officer is to be obeyed in righteousness, in the field of his presidency. And so it is clear that
we obey the President of the Church, the president of the stake, the bishop of the ward, and
president of the quorum each in his field of service. And finally, forgotten by many as a
requirement of heaven, is the necessity of obedience to our parents.
</p><p>
Too many of our children do not realize that obedience to parents is a principle of the gospel.
</p><p>
Young people feel some responsibility for obedience to the law of tithing and of obeying the
law of the fast. They know they should attend Sunday School or MIA or Primary. They feel
guilty if they do not attend sacrament meeting, and they generally know enough to understand
that to break the law of chastity is to break the law of God. But too many of our children do
not consider disobedience to their parents as breaking the law in the same manner as is
breaking the law of tithing. The fault for this lack does not necessarily lie at the feet of the
children. Children know what they are taught, and if they are not taught to understand and
obey this first law of heaven, they cannot be expected to obey it.
</p><p>
There is a clear scripture that has to do with this relationship: 
</p><p>
<b>Divine charge to parents</b>
</p><p>
". . . inasmuch as parents have children in Zion, or in any of her stakes which are organized,
that teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance, faith in Christ the Son of the
living God, and of baptism and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the hands,
when eight years old, the sin be upon the heads of the parents" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25#25">D&amp;C 68:25</a>).
</p><p>
While this revelation does not specifically mention all that should be taught to children,
certainly it is clear that parents must teach if children are to obey the teaching.
</p><p>
<b>Obedience to parents</b>
</p><p>
Home evenings and the daily association with children provide the schoolroom for the
teaching. While they are small, children should be taught to obey their parents and teachers.
When they enter adolescence, it should be understood that with the addition of new freedom
(growing up is a process of becoming progressively free) comes new responsibility of
obedience to the laws upon which that freedom is predicated. The law is clear that children
obey their parents in righteousness until they reach their legal maturity. This is not something
to be enforced by the parents; it is rather an obligation to be voluntarily obeyed by the
children. Children should be taught that they obey their parents in the same spirit that they
pay tithing, attend sacrament meeting, or keep the fast once a month.
</p><p>
<b>Law of God</b>
</p><p>
It is a law of God.
</p><p>
Our first parents set the example. After he left the garden with Eve, Adam heard the voice of
the Lord over toward Eden, which commanded him to offer a sacrifice. The voice made no
explanations but merely stated the command. Adam and Eve obeyed (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/4-5#4">Moses 5:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
It was a long time, during which they obeyed explicitly, before an angel came and asked
Adam why he offered sacrifices. His reply was short but truthful.
</p><p>
"I know not, save the Lord commanded me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/6#6">Moses 5:6</a>).
</p><p>
In that reply is the example that should be followed by all children. If parents tell children to
be in from a party at midnight, or that they may not have the car, or that such tight clothes
must not be worn, or that dresses are too short, or that the allowance this month cannot be
increased, or that the lawn must be cut on Saturday, the reply of the children should be "we'll
obey." The Lord didn't give Adam a reason. Children should not expect reasons from parents,
although most parents are glad to tell their children the reasons.
</p><p>
I marvel at the meticulous care with which the Lord conducts his affairs in obedience to the
laws he himself establishes: 
</p><p>
Remember the night of September 21, 1823, when Joseph Smith was visited three times by
Moroni, and how the next day Joseph, feeling ill, was sent home to rest. He crossed the fence
and fainted. As he regained consciousness, there once more stood Moroni, who told him to go
to his father and tell him all that had transpired. Why? For many reasons, one of which was
that he had told Joseph to go to the Hill Cumorah. Joseph could not in righteousness leave
that farm without his father's permission. That was the law. Generally it was enforced. So to
leave the farm and go to the hill, Joseph had to obtain the approbation of his father. Upon
completion of his account of what had happened, the father told him that this was of God and
to obey (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/48-50#48">JS&mdash;H 1:48-50</a>).
</p><p>
I do not recall a single time that Joseph asked permission of his father to perform any act
after he was 21. Until that time he was completely obedient.
</p><p>
It is so with you and me and with our children. Let us, who are fathers, be engaged in
the business of rearing children, teaching them the law of obedience to parents.
</p><p>
<b>Obey the law of God</b>
</p><p>
Let children learn this law of God as a commandment to be obeyed. Let us also teach them
that this is the great restoration of the gospel promised by ancient prophets. Let us teach them
that obedience to their parents, and to those who preside over them, from the quorum leader
to the president of the Church, is the foundation of their future success in this world and their
exaltation in the world to come.
</p><p>
These are the last days. This is the last time. Through President McKay as prophet, seer, and
revelator we may hear the inspired word of the Lord God if we will but listen and obey. In
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
