<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Into His Marvelous Light"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 71-75</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I sincerely trust that I might have an interest in your prayers in
my behalf. Without prayer, it would be impossible to express one's thoughts and give
testimony of the existence of the Lord Jesus Christ and his Church.
</p><p>
Our general conference being held on April 4, 5, and 6 recalls vividly those memorable days
of the crucifixion and the resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ.  The words of Paul voice the
testimony of each of us when he said,
</p><p>
Jesus Christ the same yesterday, and to day, and for ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/13/8#8">Heb. 13:8</a>).
</p><p>
As Latter-day Saints, we are particularly interested in two great individuals: one, Jesus Christ,
the Son of God, and the other, Joseph Smith&mdash;the one at the age of twelve, the other at the
age of fourteen.  Christ visited Jerusalem for the first time with Mary and Joseph, who had
gone there to attend the Feast of the Passover and to pay their taxes. When they started
homeward, and after one day's travel, they discovered the Christ was not in their company.
Returning to Jerusalem, they found him in the temple where he was engaged in discussion
with the great men of the day and was, no doubt, telling them of his future assignments and
teaching them the gospel that was to be given to the world. Mary and Joseph entered the
temple. Mary said, ". . . Son, why hast thou thus dealt with us?  behold, thy
father and I have sought thee sorrowing"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/48#48">Luke 2:48</a>). Christ then made that marvelous
answer, ". . . How is it that ye sought me? wist ye not that I must be about my Father's
business?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>).
</p><p>
Some years later, the Christ sought John the Baptist who was preaching repentance and
baptism for the remission of sins, and John impressed those with whom he came in contact,
saying that the Christ, ". . . shall baptize you with the Holy Ghost, and with fire"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/11#11">Matt. 3:11</a>).
</p><p>
Christ requested baptism of John,
</p><p>
But John forbad him, saying, I have need to be baptized of thee, and comest thou to me?<br /> 
And Jesus answering said unto him, Suffer it to be so now: for thus it becometh us to fulfil
all righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/14-15#14">Matt. 3:14-15</a>).
</p><p>
As Christ came up straightway out of the water, a voice was heard from the heavens
saying . . . "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>).
</p><p>
In requesting baptism of John, Christ recognized that John held the Aaronic Priesthood, the
office of a priest.
</p><p>
After the Church was organized, we read in Ephesians 4:11, "And he gave some apostles; and
some, prophets; and some evangelists; and some, pastors and teachers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11#11">Eph. 4:11</a>). The teachers held the
Aaronic Priesthood.
</p><p>
We read in Philippians 1:1 from a statement of the Apostle Paul as follows,
</p><p>
Paul and Timotheus, the servants of Jesus Christ, to all the saints in Christ Jesus which are at
Philippi, with the bishops and deacons (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/1/1#1">Philip. 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
It is a great source of inspiration to every member of this Church to know that the Aaronic
Priesthood actually existed in the days of the Christ and the apostles.  Others were called to
receive the Melchizedek Priesthood. Elders were called and ordained, as we read in Acts
14:23,
</p><p>
And when they had ordained them elders in every church, and bad prayed with fasting, they
commended them to the Lord, on whom they believed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/14/23#23">Acts 14:23</a>).
</p><p>
In addition to elders, there were selected seventies receiving the Melchizedek Priesthood, for
in Luke 10:1 it states,
</p><p>
After these things the Lord appointed other seventy also, and sent them two and two before
his face into every city and place, whither he himself would come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/1#1">Luke 10:1</a>).
</p><p>
The Christ was the great high priest. Others were also so blessed, including the apostles. We
read in Hebrews 5:1,
</p><p>
For every high priest taken from among men is ordained for men in things pertaining to God,
that he may offer both gifts and sacrifices for sins
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/1#1">Heb. 5:1</a>).
</p><p>
The history of the New Testament points out definitely the existence of the Aaronic
Priesthood, wherein there were deacons, teachers, and priests, and the Melchizedek Priesthood
with elders, seventies, and high priests. There stood at the head, the apostles and the bishops,
guiding and directing the two priesthoods.  The members of the Aaronic and Melchizedek
priesthoods taught the membership of the Church faith, repentance, baptism for the remission
of sins, and laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost by those who held the
Melchizedek Priesthood. The seventies with the apostles were assigned to preach the gospel to
the known world at that time.  Those who held the priesthood were directed to be helpful to
the poor, teach the membership of the Church to pay their tithing, to observe the Lord's day,
not to profane, to be honest, and to attend Sacrament meeting.  Again, the New Testament
makes it clear that work was being done for the dead, for did not the Apostle Paul say in 1
Corinthians 15:29,
</p><p>
Else what shall they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? why are
they then baptized for the dead? (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/29#29">1 Cor. 15:29</a>).
</p><p>
So with both the Aaronic and Melchizedek priesthoods, the saints of the Church 2,000 years
ago enjoyed the same privileges, divine direction, and inspiration as do the membership of the
Church in this day. The Church 2,000 years ago was one of activity and opportunity for
services to be rendered by every individual member to assist in building up the kingdom.  For
again, reading the words of the Apostle James,
</p><p>
Yea, a man may say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: shew me thy faith without thy works,
and I will shew thee my faith by my works
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/18#18">James 2:18</a>).
</p><p>
After the resurrection of the Christ, there stood as the president of the Church the Apostle
Peter, who through divine direction and inspiration continued to teach the gospel and the
existence of the Lord Jesus Christ to the people and those not of the faith. To those who were
loyal, devoted, true, and active in the gospel, it is said,
</p><p>
But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye
should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvelous
light (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
It was Paul who realized there was soon to come about a change in the Church, for did he not
declare in 2 Timothy 4:3-4,
</p><p>
For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine, but after their own lusts
shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears;<br />
And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/3-4#3">2 Tim. 4:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
He realized that the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ would soon be changed from the
teachings of the Christ and the apostles to that of individuals who were teaching false
doctrine.
</p><p>
Two hundred years later, the gospel had been changed, the priesthood had been taken away,
and the earth was left in spiritual darkness; but this was not to exist forever, for John the
beloved had said in Revelation 14:6,
</p><p>
And I saw another angel fly in the midst of heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach
unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>).
</p><p>
Two thousand years later, there was a boy at the age of fourteen, Joseph Smith, who lived in
Palmyra, New York. Among the churches in Palmyra, New York, was great misunderstanding
of the gospel. It was impossible to find the church organization and the priesthood as it
existed nearly 2,000 years before. Joseph was very much concerned about the differences of
opinion among the various churches and the doctrines they were teaching.  He was one in
whose heart was a testimony that in the Bible could be found the answers to his many
questions.  The statement of James the Apostle gave him the necessary information,
</p><p>
If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and
upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.<br />
But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering. For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea
driven with the wind and tossed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5-6#5">James 1:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
Joseph followed the admonition given to him by the Apostle James and made it a matter of
prayer, asking God where he might find the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ.  In answer
thereto, there appeared the Father and the Son, the first appearance of the Father and the Son
since Jesus Christ was upon the earth nearly 2,000 years before. The Lord said to the Prophet
Joseph, "This is My Beloved Son.  Hear Him!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>). Instructions to Joseph by
the Christ indicated that his Church was not upon the earth, but in time it would be
re-established.
</p><p>
There appeared other heavenly beings to the Prophet Joseph, among whom was Moroni, who
had lived upon the American continent and had prepared the history of the great events that
had taken place in the coming of Lehi and his sons and in the establishment of both the
Nephite and Lamanite nations and that Jesus Christ the Son of God actually appeared upon
the American continent, established his Church, and organized the Aaronic and Melchizedek
priesthoods.  Jesus taught the Nephite people the gospel as he had the people in Israel,
bestowing upon them the same rights, blessings, and privileges. Moroni also indicated to
Joseph that he would receive the gold plates containing the history of America
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/34#34">JS&mdash;H 1:34</a>).  The gold
plates were written in a strange language, which the Prophet Joseph translated, and Oliver
Cowdery acted as scribe. In so doing, they came across the manner of baptism, which was not
clear to them. They made it a matter of prayer to the Lord, and there appeared a heavenly
being who introduced himself as John the Baptist.  This event took place on
May 15, 1829, in Harmony, Pennsylvania.  He placed his hands upon the heads of Joseph
Smith and Oliver Cowdery and uttered these words,
</p><p>
Upon you my fellow servants, in the name of Messiah I confer the Priesthood of Aaron,
which holds the keys of the ministering of angels, and of the gospel of repentance, and of
baptism by immersion for the remission of sins; and this shall never be taken again from the
earth, until the sons of Levi do offer again an offering unto the Lord in righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/13/1#1">D&amp;C 13:1</a>).
</p><p>
Through the appearances of the Father and the Son, Moroni, and John the Baptist, the Aaronic
Priesthood was restored and placed upon the earth. Some few weeks later, three apostles,
Peter, James, and John, appeared and bestowed upon Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery the
Melchizedek Priesthood. We can readily see that the Church of Jesus Christ was again
restored, organized, and placed upon the earth with both the Aaronic and Melchizedek
priesthoods, for the salvation, inspiration, and guidance of the sons and daughters of our
Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
As the Aaronic Priesthood and Melchizedek Priesthood 2,000 years ago had very definite
assignments, it is now true that those who hold the Aaronic and Melchizedek priesthoods have
the same assignments to teach faith, repentance, baptism for the remission of sins, laying on
of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost by those who hold the Melchizedek Priesthood,
fasting, missionary work to preach the gospel to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people,
helping the poor, paying tithing, observing the Lord's day, being honest, attending Sacrament
meeting, and doing work for the dead. The Prophet Joseph Smith received a marvelous
revelation from the Lord which is recorded in the Doctrine and Covenants, section 2, wherein
the membership of the Church were instructed to do work for the dead.  The Lord said,
</p><p>
Behold, I will reveal unto you the Priesthood, by the hand of Elijah the prophet, before the
coming of the great and dreadful day of the Lord.<br />
And he shall plant in the hearts of the children the promises made to the fathers, and the
hearts of the children shall turn to their fathers.<br />
If it were not so, the whole earth would be utterly wasted at his coming
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/2/1-3#1">D&amp;C 2:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, I bear you my testimony that the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and
the organization of the Church with the Aaronic and Melchizedek priesthoods have been
restored to the earth through the Prophet Joseph. He actually saw the Father and the Son. 
Those of us who have the privilege and blessing of membership in the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints have very definite responsibilities and assignments, particularly in
connection with the marvelous revelation wherein the Lord said,
</p><p>
For I will raise up unto myself a pure people, that will serve me in righteousness;<br />
And all that call upon the name of the Lord, and keep his commandments, shall be saved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/100/16-17#16">D&amp;C 100:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
This is a definite promise for each and every one of us who is sweet and clean in body and
mind, wherein there will come the gift of the Holy Ghost in building up our testimonies and
giving us the full understanding of the restored gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ. In addition
thereto, in our hearts will be that testimony that there stands at the head of the Church an
apostle of the Lord Jesus Christ as there was 2,000 years ago in the days of Peter, with the
same desire to inspire the Saints of today. Peter visited many of the saints, as does our
president and apostle today, with the same attitude and feeling with reference to the
membership of the Church as Peter had when he said,
</p><p>
But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye
should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvelous
light (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, it is wonderful to know that all of us are here enjoying the blessings
of the Church and the gospel because we are among those who have literally been called out
of darkness into his marvelous light.  One hundred years ago, our grandfathers and
grandmothers and many of our own fathers and mothers were literally drawn
out of the darkness of the world into the marvelous light of the Lord Jesus Christ through
missionaries.  Men and women today are accepting the truth and becoming members of his
Church. There is no other Church in the world where individuals have as great
responsibilities, particularly those who hold the Aaronic and Melchizedek priesthoods.
</p><p>
I humbly pray that we shall be worthy to follow in his footsteps and be inspired by the
statement of the Christ 2,000 years ago when he said,
</p><p>
. . . wist ye not that I must be about my Father's business?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>),
</p><p>
and I ask it in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
