<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Witness of the Spirit</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder A. Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 143-145</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters, obedient to my responsibility as a seventy, having been "called to
preach the gospel, and to be [an] especial witness . . . unto the Gentiles and in all the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/25#25">D&amp;C 107:25</a>),
I humbly take this opportunity to give my witness or to bear my testimony to
you all. In so doing I seek for the spirit of which Nephi spoke: 
</p><p>
". . . for when a man speaketh by the power of the Holy Ghost the power of the Holy Ghost
carrieth it unto the hearts of the children of men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/33/1#1">2 Ne. 33:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Testimony and witness</b>
</p><p>
I bear my testimony that God lives, that he is our Eternal and Heavenly Father, and that he
loves us because we are his children.
</p><p>
I bear witness that Jesus is the Christ, that he was the First Begotten in the spirit and the Only
Begotten in the flesh, that he was in the beginning with God, that he is the Creator of the
world and all that is in it, that he is the promised Messiah of whom the prophets spoke for
4,000 years bear witness that he is our Savior and Redeemer, that he wrought the atoning
sacrifice in our behalf. I know that he was resurrected on the third day, that he lives today and
is the head of this his church. I testify that he will come again the second time, as has been
said so often in this conference.
</p><p>
I bear my testimony that Joseph Smith was a prophet, sent to the earth to open this the last
dispensation of the gospel. I know that he actually saw God the Father and his Son Jesus
Christ and that he was instrumental in restoring the true Church of Jesus Christ to the earth.
</p><p>
I bear witness that the apostleship with its keys and powers that were conferred upon the
Prophet Joseph have been conferred upon his successors and that President David O. McKay
holds them today. I bear witness that this courageous, determined, noble man is indeed a
prophet of God.
</p><p>
I know that the modern scriptures found in this Church, consisting of the Book of Mormon,
the Doctrine and Covenants, and the Pearl of Great Price, are true; that to follow the plan of
salvation contained therein will lead us to our exaltation.
</p><p>
I know that we are members of "the only true and living church upon the face of the whole
earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30#30">D&amp;C 1:30</a>), with which the Lord is pleased.
</p><p>
<b>Power of the Holy Ghost</b>
</p><p>
Some of you may wonder how it is possible to say without reservation and with such
certainty that "I know" these things. This witness comes through the gift and power of the
Holy Ghost, and it has come to me. This is characteristic of the true church in this and all
other ages. This certainty has always been present with the prophets or whenever the Church
with its authority and priesthood has been on the earth.
</p><p>
In days of old Job spoke with this same certainty: 
</p><p>
"For I know that my redeemer liveth, and that he shall stand at the latter day upon the earth: 
</p><p>
"And though after my skin worms destroy this body, yet in my flesh shall I see God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/19/25-26#25">Job 19:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Book of Mormon Testimonies</b>
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon is a classic example of such definite declarations on testimony. The
word "know" and such derivations as "knew" "knowledge," "known" appear frequently in the
Book of Mormon. The phrase "I know" appears more than 100 times&mdash;virtually all of them
testimony oriented, the prophets declaring a knowledge of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Testimonies about the Book of Mormon are equally certain. After having seen an angel and
the plates from which the Book of Mormon was translated, the Three Witnesses bore
testimony with words of soberness, saying: "And we also know that they have been translated
by the gift and power of God, for his voice hath declared it unto us; wherefore we know of a
surety that the work is true" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/thrwtnss">BM Three Wit.</a>).
</p><p>
About the Doctrine and Covenants, the Lord said: "Search these commandments, for they are
true and faithful, and the prophecies and promises which are in them shall all be fulfilled"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/37#37">D&amp;C 1:37</a>).
</p><p>
In spite of such certainty of knowledge, there are those who still doubt the revelations from
God.
</p><p>
I had a bright, but confused, young man in my office just last week. His problem may be
typical of this generation's searching, doubting youth. He believed only that which can be
proved. It seemed easy for him to accept and believe the discoveries and conclusions of the
scientist, but he was having difficulty believing <i>revealed knowledge</i>. I explained to him that
there are different kinds of knowledge, some more readily discernible than others, but that
spiritual matters must needs be discerned by the spirit.
</p><p>
This problem pertains not to this generation only. Paul, speaking to the Corinthians,
explained: 
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge by the Spirit of God</b>
</p><p>
"For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so
the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God.
</p><p>
"Now we have received, not the spirit of the world, but the spirit which is of God; that we
might know the things that are freely given to us of God.
</p><p>
"Which things also we speak, not in the words which man's wisdom teacheth, but which the
Holy Ghost teacheth; comparing spiritual things with spiritual.
</p><p>
"But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness
unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11-14#11">1 Cor. 2:11-14</a>).
</p><p>
My young friend held to that old statement, "Seeing is believing." There is one realm,
however, where it works the other way: Believing is seeing! The Lord hides some choice
truths behind obstacles that will melt only before the warmth of faith. Faith, like courage, is
tempered by trial. Moroni was speaking thus when he said: 
</p><p>
"And now, I, Moroni, would speak somewhat concerning these things; I would show unto the
world that faith is things which are hoped for and not seen, wherefore, dispute not because ye
<i>see not</i>, for ye receive no witness until <i>after</i> the trial of your faith"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/6#6">Ether 12:6</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
<b>"The still small voice testifies"</b>
</p><p>
When one hears the still small voice (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/12#12">1 Kgs. 19:12</a>)
of the Spirit testifying that Jesus is the Christ, this kind
of knowledge, for that person, is as valid as a mountain of so-called "scientific" evidence.
That person really knows a truth. It affects his whole being. It affects all other kinds of
knowledge that he may have.
</p><p>
This kind of knowledge is not restricted to a special few. It is available to all who will
receive it. It is our Father's desire that all his children shall come to a knowledge of his son:
"Search the scriptures; for in them ye think ye have eternal life: and they are they which
testify of me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/39#39">John 5:39</a>).
</p><p>
A testimony can come to anyone who desires a testimony on the basis that Elder Hinckley
outlined yesterday&mdash;by a study of the scriptures, by serving in the Church, and by asking the
Lord for a testimony. A testimony, when it comes, stimulates a man to want to progress. It
gives him a desire to achieve.
</p><p>
I met a man in Mexico recently. Several years ago when he was baptized, he could neither
read nor write. It is amazing today, however, to see this man holding a position of leadership
in the branch, filling out the numerous reports that a branch president must send in, preaching
from the scriptures, and counseling with his brethren.
</p><p>
This achievement was not imposed externally. This yearning to do and to be was kindled
internally by as simple a thing as a testimony of the gospel.
</p><p>
I have received that testimony. I have given you my witness. The test of the truthfulness of
my witness, as well as the witness of all those who have so testified in this conference, is not
the acceptance by the nonmembers of the Church, nor even by the members of the Church.
The test is whether God inspired it and recognizes and honors such testimony. Any of you may
know of the truthfulness of these things which have been spoken by asking the Lord for your
own personal witness that these things are true. May each of you be concerned enough about
your eternal destiny so to ask, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
