<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Labor Today"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 131-135</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
To you who are listening in over radio and looking in by television, I extend the hand of
fellowship.  I sincerely pray that while I speak to you a few moments, I may say something
which will be beneficial to you and which, perhaps (and this is my greatest desire), will
stimulate you to think of things of eternal value and renew in you a determination to live to
obtain them.
</p><p>
To you who are assembled together in this historic Tabernacle I extend the same greeting.  I
marvel at your faithfulness, your willingness to return to this meetinghouse on this mid-week
day and listen to more preaching.  I think you are the group who would attend the second
session in a stake conference.
</p><p>
Seeing you here, and realizing that many of you attended the Primary conference, so that now
you have been in meetings constantly for five days, I am reminded of an experience my wife
and I had one time as we rode from St. George to Cedar City.  The driver of the automobile
in which we rode had with him his little boy, who was just tall enough to stand on his feet
and look out through the windshield. He wore cowboy chaps and a cowboy hat.  His father
told us of two things he liked to dine was to put on his cowboy clothes and ride his pony, and
the other was to go to picture shows. It was difficult to persuade him to terminate either
experience when he got at it. They would try to get him home after he had seen a show
through once, but he continued to stay on.
</p><p>
One Sunday morning after Sunday School, he went home.  His mother had gone to fast
meeting, which followed Sunday School.  The boy took off his Sunday clothes and put on his
cowboy clothes and then looked for something to eat.  Not finding what he wanted, he
returned to the meetinghouse to find his mother.  Spying her as he came down the aisle, he
said, in a rather loud voice, "Mother, why don't you come home?  Are you going to stay here
and see this thing through three times?"
</p><p>
Gathered together here as we are, and remembering the sustaining of a member of the
Quorum of the Twelve and an assistant to that Quorum, I cannot help feeling the loss of
Brother Cowley.  We listened here just six months ago to his golden voice.  I want to read to
you one paragraph from his final message.  I think it is significant for many reasons.  One is
that in this paragraph he mentioned Brother Morris, who today fills the vacancy left in the
Quorum by his passing.  We may be able to catch in this excerpt something of his eloquence
and of his humility.
</p><p>
We have heard the prayer of the Prophet referred to this morning. Here was a young lad who
believed in a promise that man lacked wisdom and would ask of God it would be given to
him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>);
and in response to that injunction he took himself out into that grove, away from the
superficial structures men, and he didn't stand looking into heaven; he bowed upon the bends
knees of his body, and he offered up his prayer to God his Father to bring clearness of vision
to his mind, to divest from his mind the confusion which existed there
pertaining to religion.  How can people doubt that God heard that prayer?  Anyone who
would question that God heard the prayer of that boy must believe that the Father in heaven is
cruel and shuts himself away from his children when they seek him.  But he did hear that
prayer, and as Elder Morris has mentioned, the light burst from heaven; down through that
channel of light came the Father and the Son
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
Young people, if you prayed for your father to
come in your hour of need, would he hide from you?  Of course not.  Neither will our Father
who is in heaven hide from us who seek him out.
</p><p>
God grant that we may always have the spirit of prayer in our hearts (<i>The Improvement Era</i>,
December 1953, p. 962).
</p><p>
I extend to Brother Morris a hearty welcome as he comes into the Council of the Twelve.  I
have loved him for a long time.  I remember some years ago attending a meeting where he
addressed a group of Scout leaders.  He said there something which still lingers in my mind. 
He was talking about boys who had been brought into the Church through the activities of
that organization, about their conversion, and then he said this, in substance: That not only
had boys been converted from out of the Church, but that many boys born in the Church had
been converted. Then he emphasized the truth that whether one is born in the Church or out
of the Church, he must be converted in order to receive the blessings of heaven.
</p><p>
I welcome Elder Sill into the Councils of the Church.  I have known him for nineteen years
now.  Back in those days he and I were companion bishops serving under President Joseph L.
Wirthlin, who was then our stake president.  I know of his ability and of his loyalty. I know
that he never let his tithing go unpaid.  I remember an occasion when he consulted me about
it at the end of the year, when some of his calculations had gone wrong, and he did not have
the ready cash to pay his tithing in full.  We talked it over, and he went to the bank and
borrowed the money to make it up.  I am sure he will render a great service.
</p><p>
As I sat here in this conference and realized that it was drawing to a close, I thought of what
I might say here in these closing moments which would be of worth to the people of the
Church, and this statement from the Prophet came to my mind: 
</p><p>
It is one thing to be on the mount and hear the excellent voice, etc., and another to hear the
voice declare to you, You have a part and lot in that kingdom. (<i>DHC</i> 5:493.)
</p><p>
That passage from the Prophet's writings has been on my mind a great deal.  He gave it at
the end of a long sermon, in which he had been urging the people of his day to make their
calling and their election sure. He himself had made his calling and election sure.
</p><p>
The Lord said to the Prophet Joseph Smith on one occasion,
</p><p>
For I am the lord thy God, and will be with thee even unto the end of the world, and through
all eternity; for verily I seal upon you your exaltation, and prepare a throne for you in the
kingdom of my Father, with Abraham your father
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/49#49">D&amp;C 132:49</a>).
</p><p>
And then the Lord specifies in the next sentence the conditions that brought that great
blessing to the Prophet Joseph.
</p><p>
Behold, I have seen your sacrifices, and will forgive all your sins; I have seen your sacrifices
in obedience to that which I have told you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/50#50">D&amp;C 132:50</a>).
</p><p>
He gave that same witness to Heber C. Kimball.  I suppose that a man who had that witness
would be enjoying the more sure word of prophecy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/19#19">2 Pet. 1:19</a>), which the Prophet defines as
</p><p>
. . . a man's knowing that he is sealed up unto eternal life, by revelation and the spirit of
prophecy, through the power of the Holy Priesthood
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/5#5">D&amp;C 131:5</a>).
</p><p>
In this conference we have been greatly entertained at times with eloquent oratory.  We have
been taught by great teachers.  We have heard enough truth and direction in this conference to
bring us into the presence of God if we would follow it.  We have been
taken on to the spiritual mountain and shown visions of great glory, but how many of us have
heard that voice saying we would have a part therein.
</p><p>
I want to read a text by which we may test ourselves today and always as to where we stand
with reference to our faith and belief in God.  It is the 25th verse of the 64th Section of the
Doctrine and Covenants: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, if ye believe me, ye will labor while it is called today
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/25#25">D&amp;C 64:25</a>).
</p><p>
In the two paragraphs which precede it, the Lord makes clear three things: First, the meaning
of the word <i>today</i> as used in the text; second, certain things which his people should do
today; and third, some events which will come to pass tomorrow.  Here are his words: 
</p><p>
Behold, now it is called today until the coming of the Son of Man, and verily it is a day of
sacrifice, and a day for the tithing of my people; for he that is tithed shall not be burned at
his coming.
</p><p>
For after today cometh the burning . . . for verily I say, tomorrow all the proud and they that
do wickedly shall be as stubble; and I will burn them up, for I am the Lord of Hosts; and I
will not spare any that remain in Babylon.
</p><p>
And then follows our text: 
</p><p>
Wherefore, if ye believe me, ye will labor while it is called today
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/23-25#23">D&amp;C 64:23-25</a>).
</p><p>
I have in my heart a desire to emphasize the importance of doing the will of God now while
today lasts.  Perhaps more hangs upon what a man does during the short period of his mortal
probation than upon his performance in any other period of equal duration since the spirit
hosts took sides in the great war in heaven.
</p><p>
Amulek, Alma's missionary companion, speaks to this subject as follows: 
</p><p>
. . . now is the time and the day of your salvation . . .
</p><p>
For behold, this life is the time for men to prepare to meet God; yea, behold, the day of this
life is the day for men to perform their labors.
</p><p>
. . . therefore, I beseech of you that ye do not procrastinate the day of your repentance until the
end; for after this day of life, which is given us to prepare for eternity, behold, if we do not
improve our time while in this life, then cometh the night of darkness wherein there can be no
labor performed (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/31-33#31">Alma 34:31-33</a>).
</p><p>
Nephi taught this same doctrine and went one step farther.  He declared that we must not only
labor in this life, but that we must also continue that labor until the end of life.  He pointed
out that the gate by which one enters upon the straight and narrow path is repentance and
baptism by water and of fire and the Holy Ghost, and then continued: 
</p><p>
And now, my beloved brethren, after ye have gotten into this straight and narrow path, I
would ask if all is done?  Behold, I say unto you, Nay . . .
</p><p>
ye must press forward with a steadfastness in Christ, having a perfect brightness of hope,
and a love of God and of all men.  Wherefore, if ye shall press forward, feasting upon the
word of Christ, and endure to the end, behold, thus saith the Father: Ye shall have eternal life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/19-20#19">2 Ne. 31:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
And now, my beloved brethren, I know by this that unless a man shall endure to the end, in
following the example of the on of the living God, he cannot be saved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/16#16">2 Ne. 31:16</a>).
</p><p>
Mormon's performance, along with his counsel to his son Moroni, is a heroic example of
one's continuing unto the end under the most trying circumstances.  You will recall that it
was Mormon who led the degenerate Nephites in their final struggle against the Lamanites.
And a discouraging and thankless job it was! As he approached the inevitable end, he wrote
to his beloved son Moroni, advising that he had just fought an important battle in which he did
not conquer, and in which three of his most valiant leaders and a great number of his choice
men had been killed.  He continued,
</p><p>
And now behold, my son, I fear lest the Lamanites shall destroy this people; for they do not
repent, and Satan stirreth them up continually to anger one with another.
</p><p>
Behold, I am laboring with them continually; and when I speak the word of God with
sharpness they tremble and anger against me; and when I use no sharpness they harden their
hearts against it; wherefore, I fear lest the Spirit of the lord hath ceased striving with them.
</p><p>
For so exceedingly do they anger that it seemeth me that they have no fear of death; and they
have lost their love, one towards another; and they thirst after blood and revenge continually
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/9/3-5#3">Moro. 9:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
Then, notwithstanding these discouraging circumstances, he declares his intention to continue
to labor and encourages his son Moroni to do likewise. Listen to his plea and take courage
therefrom: 
</p><p>
And now, my beloved son, notwithstanding their hardness, let us labor diligently; for if we
should cease to labor, we should be brought under condemnation; for we have a labor to
perform whilst in this tabernacle of clay, bat we may conquer the enemy of all righteousness,
and rest our souls in the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/9/6#6">Moro. 9:6</a>).
</p><p>
In the light of these teachings, it would seem to be most unwise to rely upon the doctrine of
the so-called second chance and wait until after death to perform our good works.  I am
acquainted with the doctrine that those who have had no opportunity to hear and receive the
gospel in this life will have that opportunity in the world to come, and I rejoice in it.  I
rejoice in the vision and the revelation received by the Prophet Joseph Smith on the 21st day
of January 1836, which teaches this doctrine.  The Prophet reported that vision and that
revelation in part as follows: 
</p><p>
The heavens were opened upon us, and I beheld the celestial kingdom of God, and the glory
thereof . . . I saw the transcendent beauty of the gate through which the heirs of that kingdom
will enter, which was like unto circling flames of fire; also the blazing throne of God,
whereon was seated the Father and the Son.  I saw the beautiful streets of that kingdom,
which had the appearance of being paved with gold.  I saw Fathers Adam and Abraham, and
my father and mother, my brother, Alvin, that has long since slept, and marvelled how it was
that he had obtained an inheritance in that kingdom, seeing that he had departed this life
before the lord had set His hand to gather Israel the second time, and had not been baptized
for the remission of sins.
</p><p>
Thus came the voice of the lord unto me, saying&mdash;
</p><p>
"All who have died without a knowledge of this Gospel, who would have received it if they
had been permitted to tarry, shall be heirs of the celestial kingdom of God; also all that shall
die henceforth without a knowledge of it, who would have received it with all their hearts,
shall be heirs of that kingdom, for I, the lord, will judge all men according to their works,
according to the desire of their hearts." (<i>DHC</i> 2:380;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/137/1-9#1">D&amp;C 137:1-9</a>).
</p><p>
All this I accept with joy.  However, it does not teach, and I have never found anything in the
scriptures nor in the teachings of the prophets which encourages me to believe, that those who
have the gospel taught to them here will be able to make up their loss if they choose to wait
for the next life to obey it.  I would not advise anyone to take that chance.  As I understand
the scriptures, taking such a hazard would be fatal.
</p><p>
Amulek, after speaking of "the night of darkness wherein there can be no labor performed"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/33#33">Alma 34:33</a>) added: 
</p><p>
Ye cannot say, when ye are brought to that awful crisis, that I will repent, that I will return to
my God.  Nay, ye cannot say this; for that same spirit which doth possess your bodies at the
time that ye go out of this life, that same spirit will have power to possess your body in that
eternal world.
</p><p>
For behold, if ye have procrastinated the day of your repentance even until death, behold, ye
have become subjected to the spirit of the devil, and he doth seal you his; therefore, the Spirit
of the Lord hath withdrawn from you, and hath no place in you, and the devil hath all power
over you; and this is the final state of the wicked
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/34-35#34">Alma 34:34-35</a>).
</p><p>
On this point of deferring obedience to the gospel, we might with profit consider the Savior's
parable of the ten virgins.  I do not remember any provision being made in that parable for
the five foolish virgins to enter into the marriage at a later time.  I do remember, however,
that after the door was shut they, having in the meantime filled their lamps with oil, came
saying, "Lord, Lord, open to us," and that his answer was, Verily I say unto you, I know you
not" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/1-13#1">Matt. 25:1-13</a>).
</p><p>
In 1831 the Lord continued with the lesson he had in mind to teach with this parable. 
Speaking to the Prophet Joseph, he specified some of the blessings to be received by the five
wise virgins. Said he: 
</p><p>
And at that day, when I shall come in my glory, shall the parable be fulfilled which I spake
concerning the ten virgins.
</p><p>
For they that are wise and have received the truth, and have taken the Holy Spirit for their
guide, and have not been deceived&mdash;verily I say unto you, they shall not be hewn down and
cast into the fire, but shall abide the day.
</p><p>
And the earth shall be given unto them for an inheritance; and they shall multiply and wax
strong, and their children shall grow up without sin unto salvation.
</p><p>
For the Lord shall be in their midst, and his glory shall be upon them, and he will be their
king and their lawgiver (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/56-59#56">D&amp;C 45:56-59</a>).
</p><p>
No mention is made in this revelation of the whereabouts of the foolish virgins.  Said the
Prophet Joseph,
</p><p>
If men would acquire salvation they have got to be subject, before they leave this world, to
certain rules and principles, which were fixed by an unalterable decree before the world was.
</p><p>
[Otherwise] the disappointment of hopes and expectations at the resurrection would be
indescribably dreadful (<i>DHC</i> 6:50-51).
</p><p>
In view of these teachings and the many others which carry the message that today is the day
for us to perform our labors, it would seem to be wisdom on the part of every soul who has
been taught the gospel, to here and now make a daily conscious and sincere effort to live it. 
And this effort should continue to the end of mortal life. Failing to make such an effort, a
person identifies himself as one who does not believe the Lord, for, said he, ". . . if ye
believe me, ye will labor while it is called today"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/25#25">D&amp;C 64:25</a>).
</p><p>
That we may, by laboring today, inherit the great blessings we have heard so much about in
this conference, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
