<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Responsibility Placed on a Latter-day Saint</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bernard P. Brockbank</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bernard P. Brockbank, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 124-126</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brothers and sisters, it is a humbling and frightening experience to be in this position and one
of great responsibility. We have so many interesting things happen to us these days that we
little realize some of the great circumstances we find ourselves in.
</p><p>
As I was reflecting just a moment ago, I think two of the greatest missionaries that the world
has ever known are right here today&mdash;our Prophet David O. McKay and our Tabernacle
Choir. It is good to be in the presence of good people. I am going to take just a moment and
reflect on one or two of the simple important teachings of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
In preaching to the missionaries many times I have said that these commandments are the test
of a missionary. I believe also they are the test of a Saint. The Savior had the ability to put
many volumes and many sermons into few words, and we find ourselves taking inventory
when we read into the depth of his great counsel. These commandments
have been mentioned many times. You are well-acquainted with them.
</p><p>
Jesus said, "But I say unto you, Love your enemies" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
That's not just so many words, you
know, that's a responsibility placed on a Saint. Quite often if we have an enemy, "Well, if he
doesn't like me I don't like him. I can get along without him." There is no Christianity in this
attitude. When Christianity is shown, it's when the individual says, "Well, I love you no
matter how you act or feel toward me." When one does this, the tide of evil, the tide of
degeneration is stopped, love takes the place of enmity. Wouldn't it be great if we were all
Christians with love for all in our hearts; there would be no enmity.
</p><p>
"Bless them that curse you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
Have you ever had someone curse you, and it made you angry,
so you cursed them back? You showed them how to curse. Satan enjoys that; there's no
Christianity in cursing back. There's a responsibility if someone curses you, and in this
Church it is not so unusual to be cursed or spoken against. "Bless them that curse you," a
responsibility as a Christian&mdash;a follower of Jesus Christ. We must bless them that curse us.
Wouldn't it be great if you would visit and bless them. "God bless you, I want you to know
you have my blessings." Can you see the tide of Christianity turning back the evil trend of
cursing among God's children.
</p><p>
It's not too easy to be a Christian. I'm only on one verse here of the Savior's many verses.
There are four commandments in one verse (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
</p><p>
"Do good to them that hate you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
Do we always practice this commandment? Well, it is not
easy. "And pray for them that despitefully use you, and persecute you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>). Did the Savior
practice this? You know, to be a Christian, we must follow the Savior. It is easy to hide
behind Christianity, but it is not easy to be a Christian. Let's see whether the Savior practiced
what he taught.
</p><p>
I'm not going to take time because the time is very short, but remember when the Savior was
hanging on the cross, his accusers, his murderers at his feet; he could have said something
rather severe and scolding, but no, he practiced what he preached. "Father in heaven, forgive
them" (see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/34#34">Luke 23:34</a>).
He prayed for those who persecuted him and bitterly abused him.
</p><p>
I'm going to turn over a page to hurry, in this same great sermon. "Enter ye in at the strait
gate: for wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there be
which go in thereat" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/13#13">Matt. 7:13</a>).
It's real wide, the gate's wide, and there is a great
multitude headed for it and many there be which go in thereat. These are the words of the
Savior. ". . . strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto life, and few there
be that find it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/14#14">Matt. 7:14</a>).
Not many will find the gate to heaven.
</p><p>
"Beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep's clothing, but inwardly they are
ravening wolves" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/15#15">Matt. 7:15</a>).
A false prophet will teach false doctrine. Any false teacher is in that category.
</p><p>
Now the Savior gives us many wonderful keys here. "Ye shall know them by their fruits. Do
men gather grapes of thorns, or figs of thistles?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/16#16">Matt. 7:16</a>). What if you saw figs growing
on a thistle? You'd know they were out of place, wouldn't you? Grapes growing on thorns,
it's just as obvious and just as easy to tell a true prophet as it is to tell that figs are out of
place on a thistle bush.
</p><p>
Well, a God without body, parts, or passions, uncreate&mdash;and the Prophet Joseph Smith
introducing back again a God with body, parts, and passions. Man saying the Godhead is
three in one and one in three&mdash;most difficult to explain and understand. Joseph Smith
restoring the knowledge of three separate Personages. You know the agnostic could say they
are both wrong, but it is obvious they are not both right. It's as obvious as a fig on a thistle
that one is opposite the other.
</p><p>
Jesus had Twelve Apostles&mdash;many churches do not have apostles. Our message is not a
difficult one to deliver to the world as soon as we can prepare the world for it. Then the Lord
clarifies this, "Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit, but a corrupt tree bringeth
forth evil fruit.
</p><p>
"A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring
forth good fruit" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/17-18#17">Matt. 7:17-18</a>).
President McKay does not build the kingdom of Satan, he
builds the kingdom of God. He teaches the same gospel and doctrines that Jesus Christ and
the apostles taught.
</p><p>
Our prophet has asked us all to be missionaries&mdash;every member a missionary. That's the way
to build this Church. Wouldn't it be great if all two million each brought one soul into the
Church. How many of you brought one new member into the Church last year? The prophet
asked us to do it under the inspiration of the Lord because the Lord knows how to build his
Church.
</p><p>
What if it meant your life if you did not bring a soul in this coming year? You'd have him or
her, wouldn't you? You'd bring your soul in. This is just a little way for the Lord to test and
tell whether we love our neighbor as ourselves (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>).
We'd do pretty nearly anything to save and preserve our own lives.
</p><p>
I bear witness that God lives, that David O. McKay is his prophet and mouthpiece. It is good
to be in your presence. May the Lord bless each one, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
