<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Repentance&mdash;Spelled with 7 R's</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder William J. Critchlow, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">William J. Critchlow, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1962, pp. 36-39</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
People in all of the nations of the earth need to repent. The need is urgent. This declaration of
need constitutes an indictment of guilt&mdash;transgressions are implied.
</p><p>
For what need we repent I may be asked? My answer: 
</p><p>
For the same sins that brought low the impenitent inhabitants of Sodom and Gomorrah; 
</p><p>
for the identical sins that brought extinction to the impenitent Nephites on this continent; 
</p><p>
for the same sins that brought destruction to the impenitent souls in Noah's day; 
</p><p>
for the same sins that will bring the judgments of God upon the impenitent people in our
day&mdash;unless we repent.
</p><p>
". . . as it was in the days of Noe, so shall it be also in the days of the Son
of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/26#26">Luke 17:26</a>).
</p><p>
Our world has become a modern Babylon. Cities like Sodom and Gomorrah dot the earth.
</p><p>
"If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/1/8#8">1 Jn. 1:8</a>).
</p><p>
In a very few moments, one could inventory in the mind his or her more serious
transgressions&mdash;those already repented of, and those still to be repented of. It will take a
little longer, and the list will grow a little longer, if we add to it our sins of omission.
Sometimes our sins of omission are greater than our sins of commission. Now, how did we
rid ourselves of sin or how shall we rid ourselves of the sins so listed? Is there a pattern or
formula for repenting? Definitely there is, in my humble opinion, and those who will pause to
list their sins will, by so doing, be taking the first step in the repenting process. In such a
mental inventory we automatically recognize certain of our acts as transgressions, otherwise
we would not list them. No problem can be solved, no sin can be resolved until it is first
recognized. Recognition of sin therefore is the first step in the repenting processes.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul assented to the stoning of Stephen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/58#58">Acts 7:58</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/20#20">Acts 22:20</a>).
He held the cloaks of those who threw
the stones. Not until he was chastened by the Lord did he recognize the full extent of his sin.
Great was his remorse thereafter.
</p><p>
A convert to the Church was unaware that he was transgressing a law of God as he imbibed
tea, coffee, and tobacco until he was taught God's law of health&mdash;the Word of Wisdom. His
conversion forced upon him recognition of the law. Violations thereafter constituted
transgressions.
</p><p>
For the purpose of my theme I propose to spell repentance with seven big capital "R's." The
first "R" obviously stands for <i>recognition.</i>
</p><p>
Paul's godly sorrow (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/7/10#10">2 Cor. 7:10</a>)
for his sin suggests the second "R"&mdash;<i>remorse</i>. Our Lord, teaching his
followers to pray, said: ". . . lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/13#13">Matt. 6:13</a>).
</p><p>
He said that nearly two thousand years ago. Brought up to date, the 1962 version seems to be:
"Lead us not into temptation but deliver us from being caught."
</p><p>
Sorrow for being caught in sin is not remorse.
</p><p>
The third "R" stands for <i>relating</i>. All sins should be confessed unto the Lord.
</p><p>
"Where," said Elder Marion G. Romney, "one's transgressions are of such a nature as would,
unrepented of, put in jeopardy his right to membership or fellowship in the Church of Jesus
Christ, full and effective confession would, in my judgment, require confession by the
repentant sinner to his bishop or other proper presiding Church officer&mdash;not that the Church
officer could forgive the sin (this power rests in the Lord himself and those only to whom he
specifically delegates it) but rather that the Church, acting through its duly appointed officers,
might with full knowledge of the facts take such action with respect to church discipline as
the circumstances merit" (<i>Conf. Report</i>, Oct. 1955).
</p><p>
The fourth "R" stands for <i>restitution.</i>
</p><p>
"For misconduct which offends another, confession should also be made to the offended one,
and his forgiveness sought" (<i>Conf. Report</i>, Oct. 1955).
</p><p>
Restitution means to restore&mdash;to repair the damage. Three boys about to receive scouting
awards were apprehended breaking street lights. And were they sorry for being caught! Later,
but before they accepted their awards, they <i>recognized</i> their acts as unbecoming Eagle Scouts
and with a true feeling of <i>remorse</i> went to the power company to <i>relate</i> their transgression
and offered to make <i>restitution</i> by paying for the lights. Incidentally, the only restitution
exacted was that they be guardians of those lights. From then on the lights burned on and on
and on.
</p><p>
Some things cannot be restored. Street lights can be replaced, embezzled funds and stolen
property may be returned, but how does one make restitution for the sin of
blasphemy&mdash;taking the name of God in vain. Blasphemy, used so freely to emphasize our conversation, is
the most thoughtless of all conversational crimes. How does one make restitution for
lies&mdash;for hearing false witness?
</p><p>
The wagging tongue like&mdash;
</p><p>
"The moving finger writes: and having writ,<br />
          Moves on: nor all thy piety nor wit<br />
          Shall lure it back to cancel half a line,<br />
          Nor all thy tears wash out a word if it."
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp;                                        &mdash;Omar Khayyam
</p><p>
Paul's sincere apology to the Lord for assenting to the stoning of Stephen never brought back
Stephen's life. Nor will all the prayers of repentant sinners ever restore virtue to a maid or a
boy.
</p><p>
The fifth "R" stands for <i>resolution</i>. It implies a firm resolve to forsake our sins. There are two
kinds of resolutions, one is called the New Year type. These come cheaper by the dozen and
are branded with insincerity and guaranteed to last only till the next temptation. Few ever last
longer than the winter snows. The other is the sincere type resolved and guaranteed to last
forever.
</p><p>
"By this ye may know if a man repenteth of his sins&mdash;behold, he will confess them and
forsake them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/43#43">D&amp;C 58:43</a>).
</p><p>
Resolves which are repeatedly broken merit no forgiveness.
</p><p>
". . . go your ways and sin no more; but unto that soul who sinneth shall the former sins
return, saith the Lord your God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/7#7">D&amp;C 82:7</a>).
</p><p>
We do not trifle with the Lord.
</p><p>
A resolution is an expression of faith and like faith needs to be supported by works. The next
step therefore involves works. It is represented by a big "R" which stands for <i>reformation</i>. A
resolution is an intention to do well. Reformation is actually doing well.
</p><p>
". . . let every man learn his duty," said the Lord, ". . . he that learns not his duty and shows
himself not approved shall not be counted worthy to stand" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100#99">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>).
</p><p>
Transgressors seek the forgiveness of Heavenly Father. Their fellow men will forgive "seventy
times seven" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/21-22#21">Matt. 18:21-22</a>)
because they have been so commanded.
</p><p>
"I, the Lord, will forgive whom I will forgive, but of you it is required to forgive all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/10#10">D&amp;C 64:10</a>).
</p><p>
To earn his forgiveness one should go the extra mile, forsaking not only his sins but adding
the while devotion and service to prove his love for him. Such devotion and service
constitutes <i>reformation</i>.
</p><p>
Now if in the process of repenting we follow these six steps, represented by the six
"R's"&mdash;may I list them: <i>Recognition, remorse, relating, restitution, resolution, and reformation</i>
we should have placed ourselves in a position to enjoy the seventh step represented by another
great big "R" which stands for <i>realization</i>&mdash;realization of the happiness that comes from
righteous living. Happiness is righteousness, said President McKay. ". . . if there be no
righteousness there be no happiness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/13#13">2 Ne. 2:13</a>).
A realization too, that we are forgiven
by him whose forgiveness really counts, and a peaceful feeling will burn within our bosoms,
and our minds will be at peace. Elder Sterling Sill told us this morning that the number "7"
was a symbol of completeness. These seven "R's" accordingly symbolize a complete process
of repentance.
</p><p>
If spelling repentance with so many "R's" complicates for you the repenting process, be of
good cheer. Many good souls who couldn't spell it with seven "R's" or any other way have
sincerely repented and have been forgiven. One's conscience seemingly has a way of
conforming unwittingly. So let your conscience be your guide. "The sum-bonum of the
proposition" (Henry Drummond) is repent&mdash;everybody repent.
</p><p>
"If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all
unrighteousness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/1/9#9">1 Jn. 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
After forty years of wandering in the wilderness, Moses brought the children of Israel to the
borders of the promised land. There they were halted so they could sanctify themselves before
they entered.
</p><p>
Today after six thousand years of mortal living, dying, striving, and wandering upon the face
of the earth, the children of God stand on the threshold of another promised land&mdash;a
promised millennium of peace, and just as God sifted out the impenitent in Moses' day, so
will he sift out the impenitent in our day before the dawn of the millennial morn. We have so
little time left to sanctify ourselves&mdash;it's later than we think. How else can we sanctify
ourselves save by repentance? I plead with all&mdash;give it top priority. Our Lord
gave it priority when he counseled: 
</p><p>
"Hearken ye people of my Church . . . Hearken ye people from afar; and ye that are upon the
islands of the sea . . . Prepare ye, prepare ye, for that which is to come, for the Lord is nigh .
. . For I the Lord cannot look upon sin with the least degree of allowance . . . Nevertheless,
he that repents . . . and doeth the commandments of the Lord shall be forgiven, and he that
repents not, from him shall be taken even the light which he has received" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1,12,31-33#1">D&amp;C 1:1,12,31-33</a>).
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
