<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Promise unto the Children</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1943, pp. 69-73</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is a real pleasure to have the privilege of attending this conference. Last night most of you
were present at the bishops' meeting in the Assembly Hall, and while we were together two
and a half hours, we only covered a very small portion of the program in which you bishops,
particularly, are as much interested as are we.
</p><p>
THE AARONIC PRIESTHOOD PROGRAM
</p><p>
I thought tonight I would like to say a few words about the Aaronic Priesthood program of
the Church. I am very grateful for my assignment to labor with the young men and for the
fine work that is being done by the bishops and their associates in their behalf. I feel we have
a program that really is effective.
</p><p>
I have no thought of criticism for the past, but in trying to follow our program of a record of
every boy, and a monthly boys' leadership meeting, where the bishopric Sit at the head and
with them those who are interested in the care of the Aaronic Priesthood in the wards&mdash;the
Mutual, and Sunday School officers, who also are charged with the responsibility of working
with the same age group&mdash;it seems to me that we have been able to keep closer in touch with
the boys.
</p><p>
For instance, through this program we found in one ward thirty-three boys between the ages
of twelve and twenty-one who held no Priesthood. Another ward had twenty. When the
bishop discovered this, he was as much surprised as anyone could be. He had never checked
before.
</p><p>
When visiting a stake recently, it was reported to me that a son of one of our recent General
Authorities had never been ordained, even to the office of a deacon. When his own son was
to be ordained, the bishop asked him if he held such Priesthood that he could officiate, and he
had to apologize and tell the bishop that he had never even been ordained a deacon. A time
had been set, but for some reason he could not come, and no one followed the matter up to
find out why.
</p><p>
Only this week I learned that one of our present General Authorities was not baptized until he
was fifteen, because there was no checkup in the ward. We now have a program whereby
every boy is being looked after&mdash;and we are trying to consider the boys more individually
rather than in groups. It is my impression that we will come to a day in the Church when our
greatest achievements will be through individual work.
</p><p>
INDIVIDUAL WORK WITH BOYS
</p><p>
In our work this winter with the Aaronic Priesthood, we are studying in the teachers' training
course, Dr. Stott's book, <i>How to Win Boys</i>, and the author paraphrases a statement of the
Master as he went along the Sea of Galilee and gathered to himself the fishermen, saying,
"Come, and I will make you fishers of men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/19#19">Matt. 4:19</a>);
Dr. Stott says, "Come, and I will make you
fishers of boys."
</p><p>
Then he indicates that all over the world there are literally thousands and tens of thousands of
boys, waiting to be caught, if we only use the right kind of bait.
</p><p>
In a demonstration of a boys' monthly leadership meeting in a stake recently, one of the
brethren in reporting a visit he had made to a home said: "You'll never get John into his
Priesthood meeting on Sunday morning so long as there is snow on the mountain so he can
go skiing." After the discussion was ended and no solution was offered to get John off the
mountain, I said to the bishop, "Bishop, are you going to leave John out on the mountain
skiing on Sunday mornings?"
</p><p>
We have a feeling that there should be sufficient genius of leadership in this group with the
bishopric at the head assisted by their helpers in the Aaronic Priesthood, the M.I.A., and
Sunday School workers, that when they pool their wisdom, certainly they can find the kind of
bait that will bring John off the mountain on Sunday morning.
</p><p>
There are some of us, I fear, who have the feeling that there are only a few that will be
saved. I am not unmindful of the fact that the Savior said, "Strait is the gate and narrow is the
way" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/14#14">Matt. 7:14</a>),
but I also remembered that in the 76th section of the D&amp;C, the Lord indicates that He
will save all the works of His hands, except the Sons of Perdition
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/42-43#42">D&amp;C 76:42-43</a>), and I have never been able
to feel that the sons of Latter-day Saint fathers and mothers born under the covenant, are
likely to be so classified. They are born heirs of all the gifts and blessings of the Gospel of
Jesus Christ. So, as far as I am concerned, I believe if we will do our duty, with the help of
the Almighty, we need not fear that any of our boys will be lost.
</p><p>
Now, when we gather them in, it is very important that we have something for them. They
want to be fed, and I think besides teaching them their duties in the Priesthood, one of the
greatest things we ought to have in mind is to try to plant in their hearts a testimony of the
Gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
A TESTIMONY OF THE GOSPEL OF GREAT WORTH
</p><p>
My experience in the Church has taught me that the most powerful motivating thing I know
of in this world is a testimony of the Gospel. Possessing it, men and women will do anything;
they will make any sacrifice. When we listened here yesterday to the testimonies of Brother
Kimball and Brother Benson, whom we sustained as new members of the Quorum of the
Twelve, both indicated that they were making financial sacrifices. I had the privilege of
attending Washington Stake conference a week ago last Sunday with President Benson, and he
told me of some of the financial offers that had been made to him. I took occasion before the
people of the stake to compliment them on the honor that had come to them in the call of
their stake president, but I assured them that Brother Benson would make great financial
sacrifices, but God granted unto the children of men blessings that were worth far more than
money, and reminded them of when Peter and John went to the temple and at the gate thereof
found a man who had been a cripple from his youth, and when he asked alms at their hands,
Peter said: "Silver and gold have I none, but such as I have, give I thee. In
the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, rise up and walk." And immediately the cripple's feet
and ankle bones received strength, and he walked into the temple with Peter and John
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/1-8#1">Acts 3:1-8</a>).
</p><p>
You do not buy gifts like that with money. They are the riches of heaven, that come through
faith and a testimony of the Gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Recently I read the new book by Brother Hinckley on the life of President Daniel H. Wells,
and I was greatly impressed with the power of his testimony. When he saw the Saints move
toward the West, although he was not a member of the Church and at that time possessed
much property and a wife who was opposed to the Church, and a son, he had to make a
choice to cast his lot with the Saints or remain with his wife and son and his property. He left
his property to her, and left her and the boy behind, going on with the Saints; and the Lord
multiplied unto him because of his sacrifice, and that because of his testimony of the Gospel.
</p><p>
You and I know, as we have witnessed on every side, particularly in our ministry in this
Church, how marvelously people sacrifice, and how willingly they do it when their souls are
touched with a testimony of the Gospel.
</p><p>
WILLING SACRIFICES
</p><p>
I think of a little woman in our ward. We as a bishopric approached her and her husband,
who was not a member of the Church, and asked them if they were in a position to send their
son on a mission. We said, "We don't know whether you have any rich relatives who can
help you." We knew they were of meager circumstances. We said, "The boy is worthy to go, and
we would be proud to have him represent our ward."
</p><p>
By that time tears were trickling down the little mother's face, and she said, "Bishop, if you
will send my boy on a mission, I'll see that he has the money if I have to work every day he
is gone to keep him in the mission field."
</p><p>
When living in California, I passed a bakery night after night on my way home from work
and saw one of our good sisters in her little bakery uniform clerking while she kept two of
her sons in the mission field.
</p><p>
I would like to see this testimony planted in the hearts of our boys and our girls, and I want
you to know that I know boys can have a testimony of the Gospel, even in their youth.
</p><p>
THE PROMISE OF SPIRITUAL GIFTS
</p><p>
A statement reached us at the Presiding Bishop's office a few days ago from one of our
educators who in teaching a Sunday School class made this statement: "I don't know whether
it would be proper for us to teach our young people to read <i>Leaves from My Journal</i>, by
Wilford Woodruff, for fear they might expect similar spiritual experiences, and be
disappointed."
</p><p>
I wonder if there are really very many Latter-day Saints who would be
afraid to promise unto the youth of Zion the spiritual gifts and blessings that God, the Eternal
Father Himself, has promised.
</p><p>
We cannot offer our young people the Bible as the word of God, or the standard Church
works, and believe only a small portion of that which is written therein.
</p><p>
After the Savior was resurrected, He commissioned His disciples to go into all the world and
preach the Gospel to every creature, and then he promised them spiritual gifts and blessings as
a result of their faith (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-18#15">Mark 16:15-18</a>).
I find nowhere in all Holy Writ where the Savior ever rescinded the
promises He made unto those who would accept His Gospel.
</p><p>
On the day of Pentecost, the Spirit of God was poured out like cloven tongues of fire, and
Peter, representing the apostles, spoke until men were moved upon and smitten in their hearts,
and said: "Men and brethren, what shall we do?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37#37">Acts 2:37</a>).
And Peter, the mouthpiece of God upon the earth, replied:
</p><p>
Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of
sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38-39#38">Acts 2:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
I want you to know that as far as I am concerned, that promise has been made good in my
life, and I have faith it will be made good in the lives of my children and their children, unto
the latest generation, if they have faith in God and are willing to keep His commandments.
</p><p>
Then I remind you that in the last chapter of the Book of Mormon, Moroni writes at some
length on this subject. He tells of the marvelous gifts of the Holy Ghost, and says that by the
power of the Holy Ghost might we know the truth of the words contained in that book, for
"by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/5#5">Moro. 10:5</a>). Then
he warns us that we deny not the gifts of God, and enumerates them and then adds that these
gifts shall never be taken away as long as the world shall stand, except according to the
unbelief of the children of men (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/7-25#7">Moro. 10:7-25</a>).
</p><p>
Closing that historic record with that promise, I feel we ought to live to anticipate and expect
the gifts of the Spirit of God. . . I was in this tabernacle when Wilford Woodruff told&mdash;and I
think it was his last public address&mdash;how marvelously the Lord had led and guided and
inspired him, and how we would not have Bishop So-and-So, if he had not heeded the
promptings of the Spirit of God not to take the company of emigrants on the boat down in
New Orleans, how that by the inspiration of the Spirit he arose in the night aria moved his
team and wagon just in time to escape the falling oak that had stood there all those years, etc.
</p><p>
That made an impression upon my life. I would like my children impressed with that kind of
inspiration, spiritual power, spiritual gifts. Now, as I look back over my life, I want to bear
testimony to you, my brethren, here this night, that the Lord has been kind to me, and I have
had evidences enough all through my ministry to know that the sweetest thing in this world
that I know anything about is the companionship of the Spirit of God, and the gifts and
blessings that come by virtue of the same.
</p><p>
A KNOWLEDGE OF GOD COMES THROUGH HIS SPIRIT
</p><p>
It is my testimony that when you read the words of the Master that "this is life eternal, that
they might know Thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom Thou hast sent"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>),
you are not going to know Him just because you read about Him in books; you are
going to know Him because you have partaken of His Spirit and of his power, and you have
been lifted up until you know there is a power in this world so much greater than yours that it
leaves no room for doubt.
</p><p>
We should remember the words of Paul when he said that the things of God are understood
by the Spirit of God, and the things of man are understood by the spirit of man, and the
natural man understandeth not the things of God, for they are foolishness unto him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11-15#11">1 Cor. 2:11-15</a>). We do
not want natural men teaching our boys in the Aaronic Priesthood; we want men of God, who
have faith in God and faith in His promises, and faith in spiritual gifts and spiritual power.
</p><p>
You brethren do not need to be afraid to promise your children or the youth of Zion that the
blessings and gifts of the Holy Ghost will be theirs if they will live for them. You do not
have to fulfill these promises. God, the Eternal Father, who made them, will fulfill them. And
when they have a testimony and spiritual conviction in their souls, you do not need to worry
about your boys or your girls, no matter where they go.
</p><p>
God bless you, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
