<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Tabernacle</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Stephen L Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Stephen L Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1952, pp. 43-49</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I sat in the Tabernacle a short time ago listening to beautiful music. After the concert was
over I was a little embarrassed inwardly to recognize that I had heard but very little of what
went forward, for almost at the beginning of the program my thoughts turned to this great
building in which we are met today. Somehow or other, its place in our history and its
connotations assumed such proportions in my thinking that I decided that it might be worthy
of a little of our attention as we ponder the progress and mission of the restored Church of
our Lord.
</p><p>
This Tabernacle of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, erected on what we
designate as Temple Square in Salt Lake City, Utah, has come to be one of the most
interesting and widely known buildings in western America, and perhaps in all America,
excluding structures at the national capital and at points of great historic interest in the
formation of the republic.
</p><p>
The first work on the Tabernacle was begun in the spring and summer of 1863. The first
foundation stone was laid July 26, 1864. The Tabernacle was completed, so far as to be
usable, by October 6, 1867, when the first conference was held in the building. The following
is a quoted notation in the record: 
</p><p>
"The gates to the Temple Block were opened at nine o'clock, and the people flooded in. Long
before ten o'clock, the time for the commencement of the conference, the seats in the great
Tabernacle were filled, the aisles and door ways were crowded, and many were left outside.
The stand was filled with the Church officials and the various choirs who were present to take
part in the service."
</p><p>
The conditions here described are not difficult for the present generation to visualize.
</p><p>
The organ was only one-third completed by this time but was used to accompany the singing.
Temporary seats were used since the installation of permanent seats was not completed until
sometime during the summer of 1868. The gallery was not completed until later, and was first
used at the postponed general conference of the Church on May 5, 1870. It is recorded that
this additional seating capacity was much appreciated, and that the installation of the gallery
improved the acoustics of the building.
</p><p>
The Tabernacle was not dedicated until October of 1875. I shall speak of the dedication later.
</p><p>
Perhaps one of the first significant items about the building is its size. It is 250 feet long by
150 feet wide; 6 feet to the ceiling, 75 feet to the top of the roof, standing upon 44 stone
pillars with 16 doors 10 feet wide, and 4 doors 4 1/2 feet wide, allowing the exit of 13,000
persons in 5 minutes. Its architect, Henry Grow, claimed that it was the largest hall in the
world unsupported by columns. I have made no research to determine for how long a time the
architect's statement may have been true.
</p><p>
The huge capacity of the building is most tangible evidence of the firm conviction of the
builders in the growth and destiny of the cause they upheld. Without its great size it never
could have served its mighty purpose. In the early days of our settlement in these valleys of
the mountains, communication was very difficult. Even after the coming of the telegraph and
the railroads, people had to come and see and hear to get correct impressions and information.
Had the building been smaller, countless thousands would have been deprived of opportunities
and blessings they have most highly prized. Then, too, it seems to me worthy of note that the
building was built just about as large as it could have been built so that an audience within it
could be made to hear, long before the day of electrical magnification of sound. The acoustics
of the Tabernacle have been the subject of comment by scientific persons and others for many
years. I don't know that a full treatise has ever been written, but it would make a deserving
and interesting thesis. This great structure, enormous at the time of its building, is the physical
embodiment of a mighty concept that the work of God is expansive, all-embracing, with room
for all who will come and listen and receive.
</p><p>
The Tabernacle has been a great cultural center. For eighty years it has housed substantially
all of the major concerts, symphonies, bands, choirs, and vocal and instrumental artists who
have come to this section of the country. It is safe to say that without it the communities in
this area would have been deprived of innumerable opportunities to see and hear the
outstanding talent of the world. It has been the scene of great pageants that will long live in
our memories; and in addition to being the greatest stage for artistic presentations in our
community, it has been a place of instruction and rehearsal for thousands upon thousands of
children, young people, and adults, developing talent and artistic appreciation wholly beyond
our power to measure. Throughout the years the building has generally been contributed to
almost every conceivable cultural project which has come our way.
</p><p>
In thus extending the use of the building, the Church has had what I believe to be a unique
experience. I don't know that there is a comparable situation in the country. It has always
been the effort to maintain standards of conduct in this building and on the grounds
roundabout which comport with the beliefs and standards of the Church. Those who come
here are asked not to smoke or drink or use profane language, and I think that, with few
exceptions, they who are not of our faith, and who do not practice our standards, have been
sufficiently respectful of our views to observe the decorum of this building. We appreciate
their consideration.
</p><p>
This Tabernacle has been, in some respects, a civic center. It has been a forum for Presidents
of the United States, candidates for the Presidency, notables from foreign countries, and
lecturers, and for the discussion of some of the most important issues which have ever
confronted the nation. It has been used as a gathering hall for great national conventions, and
it has played a part in the advancement of important civic causes. It has paid tributes of
homage and honor to our national heroes; it has met the demands of emergency; it has been
through the years an invaluable asset in our community life.
</p><p>
More important than any of these however, in the history of this great Tabernacle, is its place
and function as a house of worship.
</p><p>
Since singing usually begins our public worship, at this point I would like to speak a little of
the choirs of the Tabernacle. Here is and has been for over seventy-five years the home of the
Tabernacle Choir. I would not venture to say whether the Tabernacle has made the choir or
the choir has made the Tabernacle famous. It is sufficient to know that all through the years
we have had a great choir in a great setting. As many as sixty years ago the Tabernacle Choir
had a national reputation. Through eisteddfods, its high placement in contest in the World's
Fair, and through concerts in big cities, east and west, it early attained renown in musical
circles. In recent times, through national and international broadcasts, the Tabernacle Choir
and the Spoken Word are household words throughout the land. During its history, both
before and after enlarged facilities became available, two aspects of its work have been
outstanding and conspicuous: First, the devotion of the members; and next, the excellence of
its leadership. I doubt if any comparable volunteer organization of its size and responsibilities
can present as fine a record for as long a time. The Church is and has been for these many
years proud of this great organization, and I believe we all feel a lasting debt of gratitude to
the great conductors, the great organists and technicians, and the great members of this
illustrious organization. I attribute their greatness, in large measure, to the deeply religious
fervor which has always actuated them. I know that with their artistic temperaments they have
loved to sing, but the consistency of their performance has come out of a sense of
conscientious duty and opportunity to serve the Lord and advance his kingdom. From that
sentiment have come some of the great contributions which the choir has made&mdash;contribution
which breathe the spirit and essence of the latter-day work, contribution which have inspirited
the missionary for his work, which have honored and venerated the pioneers who laid the
foundations, which have extolled the glory and virtue of Christ our Lord and his honored
prophets, and which have brought comfort and solace to the poor, the discouraged and
bereaved. Here is a choir which, through the generations, has seen purpose in its work, which
has striven steadfastly to advance a great cause, which has made art serve its Author, the Lord
of the universe. God bless our Tabernacle Choir, from the beginning through the generations,
as an emissary of art and truth in the earth.
</p><p>
Housed within the building is the great organ. Its impressive facade of colossal pipes and
ornamental column and caps makes it appear as an ornate temple within the auditorium,
beautiful and intriguing to behold. The history of its initial construction is itself a glorious
record of pioneer achievement. Its melodic voice now heard in nearly all civilized portions of
the globe has been a thing alive, proclaiming in sonorous and tender tones the solemn and the
sweet message of the Savior's gospel to all who have the heart and the ear to interpret and
apply. Just as the choir is integral with the Tabernacle, so is the organ with both.
</p><p>
I stand today in a pulpit sanctified by its history. When I recall the noble servants of our
Heavenly Father who have stood here and given inspired counsel to the people, and borne
testimony with such power and conviction and spirit as to electrify every soul who heard;
when I contemplate the operation of the still, small voice, which has come from simple and
lowly word given here, which have touched the hearts and sympathies of the people; when I
think of the vast volume of precious truth which has been proclaimed from this stand, I feel
very small and weak within it. My only comfort comes from the realization that the noble
ones who have graced this pulpit have been called to speak here as I have been called, and
that they were common men, so far as the aristocracy of the world is concerned, drawn from
all walks of life, just as my brethren and I are today.
</p><p>
What a difference in the history of the Tabernacle it would have made had the building come
to be merely a great preacher's church. We have had in America such preachers and such
churches. For periods of time eloquent men have enthralled audiences, achieve wide
distinction, and have undoubtedly done much good. In the providence of the Lord, this pulpit
has never been any one man's forum. Rather it has been the oracle of a divine dispensation
where the cause has overshadowed the man, where humility has higher rating than
self-assurance, where worship is measured in deeds rather than protestations.
</p><p>
Ponder for a moment, my brethren and sisters, and all who listen, the glorious and vital truths
which have been proclaimed in this building&mdash;the nature and composition of the Godhead,
the organization of the universe, the history and placement of man in the earth, his purpose in
living, and the divine destiny set for him, the laws governing his conduct and his eligibility
for exaltation in the celestial presence the true concept of family life in the eternal progression
of the race, the truth about liberty and the place of governments in the earth, the correct
concept of property, its acquisition and distribution, the sure foundations for peace,
brotherhood, and universal justice. All these elemental things, and many others incident
thereto, have been the burden of the message of truth which has come from this building
through the generations.
</p><p>
These messages have not changed with the passing of time. The Lord revealed these enduring
principles. They are part and parcel of eternal truth. Man may, by his faithful research and
study, discover more about them, but he will never change them. I would not discourage the
inquiring mind in its exploration of the universe and quest for truth. My only caution is to
begin with recognition of the divine source of truth and the revealed word of God.
</p><p>
What confidence and assurance it brings to us to know that our men and women of today,
surrounded by an environment radically different from that of our forebears who brought this
great building into existence, proclaim the same doctrine as did they. How upsetting it would
be if we had to choose between the principles and doctrines of their time and ours. We in this
Tabernacle hear the same message as did the people in Kirtland and Nauvoo.
</p><p>
It is true that methods and practices change. They have done in the past, and they may be
expected to in the future. It is within the province of a receptive priesthood, obedient to the
inspiration of our Father, to adopt and adjust methods, looking toward the advancement of his
kingdom. It is also within the province of his chosen servants to interpret and apply the law,
but they will never change it, for the law of God is eternal.
</p><p>
I wish to say a word about the comfort and solace which have come to our Father's children
in this great building. Funeral services have been held here for many noble men and some
women. Heavenly music has been rendered, so inspiring and touching that it seemed as if
those from the other world could have joined in the singing. Sermons depicting the transition
into immortality, and expounding the atonement and redemption wrought by our Savior, have
been given with such convincing assurance as to elevate the aggrieved and despondent to the
sublimity of resignation, hope and firm faith. Within these sacred walls have the great of our
community found opportunity for the expression of their noblest thoughts and convictions, and
from here they have been laid to rest in the closing of their lives. All the life dramas that
have here been enacted, all the vital episodes in this historic setting will never be recounted;
but they are all known to one who keeps the record, and every resolution, every change of
heart, every contrition arising out of the service rendered in this building, will be a fitting
tribute to the purposes it has served.
</p><p>
In some respects the Tabernacle may appropriately be designated as the center of our
missionary work. More sermons expounding the doctrines of the Church and calling the world
to repentance and defining the way to life eternal have been preached from this pulpit than
from any other place in the Church. These sermons, testifying to the divine calling of the
Prophet Joseph Smith in the restoration of the holy gospel, have been heard not only by the
vast congregations who have assembled here, but also they have been printed, translated into
various languages, and circulated in many countries throughout the earth. The pronouncements
from this very stand have furnished to our armies of missionaries, in large measure, the
material for their work among the people to whom they are sent. In the earlier days the
missionaries were personally called from the stand in this Tabernacle. One can well imagine
the thrill and deep impression made by such procedure. Here the courses of life were changed
by assignments from the Presiding Brethren. Here the spirit of sacrifice chastened the soul,
and men and women were dedicated to the work of God. Here was the true spirit of
missionary work&mdash;love and sacrifice for fellow man&mdash;developed and fostered.
</p><p>
In more recent times the Tabernacle with its wonderful Sunday morning program, has made
an invaluable contribution to our missionary endeavor in bringing to our missionaries a more
kindly and considerate reception as they bear the message of the gospel from door to door out
in the world. Also in later years, with visitors to Temple Square reaching more than a million
a year, this historic structure has achieved a position subordinate to but few places in the
country in tourist interest. Thousands there are who come here every year, whose unfavorable
preconceptions are altered, and who must go away with unforgettable impressions emanating
from the teachings and influences coming from this building and the grounds round about.
Surely a large part of Isaiah's prophecy has been realized. The Lord's house has been
established in the top of the mountains, and many nations flow unto it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/2#2">Isa. 2:2</a>). We await the day which
will surely come when the remainder of this great prediction shall be fulfilled, when
</p><p>
. . . many people shall go and say, Come ye, and let us go up to the mountain of the
Lord, to the house of the God of Jacob and he will teach us of his ways, and we will
walk in his paths: for out of Zion shall go forth the law, and the word of the Lord
from Jerusalem (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/3#3">Isa. 2:3</a>).
</p><p>
Can we doubt, my brethren and sisters, that these things have been wrought by the hand and
power of the Lord? In all humility I bear witness that here is the seat of the government of
the kingdom of God, here is the place where the authorized servants of our Lord are sustained
and confirmed by the voice of the people. Here in this venerated Tabernacle has every
President of the Church, save only one been upheld as prophet, seer, and revelator, and
President of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. From here has gone forth the law
out of Zion, and the blessings, the love and compassion of the servants of the Lord for his
children.
</p><p>
For nearly half a century I have been the beneficiary of the teachings and the influence
coming from this historic building. I thank God for it. I do not wish to worship things
material but I bow before the inspired vision and the lofty aspirations which brought this
sacred edifice into being. If my regard for it, and my meager recital of the part it has played
in the advancement of beauty and righteousness and truth in the earth shall bring any measure
of increased deference and respect for the Tabernacle and the holy cause it represents, I shall
be profoundly grateful.
</p><p>
I said I would refer again to the dedication of this building. The notation in the record is that
the dedicatory prayer of the "New Tabernacle in Salt Lake City was read by Elder John
Taylor" on Saturday, October 9, 1875. In my opinion the prayer is a masterpiece in
composition, and in its comprehensive recital of the conditions and aspirations of the people
at that time. It breathes a spirit of humility, repentance, deep gratitude, and a faith so realistic
and compelling as to overcome all obstacles in the achievement of the mighty destiny
conceived for God's work in the world. I wish every member of the Church could read it.
<i>The Deseret News</i> printed it three-quarters of a century ago. Perhaps they might care to do it
again at some convenient time. This remarkable prayer went into great detail. In it were
dedicated not only the usual components of a great building, but also "the mortar which binds
the foundation stones together," the "nails, bolts, and straps of iron, of copper, and the brass,
the zinc, the tin, and the solder wherewith the metal is soldered together," the plaster of the
building, even "all the lath and the nails and the sand and the lime," the locks and the hinges
on the doors and windows, and the paint and the varnish "and all the ornamentation of this
building, both within and without." All these minute things represented work and sacrifice
which made them sacred.
</p><p>
Every portion of the building was dedicated that it might fulfill its sacred purpose. Listen to
the words regarding this historic rostrum, where my associates of the General Authorities of
the Church now sit in your presence: "And we dedicate and consecrate that portion of this
house where our president and thy servants now are, to be a holy and sacred place wherein
thy servants may stand forth to declare thy words and minister unto thy people in the name of
thy Son forever....
</p><p>
"May thy holy angels and ministering spirits be in and round about this habitation, that when
thy servants are called upon to stand in these sacred places, to minister unto thy people, the
visions of eternity may be open to their view, and they may be filled with the spirit and
inspiration of the Holy Ghost and the gift and power of God; and let all thy people who
hearken to the words of thy servants drink freely at the fountain of the waters of life that they
may become wise unto salvation, and thereby overcome the world and be prepared for an
everlasting inheritance in the celestial kingdom of our God....
</p><p>
"We pray thee to bless the Twelve Apostles; fill them with the spirit of their office and
calling, clothe them with the intelligence of heaven, the light of revelation, and the gift and
power of God."
</p><p>
Then followed prayers, in the order indicated, for the Patriarch to the Church, for the
seventies, the high priests, the high councils, the elders, the Presiding Bishop, the priests,
teachers, and deacons. There were prayers for the Jews, for the Lamanites, and for all who
desire to do good in this and all other nations. There were prayers also for the cooperative
institutions, for those who entered into the United Order "according to thy word," the Relief
Societies, the Retrenchment Societies [the Mutuals], the Sunday Schools, and then this mighty
appeal: "Let the comforting influence of thy Holy Spirit rest upon the Saints, and the
quickening power of the Holy Ghost unite thy people in sympathy, affection, kindness and
interest. May thy people, O God, be one&mdash;one with Jesus as he is one with the Father . . .
one in spirit and feeling and interest; one in temporal and one in spiritual things, a band of
brethren; one in rolling forth the kingdom, united together by eternal, indisputable ties; one in
gathering thine elect, in building Temples and administering to the living and for the dead;
one in building up the Zion of our God; one with all the redeemed and all the angelic hosts,
in introducing the principles and laws of life to all of Adam's race and ushering in the
millennial reign."
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, I re-utter that prayer in your presence today. It is the supreme desire
and ambition of my life that this glorious destiny for our people and God's work be realized.
I testify that Jesus the Christ lives, that he is the Lord of the earth, and the Author of our
salvation, that his precious gospel and his Church have been restored and reestablished
through his chosen servant, the Prophet Joseph Smith, and that the Holy Priesthood and the
authority to represent the Lord have descended upon our present leader in authentic
succession, and that he stands before us today in humility, in heart and mind receptive to the
divine Spirit, to lead us in the greatest cause ever committed to men. I give you also my firm
conviction that if we will but follow the teachings and the counsels of our President and his
associates, all of which are in conformity with the pronouncements and principles given in
this sacred Tabernacle for nearly a century of time, there will be fulfilled every prophecy and
glorious promise ever made to Zion. God bless us to this end, I humbly pray in the name of
Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
