<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">It Has Been Glorious</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960,  pp. 114-116</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We must take time before the closing song and benediction to express a word of appreciation
to those who have contributed to the success and comfort of those who have attended this
great conference. I wish first to mention the officers of this city who have watched with care
the number of automobiles and their occupants and guided so successfully the hundreds of
cars and taken care of the thousands of people who have surrounded the block and driven to
and fro. You have noticed them on every corner&mdash;their courtesy, their attention, their
protecting and guiding care, and in your behalf, in behalf of the General Authorities
particularly, I express thanks to the city government, and to the police who have protected
your interests so carefully and so ably.
</p><p>
To the General Authorities we express deep appreciation for the
inspirational messages they have given us. We haven't had any better. The Lord has guided
us from this pulpit during our sessions in the daytime and last evening.
</p><p>
We must not be unmindful of the reporters for their fair and accurate reports through our
sessions of this conference. They have been here daily and given to the people, to their
subscribers, and to the world a very accurate report, not only in word, but in the spirit of the
messages given at this conference.
</p><p>
The fire department and the Red Cross have been on hand to render assistance and service
whenever or wherever needed. The Tabernacle ushers have rendered service in seating the
vast audiences of these conference sessions. We have expressed before, but repeat, our
appreciation to the radio and television stations&mdash;forty-five television and sixty-two radio
stations throughout our own city and the nation have carried the proceedings of this
conference. This has been the means of permitting untold thousands of persons to hear the
sermons given during the one hundred thirtieth semi-annual conference. They have rendered
that service free.
</p><p>
We appreciate especially those who have furnished the singing throughout the conference. I
remind you again of the Relief Society Singing Mothers from the Ogden and northern Utah
regions, who furnished the singing for the Friday morning and Friday afternoon sessions; also
the University of Utah Choral Society and the Bonneville Strings&mdash;the singers from the
Institute of Religion and the University of Utah choral groups, who furnished the singing for
the Saturday morning and Saturday afternoon sessions. Both those sessions were inspirational.
Think of the hours that the mothers spend practicing, and think of those young people, of the
hours and hours that they practiced, and of their willingness to come and give their talents so
impressively. And then last evening, the male members of the Tabernacle Choir came in a
body, dressed neatly, in a dignified way, and impressed the fifty thousand priesthood members
of the Church with their excellent singing.
</p><p>
Today we are privileged to have the Tabernacle Choir! Words cannot express our heartfelt
feelings for their devotion to the cause. I met one sister the other day who was a member for
many years, but she has retired. Her heart was just overflowing with gratitude for the
opportunity she had had in singing as a member of this choir. That is the feeling that these
sisters and the brethren have as they sit under the baton of this great leader and his assistant,
practicing hour after hour, day after day, week after week, month after month, to become
efficient in this great choral organization. We do not say much about it, brethren and sisters,
but we do appreciate what you are doing!
</p><p>
Too many of us are like that Scotsman of whom I told you, who had lost his wife by death,
and his neighbor came in, gave comfort, and said what a good neighbor she had been, how
thoughtful of others, what a good wife she had been to Jock, who was mourning. Jock said,
"Aye, Tammas, Janet was a guid woman, a guid neighbor as you say; she was a' you say an'
mair. She was aye a guid, true wifey tae me, and I <i>cam' near tellin'</i> her sae aince or twice."
</p><p>
We express again our appreciation to those who sent these lovely flowers to us. We want to
thank all those who have contributed in any way to the success and inspiration of this great
conference.
</p><p>
Now, brethren and sisters, may I say just a word in conclusion. I have a deep admiration in
my heart for Simon Peter, President of the Twelve Apostles. He said in one of his general
epistles:
</p><p>
"... to them that have obtained like precious faith with us through the righteousness of God
and our Saviour Jesus Christ:
</p><p>
"Grace and peace be multiplied unto you through the knowledge of God, and of Jesus our
Lord,
</p><p>
"According as his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and
godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us to glory and virtue:
</p><p>
"Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be
partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in
the world through lust" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/1-4#1">2 Pet. 1:1-4</a>).
</p><p>
That comes from Simon Peter who was only two and a half years&mdash;a little more&mdash;in the
personal presence of his Lord. Before that he did not care much for the Church, but before
this writing he had a testimony of the divinity of the Sonship of Jesus Christ. More than that,
he had experienced that communion of the Spirit with his Resurrected Lord, and speaks here
of being a partaker <i>of the divine nature</i>.
</p><p>
Hold to that thought in the midst of an atheistic world, mentioned by Brother Benson and
others, while there are godless men who deny the resurrection of Christ, who deny his living
spirit, and who have taught for forty years young men and young women to deny him. That is
a terrible thing when you think of it. Some of us thought twenty years ago that such a godless
organization would break of its own weight, and now young men who were ten years of age
when communistic ideology took possession of so many are now fifty years of age.
</p><p>
Peter says to those who knew Christ, who had partaken of his Spirit:
</p><p>
"Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be
partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust.
</p><p>
"And beside this, giving all diligence, add to your faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge;
</p><p>
"And to knowledge temperance; and to temperance patience; and to patience godliness;
</p><p>
"And to godliness brotherly kindness; and to brotherly kindness charity.
</p><p>
"For if these things [virtues] be in you, and abound, they make you that ye shall neither be
barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/4-8#4">2 Pet. 1:4-8</a>).
</p><p>
To know God and his Beloved Son is eternal life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
I do not know the author, but there comes to my mind now these lines:
</p><p>
"Admire the goodness of Almighty God<br />
He riches gave, intellectual strength to few<br />
Nor now commands to be nor rich, nor learned<br />
Nor promises reward of peace to these.<br />
On all He moral worth bestowed,<br />
And moral tribute asks from all.<br />
And who that could not pay?&mdash;<br />
Who born so poor, of intellect so mean<br />
As not to know what seemed the best<br />
And knowing might not do?<br />
And He who acted thus fulfilled the law eternal<br />
And His promises reaped in peace.<br />
Who sought else (did not do what his judgment bade or the spirit prompted) sought mellow grapes beneath the icy poles,<br />
Sought blooming roses on the cheek of death,<br />
Sought substance in a world of fleeting shades."
</p><p>
God help us to be <i>partakers of the DIVINE NATURE</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/4#4">2 Pet. 1:4</a>). May the
spirit of this great conference radiate from your hearts to those whom you will meet when
you go back to your stakes and wards, and especially may it radiate in your homes, I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
