<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Articles of Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 131-133</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: I appreciate the privilege of saying a word this afternoon.
</p><p>
<b>Wentworth letter</b>
</p><p>
More than a century ago, the excitement about religion in the United States probably reached
its highest point. It was during these days of agitation and conflict that the editor of the
<i>Chicago Democrat</i>, John Wentworth, asked Joseph Smith, the Prophet, for a statement of his
religious beliefs. The Prophet's reply on March 1, 1842, included the now famous Articles of
Faith. There are 13, each one expressing a belief of the newly organized Church. They have
now become the official expression of Mormon doctrine.
</p><p>
We know little about the immediate influence of the Wentworth letter, but we do know that
today thousands have read and pondered these declarations of faith. Many have examined and
believed them, for they are in harmony with the Holy Bible. They reach into the heart of
sectarianism; they deny the creeds of the mother church; and they strike hard at all established
creeds. When the Prophet summarized the claims of the Church, he carefully avoided a
dogmatic style. All in all, it is a magnificent and friendly appeal to an honest and
conscientious seeker after truth.
</p><p>
<b>First Article of Faith</b>
</p><p>
In the first article Joseph Smith resurrects the true concept of the Godhead
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>). It was a challenge
in his day. It is still a challenge. He left no room for dispute over this important and
fundamental doctrine. "We believe in God, the Eternal Father, and in His Son, Jesus Christ,
and in the Holy Ghost."
</p><p>
This definition of God is understandable without prolonged and tedious discussion. It
reaffirms the teachings of Genesis that man is created in the image of his Maker (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26-27#26">Gen. 1:26-27</a>). The vague
and confused notions of Deity during the past centuries have robbed people of God's reality.
A new revelation of the Godhead, such as Joseph Smith gave the world, is the only solution
to the religious misunderstanding that exists throughout Christendom.
</p><p>
Jesus made this clear when he said: "And this is life eternal, that the might know thee the
only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Second article</b>
</p><p>
In the second article, the Prophet states "that men will be punished for their own sins, and not
for Adam's transgression" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/2#2">A of F 1:2</a>). It was a revolutionary thought when it was given 126 years ago.
Man is not "born in sin" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/51/5#5">Ps. 51:5</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/55#55">Moses 6:55</a>),
as is taught by many churches in Christendom. Man is a child of
God and had an existence before his sojourn in mortality. He came to the earth pure and
sinless. To claim otherwise is to attribute the capacity for sin to one who does not know right
from wrong.
</p><p>
Man is precious in the sight of God. I quote from Psalms 8:4-5: "What is man, that thou art
mindful of him? and the son of man, that thou visitest him? For thou hast made him a little
lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honour" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/4-5#4">Ps. 8:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
"Man and God are of the same race," said President Bruce R. McConkie. (<i>Mormon Doctrine</i>,
pp. 465-66.) Man's destiny is godlike, for he has the opportunity to reach the heights of a
glorious exaltation. The restored Church is the most important thing in the universe, for it
points the way to eternal salvation and exaltation in God's kingdom.
</p><p>
<b>A great document</b>
</p><p>
I have always regarded the Articles of Faith submitted by the Prophet Joseph Smith as a great
document. They cover in a brief way the fundamental beliefs of the Church. They do not
antagonize. The style and wording are full of appeal, especially to those who are familiar with
Bible teaching. The language is simple and direct and is readily understood by the ordinary
reader. The reader is not confused in his investigation, nor led away from the doctrinal
teachings of the apostles in the meridian of time. The Articles of Faith bring to light the
doctrines and standards set forth so plainly in the holy scriptures. There is a tone of authority
and certainty in each one that is most impressive.
</p><p>
<b>Article 6</b>
</p><p>
I quote article 6: "We believe in the same organization that existed in the Primitive Church,
viz., apostles, prophets, pastors, teachers, evangelists, etc." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/6#6">A of F 1:6</a>). Who can read that declaration
without calling to mind the twelve apostles commissioned and sent forth by the Savior? There
are no apostles today in any Christian church except those who are serving in the restored
Church. It would be exceedingly difficult to present a better introduction to the gospel
message than those presented by the Prophet in the Wentworth letter.
</p><p>
<b>Salvation defined</b>
</p><p>
The Articles of Faith define salvation and introduce a plan by which mankind maybe saved
and brought back into Gods presence. The problem of salvation, as you know, has split
Christianity into many sects. Salvation means continuous progress and growth. The Third
Article of Faith is a concise explanation of its meaning: "We believe that through the
Atonement of Christ, all mankind may be saved, by obedience to the laws and ordinances of
the Gospel" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>). There is nothing shallow or narrow in universal salvation, through the grace of
Christ. Man must progress according to law. He must be obedient under the law and strive
step by step to obtain the reward. In this striving, free agency is paramount, and all necessary
ordinances must be complied with.
</p><p>
<b>Revelation</b>
</p><p>
I read article 9: "We believe all that God has revealed, all that He does now reveal, and we
believe that He will yet reveal many great and important things pertaining to the Kingdom of
God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>). Revelation is the rock upon which the true Church is founded. It is the source of
Christ's gospel. It is the rock referred to by Jesus Christ when he said to Peter, "Blessed art
thou, Simon Bar-jona: for flesh and blood hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which
is in heaven.
</p><p>
"And I say also unto thee, That thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and
the gates of hell shall not prevail against it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/17-18#17">Matt. 16:17-18</a>).
</p><p>
The prophets, ancient and modern; drank deeply from the fountainhead. By doing so they
were refreshed and satisfied. Ralph Waldo Emerson is reported to have said, "We ought to
have a religion of revelation to use, and not the history of one."
</p><p>
<b>True index to beliefs</b>
</p><p>
In summary may I say: For more than a century the church has strictly followed the Articles
of Faith. There has never been a revision of, an amendment to, or a deviation from these
declarations of belief. They are true and will stand forever. It is well to remember that the
Church has forged ahead for more than 138 years. Regardless of persecution, mobbings,
drivings, and the hostility from many sources, the work has moved forward. It has never
faced a setback. The gospel of Jesus Christ is consistent and reasonable. Its aim and mission
is to give every individual a chance to accept or reject it. The gospel message will be heard
by all of God's children, whether living or dead.
</p><p>
I testify, brethren and sisters, that the 13 Articles of Faith are true and that they are an index
to the beliefs of the Latter-day Saints. May we believe them, and may we introduce into our
lives the saving principles of life and salvation, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
