<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">On Common Ground</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1943, pp. 79-81</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
As I have looked over this audience, and all of the congregations that have been present in
this great tabernacle the past two days, my feeling has been that some people are not far from
the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE EXPRESSED FOR LOCAL MISSIONARY WORK
</p><p>
We have heard, and heard rightly and beautifully, about the missionary effort that is being put
forth to teach the people of the world something new, something deep, something of truth
about the kingdom of God, and I want to take this opportunity to thank the presidents of
stakes, and all the bishops of wards for their faithful support and help in spirit and in prayer
for the work that is being undertaken by all the missionaries of the stakes of Zion. It is a
great work in which they are engaged, and they are unafraid. You missionaries who are
present at this conference, remember, please, that you are in the service of God; and all the
sacred scriptures&mdash;the scriptures are great and many&mdash;have been have been entrusted to you to
study, to think about, and to teach.
</p><p>
A SACRED CALLING
</p><p>
Yesterday we heard beautifully expressed the admonition of Jesus Christ to His disciples to go
forth and preach the Gospel unto all people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15#15">Mark 16:15</a>),
and that causes us to recall the words of the Lord
that have been written by the Prophet Joseph Smith:
</p><p>
And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of My disciples, whom I
have chosen in these last days
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4#4">D&amp;C 1:4</a>).
</p><p>
You are called to go forth to learn, and to teach, and to bear your testimonies, which are
sacred. And when you do bear your testimonies, it is the depths speaking unto the depths of
people's souls.
</p><p>
Above the door of the School of Music at Harvard University are these words: "To charm, to
strengthen, and to teach, these are the three great cords of might." Remember, my fellow
missionaries, the words of a prophet of old when he said:
</p><p>
We have heard with our ears, O God, our fathers have told us, what work thou didst in their
days, in the times of old. . . . For they got not the land in possession by their
own sword, neither did their own arm save them; but thy right hand, and thine arm, and the
light of thy countenance, because thou hadst a favor unto them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/44/1,3#1">Ps. 44:1,3</a>).
</p><p>
You must awaken, strengthen, teach all people, and with your faith in the Lord securely fixed,
you will be able to reach the hearts of those people with whom you speak. It is truth and
sincerity that are called for today, and you have the power to say: "In the name of Jesus
Christ of Nazareth, rise up and walk"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/6#6">Acts 3:6</a>).
You are called to do service. You are servants of the Lord.
</p><p>
What a great thing it is to say to people, "We believe in God, the Eternal Father." Think of it!
The Creator of heaven and earth and the stars, the Father of all things, our Father and our
God. "And in Jesus Christ," the Redeemer of the world, Christ the King, our Lord, who died
for us that we might have life eternal if we will but work out our own destinies by Him.
"And in the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>).
What a sacred message you and I carry to the world!
</p><p>
VISITORS AT TEMPLE SQUARE IMPRESSED
</p><p>
Before any of you were admitted to these grounds this morning, I met a lady and gentleman
just outside the gate and because of their desire to see the flowers, trees, and buildings, I had
them admitted with me, when I explained something of the history of the temple and
tabernacle, the sea gull monument, and the monuments of Joseph and Hyrum Smith. The
conversation was soon over, when the gentleman said: "I take it that you are a Mormon. We
are Lutherans. I have often wondered what you people believe."
</p><p>
You see, there was a family with certain ideals of life, as I had my ideals of life. The very
spirit of the surroundings gave them a feeling of reverence, for they so expressed themselves.
Said the lady: "What noble buildings to be created by the pioneers of your state. Only good
people could build such houses of worship."
</p><p>
Now, my brother missionaries before we can teach, we must get on common ground, with
that love that has just been spoken about, with that genuineness of understanding of the
human heart. This man said, "I am a Lutheran."
</p><p>
I had the pleasure of saying to him, "I remember what Luther taught his people when he Said:
'I believe it takes the truth of the heart and soul to understand the truths of God.'"
</p><p>
He replied: "I believe that." And continuing, he said, "You are a great admirer of Luther?"
</p><p>
"Yes, very much so." I will not go into detail, for my time is up, but when he went through
the gate he turned to me and said: "And I want to say to you, friend, that I am an admirer
now of Joseph Smith, who, you say, is a prophet of God."
</p><p>
You see, we came on common ground, and he felt happy that we found something good in
his belief, and I felt happier that he found something noble in mine.
</p><p>
God bless you, and let us all remember that we are missionaries of God, declaring the Gospel
of His kingdom, that it may be lodged in the hearts of men. I have a humble testimony of this
great work of God that has been revealed in these the last days through prophecy, of those
servants who have been near to God and have spoken for him and His holy word. God bless
you all, I ask, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
