<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 72-75</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Grant, President Clark, President McKay, members of the priesthood, and all the
radio audience: I stand before this assembled group today in deep humility, in trembling and
weakness. I have no words to express the intense feelings that have completely filled me
during the past twenty-four hours. The more I contemplate the call which has been made upon
me the greater the responsibility looms before my mind, and the more I recognize my
weakness and incapability in filling this position. I knew that without the help of God the task
will be too great, but I do trust and pray with all my heart that I might have his Holy Spirit to
be with me, that in this new call I may be a worthy servant in helping to proclaim the gospel
of Jesus Christ. I do covenant before my Heavenly Father and before you that I will put forth
my very best efforts, that I will give all of my time and talents and anything that God has
blessed me with for the upbuilding of his Church and kingdom here upon this earth.
</p><p>
I hope you will pardon me this morning if I say a few things that are personal, but during the
past twenty-four hours with such a sudden change coming into my life, my mind has been
going back in retrospect over the events of my past life and also of my future. I desire to
express, with the help of the Lord, a few of my feelings, a few of my hopes.
</p><p>
EXPERIENCE IN SEMINARY WORK
</p><p>
I have always loved the gospel of Jesus Christ more than anything else in life. I have
continuously labored in the Church from my boyhood up, willingly and happily. The gospel
and the opportunities to serve in the Church have been the greatest blessing and joy in my
life. When I was attending high school seminary under one of our very excellent teachers,
Brother William Tew, I made up my mind that if I ever had the opportunity I should like to
be a seminary teacher and devote my time and my entire life to teaching the gospel of our
Lord Jesus Christ. With that thought in mind I went on through school. Elder Joseph F.
Merrill offered me the opportunity, which I gladly accepted, and in happiness I undertook the
work.
</p><p>
I have had the great privilege of spending seventeen years in the Church system of education
in the high school seminaries and in the institutes. They have been years of much happiness to
me, years I know that have furnished me wonderful opportunities. Throughout that time I
have never lost opportunity on any occasion to bear testimony to the students of the
truthfulness of the gospel and to try to help them with all evidence possible to gain a
testimony of the gospel; and to gain facts and the proper spirit which will
sustain this great Church of our Master to which we belong.
</p><p>
I would like on this occasion to remark to the parents of the young people of the Church and
to the First Presidency and to the officers of the Church, that I have found through working
with the young people that they are great; they are wonderful; they are filled with the
testimony of the gospel; they are just as staunch, just as true, just as faithful, I am sure, as
were their parents or their grandparents. I have never seen more faith exhibited in my life by
any group of people than I have seen among the young people of our Church with whom I
have had the privilege of working. I do not fear for the future of the Church so long as our
young people are of this splendid type, and so long as they are filled with the spirit of the
gospel and continue living their present type of lives. I am sure that they will take leadership
in the Church in due time and carry it on very effectively. I accept the promise made to the
Prophet Joseph that the gospel is upon the earth never to be taken from the earth again and
never to be given to another people.
</p><p>
We should thank the Presidency of the Church and all those working for this great cause who
have made possible our educational system. They foster the great opportunities that we have
therein. I speak of that subject definitely this morning because of my close contact for many
years with that particular work. I am convinced that the educational program is completely in
line with the gospel as revealed to the Prophet Joseph Smith&mdash;that man "cannot be saved in
ignorance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>);
that "we are saved no faster than we gain knowledge"; that "the glory of God is
intelligence" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
The educational program is also definitely in line with the practices of the
Church from the beginning, during pioneer days, and on down to the present time. We are a
group of people who know that we must gain knowledge of truth in order that we may
progress on to godhood. So I do express my appreciation to the First Presidency and their
associates for the privilege I have had of spending seventeen years in that very excellent work
and also for all the opportunities that I have had in the Church.
</p><p>
When I completed my doctor's degree in California, I was given the opportunity to teach at
the institute in Logan. I was delighted; but when I went down to California and told the
professors under whom I had taken my graduate work, they tried to persuade me to not come
back to Utah to teach. They wanted me to teach in history, the field that I had taken my
special work in, but I talked to my wife&mdash;who is a very faithful and devout Latter-day Saint
and a splendid companion&mdash;and her feelings agreed with mine. We recognized that we had a
great opportunity at Logan to help the young people of the Church, and we felt that we
wanted to rear our family in Utah, and so we turned our backs upon that suggestion and
returned to our home state. We have been very happy in our decision.
</p><p>
PERSONAL TESTIMONIES
</p><p>
Before closing my remarks, I would like to bear my testimony. I know that God lives. I know
that Jesus the Christ is his Beloved Son. He is the Savior of the world, the Redeemer, the
author of the eternal plan of salvation. I know that God, the Eternal Father, through his only
begotten son, restored the gospel upon the earth through the Prophet Joseph Smith in our
dispensation; that it is the true gospel; that it is the power of God unto salvation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>). I know that
if we live by these eternal principles we shall gain a great reward, even that of eternal life in
the kingdom of God. I know that our Heavenly Father is good; that he hears and answers
prayers; that he is gracious and kind even beyond our comprehension; and that he delights in
blessing those who keep his commandments. The Holy Ghost has borne this testimony to my
soul so strongly that I am as sure of these facts as I am that I live. I pray that I may ever live
worthy enough to retain this testimony.
</p><p>
Everyone in this audience no doubt has had many experiences which to them have testified to
the goodness of God and which have given them a testimony of the truthfulness of the
restored gospel. Herein lies the strength of Mormonism. I would like to give an experience or
two of mine.
</p><p>
At least twice in my life I was at the point of death and was brought back to life through the
power of the priesthood, through the goodness of God. One June day when I was twenty-one
years old, I had climbed the hay pole to thread it in order that we might harvest our crop. Just
as I had finished, the guy wire broke, and the pole came crashing to the earth. It splintered
into many pieces. The hayfork lit with the tines straight up just a few feet from where I lit.
Although I fell nearly fifty feet, the only injury that I received was a broken foot. Of course
the shock was terrific. I went to bed, and the next day I thought I could get up. I crawled out
of bed and immediately everything went black, but through the power of God I was restored
to health and strength.
</p><p>
Eleven years later, when I finished my doctor's degree, my physical condition was poor
because I had worked very hard. I was teaching seminary in Provo. In November I went to
Salt Lake City and had my wisdom teeth extracted. On the way home a storm arose and
within twenty-four hours I was seriously ill. A streptococcus infection had settled in my
throat, and for the next three weeks I lay at the point of death. The doctor had no hopes that I
would recover. The bishop came to our home, and as kindly as he could, told my wife I
should not be able to recover. But the seminary teachers I worked with came daily and
administered to me. Never once did I have the thought in my mind that I would not get well.
I knew there were many things in this world that I was to do yet. In three weeks' time I got
out of bed and went back to my schoolroom. It took a year, however, to get the infection out
of my system. I am sure that it was through the help and blessings of God
that I was restored to life. Upon returning to my school, the students asked me to what I
attributed my recovery from such a severe sickness. I testified to them on that occasion, and
have done so on many occasions since, that it was through the power of the priesthood and
because of the goodness of God that my life was preserved.
</p><p>
I want to bear my testimony today that I know these things are true and that my Heavenly
Father has been kind and good to me, blessing me more abundantly than I have deserved. I
sincerely hope and pray that I have the full support and the faith of all the members of the
Church and the same help from God in the performance of my duties as a member of the
First Council of the Seventy. This is my humble prayer in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
