<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Way to Eternal Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 50-51</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My good brethren and sisters and friends, I realize that this is a very important and
responsible position; that our words go out, the extent of which we do not know.  It is
needful, therefore, that we have the guidance of the Spirit of the Lord, that we may speak his
truth.  I trust that the few words that I say may find an echo in your hearts and be dictated by
the Spirit of the Lord.
</p><p>
Near the close of a discourse by our Lord and Savior, many believed on him. It is written:
"Then said Jesus to those Jews which believed on him, If ye continue in my word, then are ye
my disciples indeed; 
</p><p>
"And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/31-32#31">John 8:31-32</a>).
</p><p>
The only truth that makes us free is the truth of the gospel of Jesus Christ. In fact, all truth
belongs to the gospel of Jesus Christ.  When our Savior was brought before Pilate, Pilate
questioned him and asked him if he were a king. Jesus answered, "Thou sayest that I am a
king. To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world, that I should bear
witness unto the truth. Every one that is of the truth heareth my voice"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/37#37">John 18:37</a>).
</p><p>
Then Pilate asked him, "What is truth?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/38#38">John 18:38</a>).
Perhaps the Savior had no time given him to answer. 
Perhaps he was silent, and from that time until now volumes have been written asking that
question.  The only true answer that has been given was given by the Lord to the Prophet
Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
"And truth is knowledge of things as they are, and as they were, and as they are to come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/24#24">D&amp;C 93:24</a>).
In other words, truth is that which endures.  All else must perish.  This
being true, it behooves us to search for truth&mdash;this truth the Savior spoke of that makes us
free.
</p><p>
Not all truth is of the same value or importance.  Some truths are greater than others.  The
greatest truth, or the greatest truths, we find in the fundamentals of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
First of all, that Jesus Christ is the Son of God, the Redeemer of the world, who came into
this world to die that men might live. That truth we should know. It is far more important to
know that Jesus Christ is our Redeemer, that he has given unto us the principles of eternal
life, than it is to know all that can be obtained in secular education.
</p><p>
It is far more important to know that baptism is for the remission of sins, and when properly
performed by one who has the authority, remission of sins will come, and through the baptism
following, of the Holy Ghost, we come back into the presence of God our Father, at last,
through the guidance of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
To know the way to eternal life is far more important than all the learning that the world can
give.  We find that in the sacred principles which have been revealed for the last time, and in
these ordinances which are being performed for the last time&mdash;that is, in the Dispensation of
the Fullness of Times&mdash;for the gospel will never be restored again. It has been restored to
remain.  The Lord has ordained his servants, and has given them authority to execute his
laws, to preach his gospel, to cry repentance, to call upon men to humble themselves and
receive these fundamental principles of eternal life.
</p><p>
The way of eternal life is here.  The covenants that were promised that lead to that great gift
are here.  All men on the face of the earth have now the privilege not only of repentance, but
also of remission of sins through the waters of baptism, and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the
laying on of hands, and to receive the covenants and obligations which were promised
anciently that will bring them back into the presence of God, our Father.
</p><p>
These blessings are free.  They are the most important truths in all the world.  Brethren and
sisters, we have received them.  Let us be true and faithful, turning neither to the right nor to
the left in the keeping of the commandments of the Lord, and by example as well as by
precept, serve him, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
