<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Cherish Noble Aspirations</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1965, pp. 144-146</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<b>Jesus Christ, the Personification of Perfection</b>
</p><p>
My dear brethren and sisters: As we come to this parting hour, I hope that the teachings and
life of the Master seem to you all to be more beautiful, more necessary, and more applicable
to human happiness than ever before. Never have I believed more firmly in the perfection of
humanity as the final result of man's placement here on earth. With my whole soul I accept
Jesus Christ as the personification of human perfection&mdash;as God made manifest in the flesh,
as the Savior and Redeemer of mankind. Accepting him as my Redeemer Savior, and Lord, I
accept his gospel as the plan of salvation, as the one perfect way to human happiness and
peace. There is not a principle which was taught by him but seems to me to be applicable to
the growth, development, and happiness of mankind. Every one of his teachings seems to me
to touch the true philosophy of living. I accept them with all my heart and pray that all who
participated in this great conference, either as listeners or speakers, may have that same desire
in their hearts.
</p><p>
Let us strive so earnestly to represent him or to follow him that our spirits may be eternally
young. If thoughts affect the physical being, might it not be true that eternal truths will
contribute to the eternal nature of the spirit within? On the night of his betrayal, the Savior
said: "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ,
whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
And how may we know of the doctrine? "If any man will
do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of
myself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Effort Required to Gain Righteousness</b>
</p><p>
Wisdom comes through effort. All good things require effort. That which is worth having will
cost part of your physical being, your intellectual power, and your soul power&mdash;"Ask, and it
shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>).
But you have to seek, you have to knock. On the other hand, sin thrusts itself upon you.
It walks beside you, it tempts you, it entices, it allures. You do not have to put forth effort. It
is like the poor, fallen woman who lies in wait to deceive. It is like the billboard advertising
attracting you to drink and to smoke. It is like the message that comes into your very homes
with the television and radio or the golden packet put right into your hand. Evil seeks you,
and it requires effort and fortitude to combat it. But truth and wisdom are gained only by
seeking, by prayer, and by effort.
</p><p>
We cannot be true to ourselves and to our loved ones, to our associates, without feeling a
determination to know more about this great truth to which testimonies have been borne here
throughout this conference. The spirit within bears testimony that truth exists in this old
world.
</p><p>
<b>"What Seek Ye?"</b>
</p><p>
"What seek ye?" were the first words that Christ uttered to some of his Twelve, or some who
afterwards became members of the Twelve. "Master, where dwellest thou?" He didn't say
over here or over there, but he said, "Come and see"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/38-39#38">John 1:38-39</a>).
And they went with him that day and spent the rest of the afternoon in his presence.
</p><p>
I ask the youth of the Church today, "Whom do you seek?" Would you keep that youth which
is yours now? Then love the Lord your God with all your mind, with all your heart, and with
all your soul (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37#37">Matt. 22:37</a>);
and though the body becomes decrepit and like an old house begins to tumble,
your spirit will still be young, as young as the little babe that might be in that tumbled-down
house, because your body, after all, is but the house in which you live. Even when your heart
stops beating, your eyelids close, and you respond no more to your physical environment, that
spirit, still young, will go into the presence of him whom you have made your ideal. Then
truly will it be demonstrated that: 
</p><p>
"The stars shall fade away, the sun himself<br />
     Grow dim with age, and Nature sink in years; <br />
     But thou shalt flourish in immortal youth,<br />
     Unhurt amidst the war of elements,<br />
     The wreck of matter, and the crash of worlds."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          (Joseph Addison, <i>Cato</i>, Act V, sc 1.)
</p><p>
And now this great conference draws to a close. Our anticipation, our hopes, and our prayers
that it might prove to be uplifting and inspirational have been realized, and for that we are
grateful to our Heavenly Father, grateful for the inspiration he has given to us and to the
world. Truly, our hearts have been filled with gratitude that the Lord has magnified each one
who has spoken to the end that his words have emanated from the presence of our Father.
</p><p>
<b>Resolve to Hold Fast to Good</b>
</p><p>
As we leave to go to our various homes, let us make real the good feelings that have been
aroused in our souls. Let us not permit to evaporate from our minds and feelings the good
resolutions we have formed. Let us resolve that from now on we are going to be men of
higher and more sterling character, more conscious of our own weaknesses, more kind and
charitable towards others' failings. As we depart let us be more determined to be kinder
husbands, more thoughtful wives, more exemplary to our children, more determined that in
our homes we are going to have just a little taste of heaven here on earth.
</p><p>
<b>Cherish Testimony of Truth</b>
</p><p>
Cherish in your hearts the testimony of truth; make it as solid and as firm and unwavering as
the fixed stars in the heavens. May there come into everyone's heart and into all our homes
the true Spirit of Christ, our Redeemer, whose reality, whose inspiring guidance I know to be
real. May a kind heaven help us to cherish worthy ideals and noble aspirations. Whatever our
joys and sorrows, let us ever remember that what we ardently desire in our hearts will
determine what we really are. How constantly and consistently we cherish noble aspirations in
our minds and follow them will determine whether we drift as failures along life's highway or
fulfill the divine purpose of our being.
</p><p>
<b>Be Faithful to Constitutional Government</b>
</p><p>
Finally, let us be true to our country and to our country's ideals. Nearly three thousand years
ago an ancient prophet said that this is a land choice above all other lands
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>),
and it is, and the Constitution of the United States, as given to us by our fathers, is the real
government under which individuals may exercise free agency and individual initiative.
</p><p>
Let us oppose any subversive influence that would deprive us of our individual freedom or
make this government a dictator instead of a servant to the people.
</p><p>
God bless you officers and leaders of the Church. May the love of the Redeemer be in each
heart, and that means that that love will be expressed in serving one another. God bless these
brethren of the General Authorities with increased health and strength to carry on their
responsibilities throughout the world. I know that God lives, that his Son Jesus Christ is the
Savior of the world, and that divine beings restored to the Prophet Joseph Smith the gospel of
Jesus Christ as he established it in the Meridian of Time.
</p><p>
I bear you this testimony as we part this afternoon and pray the blessings of the Lord to be
upon each and every one of you, that the influence of the priesthood quorums, of auxiliaries,
and of the missionaries may be more effective from this time forward than ever before in
leading the honest in heart of the whole world to turn their hearts to the worship of God and
give them power to control the animal nature and live in the Spirit, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
