<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Thou Art You</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 113-115</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is a wonderful blessing to be in this beloved building on these cherished and sacred grounds
again. It is glorious to sing with you and to respond to the inspiration of this choir. It is good
to be home.
</p><p>
As I walked out of the Church Office Building yesterday morning, I heard a man say to his
companion, "If I keep up this schedule I'm going to end up in the grave." My immediate
reaction was to feel that whatever schedule he followed his chances of that were pretty good.
But the second thought came, a thought expressed by a fine but leaden-footed youngster
interrupted in the middle of a drag race by a somewhat stem officer. The boy was asked what
he was doing, and he said, "I didn't want to get left in the dust." Well, he
won't. No one will, and no one will end up in a grave.
</p><p>
<b>Choose the "Eternal Way" now</b>
</p><p>
The spirit of every child of God goes on living as we experience mortal death&mdash;the
temporary separation of the body and spirit&mdash;and through the atonement of Christ there will
be a universal resurrection. The body and spirit will be joined together again as the eternally
living soul. The circumstances under which we shall live eternally, in whose presence, with
what companions, and in what condition of opportunity and creative service, we are now
deciding by the choices we make.
</p><p>
The great messages of this conference and the stirring and solemn assurances that have come
have brought to our hearts renewed assurance that this is the truth. We have been teaching
that truth in Europe in the past several years with many of your choice sons and daughters
and their older companions. It has been a wonderful experience to see the transforming Spirit
of the Lord work upon them as it worked anciently when the Savior called his Apostles from
the counting place and the fishing nets and bade them become fishers of men
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/19#19">Matt. 4:19</a>). It is an
experience that we wouldn't miss nor trade for anything.
</p><p>
<b>Missionary Motivations Commended</b>
</p><p>
Some years ago a wonderful, successful man, who knew nothing of the Church, spent a few
days with his son at a boys' camp where several of these missionaries were serving as
counselors. A little time later he wrote a note to one of them. Let me read it:
</p><p>
"It's hard for a person untrained in writing to say what I want to and not sound a bit
overboard. I think you know me well enough, though, to know that I mean just what I say. I
want to tell you and the others how I feel. There is very little that I know about the Mormon
religion, but this I see from my contact with you men during this camp period. In some way
it has made itself so vital to young men like you that you found yourself answering a call.
You've had to do something personally because your religion is so very personal and
important to you. This is a living religion.
</p><p>
"I am a ruling elder in a Protestant church, and I covet for my own church, more than I can
tell you, the sort of teaching, leadership, and conviction that breathes such a vital force into
its young men. We have our missionaries, of course, but this thing which you do is a different
thing. It reaches out within your church in a different way, I judge, and in my humble
judgment it is one of the grandest ways I have yet heard of for a fellow to repay in some
measure to his God the great debt we all owe. I know that God will richly bless your mission
and you. I want you to know that through you and the other men I have had a glimpse of
something which to me has the possibility of being an answer to many of the problems that
beset my own church and the whole world in these troubled times."
</p><p>
Well, I agree with Mr. Cary's generous and challenging words, his sincere words of
commendation and expectation. And I agree with the wonderful implications in them for the
missionary, and his younger brother and sister and his parents, for me and you, for all of us.
They are to me a sobering portrait of our possibilities and our responsibilities.
</p><p>
<b>Commendation and Confidence for Youth</b>
</p><p>
As we worked with the missionaries, we worked also with wonderful members of the Church
and met multitudes of choice young and older people. I see them in my mind's eye this
morning in Frankfurt and Orleans and Berchtesgaden, in London and Bristol and Glasgow,
and in a lot of other places. Last Sunday night at a fireside gathering in the Brigham Young
University field house there were more youngsters gathered than are congregated on these
grounds today. A night or two later at Utah State University I met another great group. I feel
in my heart for them and their generation the strongest commendation and confidence. But
they have a mighty burden to bear and a great challenge to face.
</p><p>
I have been thinking the last few days of the statement of the Psalmist who
sang the sweet strains of heaven: "Thou preparest a table before me in the presence of mine
enemies" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/23/5#5">Ps. 23:5</a>).
Our young people have a table prepared all right, and it is a table
laden with the gifts that can make this life meaningful and happy and that can fill them in the
eternal sense. But the table is in truth, as the Psalmist said, set in the presence of their
enemies.
</p><p>
<b>Enemies of Youth</b>
</p><p>
Who are their enemies? Some of them have been spoken of this morning: men who dig gold
out of dirt; certain ones who manufacture and market filth; they who, whether misguided or
designing, put before our young people a picture of life as some live it but emphasizing the
least affirmative and least Godly aspects of man's divine nature. The young have a table
prepared for them in the presence of many enemies. One of the enemies is, in every
individual case, our own accumulated sinfulness and bad memory. We are constrained to
excuse ourselves because of the failings and faults of others. We are constrained to feel that
since everybody is doing it, it is all right for us to do it, and this is persuasively propounded
by people in various fields who rely on the statistical method and suggest that since large
numbers are doing it, then it must be all right for everybody to do it, just so long as you
don't go too far.
</p><p>
Well, a tendency in man to excuse himself has ever been with us. Saul was sent on a great
mission. Saul failed and then blamed it on his people when he was confronted by the Prophet
Samuel. Saul told a falsehood, and Samuel said, "Then what is this bleating I hear in my ear"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/15/14#14">1 Sam. 15:14</a>), and then Saul
blamed his defection on his people.
</p><p>
<b>"Turn Right&mdash;Go Straight"</b>
</p><p>
In the day of the restoration a great young prophet had to learn the lesson, too. Many of you
are acquainted with the third section of the Doctrine and Covenants, this "handbook of the
restoration." May I read from it a verse or two which the Lord gave to Joseph Smith after a
misfortune in which he had succumbed to the pressure to do something he knew wasn't
exactly right. His benefactor and friend who was helping him, providing for him, working
with him, wanted some assurance for his wife and family that there really was a prophet at
work, and so Joseph Smith reluctantly surrendered to him the manuscript of the then
translated portion of the Book of Mormon. This came in response:
</p><p>
"And behold, how oft you have transgressed the commandments and the laws of God, and
have gone on in the persuasions of men.
</p><p>
"For, behold, you should not have feared man more than God. Although men set at naught the
counsels of God, and despise his words&mdash;
</p><p>
"Yet you should have been faithful; and he would have extended his arm and supported you
against all the fiery darts of the adversary; and he would have been with you in every time of
trouble.
</p><p>
"Behold, thou art Joseph" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/3/6-9#6">D&amp;C 3:6-9</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Thou Art You"</b>
</p><p>
Could there be any more sublime or sweet or perceptive answer to the suggestion, this siren
song of foolishness, that "everyone is doing it"? Behold, thou art <i>you</i>. And God has given you
a table, bounteously laden with the good things of eternity. Will you give it up because others
are giving up? Will you surrender the sweet and sound and strong principles of this "vital
force" and "living religion"?
</p><p>
Why is it a vital force and whence are its roots? It is a vital force because this is a vital
religion. God lives. He is a living, revealing, communicating Father. Christ lives. He is the
living Head of this Church. There is a living prophet on the earth to whom the Father
communicates and reveals his will. Man was in the beginning with God, and we are always
going to live.
</p><p>
God bless us to choose to live in his presence with our loved ones, creatively, actively,
effectively serving and loving and learning, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
