<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Fruits of the Gospel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1949, pp. 39-45</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I bring you greetings from my beloved colleague, Elder Thomas E. McKay. I stood at his
bedside early this morning and said, "Thomas, it is time to get up and go to conference."
There is nothing in the world he would rather have done, but he was unable to come. He
asked me to express his love to you and also his appreciation for the prayers you have offered
in his behalf. He feels that our Heavenly Father has heard your prayers.
</p><p>
I am very grateful for these conferences. They revive my soul. Every one I have attended for
years has lifted me up and induced me to renew my determination to devote myself more
fully to works of righteousness. During them, the importance of this world's interests and
distractions seems to diminish, and life's true values, as set forth in the gospel of Jesus Christ,
come into plainer view.
</p><p>
FRUITS OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
Does each of you find it so? I hope you do, and I encourage you to take every available
opportunity to renew within yourself a determination to obtain the full fruits of the gospel of
Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
When earth life is over and things appear in their true perspective, we shall more clearly see
and realize what the Lord and his prophets have repeatedly told us, that the fruits of the
gospel are the only objectives worthy of life's full efforts. Their possessor obtains true
wealth&mdash;wealth in the Lord's view of values. We need constantly to deepen our
understandings and sharpen our realization of what the fruits of the gospel are.
</p><p>
The Lord has defined them as . . . peace in this world, and eternal life in
the world to come (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>).
</p><p>
It is a bit difficult to define the "peace in this world" referred to it the revelation. But we may
be assured that it is not the ease luxury, and freedom from struggle envisioned by the world's
utopian dreamers. Jesus told his apostles that it would be found by them even in their days of
tribulation.
</p><p>
Peace I leave with you, he said, . . . my peace I give unto you. And then, by way
of caution, it seems to me, he added, . . . not as the world giveth, give I unto you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
PEACE AMIDST TRIBULATION
</p><p>
A little later he re-emphasized this statement in these words:
</p><p>
These things I have spoken unto you, that in me ye might have peace. In the
world ye shall have tribulation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>).
</p><p>
Convincing evidence of the truth of this saying of the Master&mdash;that people suffering
tribulation in this world could at the same time find peace in him&mdash;has come out of the most
severe experiences.
</p><p>
I suppose that the last few days of the Prophet's life were crowded with about as much
tribulation as any human being could endure. He was hounded by traitors, impeached by
misguided and false-accusing associates, called to account, promised protection, and then
abandoned by his government. That all the while he knew he was approaching martyrdom is
clear from the record. On the evening of Saturday, June 22, he wrote in his journal:
</p><p>
I told Stephen Markham that if I and Hyrum were ever taken again we should be
massacred, or I was not a prophet of God.
</p><p>
On Sunday, the 23rd, he said to his brother Hyrum, If you go back, I will go with
you, but we shall be butchered.
</p><p>
Monday, the 24th, on leaving Nauvoo, he paused when they got to the temple, and looked
with admiration first on that, and then on the city, and remarked,
</p><p>
This is the loveliest place and the best people under the heavens; little do they
know the trials that await them.
</p><p>
In this setting, knowing
that his own life would be taken from him by force and violence and viewing the
trials and suffering which would be visited upon his beloved followers, he said to
the company who were with him,
</p><p>
I am going like a lamb to the slaughter, but I
am calm as a summer's morning
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4#4">D&amp;C 135:4</a>).
</p><p>
This is a classic example of a person having at the same time tribulation in this world and
peace in Christ. Many others, both in ancient and in modern times, have had similar
experiences.
</p><p>
ETERNAL LIFE
</p><p>
The other fruit of the gospel named in the quotation&mdash;"eternal life in the world to
come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>)&mdash;must
be a glorious thing, for the Lord has said that "he that hath eternal life is rich"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>), and that the "gift of
eternal life is the greatest of all the gifts of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>).
He who obtains it will obtain an exaltation in the celestial kingdom of our Father in
heaven. Speaking of such the Lord says, among other things:
</p><p>
They are they who are the church of the Firstborn.
</p><p>
. . . into whose hands the Father has given all things&mdash;
</p><p>
They are they who are priests and kings, who have received of his fulness, and of
his glory;
</p><p>
. . . they are gods, even the sons of God . . .
</p><p>
These shall dwell in the presence of God and his Christ forever and ever.
</p><p>
These are they whom he shall bring with him, when he shall come in the clouds
of heaven to reign on the earth over his people . . . who shall have part in the first
resurrection.
</p><p>
. . . who shall come forth in the resurrection of the just. These are they whose
names are written in heaven . . .
</p><p>
. . . of God, the highest of all, whose glory the sun of the firmament is written of
as being typical
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/54-56,58,62-65,68,70#54">D&amp;C 76:54-56,58,62-65,68,70</a>).
</p><p>
ASSURANCE OF BLESSINGS
</p><p>
This gift of eternal life in the world to come may not, of course, be fully realized during earth
life. An assurance that it will be obtained in the world to come may, however, be had in this
world. As a matter of fact, the blessings of the celestial kingdom are promised only to those
who have such an assurance. According to the vision, a successful candidate for these
blessings must qualify on three counts: First, he must have ". . . received the testimony of
Jesus, and believed on his name" and been ". . . baptized after the manner of his burial";
second, he must have received "the Holy Spirit by the laying on of the hands of him who is
ordained and sealed unto this power"; and third, he must be "sealed by the Holy Spirit of
promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/51-53#51">D&amp;C 76:51-53</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph taught that one so sealed would have within himself an assurance
born of the spirit, that he would obtain eternal life in the world to come. He urgently and
repeatedly admonished the Saints of his day to obtain such an assurance by making their
calling and election sure (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/10#10">2 Pet. 1:10</a>).
It is this assurance within a person which brings to him the peace in
this world which will sustain him in every tribulation.
</p><p>
MORE SURE WORD OF PROPHECY
</p><p>
So taught the Prophet in explanation of the words of Peter. Although that apostle had heard
the voice of God declare, when he was with the Savior on the holy mount,
</p><p>
This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/17#17">2 Pet. 1:17</a>),
</p><p>
he nevertheless wrote to the Saints,
</p><p>
We have also a more sure word of prophecy; whereunto ye do well that ye take
heed (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/19#19">2 Pet. 1:19</a>).
</p><p>
Explaining this statement the Prophet said:
</p><p>
Though they might hear the voice of God and know that Jesus was the Son of
God, this would be no evidence that their election and calling was made sure, that
they had part with Christ, and were joint heirs with him. They then would want
that more sure word of prophecy, that they were sealed in the heavens, and had
the promise of eternal life in the kingdom of God. Then, having this promise
sealed unto them, it was an anchor to the soul, sure and steadfast. Though the
thunders might roll and lightnings flash, and earthquakes bellow, and war gather
thick around, yet this hope and knowledge would support the soul in every hour
of trial, trouble and tribulation (<i>DHC</i> 5:387-390).
</p><p>
It was such an assurance which sustained the Prophet himself as he went to martyrdom, for
unto him the Lord had said in a direct revelation:
</p><p>
. . . I am the Lord thy God and will be with thee even unto the end of the world,
and through all eternity: for verily I seal upon you your exaltation, and prepare a
throne for you in the kingdom of my Father, with Abraham your father
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/49#49">D&amp;C 132:49</a>).
</p><p>
SUSTAINED BY ASSURANCE
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul was likewise sustained by such an assurance. From the hand of the Lord "he
had a promise of receiving a crown of righteousness."
</p><p>
. . . I am now ready to be offered,
</p><p>
he wrote to Timothy just previous to his death.
</p><p>
I have fought a good fight. I have finished my course, I have kept the faith:
</p><p>
Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the
righteous judge, shall give me at that day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/6-8#6">2 Tim. 4:6-8</a>).
</p><p>
I think Apostle Alonzo A. Hinckley had an assurance that he would receive the
gift of eternal life in the world to come and that he was sustained by that
assurance as he endured the sufferings of a slow death, for in a letter which he
wrote to the First Presidency after he had been told by his physician that his
illness would be fatal, he said:
</p><p>
I assure you that I am not deeply disturbed over the final results. I am reconciled,
and I reach my hands to take what My Father has for me, be it life or death. With
a spirit of thanksgiving, and I trust free from vanity or boastfulness, I look over
the past with satisfaction. I would not turn the leaf down on any chapter of my
life. So far as I know, I have honored my Heavenly Father with my time, my
humble talents, and all the means that he has blessed me with, and I have dealt
justly with all men. I have fought, but I have fought fairly.
</p><p>
As to the future. I have no misgivings. It is inviting and glorious, and I sense
rather clearly what it means to be saved by the redeeming blood of Jesus Christ
and to be exalted by his power and be with him ever more (<i>Church Section</i>,
March 27, 1949).
</p><p>
WHOLEHEARTED DEVOTION
</p><p>
These fruits of the gospel&mdash;assurance that we shall obtain eternal life, peace in this world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>)
sustained by such an assurance, and finally eternal life in the world to come&mdash;are within the
reach of us all. Sometimes, however, because of our lack of understanding and appreciation of
them, I am persuaded that we take too much for granted. We assume that because we are
members of the Church, we shall receive as a matter of course all the blessings of the gospel.
I have heard people contend that they have a claim upon them because they have been
through the temple, even though they are not careful to keep the covenants they there made. I
do not think this will be the case.
</p><p>
We might take a lesson from an account given by the Prophet of a vision of the resurrection,
in which he records that one of the saddest things he had ever witnessed was the sorrow of
members of the Church who came forth to a resurrection below that which they had taken for
granted they would receive.
</p><p>
I conceive the blessings of the gospel to be of such inestimable worth that the price for them
must be very exacting, and if I correctly understand what the Lord has said on the subject, it
is. The price, however, is within the reach of us all, because it is not to be paid in money nor
in any of this world's goods but in righteous living. What is required is wholehearted
devotion to the gospel and unreserved allegiance to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints. Speaking to this point, the Prophet taught ". . . that those who keep the
commandments of the Lord and walk in his statutes to the end, are the only individuals" who
shall receive the blessings.
</p><p>
Referring to Paul's devotion he said:
</p><p>
Follow the labors of this apostle from the time of his conversion to the time of his
death, and you will have a fair sample of industry and patience in promulgating
the gospel of Christ. Derided, whipped, and stoned, the moment he escaped the
hands of his persecutors he as zealously as ever proclaimed the doctrine of the
Savior. None will say that he did not keep the faith, that he did not fight the good
fight (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/7#7">2 Tim. 4:7</a>),
that he did not preach and persuade to the last. And what was he to receive?
A crown of righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/8#8">2 Tim. 4:8</a>),
and what shall others receive who do not labor
faithfully, and continue to the end? We leave such to search out their own
blessings if any they have (<i>DHC</i> 2:19-20).
</p><p>
Explaining to the Prophet Joseph Smith the reason why his exaltation was sealed upon him,
the Lord said:
</p><p>
Behold, I have seen your sacrifices and will forgive all your sins; I have seen your
sacrifices in obedience to that which I have told you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/50#50">D&amp;C 132:50</a>).
</p><p>
CALLING AND ELECTION MADE SURE
</p><p>
A half-hearted performance is not enough. We cannot obtain these blessings and be like the
rich young man who protested that he had kept the commandments from his youth up but
who went away sorrowful when, in answer to the question, "What lack I yet?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/20#20">Matt. 19:20</a>). Jesus said unto him,
</p><p>
If thou wilt be perfect, go and sell that thou, hast, and give to the poor . . . and
come and follow me (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/21#21">Matt. 19:21</a>).
</p><p>
Evidently he could live everything but the welfare program.
</p><p>
There can be no such reservation. We must be willing to sacrifice everything. Through
self-discipline and devotion we must demonstrate to the Lord that we are willing to serve him
under all circumstances. When we have done this, we shall receive an assurance that we shall
have eternal life in the world to come. Then we shall have peace in this world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith made this perfectly clear. He said,
</p><p>
After a person has faith in Christ, repents of his sins, and is baptized for the
remission of his sins and receives the Holy Ghost (by the laying on of
hands)....then let him continue to humble himself before God, hungering and
thirsting after righteousness, and living by every word of God, and the Lord will
soon say unto him, Son, thou shall be exalted. When the Lord has thoroughly
proved him, and finds that the man is determined to serve him at all hazards, then
the man will find his calling and his election made sure (<i>DHC</i> 3:380).
</p><p>
Now may the Lord bless us, my brethren and sisters, with an understanding of his great
gospel. And may we press forward with diligence and energy to perfect and qualify ourselves
to receive and enjoy the full fruits thereof, for they are of all things the most joyous to the
soul (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/21-23#21">1 Ne. 11:21-23</a>).
Let us each day in solemn honesty confront ourselves with the
rich man's question, "What lack I yet?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/20#20">Matt. 19:20</a>).
And thus, with utter frankness, discovering our own
limitations, let us conquer them one by one until we obtain peace in this world through an
assurance that we shall have eternal life in the world to come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/23#23">D&amp;C 59:23</a>). For these blessings I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
