<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Spirit of Missionary Work in South America</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder A. Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 7-10</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I want to testify, my brothers and sisters and friends, that he to whom we have just listened is
indeed a prophet of the Living God, and if we can follow and comprehend this inspired
message it will bring a solution to the evils that beset us in this day and age.
</p><p>
<b>Greetings from 40,000 Members</b>
</p><p>
Two years ago from this pulpit I brought you greetings from 20,000 members of The Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints in South America. Today, because of the bounteous
blessings of the Lord and the dedicated efforts of missionaries and members alike, I am
privileged to bring you greetings from more than 40,000 members of the Church. Thirty-three
years were required to convert the first 10,000 members in South America. Only two more
years were required to convert the next 10,000. Since I reported two years ago, 21,000 more
converts have found the truth in the seven missions of South America.
</p><p>
In an atmosphere unfriendly to the biblical doctrines of continued revelation, a Church
founded on prophets and Apostles, belief in a Personal Father in heaven and Jesus Christ as
the actual and divine Son of God, how can a Church that teaches these biblical doctrines grow
so rapidly? What is it that brings people into the restored gospel in such unprecedented
numbers in these South American countries?
</p><p>
Return with me to this great land to get some feeling of the people among whom the Spirit of
the Lord is working.
</p><p>
We find ourselves on a plane flying between Porto Alegre, Brazil, and Buenos Aires,
Argentina. Seated next to me is an executive of a large international corporation. Upon
learning that I was a representative of the Mormon Church, he asked, "What would a man like
me have to do to join the Mormon Church?"
</p><p>
<b>Conversions in South America</b>
</p><p>
Since he was smoking as he drank his cocktail, I commenced by suggesting that he would
first have to give up both of these habits and abstain from the use of tea and coffee as well. I
started to mention such other necessary requirements as faith, repentance, and baptism, when
he interrupted by saying, "Under those restrictions, can you get anybody down here to join
your church?" "Yes," I replied. "Thousands of people join the Church in these lands, in fact, in
Uruguay the ratio of conversion to population is as great as any place in the world. In fact I
know a member who has helped to bring ninety-three other persons into the
Church since she joined a year ago. But you made a mistake by calling it my church. It is not
my church, nor is it any man's church. In reality it is the actual Church of Jesus Christ and
the only one on the earth of which he is the head. When you come to know that, my friend,
and you can gain that certain knowledge, then, changing your life to conform to the revealed
word of the Lord is not as difficult as at first it might seem."
</p><p>
He then asked, "If your church is growing so fast, what do you do with all the people?"
</p><p>
"The Church is a perfect organization," I explained, "founded upon prophets and apostles
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20#20">Eph. 2:20</a>), and
it expands in an orderly way under pressure of numbers.
</p><p>
"It does not require a professionally trained nor paid ministry to administer it. Ordinary
people like yourself are called, instructed, and empowered to conduct the affairs of the
Church, as in ancient times; for instance, I am an educator, our mission president in Buenos
Aires is an automobile salesman by occupation, and our president in Brazil is a contractor.
Men are ordained to the priesthood of God. They are endowed with the power of the Holy
Ghost and led by personal revelation. A living prophet guides the Church today. It is the
practice of the leaders in the Church to call people to work in a position suitable to their
talents and capacities. Here in South America, for instance, we use new members in one of
the organizations shortly after their baptism. Work in the Church is both a means to an end,
as well as an end in itself. People are called to fill positions in order to grow and develop
personally, as well as to make the organization function more effectively to bless others. This
personal growth is the great benefit one receives through service."
</p><p>
I further explained to my friend that because of the increasing numbers in the Church in
South America, we have in operation an extensive training program, the express purpose of
which is to give specific training to every person newly called to a position in the Church.
This is to make certain that each new officer knows his duty. It is our goal to fill every
position in the church organization. This gives members opportunity to develop through an
on-the-job training program. This training touches every facet of one's personality. He
becomes not only more effective as a church official, but a better, more capable citizen as
well.
</p><p>
"Therefore, with a steady stream of people joining the Church," I continued, "the
organizations can expand in an orderly fashion. Leadership training can benefit and bless
more and more of your fellow countrymen. I even have the temerity to suggest that this kind
of people&mdash;people who have been trained to think, who have had experience in solving
problems, who have accepted and discharged leadership responsibility&mdash;are the people you
ought to be seeking to staff your corporation."
</p><p>
<b>Promises Being Fulfilled</b>
</p><p>
I bore testimony to this man that the Lord is now hastening the fulfillment of his promises
and prophecies concerning this choice land and its people. They are receptive to the message
that God lives and that he directs, through revelation, his perfectly organized Church.
</p><p>
Our next stop is at El Cuzco, the ancient capital city of the Incan empire, situated at 11,000
feet in the tops of the Andes Mountains. We are in a press conference, and a reporter asks,
"What is the difference between The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints and other
churches?"
</p><p>
<b>Authority by Direct Revelation</b>
</p><p>
We quote from a living prophet to explain one of the major distinguishing features of the
Church. President David O. McKay has said, ". . . we believe in divine authority by direct
revelation rather than by descent." The power and authority came to this Church through the
visitation of angelic messengers: Peter, James, and John, the Apostles of old who as
resurrected beings, conferred their authority and power upon Joseph Smith and Oliver
Cowdery in this dispensation. We explained that this doctrine is both scriptural and logical,
for the Bible itself is a compilation of revelations. They were given at different periods of
time through various prophets over approximately 4,000 years. Just as each
prophet in times past left scripture as evidence of the divinity of his calling, so we offer to the
honest in heart today additional scriptures, both ancient and modern. These additional
revelations form the scriptural basis for the doctrine of The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
Next, stand with me in Chile at the doorway to a school, recently opened by the Church.
Bright-eyed youngsters march past into a new and marvelous world of learning that they have
never known before, of books and methods that are the newest and finest. We see a skilled
and experienced teacher willing to go at her own expense to teach these eager children and to
lead them to a testimony that the glory of God is intelligence
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>)
and that truth will make them free (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>).
</p><p>
Journey next to a city nestled in the center of the Brazilian coffee plantations (an industry,
incidentally, that we have been accused of trying to put out of business in Brazil). We are
here to attend a district conference. A fine-looking man, not a member of the Church two
years ago is speaking: "The first time I entered the chapel I could actually feel a good spirit
here&mdash;a spirit of warmth and friendliness, one of concern and love for one another, and of
brotherhood. I also felt that I must clean up my life in order to associate with you people.
You made me feel welcome and needed."
</p><p>
Like all those who visit our meetings, he was welcome and is needed. He is particularly
needed today because he now presides as the president of the branch he once visited. He holds
the authority and has the power to share with all men the same spirit that so influenced and
blessed his life.
</p><p>
<b>Brotherly Kindness</b>
</p><p>
The feelings of fraternity in this Church and the functions of its priesthood quorums bind men
together in a bond of brotherhood. It brings warmth of companionship that delights the soul
and makes life worthwhile. Love of fellow men penetrates from heart to heart across national
borders. It becomes the only effectual process that erases men's artificial boundaries and
unites them in a cause greater than their own political nationalism.
</p><p>
Finally accompany me as we become junior companions to some of the missionaries over
whom I preside. Recently, down in Argentina, my companion and I, at the invitation of a
member, went to visit his friend. Evidently we entered the wrong apartment building because
the man who responded to our knock was not the person whom we sought. My young
companion, typical of today's energetic and dedicated youth, promptly introduced us as
representatives "<i>de la Iglesia de Jesucristo de los Santos de los Ultimas Dias</i>" and asked the
man if he would like to know something about the Church. Our new-found friend said, "Yes,"
but after a short conversation when my companion offered to leave him a tract, he refused to
take it saying, "My church forbids me to read anything of a religious nature like this."
</p><p>
<b>Search for Truth Brings Freedom</b>
</p><p>
How grateful I am, my friends, that the enlightened search for truth by this Church frees a
man from fear and teaches him that life is to learn, that truth is to be sought and accepted
from any source&mdash;scientific or revealed. It teaches that God is our Father and teacher, that
we are son and pupil, and that we can actually become like him, this by learning and keeping
his commandments and doing his revealed will. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints teaches that man's pursuit of truth is his eternal quest: 
</p><p>
"And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom
thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
And now as we return from South America, I speak to all who can hear. Perhaps for the first
time you have heard the glad message that the gospel of Jesus Christ has been restored.
Perhaps you have had friends or neighbors who have recently joined The Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints. You have probably wondered why their lives changed so much;
why they seemed to be happier and busier, why they seemed to live more purposefully.
Should you, too, not seek information about this marvelous and sacred
message?
</p><p>
"Prove all things," Paul admonished, "hold fast that which is good"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_thes/5/21#21">1 Thes. 5:21</a>).
</p><p>
You, father and husband, as head of your household, should you not find release from the sins
of the world that beset you, through faith, sincere repentance, and baptism by immersion for
the remission of sins? Should you not find the strength to complete the change in your life,
for the strength will come through receiving the gift of the Holy Ghost? Should you not
possess the priesthood and experience its power? Should you not have the joy of certain
knowledge that Jesus is the Christ, that God lives? The Lord will not withhold this blessing
from any who sincerely seek it.
</p><p>
Look at that sweet companion by your side. Should your wife not find an outlet for sharing
her heaven-endowed gifts in unison with other good women? Would you deny her the
influences which strengthen her as a wife and mother?
</p><p>
And your most priceless possessions, what of them? I see that teenager at your side. Should
your teenager not have the opportunity to participate in a youth organization where youth
mutually improve one another?
</p><p>
And your little ones, what of them? How pliable, how susceptible to all the influences of life?
Should they not have the protection and the advantage of training in child-centered
organizations which teach them: "I am a child of God. My Heavenly Father loves me."
</p><p>
Should your entire family not kneel night and morning and receive the additional strength that
comes through a Wise and Loving Father? Should you and all members of your family not
seek and find the supreme joy and the abundant life that the Savior taught in his Church
restored again?
</p><p>
<b>Search for Better Life</b>
</p><p>
While men have been blinded by men and prejudiced by tradition in the lands of South
America, nevertheless, when they hear explained the doctrines of this Church, when they
understand its teachings, and when they see its programs in action, they are not antagonistic to
its message. Rather, they respond to the opportunity to hold the priesthood, to give service
freely, to exercise the power of leadership, to do something and be somebody, because the
promises of the Lord and the prophecies of his servants concerning these lands and this
people are now being fulfilled.
</p><p>
I bear my witness that this Church is indeed the restored Church of Jesus Christ, that he is at
its head directing it today by direct and authoritative revelation to his living prophet, President
David O. McKay. I know there is a great awakening among the people of South America and
a yearning for a better life&mdash;not only a desire for the material blessings but a deep searching
and longing for the spiritual heritage which they have been promised, to which they are
entitled. The Lord has set his hand to bless this choice land and this people of promise and
destiny. I invite all men everywhere to seek within this gospel the supreme joy that comes
from the certainty of this testimony, and I do it in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
