<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Samuel O. Bennion</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Samuel O. Bennion, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1944, pp. 65-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
At the beginning of my remarks I acknowledge the hand of the Lord in permitting me to be
here today. I pray the Lord that I may be sustained.
</p><p>
It was forty years ago now, at this particular time of the year that I was preparing to go on
my mission. I called on President Joseph F. Smith, according to appointment, and told him I
was ready to go. He said to me, "Brother Bennion, you stay here and help elect Theodore
Roosevelt, and then go." And I did.
</p><p>
I am delighted to be here and to see this great congregation. I enjoy the companionship of my
brethren; I would not want to live in mortality without it.
</p><p>
A TESTIMONY OF THE TRUTH HELPS UNDER DIFFICULTIES
</p><p>
Seventy-seven years ago my progenitors came down Emigration Canyon into this valley, and
they found here a desert&mdash;nothing that was inviting enough for them to want to stay. They
came from the green fields of England, into this desolate place; almost all they had in the
world was in a wagon box. And many others were in the same condition. But there was one
thing in their hearts, one thing that brought them from the shores of England: they had a
testimony of Jesus. They knew that the Redeemer lives; they knew that this is the work of
God, and they believed the prophet of God when he said, "This is the place," and, "Here we
will build a temple unto our God; here will be our home; this is where we are going to
reside."
</p><p>
The Indians could scarcely live. My parents knew them, and these Indians were living on the
rodents of the earth, and anything they could get. The same soil that is here now was here
then, but it was barren.
</p><p>
But the Lord had said through His prophet, Isaiah, centuries before:
</p><p>
The wilderness and the solitary place shall be glad for them; and the desert shall rejoice, and
blossom as the rose. It shall blossom abundantly, and rejoice even with joy and singing: . . .
they shall see the glory of the Lord, and the excellency of our God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/35/1-2#1">Isa. 35:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
Isaiah knew the Lord. He was a prophet of the living God, and it was given him to look
down through the stream of time. The Lord put those words into his mouth, and he delivered
that scripture, and this has become now one of the greatest gardens of the earth. The Lord had
planned for His people. Men could not live in this country who did not have a testimony of
the promises concerning it. All who are here today and those who hear my voice can see that
this great country has been made to blossom as a rose; it is lovely, as Isaiah predicted it
would be.
</p><p>
PROPHECIES FULFILLED
</p><p>
Go where you may, I care not where&mdash;I have not been abroad, but I have seen all the states of
the United States and Canada and Mexico, and it is all this country&mdash;and there are no more
fruitful fields than in this land where the Lord led the people, this once barren and forbidding
country.
</p><p>
Land that I positively know has been tilled for sixty years&mdash;I have seen it&mdash;has produced a
produced a better crop this year than at any time in its history, because it has been fertilized
and cared for. Water used in the right way, with crop rotation, and fertilization, have made it
what it is.
</p><p>
MEMBERSHIP OF THE CHURCH BLESSED
</p><p>
And as it has been with the land, so it has been with the membership of this Church. There
never was greater strength in the land than at the present time. It does not make any
difference to me, brethren, what people think about the Mormon Church, or its doctrines, I
cannot help thinking of the words of the Lord to Job the prophet: "Who is this that darkeneth
counsel by words without knowledge?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/38/2#2">Job 38:2</a>).
Who is it? Who dares to question? The
plan of God is here. He further said to Job:
</p><p>
Where wast thou when I laid the foundations of the earth? declare, if thou hast understanding
. . . . Whereupon are the foundations thereof fastened? or who laid the comer stone thereof. . .
and all the sons of God shouted for joy?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/38/4,6-7#4">Job 38:4,6-7</a>).
</p><p>
The great program of God for his children was planned from the beginning and when He
came to Joseph Smith, He revealed unto him this plan of salvation. And this plan came to you
and to me and will come to all men who make an investigation of it. Joseph Smith bore that
testimony to the children of men. He also brought to our attention the words of Paul the
apostle: "Wherefore I give you to understand that no man speaking by the Spirit of God
calleth Jesus accursed: and that no man can say that Jesus is the Lord, but by the Holy
Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/3#3">1 Cor. 12:3</a>).
Jesus said, "Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit he
cannot enter into the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
Nay, more, "he cannot see the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/3#3">John 3:3</a>).
</p><p>
I have listened to hundreds of men and women who have come out of the world, so-called,
into this Church, who have been baptized and who have had the witness and power of God
given to them by the Holy Ghost, say that they could no more go back into their old way of
thinking than they could go back to yesterday&mdash;they have been born again into a new world.
</p><p>
The faith of the Latter-day Saints is an established fact, and men and women of honor and
integrity, by the thousands, from all parts of the world, are located in these valleys where the
Lord led them. Here there is power such as the world has never seen; truly out of Zion goes
forth the law (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/3#3">Isa. 2:3</a>).
</p><p>
I call the attention of all to the words of the President of this Church, that were read
yesterday; they came from the Prophet of God. And to the testimony that David O. McKay
bore, and to the sermon that was delivered by President Clark. They are all readable. They set
forth the issues of the present day. How many of us will follow them when we go back into
our homes; how many will say to the children of men among whom we labor: "The word of
God came to us again." Call their attention to these commandments:
</p><p>
Thou shalt not lie, thou shalt not steal, thou shalt not bear false witness against thy neighbor,
thou shalt honor the Sabbath day and keep it holy, thou shalt not take the name of the Lord
thy God in vain, and thou shalt not commit adultery
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/7-8,14-16#7">Ex. 20:7-8,14-16</a>).
</p><p>
The plan of God is here to fertilize the spiritual fields of the Church. As the land has
produced more since the membership of the Church began to till it, as it has grown richer
under careful supervision, so will the strength of the children of men grow through the
powerful influence of God, and our people will carry off victoriously the plan of God, for this
is His work. It will never fail. It does not make any difference to me what men think about
Mormonism, or what they think about this Church. I mingle among them; I have done so for
many years&mdash;many of them are fine men, good men. There are good men in the Church and
out of the Church, and when we find out what they are good for, they should be put to use.
But even though they may not recognize it, there is a Power guiding this people to high
destiny and even now they have become, as the Prophet Joseph said they would, a "mighty
people in the midst of the Rocky Mountains."
</p><p>
A CLOSING TESTIMONY
</p><p>
I pray the Lord to bless us. I am thankful for the privilege I have of being here. I know this
is the work of God and that he lives, that he came to Joseph Smith and that Joseph Smith
brought to the world again the plan by which all men may know their Redeemer and give
praise to him.
</p><p>
I do not believe this is the end of "Sweet hour of prayer," I believe it is just a beginning. The
hour of prayer will go on into time beyond our power of conception and will be a part of the
great story of the Latter-day Saints. Last December I heard in one of our stake conferences a
lovely chorus of about a hundred and fifteen or twenty young women. Their music was most
inspiring. I said to myself then and I say it now, I expect to hear the voices of millions of
such beautiful singers and participate in countless hours of prayer.
</p><p>
The Lord bless you. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
