<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1944, pp. 156-157</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren: We come to the conclusion of a great Conference. Certainly I, in my lifetime, have
not attended a greater, and in some respects I think this is the finest of any at which I have
ever been present.
</p><p>
I just want to say one word: I think the quotation I shall use will typify the spirit of this
Conference. On the evening of the meal of the Passover chamber, after the apostles had
assembled, after they quarreled a bit among themselves about precedence, after the Savior had
washed their feet, after they had eaten the Paschal Supper, after Judas had gone to work out
the betrayal, after the Savior had instituted the sacrament, he then preached some great
discourses. The last one before they left the chamber related to the Comforter, the Holy
Ghost, and I am reading from John 14:26-27:
</p><p>
But the Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my name, he shall
teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto
you (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>).
</p><p>
The Holy Ghost has been with us during this Conference, and also the gifts of the Holy
Ghost, and may that Being continue with us, that to us also He may bring all things to our
remembrance, whatsoever we have heard here at this conference.
</p><p>
Then the Lord continues:
</p><p>
Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you: not as the world giveth, give I unto you.
Let not your heart be troubled, neither let it be afraid
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/27#27">John 14:27</a>).
</p><p>
May that peace and that comfort and that consolation go with us to our homes and be with us
until we meet again, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
