<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Two Great Truths</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Bruce R. McConkie</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Bruce R. McConkie, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 146-150</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Two great truths must be accepted by mankind if they shall save themselves: first, that Jesus
is the Christ, the Messiah, the Only Begotten, the very Son of God, whose atoning blood and
resurrection save us from the physical and spiritual death brought to us by the Fall; and next,
that God has restored to the earth, in these last days, through the Prophet Joseph, his Holy
Priesthood with the fullness of the everlasting gospel, for the salvation of all men on the
earth. Without these truths man may not hope for the riches of the life hereafter. (See THE
IMPROVEMENT ERA, vol. 38, pp. 204-205.)
</p><p>
Those words were given by the First Presidency of the Church in a testimony to the world on
the occasion of the one hundredth anniversary of the establishment of the Quorum of the
Twelve Apostles in this dispensation, and if the Spirit will give me utterance, I would like to
say a few things with reference to them.
</p><p>
SALVATION CENTERED IN CHRIST
</p><p>
We are the people of God. We are the members of the kingdom of God on earth, which is
this Church, and we have the knowledge and light and revelation which causes us to know
that salvation is centered in Christ. We believe in Christ. We are the Church of Christ. We
believe that through his atoning blood and the sacrifice which he worked out, all men will be
raised in immortality, that is to say, the body and the spirit will be reunited, a resurrection
will be brought to pass, and we believe that those who obey the laws and ordinances of the
gospel will gain, in addition to immortality, the glorious gift of eternal life.
</p><p>
We have the witness and knowledge that Christ was the Firstborn of the Father, that in the
spirit world, in the pre-existent eternities, he obeyed the laws of the Father and by diligence
and righteousness ascended even there to the status of a God.
</p><p>
We recognize him as the Creator, under the Father, of the world and all that in it is. We
worship him as the God who revealed his saving truths to all the ancient prophets, those
mighty leaders who have come in every age when he has had a people on the earth.
</p><p>
We believe that he came into the world, born of Mary, literally and actually, as we are born
of our mothers; that he came into the world, born of God the Eternal Father, the Almighty
Elohim, literally and actually, as we are born of our earthly fathers.
</p><p>
We believe that he had the power to lay down his life, and the power to take it up again
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/17-18#17">John 10:17-18</a>),
because Mary was his mother and God was his father.
</p><p>
We certify of Christ; we preach of Christ; and we have the knowledge that salvation is in and
through him and him alone. "Salvation was, and is, and is to come, in and through the atoning
blood of Christ, the Lord Omnipotent" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/18#18">Mosiah 3:18</a>), and "how great the importance," as
Lehi expressed it, "to make these things known unto the inhabitants of the earth" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/8#8">2 Ne. 2:8</a>).
</p><p>
ACCEPTANCE OF PROPHETS
</p><p>
Now it is not possible, in my judgment, for people in the world to accept Christ and come to
salvation, unless at one and the same time they accept the prophets whom Christ has sent and
receive the administration of holy ordinances under their hands.
</p><p>
Christ and his prophets are one. We could not believe in Christ if there were not prophets to
declare Christ and his saving truths unto us. The Apostle Paul reasoned on this subject, and he
said: 
</p><p>
. . . how shall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how shall they
hear without a preacher?
</p><p>
And how shall they preach, except they be sent?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/10/14-15#14">Rom. 10:14-15</a>).
</p><p>
Except for Christ, there would be no salvation. Except for the prophets of God, sent in the
various ages of the earth's history, the testimony of Christ would not be borne, the message of
salvation would not be taught, and there would be no legal administrators who could perform
the ordinances of salvation for men, that is, perform them so they will be binding on earth
and sealed eternally in the heavens.
</p><p>
So it is that the Lord has sent prophets. No one would suppose that he could believe in Christ
and reject Peter, James, and John. The Lord and his prophets go hand in hand. Christ said, "I
am the true vine, and my Father is the husbandman"; then he said to his Apostles, "Ye are the
branches" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/1,5#1">John 15:1,5</a>).
The branches and the vine are connected. He taught also that if the
branches were torn away from him, they would wither and die and be cast into the fire
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/6#6">John 15:6</a>). If
people in the world would pick the fruit of eternal life off the branches, they have to accept
the prophets, for the branches are the prophets.
</p><p>
GOSPEL DISPENSATIONS
</p><p>
This has been the system that the Lord has had from the days of Father Adam to the present
moment, and it will continue eternally. The Lord sent Adam in the beginning to teach the
principles of salvation. Adam had a dispensation of the gospel, that is, the Lord revealed
direct from heaven to Adam, dispensed to him, the saving truths; and anybody that lived in
the days of Adam, to be saved in the celestial kingdom, had to accept Jesus Christ in whom
salvation lay, and also had to accept Adam as the revealer, the prophet, the legal administrator
who taught the laws of salvation and administered the ordinances thereof. It went in just that
manner in every succeeding dispensation.
</p><p>
In the days of Enoch, if a man would be saved in the celestial kingdom, he accepted Christ as
the Savior of the world and Enoch as his prophet. And so in the days of Abraham, of Moses,
of Peter, James, and John, and of this day.
</p><p>
I suppose that the Church procedure was not too different in former days. They had testimony
meetings then, and when people stood up in them, as they were moved upon by the Holy
Ghost, they bore witness that Jesus Christ was the Son of God who would come, and that
Adam was his prophet, or Enoch, or the head of whatever dispensation was involved; and that
is the way it is today. We certify of Jesus Christ, and we certify of Joseph Smith, and they
are one. They are united perfectly.
</p><p>
For he that receiveth my servants receiveth me; 
</p><p>
And he that receiveth me receiveth my Father; 
</p><p>
And he that receiveth my Father receiveth my Father's kingdom; therefore all that my
Father hath shall be given unto him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/36-38#36">D&amp;C 84:36-38</a>).
</p><p>
VISION OF ABRAHAM
</p><p>
Now may I mention the great vision that the Patriarch Abraham had? You recall that the Lord
showed him the pre-existent hosts and, more particularly, the noble and great in that world.
Abraham saw them, the intelligences, the spirit sons of God our Father, the noble and great
spirit who were among them, and the Lord said to him, ". . . Abraham, thou art one of them;
thou wast chosen before thou wast born" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/23#23">Abr. 3:23</a>).
</p><p>
As with Abraham, so with all the prophets of God. Sometimes someone may wonder, that is,
someone in the world, how is it that the Father and the Son would appear to a
fourteen-and-a-half- year-old boy in the spring of 1820, to usher in, as we express it, the
Dispensation of the Fullness of Times.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith sat with Father Abraham in the councils of eternity, and Joseph Smith was
ordained as Abraham was ordained to come down and be the head of a gospel dispensation
here. He had ascended by virtue of obedience, intelligence, progression, and righteousness to a
high state of spiritual perfection in that world. When he came here, he brought with him the
talents and abilities, the deep spirituality, and the innate righteousness that he developed back
there under the tutelage of God the Father.
</p><p>
In the eternal worlds, the Firstborn spirit offspring of the Father was Jehovah who is Jesus
Christ. He was pre-eminent. Standing next to Christ was the great spirit, Michael. Christ was
ordained as a lamb slain from the foundation of the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/8#8">Rev. 13:8</a>), chosen to come here and be the
Redeemer. Michael was prepared and chosen and sent here as Father Adam, the first man of
all men, the first flesh upon the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/3/7#7">Moses 3:7</a>),
the head of the human race, and the presiding high
priest, under Christ, over all the earth.
</p><p>
PLACE OF JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
The spirit men who were associated with Christ and with Adam in the pre-existent eternities,
and who were more valiant than all their fellows, were the ones chosen to head the various
dispensations of the gospel. One of these was the Prophet Joseph Smith. It doesn't take much
reflection then, it seems to me, for us to know that Joseph Smith was one of the dozen
greatest spirits that God the Eternal Father had in all the councils of eternity; that he came so
as to be here at the appointed time and at the express hour and at the very moment that the
Lord designed to open this dispensation He was here to take his part in that event.
</p><p>
I do not think that the Father and the Son would have appeared to an ordinary
fourteen-and-a-half-year-old boy, if he had gone out into that grove of trees to ask the Lord
which of all the churches was right (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/11-19#11">JS&mdash;H 1:11-19</a>).
I think the Lord had been preparing Joseph Smith for that
event from all eternity; that Joseph Smith had the spiritual stature, the strength for
righteousness that enabled him to endure the vision; that he had the talent and ability to press
forward in righteousness in the kingdom of God on earth: first, to establish it; and then,
somewhat, to perfect its organization before he was taken home, before he sealed his
testimony with his blood.
</p><p>
In my judgment Christ and his prophets are one; and salvation in this day is, first, through
Christ and his atoning sacrifice, and it is, second, through accepting the atoning sacrifice and
the doctrines of Christ as they have been revealed by the Prophet Joseph Smith, and as they
are taught by the living oracles who wear the mantle of the Prophet and stand at this moment
at the head of the kingdom of God on earth.
</p><p>
PERSONAL EXPERIENCE
</p><p>
May I just tell you one experience that I had. I have never told this to any person before,
except my wife. Six months ago in the Solemn Assembly, when the First Presidency of the
Church were sustained, as I sat down here behind one of these lower pulpits, the voice of the
Lord came into my mind as certainly, I am sure, as the voice of the Lord came into the mind
of Enos (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/enos/1/5,10#5">Enos 1:5,10</a>),
and the very words were formed, and it said: 
</p><p>
"These are they whom I have chosen as the First Presidency of my Church. Follow
them"&mdash;those few words.
</p><p>
I have had a testimony of the divinity of this work from my youth. I was reared in a family
where love was the motive force, where my parents taught me righteousness, and I have
grown up with a testimony. But that witness was an added assurance. It meant to me, if I
hadn't known before, which I did know before, that this is the Lord's Church; that his hand is
over it; that he organized it; that these men who preside are called of him: that they are his
anointed; that if we will follow them as they follow Christ, we will have eternal life, which is
my prayer for myself and for all Israel. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
