<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Keep the Commandments</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Stephen L Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Stephen L Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 137-144</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters:
</p><p>
I recall an occasion in the life of President Heber J. Grant which brings to me some thoughts
for this conference. It was shortly before he became ill and near the close of his
administration. He came to the temple one Thursday to meet with the brethren of the First
Presidency and the Council of the Twelve in the regular weekly meeting. In a thoughtful and
reflective mood, he said, in substance:
</p><p>
PRESIDENT GRANT'S CONCLUSION
</p><p>
Brethren, in the natural course of events my administration is nearing its close. I have been
wondering what I might do in the time that remains to best promote the welfare of the Church
and the people.
</p><p>
For a moment I thought he had some new project to announce, but this was quickly dispelled
when he continued by saying that he had reached a very simple conclusion. He said the
conclusion he had reached was that he could do nothing that would be of more value and
lasting good to the cause of our Father and his people than to devote the remainder of his life
and effort to getting the people to keep the commandments. I am sure that all the brethren
who heard him were in agreement and deeply impressed by the farseeing wisdom of his
utterance. I was, and I have recalled the incident on many occasions.
</p><p>
We live in a world of sensationalism. "What's new?" is the inquiry on everyone's lips. It
often constitutes a form of friendly salutation. There is an insatiable demand for news, and the
news to be arresting and intriguing, must be far out of the ordinary, often shocking and tragic,
and the "scoops" which usually win the plaudits of the people in the great majority of cases
arise out of the perpetration of high crimes, catastrophes, disasters, scandals&mdash;public and
private&mdash;and the doings and antics of notorious people.
</p><p>
KEEPING THE COMMANDMENTS
</p><p>
Keeping the commandments, as President Grant used the phrase, is not news in the modern
sense. It is seldom dramatic. It doesn't often arrest attention, and very infrequently wins a
place in the headlines for a man or woman, and there are those who look with a measure of
contempt and belittlement upon persons who order their "humdrum" lives in strict conformity
with all the commandments.
</p><p>
In spite of the prosaic and commonplace aspect of this subject, I have long been convinced,
my brethren and sisters, that the most challenging, dramatic, and vital thing in our lives is this
"keeping the commandments." It tests every fiber of our beings. It is at once a demonstration
of our intelligence, our knowledge, our character, and our wisdom. I will try to show that this
is true.
</p><p>
INTELLIGENCE REQUIRED
</p><p>
It takes intelligence, and a high order of intelligence, to worship God truly and understand his
commandments and their far-reaching significance. Some of these sophisticates who call the
good "dumb" give a very convincing demonstration of their own intellectual limitations. I
observe, too, that there are some of our scholars who disparage the intellectual effort put forth
in the acquisition of religious and spiritual truth and the science of theology. Out of my own
limited exposure to education and my observation of learned men I do not hesitate to assert
that it takes just as high an order of intelligence to comprehend and assimilate spiritual truth
and divine law as it does to master the equations and formulas in the field of secular
education. The great body of divine scripture, although contained in few books, has been,
through the centuries. and will continue to be, a challenge to the most profound scholarship
and the greatest minds which the world has produced, and it would be well for the cynics and
agnostics and sophisticates of the present day to remember that many of the most outstanding
institutions of learning had their inception under religious auspices; that churches and church
people have been the foster fathers of education and that the Holy Bible has inspired more
goodness, high idealism, lofty sentiment, freedom of thought, justice, mercy, and quest for
learning than any other book and perhaps all other books ever produced in all the history of
the world. Let no man disdain the intellectuality of spiritual learning.
</p><p>
How glorious and satisfying to the inquisitive nature of man is spiritual and religious
knowledge and understanding. The intelligence and purpose of God made manifest in the
orderly organization of the universe, the place of man in the great design furnish a concept,
not only more lofty and idealistic than anything in all literature but one that is also more
practical in application to the problems of man and society than any other which has ever
been tried and tested.
</p><p>
IGNORANCE OF DIVINE TRUTH
</p><p>
From every quarter of the world we have evidences of a dearth of the knowledge of God and
his ways. I think it safe to say that the greater part of all the opposition and enmity to social
progress, to liberty, justice, and peace is attributable to lack of understanding, a woeful
ignorance of divine concepts and truth. I cannot see how the rank and file of the people who
are classed as atheistic communists could accept the godless totalitarianism of Marx and Lenin
if they really had a comprehension and knowledge of the Fatherhood of God, the brotherhood
of man, and the eternal plans of the Father for the well-being and exaltation of his children. I
can understand how their leaders, lustful for power and domination, and beset by the constant
fear of losing their unrighteous dominion will subordinate every decent, honorable, and
virtuous principle to the gaining of their ends, but I cannot believe that even their own people
would support these avaricious leaders if they had the truth.
</p><p>
REACTIONS OF RUSSIANS
</p><p>
A few years ago I was in San Francisco looking for a publishing house that would print some
of our literature in the Russian language. By mistake I went into a printing establishment
which I afterwards learned to be communistic. You should have seen the stony stare, and curt
dismissal I received, when I asked if they printed religious literature. Afterwards I found a
place where I was received by an intelligent Russian man who was sympathetic with my
errand. I told him that it was our purpose to make some preparation for missionary work
among his people. We discussed the situation for some time, and he made the significant
remark: "Only God can save Russia." He published a Russian newspaper, non-communist,
with subscribers all across the nation. He gave me the information that there are
approximately 15,000 Russian-speaking people around the San Francisco bay area and two
million in the United States. He said there are approximately 900,000 displaced Russians in
Europe, and he thought our missionaries could begin work among some of these Russians,
looking forward to the time when through them there might be an introduction of the gospel
into Russia itself. He knew something of our principles and our people and professed
admiration for them. I felt that there was some evidence of his sincerity, when, after
automatically offering me a cigarette, he immediately withdrew it and said, "Oh, I forgot, your
people don't smoke and drink." Well, Russia is not the subject of my remarks, but I think that
the present plight of that nation is a pertinent and persuasive illustration of the need of
knowledge, spiritual and theological knowledge, as a basis for righteousness and peace.
</p><p>
APPRECIATION FOR KNOWLEDGE
</p><p>
At this point, I wish to voice appreciation for the great body of knowledge which has come to
us in the revelations of this dispensation. When I think of the light which the Prophet Joseph
Smith has thrown upon the knowledge of his day and our day, his interpretations of Holy
Writ for centuries obscure in meaning to the learned of the earth, his enlargement of the
vision of man, his incomparable contributions to the understanding of the vital relationships in
life, home, family, community, government; his expositions of heaven and earth, salvation,
exaltation, and eternity&mdash;all stamping him with the unmistakable marks of mighty faith and
prophetic vision and understanding, I feel to exclaim with the author of our beloved hymn:
</p><p>
Praise to the man who communed with Jehovah, Jesus anointed that Prophet and Seer.
</p><p>
He was "blessed to open the last dispensation" and "kings shall extol him" and "nations shall
revere him" when the knowledge which he brought is disseminated through the earth to the
understanding of the people thereof.
</p><p>
REASON BEHIND EVERY COMMANDMENT
</p><p>
So, my brethren and sisters, we need knowledge&mdash;knowledge of the things of the Lord. Our
Father said in the very beginning of his work, "let every man <i>learn</i> his duty"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>). It may be that
there are a few of the commandments, the reasons for which are not very apparent to us. We
accept some on faith as did the prophets of old, but in the main there is a sound discernible
reason behind every commandment. A knowledge of the gospel reveals that reason, and gives
additional encouragement and strength in keeping it.
</p><p>
For example the man who looks upon tithing as nothing more than a method of gathering
money does not understand the law; but he who recognizes in it a great principle of true
worship and spiritual growth will find infinitely more satisfaction in complying with its
requirements. He will understand that the true test of devotion is the giving of one's sell and
that when a man parts with the proceeds of his labors, giving that which represents the
expenditure of his brain power, his muscular strength, and his energy, he not only
demonstrates his loyalty to the Lord and his work, but he adds to his own faith and his
spiritual resources, his contentment, and his happiness. He builds up loyalty. He attains power
to control rebellious and critical thoughts and tendencies. His conscience is clear. He can sleep
comfortably with himself. Truly he grows in spiritual power.
</p><p>
Every commandment of God is spiritual in nature. There are no carnal commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/34#34">D&amp;C 29:34</a>). We
have learned this from modern revelation. While the commandments have effect upon the
body and temporal things they are all in essence spiritual. The Word of Wisdom is spiritual. It
is true that it enjoins the use of deleterious substances and makes provision for the health of
the body. But the largest measure of good derived from its observance is in increased faith
and the development of more spiritual power and wisdom. Likewise, the most regrettable and
damaging effects of its infractions are spiritual, also. Injury to the body may be comparatively
trivial to the damage to the soul in the destruction of faith and the retardation of spiritual
growth. So I say, every commandment involves a spiritual growth. So I say, every
commandment involves a spiritual principle.
</p><p>
COURAGE TO SAY "NO"
</p><p>
I mentioned character in connection with keeping the commandments. When I come to think
of it, keeping the commandments is about the only yardstick I know in measuring and
appraising character, particularly with reference to those who have the knowledge our people
have. We commonly refer to character as strong or weak, gentle or harsh, honest or deceitful,
charitable or "tight," and so on all down through the long list of attributes. Perhaps, the
classification dreaded most by red-blooded people is that of weakling. That designation seems
to be resented more than them almost any other, excluding criminal appellations, and, most
unfortunately, among these are some who are boastful of sinful records and reputations.
Weaklings are those lacking in the necessary stamina, strength, and courage to sustain a
position. A person can be helpless physically and still not be a weakling, if he or she has the
disposition and inner strength and courage to fight bravely on. It is the moral cowards and the
ignorant who corrupt the world. I am aware that none of us has all the strength, resistance,
and courage he would like to have, but I am afraid that there are many among us who have
permitted their moral strength to be tapped and drained until there may not be much solid
character remaining. They wouldn't like to be called weaklings or cowards, but if they will
examine themselves thoughtfully and frankly some may well admit that their strength is gone.
I think I can tell you how many have come to this misfortune. They have been trying to ape
the ways of the world. Many have forgotten that they have been called out of the world and
enjoined to keep themselves unspotted from its sins. I suppose some haven't even known what
that meant and they have yielded to the sophistry and the sophistication and the practices of
worldly-minded institutions and groups. Teddy Roosevelt used to say that it often took more
courage to say "no" than it did to face a bear with a pistol. We've had a lot of men and
women who unfortunately didn't have the courage to say "no" and who unfortunately also did
not have the pride of their great heritage in the Church and kingdom of God. It's a great pity
that it has been so. Think of the immeasurable good these men and women might have done
if they hadn't been so weak. If they had had the strength of character to stand for the right as
they knew it. Think of the admiration they could have commanded for themselves and for
their Church by simply declining the cigarette and the glass of beer and participation in
indecent stories and tolerance for cheap jokes and witticisms directed at sacred things in their
religion. I think of the strength they might have developed in themselves and in the youth
who look to them if they had resisted the slot-machine, petty gambling on a golf game, a
horse race or cards, and the allurement of the Sunday movie.
</p><p>
RELIGION AND CONDUCT
</p><p>
I understand that there are organized forces in our communities telling young people that
these and other infractions of our moral code have no religious significance and urging them
to be free from such restraint. They would disassociate conduct from religion. Well, they
can't do it any more than they can separate living from life.
</p><p>
Do you think that weak abandonment of well-recognized standards has commanded even the
respect and admiration of new-found friends of the world? What a tragic mistake it is for any
man to reach false conclusion that in order to get business or political preferment or
social prestige he must compromise the truth. I wish that a hundred or a thousand men of this
Church, if there be that many, would withdraw themselves from lodges and secret orders
which they were counseled never to join. It is my opinion that most of our men allied with
these secret orders had to show some weakness before they were invited. It is my observation
that invitations come only to those who do not give wholehearted loyal support to the Church
and its standards. The Church needs the undivided allegiance of these men, and they need the
Church, as do their families also. Just so sure as they divide their allegiance the world will
claim them. I make an earnest appeal to all my brethren who have joined these secret orders
to leave them and renew their associations in the quorums of priesthood and the organizations
and activities of the Church. I know that every single one who responds will be blessed in so
doing.
</p><p>
MAINTENANCE OF STANDARDS
</p><p>
I have a further word to say to my brethren who are members of service clubs, chambers of
commerce, and other non-secret business, professional and social organizations. Brethren, you
don't need to abandon any principle, any standard or approved practice of the Church to
which we have the honor to belong to maintain good standing in these organizations. If you
do, you had better get out. Our men can and do win the respect of all if they have the
courage of their convictions. There is little respect on the part of any for the weakling. I have
found it a great honor to represent this mighty Church of the Lord in many capacities. I have
not always felt worthy of the honor, but I trust that the pride of membership in the Church
and kingdom of God will never leave me. The Apostle Paul must have looked down through
the ages of men and foreseen their weaknesses, when, and giving that famous definition of the
gospel, he said:
</p><p>
For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto salvation . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
It is too bad when men and women become ashamed of the gospel. When they do, they
succumb to their weakness, the world soon gets them and they lose the richest things of life.
If therefore, my brethren and sisters, and my other friends who may listen, if you would
develop great character, the strength of constant purpose, resistance to evil, nobility in thought
and purpose, if you would know the richness of life and experience contentment and its
deepest satisfactions, keep the commandments.
</p><p>
NEED OF WISDOM
</p><p>
Just another thought, and I am done. We all prize wisdom. It is said to be the greatest of
gifts. It is really the power to apply beneficent knowledge in all the decisions and vicissitudes
of life. How we need wisdom in the composition of the troubles and difficulties of the world.
How we need wisdom in our own affairs, with our families, our business, and our
associations. Almost every day is a day of decision. What to do. What choice to make. I don't
know of a better way to secure the wisdom that we need than by keeping the commandments.
We are enjoined by the commandments to study, to pray, to work and to serve, and be
humble and contrite of spirit. The great promises are to the meek who shall inherit the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/5#5">Matt. 5:5</a>).
Wisdom is not to be found among the arrogant, the haughty and self-sufficient, nor among the
sinful and the anti-Christs of the world. Wisdom is a gift to the prayerful student, to the
faithful and the obedient, to those who repose their trust in the counsels of the spirit and the
priesthood of God.
</p><p>
There was great import in those inspiring, simple words of President Grant's uttered in the
Holy Temple. They embodied the message that has come down to us through all the
presidents of the Church. I know it is the message of our present President and his associates.
It has been voiced a thousand times in the words of every true leader. It is not news, but it
will never grow old. It is the eternal message for the government of man&mdash;keep the
commandments. Oh God, grant us the intelligence, the knowledge, the character, and the
wisdom to obey, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
