<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Just One Boy"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 24-26</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I seek only to be able to speak the truth, to merit the Spirit of the Lord which will direct me
and bless me in so doing. I appreciate the wonderful sermons which have been delivered here
from the first through Brother Dyer's.
</p><p>
I sat thinking a moment ago of my sainted father who left his little family and departed this
earth more than thirty-five years ago, how he went into the missionary field at the call of the
Lord through the Brethren, in his late teens, carrying copies of the Book of Mormon with
testimony and conviction, expressing his deepest assurance of the validity of the work he
represented and yet without adequate knowledge, perhaps, because he was but a boy and
because much knowledge now available was not had, to defend his viewpoint in the eyes of
the world. He had but his testimony, his faith, and the Book.
</p><p>
As President Smith spoke I marveled that we have lived long enough and that we live in a
time, you and I, when the wise men, the honest men of the world, are coming to understand
some of the things the Lord has taught us through all the years since the establishment of the
Church.
</p><p>
As President Smith referred to the age of eight and his faith that a youngster at that age can
know, I thought of my little children and then of a book published recently, written by two of
the most accepted, and I think effective, child psychologists of the day, commenting on the
age "eight" in the lives of the young.
</p><p>
"Eight seems to be an age when much that was not comprehended before is often easily
understood. At that age it is almost as though a new dimension has been added to the child's
understanding."
</p><p>
It is remarkable that qualified and earnest seekers after truth should discover that at age eight
a new dimension enters into the life of the child. The Lord assured us of this when he talked
of the age of accountability long ago
(<a href="http://scriptures.byu.edu/getscrip.php?ID=23656#11">Gen. 17:11 (JST)</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25,27#25">D&amp;C 68:25,27</a>).
</p><p>
Of one thing implicit in both President Smith's and Brother Dyer's remarks, I would speak
for just a few moments.
</p><p>
A thoughtful friend phoned this morning to tell me of a book he had just received&mdash;I had not
seen a copy nor is it available in our bookstores yet&mdash;a book called, <i>I Found God in Soviet Russia</i>,
in which a man tells of his own experiences as a prisoner in a concentration camp in
Siberia.
</p><p>
He talks of the religious faith that permitted people to endure and survive.
He mentions in at least four different places, and this would perhaps be a satisfying if
sorrowful and surprising thing for us to know, that in a concentration camp in Siberia there is
a little band of members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, meeting faithfully
and loyally, unwilling to deny or let rest or become indifferent to their responsibilities even
though to be a member of the Church makes them liable to life imprisonment according to the
book.
</p><p>
The book notes that these Mormons insisted on coming together in the name of the 
Lord&mdash;that when they had a few minutes they met to worship God in their own way.
</p><p>
When I think how the Lord must love and look with compassion upon such individuals, when
out of my own experience as a parent I can see how much I love my little ones, I can
understand (at least within my limitations) what the Lord meant when he talked about the
worth of souls in his sight. And I believe I may understand it more impressively and
movingly today than I have ever understood it before.
</p><p>
May I read you some words with which all are familiar, and read them in context of what has
been said?
</p><p>
"Remember the worth of souls is great in the sight of God;<br /> 
"For behold, the Lord your Redeemer suffered death in the flesh; wherefore he suffered the
pain of all men, that all men might repent and come unto him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/10-11#10">D&amp;C 18:10-11</a>).
</p><p>
There follows the great statement of the joy of the Lord in the soul that repenteth, and this: 
</p><p>
"And if it so be that you should labor all your days in crying repentance unto this people, and
bring, save it be one soul unto me, how great shall be your joy with him in the kingdom of
my father!"<br />
And then the marvelous statement that ". . . if your joy will be great with one soul . . . how
great will be your joy if you should bring many souls unto me!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15-16#15">D&amp;C 18:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
I have in mind to express my testimony about the importance of the one, to add my humble
witness to the charge that has been given every teacher and parent, every youth-influencing,
every adult-influencing Latter-day Saint, to be concerned about the one individual child of
God.
</p><p>
I heard a statement as I drove toward Brigham Young University the other morning from the
Talmud, or so it was quoted: "To save one life is like saving a whole nation." And I began to
think of other statements, including the one from the eighteenth section of the Doctrine and
Covenants, to which we have alluded. I thought of the statement of Oliver Wendell Holmes,
who said, "Every individual is an omnibus." Do you see the significance and implication of
this?
</p><p>
As we have the marvelous blessing of setting missionaries apart, I can seldom refrain from
thinking of them (and occasionally say it) that in each of them, as in each of us, is wrapped
up a heritage and a promise, for each is a distillation of much that has gone before, and
beyond all that is represented in the individual now and of the past, there is also the future,
because in each of us are the seeds of the future; in each of us there is, in fact, the capacity
and possibility of becoming many.
</p><p>
Could I tell you one story which bears repetition&mdash;and I have had the blessing of repeating it
in some of the stakes of the Church. It is the most significant single experience I have ever
had, personally, about the importance of one. It happened long enough ago that I think the
individual involved would not be conscious of our noting him, though I see no harm if he is.
</p><p>
A man walked into these grounds and into an office in the Bureau of Information one day
long ago. He interrupted a conversation which was private and serious, and did it without
apology. He was quite an elderly man; he was not what you would call an attractive human
being. He was unkempt, unshaven; he reeked of alcohol and tobacco.
</p><p>
He walked over to the desk where I sat, pointed his hand in the direction of the temple, and
said, "How do you get in there?" I assumed that he was a tourist, one of the infrequent but
occasional few who do not understand the purpose and the reason of temple-going and who
have become affronted because they are not taken into the temple, and perhaps had come to
complain.
</p><p>
I told him as best I could, or began to, the story of the temple, but had 
proceeded only a little distance when he interrupted.  He waved me away and said, "Oh, you
don't have to tell me all that, I know that.  I am a Mormon."
</p><p>
"Well," I said, "if you are a member of the Church and you know all of this, what is it you
want from me?"  He said, "Frankly, nothing.  There isn't anything you have to give me.  I am
here because my wife insisted on my coming in, but I have fulfilled my errand," and out he
went.
</p><p>
I tried to pick up the threads of the conversation and finish it, and later, as I sat thinking
about him and his story, I looked out the window and saw him walking by the Joseph and
Hyrum [Smith] monuments with a younger woman.  I went out to talk with them.  She
identified herself as his wife.  He had been married three times; each previous wife had died
after bearing a large family.
</p><p>
There are two questions I asked him, which I think each person here would do well to hear
answered as he answered them.  I asked, in effect, how he had come to his feeling of
antagonism and indifference.  He told me that at age nineteen he had been ejected from a
chapel by a bishop's counselor who had been summoned because of the boy's trouble-making
in class.  One thing that had been said, this man remembered for nearly sixty years.  As he
was thrown out, someone objected.  The answer that came from the counselor who had the
task in hand was, "Ah, let him go, he is just one kid!"
</p><p>
He went, and he never came back, nor was there ever any visiting, never any outpouring or
increase of the love that should follow reproof, according to the Lord.  He moved to another
area of the land, married, had a family; his wife passed away and he married again, his
second wife died after bearing a family also.  He had come to Salt Lake City at the insistence
of his third wife, who, having been taught by the missionaries and converted to the principles
of the gospel, had brought him here hoping that somehow he might be touched&mdash;he, the
member.
</p><p>
This, also, I would like to report:  I asked him how many living descendants he had.  He
counted them and answered, "Fifty-four."  I asked him then, how many of them are members
of the Church, and I expect you know the answer, though perhaps not his interesting
expression.  He said, "Huh, ain't any of them members of the Church.  They're a pretty hard
lot."
</p><p>
This last question:  who was it the bishop's counselor propelled out the door that morning? 
Just one boy?  Just one?  This one has in his own lifetime become, in effect, a multitude, and
the current has but begun to run, and every one of them denied, according to his own witness,
the love of the gospel and the brotherhood of the Saints, the warmth and strength and
direction of the programs of the Church.
</p><p>
Oh, I can understand a little more, why the Lord said that one soul was precious to him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15#15">D&amp;C 18:15</a>).
</p><p>
I close with a statement Horace Mann made.  This is well-known also, but worth the
repetition.  To a man who questioned Horace Mann's statement at the dedication of a boy's
home or school, that if all the work and energy and effort and money put into this endeavor
had been to save just one boy, it would have been worth it, and had said to Horace Mann,
"You became too oratorical, didn't you?  You didn't really mean that, did you?"&mdash;Horace
Mann answered, "Oh, yes, I meant it.  It would have all been worth it, if the one were my
son."
</p><p>
Every son of God is important in his eyes.  Every unbaptized child, unordained boy, young
man who is not in the right stage of his priesthood progression, every boy and girl not
attending seminary when they can and should, every boy and girl not being married the
temple when they could&mdash;these are vitally important in the eyes of God and should be, in our
eyes.
</p><p>
God bless us to understand the infinite importance of the one, in God's eyes, and to do all
that we can to fulfil his purposes for them, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
