<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 3-9</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay and my beloved brethren of the Melchizedek and Aaronic Priesthood, I
sincerely trust that the Holy Spirit will guide and inspire me in my utterances this night.
</p><p>
This is a new day&mdash;a new day that dawned when a young man in the woods of western New
York supplicated God humbly for divine direction in finding the Church of the Lord Jesus
Christ. The prayer was answered
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
The Father and the Son appeared to him which appearance
reaffirmed to the world that God, our Eternal Father, is a being with body, parts and passions
and in whose image we are created.  His visit confirmed to the world that the despised
Nazarene crucified upon Calvary's Hill was the only begotten of the Father in the flesh&mdash;the
Creator of mankind.
</p><p>
By divine direction, this young man, Joseph Smith, unearthed a sacred record buried centuries
ago in the ancient Hill Cumorah.  This record contained the revelations of the Lord to the
people that lived upon this the American Continent centuries ago.  The scriptures in this holy
record are among the most profound ever given to any people or in any dispensation.  For
example, Lehi declared: 
</p><p>
Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
In this day, a new philosophy had fallen upon the ears of a disillusioned generation.  The
world was in the throes of a great apostasy.
</p><p>
As we think of the joy mentioned by Lehi, I submit the following questions: Could men have
joy in the doctrine that unbaptized babes would burn in hell forever?  Could men have joy in
being denied the right to worship God according to the dictates of conscience? Could men
have joy in being denied the right to read the word of God? Could men have joy in the
thought that mental and physical torture manifests genuine repentance?  Could men have joy
in being lead into the realms of ignorance and worshiping a God of whom they could not
conceive?
</p><p>
Many statements fell from the mouth of the young Prophet, but one which startled the world
was the declaration:  "The glory of God is intelligence"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
"Men cannot be saved in ignorance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord, through this American Prophet, revealed in the Book of Moses,
Chapter 1, Verse 39, that his glory and work was as declared by the Lord: 
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life
of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Had anyone previous to the Prophet Joseph Smith ever revealed to the world the most
important work and glory of the Creator?  Imagine if you will he who created all things&mdash;the
universe, endless worlds and man declared that his most important objective was to bring to
pass the immortality and eternal life of man.  If the work and objectives of the Lord are to be
accomplished, there had to be established a direct relationship between our Father in heaven
and man on earth. Channels of communication had to be reopened so that the Lord could
reveal his mind and will to those he selected to represent him.  Hence, the priesthood was
restored to establish the former relationship wherein God directed his work for the bringing
about the immortality and eternal life of man.  John the Baptist returned to earth and
conferred upon Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery the Aaronic Priesthood, the same authority
which existed in the days of John the Baptist which holds the keys of the ministering of
angels and the gospel of repentance and baptism by immersion for the remission of sins
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/68-72#68">JS&mdash;H 1:68-72</a>). 
Shortly thereafter, by divine direction, the Apostolic Presidency, Peter, James, and John
bestowed upon Joseph Smith and his associate the Melchizedek Priesthood
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/12#12">D&amp;C 27:12</a>) which holds the
keys of loosening and binding both upon the earth and in the heavens, the laying on of hands
for the gift of the Holy Ghost, the keys to preach the gospel to every nation, kindred, tongue
and people, the keys for the work for the dead, and, hence, the relationship which existed
between the prophets and apostles of old was established in this day to the end that the Lord's
plans for the eternal blessing of his children might be brought into fruition.  Priesthood is
divine authority, and as Joseph Smith declared: 
</p><p>
. . . is an everlasting principle and existed with God from eternity and will to eternity without
beginning of days or end of years. The keys have to be brought from heaven whenever the
Gospel is sent.
</p><p>
In Section 121, Verse 36, of the Doctrine &amp; Covenants, to confirm the above statements, the
Lord declared: 
</p><p>
That the rights of the priesthood are inseparably connected with the powers of heaven, and
that the powers of heaven cannot be controlled nor handled only upon the principles of
righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/36#36">D&amp;C 121:36</a>).
</p><p>
The priesthood is that which places a man in condition to receive the ministration of angels
and to enjoy the presence of God the Father and his son Jesus Christ, which substantiates the
declaration of the former apostle, John the Beloved, when he declared: 
</p><p>
And this is life eternal that they might know thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom
thou hast sent (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
Brethren, this is a new day&mdash;the day of which the Apostles of old spoke when they
prophesied a time of great refreshing would come when there would be a restoration of all
things before the second coming of the Redeemer of the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/19-21#19">Acts 3:19-21</a>).  Does all of this mean
anything to you and to me?  My beloved brethren who hold the priesthood must realize that
the joy of which Lehi spoke is the joy of service in the Lord's work; the joy of contributing
to the salvation of the souls of our Heavenly Father's children; the joy of rendering service
when called upon by those who preside over us and furthering the work of the Lord&mdash;his
work to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man; and the, joy in sustaining those
who preside over us.
</p><p>
Today in the stakes of the Church, there are 156,000 men endowed with the authority of the
Holy Melchizedek Priesthood, the priesthood after the order of the Son of God, and 129,000
holding the Aaronic Priesthood, or a total of 285,000 sons of God holding divine
authority&mdash;the most precious gift that has ever been bestowed upon mankind.
</p><p>
The membership of the Church in stakes only is 1,034,000 of whom 28% hold either the
Melchizedek or the Aaronic Priesthood.  By the way of comparison, the largest church in the
United States with a membership of 29,407,000 has but 45,000 members authorized to
participate in the rituals of the Church and to carry on its work, which indicates that 1.5% of
the total membership as against 28% of the membership of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints enjoy the privilege of service.
</p><p>
One of the greatest evidences of the divine origin of this great Church and its priesthood lies
in the fact that every male member of the Church over the age of twelve who is worthy may
hold the priesthood of God and function therein.  The bestowal of divine authority upon so
many of the Lord's sons is an evidence that our Heavenly Father is no respecter of persons. 
Station in life and wealth make no difference.  Faith in him and the gospel of salvation and
obedience thereto wherein men live lives that are compatible with the wishes of our Heavenly
Father qualify men to hold the priesthood.  Priesthood privileges, powers and service are not
in the hands of a few.  All of these blessings are not for the General Authorities, stake
authorities or bishoprics, but for every worthy holder of the priesthood.  After all, salvation is
an individual matter, and priesthood service in the cause of the Savior contributes to salvation
and exaltation in the Celestial Kingdom.  Brigham Young makes this point very clear in the
following declaration: 
</p><p>
The Gospel of salvation&mdash;The Priesthood of the Son of God&mdash;is so ordered and organized, in
the very nature of it, being a portion of that law of heaven by which worlds are organized,
that it is calculated to enlighten the children of men and give them power to save themselves.
</p><p>
Continuing with another statement, President Brigham Young stated: 
</p><p>
The Gospel and the Priesthood are the means he employs to save and exalt his obedient
children to the possession with him of the same glory and power to be crowned with crowns
of glory, immortality and eternal lives.
</p><p>
This is the joy of which Lehi spoke:  "Men are that they might have joy," and the highest
degree of joy will only be found in the presence of God the Eternal Father and his Son Jesus
Christ and to share his glory with him.
</p><p>
Some of our brethren who hold the priesthood and have within their grasp all of the blessings
and privileges promised to the faithful have laid aside the opportunity of service and for some
reason or another have become indifferent and thereby forgotten the covenants they made with
the Lord when they received the priesthood.  In the 108th Section of the Doctrine &amp;
Covenants, Verse 3, the Lord very implicitly reminds us of our priesthood covenants when he
declared: 
</p><p>
And arise up and be more careful henceforth in observing your vows, which you have made
and do make, and you shall be blessed with exceeding great blessings
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/108/3#3">D&amp;C 108:3</a>).
</p><p>
No individual who holds either the Aaronic or the Melchizedek Priesthood has received it but
what they were asked the question as to whether or not they would be faithful and true and to
keep themselves sweet and unspotted from the sins of the world, and to render whatever
service may be required.
</p><p>
To those who are active in the priesthood, the Lord has admonished us in the 108th Section
of the Doctrine &amp; Covenants, the 7th Verse, as follows: 
</p><p>
Therefore, strengthen your brethren in all your conversation, in all your prayers, in all your
exhortations, and in all your doings
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/108/7#7">D&amp;C 108:7</a>).
</p><p>
This places squarely upon the shoulders of all of us the responsibility to strengthen those who
may be weak in the spirit of tolerance, patience, and love.
</p><p>
As I think of our inactive brethren, I feel that they are to some degree the
"Forgotten Men."  Might I ask you the question, "What have you done to encourage and
stimulate the indifferent young men or older men to activity in the Church?"  This should be
the time to take an individual inventory of your attitude and my attitude toward our brethren. 
These men are not problem men, but they are men with a problem. Neither are they marked
men, nor are they to be stigmatized, but rather your responsibility and mine is to find
solutions to their problems.  We must never forget that the Priesthood is a Divine
Brotherhood, and the Divine Brotherhood of God should radiate love, good will and
helpfulness to all.
</p><p>
There are no deficiencies in the priesthood organization as the Lord has revealed it to us, but
there may be some deficiencies in those of us who fail to carry out the plan of the priesthood
in being our brother's keeper.  Our brethren who are not as interested as they might be have
outstanding qualities of character, and these qualities could well be emulated by all of us. 
Again, the statement of Lehi of old: "Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they
might have joy," and the greatest joy of all is brought forcibly to our attention in the 18th
Section of the Doctrine &amp; Covenants, the 15th Verse: 
</p><p>
And if it so be that you should labor all your days in crying repentance unto this people, and
bring, save it be one soul unto me, how great shall be your joy with him in the kingdom of
my Father! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15#15">D&amp;C 18:15</a>).
</p><p>
And in the 16th Verse: 
</p><p>
And now, if your joy will be great with one soul that you have brought unto me into the
kingdom of my Father, how great will be your joy if you should bring many souls unto me!
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/16#16">D&amp;C 18:16</a>).
</p><p>
Again, in the spirit of kindness, tolerance and patience let us strive to the accomplishment of
bringing back into the fold of activity every member of the priesthood, and that by uniting
together we shall lift one another up to the full stature of servants of God, even from the
deacon to the high priest.
</p><p>
These past two years due to the untiring work of stake presidencies, high councilmen,
bishoprics and senior Aaronic Priesthood advisors, it has been possible to organize 1,581
senior Aaronic Priesthood quorums and groups constituted of the following: 826 senior priests
quorums, 368 senior teachers quorums, 371 senior deacons quorums, and 16 mixed groups.
These priesthood quorum organizations require the services of approximately 5,000 of our
senior Aaronic Priesthood brethren to make up the presidencies. This is a most encouraging
accomplishment, but we cannot cease our efforts upon this accomplishment, but we must look
forward to see what there is left to be done.
</p><p>
In the stakes, there are 65,000 senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood.  If all of these
brethren were organized into quorums as the Lord has indicated in the 107th Section of the
Doctrine &amp; Covenants, we would have at least a total of 5,000 Senior Aaronic Priesthood
quorums.  The accomplishment of this will require unceasing effort.
</p><p>
In 1953, 3,000 senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood were advanced to the Melchizedek
Priesthood.  For this accomplishment, I would have you know we are most grateful, but
unfortunately there were more of our brethren joined the senior Aaronic Priesthood group than
were advanced to the Melchizedek Priesthood, which brings me to another question, "What
about our sons who hold the Aaronic Priesthood under the age of twenty-one&mdash;these
wonderful young men who Elbert Hubbard declared were made of 'Soul Stuff'?" And the
most valuable "Soul Stuff" in the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ are these young men born
in this dispensation.  They are the choice spirits, for they have been born in most instances
under the new and everlasting covenant. It causes us deep concern when we find that during
the year 1953 there were 3,332 twenty-year-old deacons, teachers and priests that within the
coming year will become members of the senior Aaronic Priesthood group. 
This terse statement tells a sad story.  If we were to go into the lives of these young men, out
of our investigation, we would find that someone, either a bishop, a bishop's counselor or an
Aaronic Priesthood advisor has been remiss in his duty.  I can't help but believe that all of
these young men have become inactive and disinterested because they have lost contact with
the Church, and we lose contact with all of these potential members of the senior Aaronic
Priesthood by our failure to keep in constant touch with them, particularly when they are
inactive and indifferent.  There is but one solution to keep Aaronic Priesthood members under
the age of twenty-one interested, motivated and active in their priesthood work, and that is
through a very definite system of personal contacts.  The Church has been built up on
personal contacts.  Your grandfather and my grandfather accepted the gospel because of many
personal contacts made by missionaries.  The contact system is still the most profitable and
only one whereby inactive and indifferent members of the Church can be brought back into
the fold.
</p><p>
I should like to relate a beautiful story of one of the great spiritual leaders of the Church,
President Edward J. Wood, former president of the Alberta Temple and Alberta Stake.  The
story as related to me by him is as follows: 
</p><p>
The bishop of his ward called into a special meeting some of the brethren, and among them
was President Wood. The bishop announced that the brethren had been called together to go
on a special mission, and this was the mission: The bishop announced, "We have a group of
young men under the age of twenty-one who hold the Aaronic Priesthood who now manifest
no interest and render no service.  They must be brought back.  Hence, I am calling each one
of you brethren on a special mission to bring back one of these boys."  President Wood said,
"I wondered at first what kind of a mission my bishop was calling me to perform when I was
president of the Alberta Temple and president of the Alberta Stake of Zion, but when he
made his announcement, I gladly responded to the call.  My assignment was to visit a boy
who lived five miles out of Cardston.  I thought first of the boy's family.  I knew I would
have to face an indifferent father and an indifferent mother, and so I decided to invite him to
attend the ward Priesthood Meeting with me which was held on a week night.  I drove the
five miles to the boy's home, and as I anticipated, the father was indifferent and the mother
was indifferent saying, 'If our son decides to go to priesthood meeting with you that is his
privilege.'"  And so the president stated that after a good deal of persuasion the boy
reluctantly consented to go to priesthood meeting.
</p><p>
During the time it took to drive the five miles, what do you suppose this wise man talked
about?  Did he talk about the Church?  "No." Did he talk about priesthood?  "No." Was he
critical of the boy for his failure to at tend to his priesthood obligations? "No." But, he talked
about the things that the boy and all boys are interested in, namely athletics.  He opened up
the subject by telling the boy of his own experience when he and his brother William were
the champion bicycle riders of the State of Utah.  Was the boy interested? "Surely," for he,
too, was interested in athletics as all boys are.  The president of the stake, the president of the
Temple brought himself down to the level of the boy in being able to look through the eyes
of a boy, and with the same viewpoint, the boy opened his heart to President Wood and was
willing to talk about his achievements in the field of athletics.
</p><p>
Arriving at the chapel, President Wood asked the boy if he would attend his deacons meeting,
"Yes," he would. Then, the president requested him to listen intently and to report to him as
to what had been said and what had been done.  After the meeting, it was easy to open up a
discussion on the priesthood, and as the boy reported in all frankness and forthrightness, he
told the president that he hadn't heard anything he liked, nor was there
anything done in the quorum meeting that inspired him. President Wood asked him what was
wrong, and the boy readily answered, "The teacher was not prepared.  I knew he was not
prepared because when the quorum opened its meeting, he handed the manual first to one boy
and then to another to read a paragraph." He said, "I might as well of stayed home, I am sure
I would have learned more." There were no assignments made to the deacons, either for
passing the sacrament or gathering fast offerings.  In fact, there was no action in the quorum
meeting, and boys love action.
</p><p>
Arriving home, the president extended another invitation to the boy to attend priesthood
meeting.  The boy consented, but during the interim between the first meeting and the second,
the president of the stake went to the advisor of the deacons quorum and pointed out to him
the reason why the boys were inactive and indifferent, the president's reason being that the
teacher was unprepared, secondly, the president of the deacons quorum was not called up to
preside over the quorum, and thirdly, no assignments were being made.  You can rest assured
that the next week the teacher was prepared, the presidency of the deacons quorum was in its
place presiding over the meeting, and assignments were made, and thus for six consecutive
weeks the man with the greatest amount of responsibility and work to do made a round trip of
twenty miles to pick up a deacon and take him to priesthood meeting. As the seventh week
dawned, the president asked himself the question, "I wonder if I am accomplishing anything
in behalf of this boy?  Tonight I will make a test of my plan."  In place of driving to the
boy's home, the president went to priesthood meeting, and soon the fruits of the president's
efforts were manifested, for thirty minutes late, the deacon came in.  At the end of the
meeting, President Wood declared, "I received the greatest thrill of my life.  That boy sided
up to me and placed his hand in mine, looked me squarely in the eye, and expressed his
gratitude and appreciation for what I had done in just two words in boy language, 'My Pal.'"
</p><p>
Brethren, that is the solution to the problem of the Aaronic Priesthood under the age of
twenty-one where they become indifferent&mdash;"Palship," and may I emphasize it is the solution. 
Palship first means contacts with boys. It means that if you establish palship, you have their
confidence, good will, and their love.  They will follow you to the ends of the earth if
necessary.  Yes, Elbert Hubbard was right when he declared, "Boys are made of Soul Stuff,"
and the most precious "Soul Stuff" in all the world is found in the Church of the Lord Jesus
Christ, for herein are potential General Authorities, stake presidents, and bishoprics, and
numerous other future leaders.
</p><p>
Yes brethren, there are some outstanding achievements due to the efforts of you Aaronic
Priesthood workers.  It affords me a great thrill to announce tonight that more than 15,000
young men will receive an Individual Aaronic Priesthood Award for their faithfulness and
service in the priesthood, for they have attended their sacrament meetings priesthood
meetings, have paid a full tithing, have kept the Word of Wisdom and met their priesthood
obligations in full.  Again, we must not look back at what we have done, but rather we should
look forward and remember that out of a total of 63,000 members of the Aaronic Priesthood
under the age of twenty-one, there are still 48,000 who have not achieved as have the 15,000.
These 48,000 should enjoy that divine thing that I choose to call "palship."
</p><p>
Brethren, there is but one question left, "Are you and I our brother's keeper?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/9#9">Gen. 4:9</a>). The answer is
obvious.  The priesthood of God is a divine order founded upon the love of God for his sons,
for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son, and his son so loved the world
that he gave his life for the redemption of all, and if you and I love our
neighbors, as God has commanded, as ourselves, we shall close our priesthood ranks and we
will gather our brethren who may be inactive in the priesthood to our side and present to the
world a priesthood solidarity which will give all of us the strength to destroy the enemy of
indifference and temptation and criticism, and which will inspire us to be as one, as are the
Father and the Son one, and as Lehi declared: "Men are that they might have joy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>), and above
that and most important of all that we shall be instrumental in the Lord's greatest work to
bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>), which I humbly pray will be the
heartfelt desire and accomplishment of all of us, in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p><p>
Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin: 
</p><p>
Brethren, the First Presidency, out of their kindness and generosity, have permitted the
Presiding Bishopric to show you a film tonight that deals with the procedures of the Adult
Aaronic Priesthood plan and program.  May I say to you that in this film there is a story and
in the story there is a character.  We want you to understand that while we show the extremes
to which this particular man went, the purpose is to show what can be done if we are kind
and patient, no matter how far afield some of our brethren may go.  This film does not intend
to carry the impression that all of our senior Aaronic brethren have gone as far as this
particular character went.
</p><p>
(There was then presented on a screen a film story entitled "Come Back, My Son.")
</p>
</div>
</div>
