<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Their Souls Are Precious</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 100-104</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Surely we all owe a debt of gratitude to this marvelous choir. Brother Condie and the choir
have won our hearts this morning.  There are many individuals in the Church and out of the
Church all over the world who greatly appreciate their beautiful music and the selections of
their renditions.
</p><p>
While standing before you today, I pray that the Lord may sustain me and direct me, and I
shall be grateful to each of you for an interest in your faith and prayers.  Truly, this is a
humbling experience.  I am sure it would be a humbling experience for you, too, but probably
that is as it should be because we are here this morning&mdash;this beautiful Sabbath Easter
morning&mdash;in true worship.  We acknowledge God as our Heavenly Father.  We accept Jesus
Christ as the Savior and the Redeemer of the world.  We teach his birth in Bethlehem, his life
in Galilee, and his sojourn in Jerusalem. We accept the mission of Jesus as
the Savior of the world. We recount that mission, his contribution, the trial of Jesus that
President Clark so beautifully told us about yesterday, and finally the crucifixion of the Savior
on the hill of Calvary in Old Jerusalem.
</p><p>
A few years ago as I stood by the side of that tomb in Old Jerusalem I think I loved Jesus
more then than I have ever done before in my life. We accept the resurrection of Jesus as
true, and we know he came forth from the tomb as the Resurrected Christ, thereby giving
eternal life, probably God's greatest gift to man.
</p><p>
We teach and we recognize the appearance of God, the Father, and his Son, Jesus Christ, to
the Prophet Joseph in the Sacred Grove. There are some of our friends who can hardly accept
that as truth, but we would plead with them to study and pray, and that testimony will come
to them.  We acknowledge Joseph Smith as a prophet of God. He was raised up, preserved,
and divinely called. We teach and we believe in the revelations received by the Prophet
Joseph.  These revelations are true, and this chosen prophet left to the world more doctrines
of life and salvation than any other person who ever lived, save Christ himself
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3#3">D&amp;C 135:3</a>). He was truly a
divinely called and inspired prophet, and sealed his testimony with his life and blood along
with his wonderful brother, Hyrum, who was  also martyred at Carthage Jail in Illinois.
</p><p>
Yes, we accept these things as factual, and we know without a doubt that they are true; that
the Lord revealed his will to this prophet, and after the death of the Prophet Joseph Smith
another great prophet was raised up, preserved, and divinely called&mdash;the prophet and
President Brigham Young, who had a great mission to perform in leading this people on that
unknown journey.  After the death of the Prophet Brigham Young, other prophets were raised
up and divinely called to lead the Church, each one in his time a true prophet of the Lord.  At
the present time one stands at the head of this Church and is the mouthpiece of God, our
Eternal Father.  President David O. McKay is a prophet of the Lord, just as were the prophets
of old. I bear testimony to you that I know this to be true, and I know it by the power and
gift of the Holy Ghost.  The Spirit of the Lord testifies to our spirits and we believe.
</p><p>
I would like to address some of my remarks to a very large group of brethren whom I regard
as fine men and of great potential power and strength and in whom I have great interest, the
senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood.  I know many of them, and I want to express to
them our love and our friendship.  We have only one desire, that we can share with them
some of the joys and blessings that we are privileged to enjoy.  When you stop to think of
this large group of men, if it were possible to assemble them, we would fill this tabernacle ten
times as it is filled this morning.
</p><p>
Where are they today, and what have we done about it?  We want to tell them that we love
them, and we welcome them back into activity in the Church.  We want to assure them of our
interest in their welfare.  We have been greatly impressed with the progress made by these
wonderful men, and we would plead with all of our brethren of this group and other groups
that if for any reason you may have become inactive in the Church, we want you back
because it will bring you greater joys and blessings than have ever come to you any other
way in your life. We can promise you that the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ changes the
pattern and the attitude and the personality and the personal spiritual strength of men who will
accept Christ and the teachings of the gospel.
</p><p>
May I give you a quotation from Alma to express to you how we feel: 
</p><p>
Behold, O Lord, their souls are precious, and many of them are our brethren; therefore, give
unto us, O Lord, power and wisdom that we may bring these, our brethren, again unto thee
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/31/35#35">Alma 31:35</a>).
</p><p>
In a recently completed survey, with 224 stakes reporting regarding the activity of their
schools for senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood, we are pleasantly encouraged and
grateful to see what is taking place.  We have, for instance, at the present time, approximately
367 schools now in session for the senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood
and their wives, some of them on a ward and some on a stake basis. We have had enrolled in
these schools in the last year more than 17,000 of these wonderful men and their wives, and
we are learning of some glorious experiences that have come into the lives of these brethren.
</p><p>
Just yesterday I shook hands with a former senior member of the Aaronic Priesthood who
now is a stake president. It is not uncommon for us to shake hands with some who are now
bishops.
</p><p>
May I give you a few excerpts from some of the special survey sheets regarding these
schools, the comments of which are from the senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood?
</p><p>
Perhaps the greatest benefit that I received from the school was the feeling that my
Church was still very much interested in me in spite of my inactivity for so many
years, and that I was still needed and wanted in the Church; that I still had a chance to
make up in a way for years of absence; that there was still time left, but that I must
not procrastinate longer.
</p><p>
Another: 
</p><p>
I have completed the first school, and I recommend that all the senior members of the
Aaronic Priesthood attend these schools. It is a great feeling to feel yourself grow as
you get interested again in the Church. This school seems to give us the spark that we
need for most of us to get started again, and I would recommend to every senior
member of the Aaronic Priesthood that you attend these schools.
</p><p>
It was through this school that my wife and I received the spark of hope, and now we
are working our way to the temple.
</p><p>
It is wonderful to see how the lives of individuals may be changed, and the lives of sons and
daughters likewise are changed, because they are happy when their fathers and mothers make
adjustments in their own lives.  To sons and daughters who come from a divided family&mdash;the
father a member of the Church or the mother a member of the Church&mdash;you can do so much
for your mother and your father. A girl, a while ago, sent this letter to her father and mother
in answer to a letter that she had received.
</p><p>
Dear Mother and Daddy: I received your letter, and I have never had such a pleasant
and wonderful surprise in my life as when I read it, telling me that Dad was now
going to join the Church.  I started to cry, and I cry every time I think of it because
really, I have never been so happy.  This is the blessing that I have been praying for
ever since I was big enough to know how to pray.
</p><p>
Young people, you, too, can do that for your fathers and your mothers.
</p><p>
Dad, I know you will now be greatly blessed, and if you will live the commandments
our Heavenly Father has given us, you will soon have the Holy Priesthood which will
give you the power to do the things that you have never dreamed of doing before. I
think it will be so wonderful if you will both live worthy of being married in the
temple some day.
</p><p>
I cannot think of a more glorious wedding gift for me than to be sealed to both my
mother and father and my sweetheart, Jim, on the same day.  Another great thing will
be that now, Daddy, you will be able to assist in many ordinances of the Church, and
someday assist in the blessings of my babies.  That will mean so much to me. Nothing
could have ever made me happier than this has made me.
</p><p>
I love you, and as your daughter, I am very proud of both of you. You have made me
so happy, and I will always be what you expect me to be.
</p><p>
We are humble and truly grateful for our membership in this Church.  We do not wish to
appear arrogant or haughty, because we realize that we are not as good as we should be, but
we are thankful we are as good as we are, and are grateful to God for what we can yet
become.
</p><p>
The Church offers us the opportunity to worship God and a chance to come into an awareness
of him.  With him there is healing of sorrows, strength for the day, and peace at the last.  If
we have been at odds with ourselves or with God, our Father, and the universe, reconciliation
with the Master, with our fellows, and our soul can come.  That change will come about if we
are humble, repentant, and seek the assistance of our Heavenly Father, but it can never take
place without communion with the Lord and a spiritual religious belief and faith.
</p><p>
The understanding of God's goodness enables man to meet everyday needs,
problems, and troubles.  We can come to a reconciliation with God, with people, and with
ourselves.  Despair and discouragement can be transformed to confidence, guilt to forgiveness;
cross purposes and uncertain goals can be changed to spiritual strength. Yes, one's real
personality heretofore utterly alone can take on a new character with true humility.  True
religion gives one strength to ask forgiveness of one's fellow men. If that be difficult, and
sometimes it is, all we need to do is to become humble, and it gives us spiritual strength to
ask for God's forgiveness. If we can only accept and thoroughly recognize that God is our
Father, if we will listen to his words, we will not be troubled.
</p><p>
The gospel as taught by the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints will lift one higher
than any other philosophy on earth. It will give one a higher knowledge, more to live for and
more to die for than any other church on the earth, because it is the true Church of Jesus
Christ.  The truths of the gospel are beautiful.  As a church and as a people, we are
particularly blessed with the scriptures of the Book of Mormon, and I would like to say to my
friends who may be inactive, or those not of the Church, the Lord has made all of us a very
definite promise in the Book of Mormon (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/3-5#3">Moro. 10:3-5</a>), and I hope that every man
within the sound of my voice who has never done so will read the following.  The Lord said: 
</p><p>
Behold, I would exhort you that when ye shall read these things, if it be wisdom in God that
ye should read them, that ye would remember bow merciful the Lord hath been unto the
children of men, from the creation of Adam even down until the time that ye shall receive
these things, and ponder it in your hearts.<br />
And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the
Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a
sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you,
by the power of the Holy Ghost.<br />
And by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/3-5#3">Moro. 10:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
Elder Orson F. Whitney has written the following concerning Mormonism: 
</p><p>
Mormonism's magnanimity&mdash;And yet "Mormonism" is said to be narrow, small and illiberal. 
Narrow, forsooth!  Then where will you find breadth? Where find justice, mercy,
magnanimity, if not in a religion that saves the living, redeems the dead . . . and glories all
who repent? "Mormonism" a small thing? It's the biggest thing in the universe!  It is the
Everlasting Gospel, the mighty soul-ship of the dispensations, launched in the days of Adam
upon the heaving ocean of the ages, and now on its last voyage over the stormy billows of
Time to the beckoning coast of Eternity! (<i>Saturday Night Thoughts</i>).
</p><p>
God can win strange victories in the hearts and lives of those who believe in him.  Too many
people have been trying to do without God, perhaps that is the reason for some of their
failures.
</p><p>
Too many people are trying to give irreligion the garb of respectability. They have acted as if
we could acquire education without acquiring a knowledge of religion, and wisdom without
the experience and practice of religion.
</p><p>
Perhaps we have not found peace within ourselves.  The lack of peace usually goes with the
lack of belief in the Almighty God and a knowledge of the availability to us of his guidance.
We have not been able to establish peace among the nations of the world. With all our
knowledge, we yet urgently need to gain sufficient understanding completely to recognize that
there is an inescapable cause and effect relationship between these mounting failures and our
diminishing faith.  Unless we are willing to prepare for a new dark age, we must soon
acknowledge that as good as we think we are, we are not good enough to get along without
the God our forefathers found indispensable.
</p><p>
Every person might follow the admonition of Alma: 
</p><p>
Counsel with the Lord in all thy doings, and he will direct thee for good; yea, when thou liest
down at night lie down into the Lord, that he may watch over you in your sleep; and when
thou risest in the morning let thy heart be full of thanks unto God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/37#37">Alma 37:37</a>).
</p><p>
May I close with this thought: 
</p><p>
We expect to pass through this world but once; therefore, any good that we can do or
any kindness that we can show to any living person, let us do it now. Let us not
defer it or neglect it, for we shall not pass this way again.
</p><p>
May God favor us by granting to each of us the companionship and the association of his
sweet, holy Spirit, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
