<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Responsibility and the Priesthood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1962, pp. 45-47</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, President McKay was not too far wrong when he said that Anthony
W. Ivins [his father] was going to talk to you. My name translated means Anthony. It is a
French translation.
</p><p>
I am happy to be with you today, my brethren and sisters, and I am
thankful for the many, many blessings which my wife and I enjoy, especially that she has the
measure of health and strength that enables her to be in the meeting today and to be my
constant companion in the work that is assigned to me. It is thirty years, my brethren and
sisters, since I first faced this congregation, that is, it will be in the October conference. Those
thirty years have been filled with many fine experiences as I have worked among the
members of the Church. I trust that the remaining time that may be allotted to me may be as
pleasurable and as beneficial to me as the past has been.
</p><p>
I am especially grateful today for the opportunity that I have had at this conference of
saluting my friends from the newly created stake in Mexico. Brother Juarez who was with
them when I was assigned to the presidency of the Mexican Mission was the elder in charge
of all the work in Mexico. He has gone through the intervening years in faith and in service,
and I congratulate him on being appointed now a bishop in that new stake.
</p><p>
I pray that they will carry back to the people of Mexico my good wishes and my faith in
them and in their ability to realize the purpose for which this new stake was created.
</p><p>
I have lived quite a bit more than half of the life of the Church, and I go back in my memory
to the difficulties with which the brethren carried on the work of the Church when I was a
lad. I remember the opposition that was created in many sections of the country to the work
of the Church, and then when one sees the success that we are having and the growth that we
are realizing today, one marvels and realizes that it really is the work of the Lord.
</p><p>
Our problem, brethren and sisters, is to move it forward and you brethren who are in the
audience today, most of you, are responsible officers in the priesthood which you have
received, and in that sense you have a very distinct obligation to your congregations.
</p><p>
I have been reading in the New Testament recently, re-reading, and I find it extremely
interesting. I would like to recommend it as a following course for the reading of the Book of
Mormon which was our assignment recently. I read as you have all read, that statement about
having faith like a mustard seed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/31-32#31">Matt. 13:31-32</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/20#20">Matt. 17:20</a>).
One wonders why the mustard seed was chosen&mdash;some
think because it is small, that may have been the case&mdash;but it is an interesting thing to study
a mustard seed. It is endowed by God with the power to grow and increase in size, in stature,
and then reproduce itself. In other words, that mustard seed carries the perfect power to
realize the purpose for which it was created by God. But we must understand, also, that if it
does realize that purpose conditions must be satisfactory. Its ability may be destroyed by frost
or drought or heat, but if it falls into the proper environment, it grows and realizes its full
purpose. I believe that in the heart of every normal child that is born into this world is that
same God-given power, and I believe, also, that the realization of that power depends, for
years at least, upon external conditions for which the fathers and the mothers and the
neighbors are responsible very largely, until people get to a maturity where they determine
their own course of thinking and living.
</p><p>
I am not so much worried about what other people do not do, as I am about what we do not
do. We have the power as members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints to
influence young people. Many of us do not appreciate and perhaps do not understand this, and
we lose, for one reason or another, the service of many wonderful young men and young
women in the Church. We have now a large group of men in the Melchizedek Priesthood who
do not appear to appreciate their opportunities and their responsibilities.
</p><p>
I have developed in my ministry with you a love for people who are in a sense indifferent
because of these conditions over which they had little control earlier in life, and I have come
to realize that once they can be touched by the spirit of God into faith and activity, they
become wonderful servants. I want them to understand that we love them. When one is
militantly opposed to the work of the Church, we have nothing but sympathy
for him. So when we realize the great number of people that have not sensed their
opportunities to become active and go through the Aaronic Priesthood into the Melchizedek
Priesthood, then when we realize the number of men who are in the Melchizedek Priesthood
who are not active in it, we cannot help realizing the tremendous responsibility that rests upon
us and how far we come from making the perfect effort in the rearing of young people and
placing them on a firm foundation of faith, faith like the mustard seed. Now, if we could
properly cultivate those people in their growing years, they would realize I think rather fully
the purposes for which we are here&mdash;God-given purposes and God-given powers that we have
which we fail to use.
</p><p>
I think that perhaps we are justified in judging one's faith by his activity, because faith is
what prompts activity, and if we do judge them by that standard, we find that there are times
when many of them are reported as having little faith because they are reported as inactive in
the Church. Why cannot we reach them, brethren and sisters? We cannot drive them into it, of
course; we have to love them into it and give them opportunity to help, because when people
serve us, they realize that they have an interest in us. I read as a boy Benjamin Franklin's
<i>Autobiography</i> in which he said that he early learned that when he wanted particular people to
have a particular interest in him, he had to give those particular people an opportunity to do
something for him, and perhaps that would be one of our approaches to these people, to find
something that they can do that will divert their interest and develop their faith and their
testimony. The testimony is the thing that has the greatest power of all in our lives, I believe.
</p><p>
When we realize through receiving a testimony, which comes from the Spirit of God, our
relationship to God, our obligation to God our Father and our obligation to each other in the
Church organization, then we devote ourselves to that service. Without a testimony we do
little.
</p><p>
So our problem, brethren and sisters, with our young people is to develop in their hearts the
testimony which can carry them over those adolescent years that are so fraught with danger
into mature manhood with a testimony that will impel them to observe the commandments of
God, that when they enter into the marriage relationship, as has been suggested, they do it for
time and for all eternity, so that then they can carry on&mdash;and only then can they carry on and
realize the full purpose for which men and women come into this world.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, let us not worry too much about other people but worry about ourselves.
Brother Lee last night said that the only comparisons that he thinks are of value are the
comparisons of a person with his past, of a ward with its past, of a stake with its past. Then if
we look at ourselves, we begin, if we have the courage to do it, to revamp our lives.
</p><p>
I remember making a talk in Idaho one time on repentance. Repentance is fundamental to us,
as you all know, but after I got through, a fine old brother walked up to me and he said,
"Brother Ivins, that was wonderful. You hit my neighbor right square on top of the head."
And a young man followed him up and he said, "Brother Ivins, it was good, and you were
talking to me all the time." That is our problem, brethren and sisters, to take to heart the
instructions we get through the scriptures we read and from the brethren who stand to teach
us.
</p><p>
May we have the strength and the power to face ourselves squarely and then take advantage
of the opportunities presented in order to acquit ourselves creditably of our responsibility to
each other and to God our Heavenly Father, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
