<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"And, Lo, I Am with You Alway"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Matthew Cowley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Matthew Cowley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 102-103</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have been thinking, my brothers and sisters, since the meeting of the Twelve in the temple
on Thursday, of the words of the Master when he was about to take his departure from the
Twelve, and he said unto them: 
</p><p>
Go ye therefore, and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and
of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost: 
</p><p>
Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you and, lo, I am
with you alway, even unto the end of the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
QUORUM OF THE TWELVE APOSTLES
</p><p>
As this Council of Twelve met in the upper room of the temple on Thursday, the Spirit of
God bore witness to my spirit that Christ was saying there to the Twelve: ". . . and, lo, I am
with you always even unto the end of the world." And where there is no Quorum of Twelve
in God's ministry upon the earth, Christ is not there as the leader of his Church and his
kingdom. This testimony has sunk deep into my heart since that meeting and during this
conference which has been presided over by the Council of the Twelve with President McKay
as its presiding officer. When Christ came to the earth he organized his Church, and at the
head, under his leadership, he had Twelve Apostles. And when he left, he left his Church
under the direction of the Twelve. When he came to the American continent he organized his
Church, and at the head of that Church, under his leadership, he placed Twelve Disciples
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/12/1#1">3 Ne. 12:1</a>).
And when he left them, he left his Church and his Saints under the leadership of that Twelve.
And when the gospel was restored again, Christ came back and appeared unto him who was
raised up to be the Prophet at the head of this dispensation. And under his direction the
Church was organized for the last time, and at the head of the Church under the Presidency of
the Prophet were the appointed Twelve. And when the Prophet was taken from the earth,
sealing his testimony with his blood, the Church was left under the direction of the Twelve.
And down through the years when the leadership of the Quorum of the Presidency has been
taken away, the keys have remained with the Twelve.
</p><p>
". . . and, lo, I am with you alway, even unto the end of the world."
</p><p>
As God has borne witness to me in that meeting in his holy house and in this conference, so I
bear witness to you that where there is no Quorum of the Twelve, the true organization of
Christ's Church is not here upon the earth, and that is my testimony to you, which I bear in
all humbleness and in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
