<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Portrait of the Man of Galilee</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder William J. Critchlow, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">William J. Critchlow, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 10-13</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my brothers, sisters and friends: 
</p><p>
President McKay, setting me apart one year ago, charged me: "to be a special witness to the
name of Christ in all the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/23#23">D&amp;C 107:23</a>).
I shall use my few minutes pursuing the business of that charge.
</p><p>
In fancy, I made a pilgrimage back through nineteen centuries of time to Palestine. I went to
seek the man of Galilee called Jesus. I fancied I was in that fabulous city of Tiberius on the
shore of the Sea of Galilee where I observed, along the water's edge, miles of palaces and
fashionable residences surrounded by palm groves and rich gardens, gay with tropical
luxuriance. On an almost deserted thoroughfare I saw the markets of rich merchants and the
stands of oriental trades people.
</p><p>
Approaching a merchant, I inquired if he knew the whereabouts of the man of Galilee, named
Jesus. For a moment he just stared at me; then said, "Where have you been? Look at this
deserted street. Only minutes ago he came this way going west, and all the customers
followed him. I would have followed, too, had I someone to watch my merchandise."
</p><p>
I overtook the multitude before it settled on a little hill. Fortunately, I found myself near him
with sitting space for some of you out there who, in fancy, will stretch your
imagination one thousand nine hundred years back into the past. Come quickly. He is
speaking: 
</p><p>
"Blessed are the poor in spirit: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.<br />
"Blessed are they that mourn: for they shall be comforted.<br />
"Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/3-5#3">Matt. 5:3-5</a>; see also Matt. chapters 5-7 for the Sermon on
the Mount).
</p><p>
He pauses, and arises from his sitting position upon a large rock as if to survey the multitude.
</p><p>
He is tall in stature, perfectly formed without spot or blemish. He wears a tunic and an outer
robe. Sandals are on his feet.
</p><p>
He settles back upon the rock and speaks: 
</p><p>
"Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after righteousness: for they shall be filled.<br />
"Blessed are the merciful: for they shall obtain mercy.<br />
"Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/6-8#6">Matt. 5:6-8</a>).
</p><p>
I find it difficult to concentrate on what he is saying, just for gazing at him.
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp; His brow is smooth.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His complexion is clear.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His eyes are blue.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His hair is long.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His beard is brown like his hair.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His every feature is perfect.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His motions are graceful.<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; His voice is soft and low. (This pen picture is by a Roman trader who, on the old silk road to
China, paused in Palestine.)
</p><p>
Listen to him: "After this manner therefore pray ye: Our Father which art in heaven,
Hallowed be thy name.
</p><p>
"Thy kingdom come. Thy will be done in earth, as it is in heaven.<br />
"Give us this day . . ." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/9-11#9">Matt. 6:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
Need I repeat more of it?
</p><p>
"Lay up not for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust doth corrupt, and where
thieves break through and steal;<br /> 
"But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth corrupt, and
where thieves do not break through nor steal;<br />
"For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/19-21#19">Matt. 6:19-21</a>).
</p><p>
"And why take ye thought for raiment? Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow; they
toil not, neither do they spin:<br /> 
"Even Solomon in all his glory was not arrayed like one of these"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/28-29#28">Matt. 6:28-29</a>).
</p><p>
"But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness, and all these things shall be
added unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
"Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto
you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>).
</p><p>
You priesthood fathers would bless your wives and children if you would gather them around
you and read to them the full text of the great Sermon on the Mount. Do it soon. It is the
greatest speech ever delivered from the lips of men. It is the most widely circulated speech
ever heard among men. It has been printed in thousands of books and uttered by thousands of
speakers from thousands of pulpits to millions of people.
</p><p>
Another time, when he sought seclusion, he went into a desert place to be away from the
crowds. The multitude found him, and he received them. And when the day began to wear
away, he gathered up five loaves and two fishes, blessed them, and fed five thousand people.
After the feeding, there remained twelve baskets of fragments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/14-21#14">Matt. 14:14-21</a>).
</p><p>
Another time he fed four thousand, after blessing seven loaves and a few fishes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/30-38#30">Matt. 15:30-38</a>).
</p><p>
The feeding of these thousands was only one of the many kinds of miracles he performed.
</p><p>
He cleansed the leper; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;turned water into wine; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;stilled the wind; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;calmed the waves; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;walked on the water; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;healed the sick and the halt; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;cast out evil spirits; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;returned sight to the blind; <br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;restored life to the dead.
</p><p>
Words of his deeds spread throughout the countryside, even to Greece and Rome, and when it
was time for the Feast of the Passover, Jerusalem was crowded with people from far and near
who had come to see this marvelous man of Galilee. And they were not disappointed. Down
from the Mount of Olives and through the streets of Jerusalem he came, riding a little donkey.
</p><p>
His path was strewn with flowers, palm branches, and the robes of friends who watched his
entry and who sang: 
</p><p>
"Hosanna to the Son of David:<br />
"Blessed is he that cometh in the name of the Lord:<br /> 
"Hosanna in the highest" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/11/9-10#9">Mark 11:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
Witnessing the procession, I fancy, were two slaves, filled with rabid curiosity.
</p><p>
"Who is he?" asked one of the other.
</p><p>
"I don't know," was the reply.
</p><p>
"Is he a king?"
</p><p>
"No, he's not a king."
</p><p>
"Well, is he crazy?"
</p><p>
"No&mdash;he's not crazy."
</p><p>
"Then who is he?"
</p><p>
"I don't know&mdash;he's not a king&mdash;he's something greater than a king."
</p><p>
Not all who watched his triumphal entry into Jerusalem were his friends. Members of the
Jewish Sanhedrin, disturbed by Jesus' miracles and preaching, and definitely alarmed by his
growing popularity with the people, plotted as they watched, for his arrest&mdash;even for his
death. Not many hours later they bribed one of his apostles with thirty pieces of silver to
betray him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/15#15">Matt. 26:15</a>).
After a trial of mockery, held informally, irregularly, and illegally during the
night while his friends, the people, slept, he was scourged, then led to a place called Calvary
where he was nailed to a cross. Among his last words were, "Father, forgive them; for they
know not what they do" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/34#34">Luke 23:34</a>).
</p><p>
The morrow was the Sabbath of the Lord their God. Lest his presence on the cross desecrate
that holy day, his body was hurriedly removed and laid away in a borrowed tomb where it lay
for three days.
</p><p>
Resurrected, he tarried off and on with his disciples for forty days.
</p><p>
One day, as he walked with his disciples on a lonely road, he paused to bless them and then
in their presence he ascended heavenward. As he disappeared a heavenly messenger
announced: 
</p><p>
". . . Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing into heaven? this same Jesus, which is taken up
from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
Whence came this Jesus of Nazareth&mdash;this man of Galilee?
</p><p>
Some thirty years before his ministry began, Mary, his mother, laden with child and in the
throes of her travail, had just arrived at Bethlehem.
</p><p>
Hers had been a long four-or-five day journey on the back of a little donkey, when she was
not afoot. When she arrived, there was no place for her at the inn where she had expected to
stay, and no one round about would give her space to stay. So a bed of clean straw was hastily
made for her in a manger in a nearby stable.
</p><p>
There, Jesus of Nazareth was born. The dumb animals tethered there were the first to hear the
infant cry.
</p><p>
"And there were in the same country shepherds abiding in the field, keeping watch over their
flock by night.<br />
"And lo, the angel of the Lord came upon them, and the glory of the Lord shone round about
them: and they were sore afraid.<br />
"And the angel said unto them, Fear not: for, behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy,
which shall be to all people.<br />
"For unto you is born this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord.<br />
"And this shall be a sign unto you; Ye shall find the babe wrapped in swaddling clothes, lying
in a manger" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/8-12#8">Luke 2:8-12</a>).
</p><p>
And there in the manger the shepherds found him.
</p><p>
Later wise men from the East brought the babe gifts of gold, frankincense, and myrrh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/2/1-12#1">Matt. 2:1-12</a>).
</p><p>
If Jesus had come, as these wise men, riding on a camel, bearing gold, frankincense, and
myrrh, with a crown on his head, he undoubtedly would have been accepted&mdash;king of the
Jews.
</p><p>
His coming had been long awaited, but they could not accept one, born so humbly and lowly
in a stable.
</p><p>
He came born away from home, in obscurity.
</p><p>
He preached&mdash;the clearest, most simple, teacher of profound truth that ever came among
men.
</p><p>
He healed&mdash;
</p><p>
He called followers about him, even apostles.
</p><p>
He suffered&mdash;betrayed, denied, and deserted.
</p><p>
He died&mdash;a horrible death upon a cross.
</p><p>
He was resurrected&mdash;after three days in a tomb.
</p><p>
He lives.
</p><p>
He will return again.
</p><p>
Listen; these words are his: 
</p><p>
     "<i>I am from above</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/23#23">John 8:23</a>).<br />
     <i>I came down from heaven</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/6/38#38">John 6:38</a>).<br />
     <i>All power is given unto me</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/18#18">Matt. 28:18</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the light</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>).<br />
     <i>Ask in my name</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/13#13">John 14:13</a>).<br />
     <i>Come unto me, all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you rest</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/28#28">Matt. 11:28</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the way</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).<br />
     <i>Keep my commandments</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/15#15">John 14:15</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the Lord of the Sabbath</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/8#8">Matt. 12:8</a>).<br />
     <i>I am greater than the temple</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/6#6">Matt. 12:6</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the life</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the resurrection and the life</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25#25">John 11:25</a>).<br />
     <i>I am the truth</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).<br />
     <i>Heaven and earth shall pass away, but my words shall not pass away</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/35#35">Matt. 24:35</a>).<br />
     <i>I will rise from the dead</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/9#9">John 20:9</a>).<br />
     <i>He that hath seen me hath seen the Father</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/9#9">John 14:9</a>).<br />
     <i>Ye call me Master and Lord; and ye say well for so I am</i> (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/13#13">John 13:13</a>)".
</p><p>
"I know," said the woman at the well, "that Messias cometh, which is called Christ."
</p><p>
Jesus answered&mdash;"I that speak unto thee am he"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/25-26#25">John 4:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
When Caiaphas shouted&mdash;". . . tell us whether thou be the Christ, the Son of God."
</p><p>
Jesus answered&mdash;"Thou hast said"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/63-64#63">Matt. 26:63-64</a>).
</p><p>
"Nearly two thousand years have passed and none has reigned, or served, or dreamed who has
so touched and molded human life. He is the ideal&mdash;the example&mdash;the greatest unalterable,
wholesome, growing influence in a world of blood and tears. Books on his life fill libraries;
the name of Pharaohs, Caesars, emperors, kings of all ages that have come and gone are but
ghosts upon a printed page. Their legions dust upon the land; their proud armadas rust upon
an ocean floor."
</p><p>
"But this one solitary life, surpasses all in power. Its influence is the one remaining hope of
future years."
</p><p>
In a Roman court, nearly two thousand years ago, the skeptic Pontius Pilate demanded of
Jesus: "Art thou a king?"
</p><p>
Jesus answered: "To this end was I born, and for this cause came I into the world, that I
should bear witness unto the truth."
</p><p>
The perplexed Pilate muttered: "What is truth?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/37-38#37">John 18:37-38</a>).
</p><p>
The truth, my brothers and sisters and friends is,&mdash;and I say it in all solemnity&mdash;it is my
witness: Jesus the man of Galilee, is Christ, the Son of the Living God.
</p><p>
Pilate spoke again: "What shall I do with this man?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/27/22#22">Matt. 27:22</a>).
</p><p>
What he did is history. Now twenty centuries later&mdash;what will you, my listening brothers
sisters and friends, do with this man?
</p><p>
Speaking for myself, I have accepted him as the Son of God.
</p><p>
He is the living Son of the Living God&mdash;that is my testimony&mdash;my witness&mdash;and I declare
it boldly, yet humbly, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
