<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Hearken...and Obey</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1950, pp. 83-88</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"It is only a question of time, unless people repent of their sins, until war will come,
not only war but pestilence will come, until the human family disappears from the world.
There is only one way to enjoy peace and happiness in this world&mdash;repent and turn to the
Lord. That is the only way."
</p><p>
In these words President Smith introduced the theme of this conference at the opening
session last Thursday. This statement went down into my heart like fire, because I did not
accept it as the statement of a man but as the word of God through his living
prophet to this living generation. I desire to say a few words about this theme. It reminds me
of the eloquent statement of Alma.
</p><p>
O that I were an angel, and could have the wish of mine heart, that I might go forth
and speak with the trump of God, with a voice to shake the earth, and cry repentance
unto every people!
</p><p>
Yea, I would declare unto every soul, as with the voice of thunder repentance and the
plan of redemption that they should repent and come unto our God that there might
not be more sorrow upon all the face of the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/1-2#1">Alma 29:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
Here indeed is a consummation devoutly to be wished.
</p><p>
FIRST PRINCIPLES
</p><p>
In the Prophet's journal under date of March 1, 1842, he made the following entry: 
</p><p>
At the request of Mr. John Wentworth, Editor and Proprietor of the Chicago
Democrat, I have written the following sketch of the rise progress, persecution, and
faith of the Latter-day Saints. (<i>History of the Church</i>, Vol. IV, p. 535.)
</p><p>
The sketch thus introduced, he concluded with the Articles of Faith, the fourth one of which
reads: 
</p><p>
We believe that the first principles and ordinances of the Gospel are: (First) Faith in
the Lord Jesus Christ; (Second) Repentance; (Third) Baptism by immersion for the
remission of sins; (Fourth) Laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/4#4">A of F 1:4</a>).
</p><p>
You will note that in the sequence here followed by the Prophet, repentance as a principle of
the gospel is preceded by faith in the Lord Jesus Christ. It is clear from the three articles
preceding the one I have quoted that to have this faith requires first, belief in God as our
Eternal Father, in Jesus Christ as his beloved Son and in the Holy Ghost; and second,
acceptance of the doctrines that men will be held accountable for their own sins, and that
through the atonement of Christ they may be saved by obedience to the laws and ordinances
of the gospel.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE LEADING TO SALVATION
</p><p>
To one believing these truths and, in the light of them, having faith in the Lord Jesus Christ,
repentance means not only "a turning with sorrow from a past sinful course of action"&mdash;as it
has been defined&mdash;but, in addition thereto, that through repentance he may bring himself
within the reach of the atoning blood of Jesus Christ, so that thereby he may be cleansed from
the effects of his transgressions and obtain forgiveness of them. His repentance is a
preparation for baptism by immersion for the remission of his sins and reception of the Holy
Ghost.
</p><p>
While turning from a sinful course at any time and for any cause is commendable and
desirable, the repentance which "worketh . . . to salvation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/7/10#10">2 Cor. 7:10</a>), as Paul puts it,
is inseparably connected with the other first principles of the gospel.
</p><p>
TRUE REPENTANCE
</p><p>
Many sober and earnest people are recognizing the need for men to repent of their sinful ways
and are advocating that they turn to God. This is good as far as it goes, but the only people
who can call the inhabitants of the earth to true repentance are the members of the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The reason this rather sweeping statement is true is because
such a call to repentance cannot be made without a divine commission.
</p><p>
For such repentance to be declared under divine commission, as President Smith declared it
at the opening of this conference, is by no means a new thing. It was not new in the days of
the Prophet. It is as old as this world. In the morning of earth's temporal existence, an angel
commissioned by the Lord himself declared repentance unto the first mortal man, saying,
</p><p>
. . . thou shalt repent and call upon God in the name of the Son forevermore.
</p><p>
And the Lord God called upon men by the Holy Ghost everywhere and commanded
them that they should repent; 
</p><p>
And as many as believed in the Son, and repented of their sins, should be saved; and
as many as believed not and repented not, should be damned; and the words went
forth out of the mouth of God in a firm decree
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/8,14-15#8">Moses 5:8,14-15</a>).
</p><p>
NEED OF THE HOUR
</p><p>
From then until now, men have lived upon the earth, and particularly in the land of America,
under this firm decree. As it has been in the past, so must it continue to be, for the Lord
Almighty has spoken it. It seems to me, therefore, that the most desperate need of this hour is
repentance, and that quickly, for it is later than we think. As long ago as 1829 the Lord said: 
</p><p>
Behold, the world is ripening in iniquity: and it must needs be that the children of men
are stirred up unto repentance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/6#6">D&amp;C 18:6</a>).
</p><p>
Time and time again in the past, as men and nations have faced destruction, the Lord has sent
his commissioned servants to declare unto them repentance as the way of escape. "Noah
called upon the children of men that they should repent," and although ''they hearkened not
unto his words," he "continued his preaching unto" them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/8/20,23#20">Moses 8:20,23</a>), saying,
</p><p>
Believe and repent of your sins and be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ, the Son
of God, . . . and ye shall receive the Holy Ghost . . . and if ye do not this, the floods
will come in upon you; nevertheless they hearkened not
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/8/24#24">Moses 8:24</a>).
</p><p>
Melchizedek, king of Salem, was commissioned by the Lord and declared repentance
unto his people. He. . . having exercised mighty faith, and received
the office of the high priesthood according to the holy order of God, did preach
repentance unto his people. And behold, they did repent; and Melchizedek did
establish peace in the land in his days; therefore he was called the prince of peace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/18#18">Alma 13:18</a>).
</p><p>
REPENTANCE IN AMERICA
</p><p>
Upon our own beloved land of America, God has repeatedly commissioned his servants to call
the people to repentance that they might escape destruction. The Prophet Ether ". . . came
forth in the days of Coriantumr"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/2#2">Ether 12:2</a>)
king of the Jaredite nation, and at the Lord's direction
sought out Coriantumr personally and prophesied unto him
</p><p>
. . . that, if he would repent, and all his household, the Lord would give unto him his
kingdom and spare the people&mdash;
</p><p>
Otherwise they should be destroyed, and all his household save it were himself.
</p><p>
. . . And it came to pass that Coriantumr repented not, neither his household, neither
the people; and the wars ceased not
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/13/20-22#20">Ether 13:20-22</a>).
</p><p>
Fifteen and a half centuries ago, because of their unrighteousness, the remnants of the Nephite
race were in a death grapple upon this land with their brethren, the Laments. Among them
stood the mighty prophet-leader Mormon, to whom the Lord said,
</p><p>
. . . Cry unto this people&mdash;Repent ye, and come unto me, and be ye baptized, and build
up again my church, and ye shall be spared.
</p><p>
And I did cry unto this people, but it was in vain; and they did not realize that it was
the Lord that had spared them, and granted unto them a chance for repentance. And
behold they did harden their hearts against the Lord their God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/3/2-3#2">Morm. 3:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
Therefore, they, as well as the Jaredites, were wiped off this land. This was true
notwithstanding the glorious promises made in the Book of Mormon, some of which were
quoted this morning by President Young. All those promises were conditioned upon
repentance.
</p><p>
UNRIGHTEOUSNESS TODAY
</p><p>
The world in which we live today is sick nigh unto death. The disease of which it suffers is
not a new one. It is as old as history. Its name is unrighteousness. The cure for it is
repentance. The Lord foresaw our present extremity long ago and prescribed the remedy. On
November 1, 1831, he said: 
</p><p>
. . . I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven,
and gave him commandments; 
</p><p>
And also gave commandments to others, that they should proclaim these things unto
the world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17-18#17">D&amp;C 1:17-18</a>).
</p><p>
Two things which the Lord had done in preparing a way of escape are here referred to. First,
he had given commandments, and second, he had commissioned men to proclaim them.
</p><p>
One of the commandments was this.
</p><p>
Hearken, O ye people of my church, saith the Lord your God . . .
</p><p>
Hearken and hear, O ye inhabitants of the earth. Listen, ye elders of my church
together, and hear the voice of the Lord; for he calleth upon all men, and he
commandeth all men everywhere to repent
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/1,16#1">D&amp;C 133:1,16</a>).
</p><p>
And surely every man must repent or suffer
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/4#4">D&amp;C 19:4</a>).
</p><p>
And here is the commission: 
</p><p>
Hearken, O ye elders of my church . . . hearken and hear and obey: 
</p><p>
Behold, verily I say unto you, I give unto you this first commandment that ye shall
go forth in my name . . .
</p><p>
And ye shall go forth in the power of my Spirit . . . in my name, lifting up your
voices as with the sound of a trump, declaring my word like unto angels of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/1-2,4,6#1">D&amp;C 42:1-2,4,6</a>).
</p><p>
And what shall we declare?
</p><p>
And ye shall go forth baptizing with water, saying: Repent ye, repent ye, for the
kingdom of heaven is at hand
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/7#7">D&amp;C 42:7</a>).
</p><p>
OUR RESPONSIBILITY
</p><p>
We who today bear the priesthood of God are the legal heirs to this great commission. Ours is
the responsibility of officially declaring repentance unto all the inhabitants of the earth. None
are exempt. We must discharge this responsibility, regardless of the manner in which our
message is received. With respect thereto, we are under the same obligation to this generation
as was Ezekiel to the house of Israel in his day. You will recall that the Lord said to him,
</p><p>
Son of man, I have made thee a watchman unto the house of Israel: therefore hear the
word at my mouth, and give them warning from me.
</p><p>
When I say unto the wicked, thou shalt surely die; and thou gives him not warning,
nor spookiest to warn the wicked from his wicked way, to save his life, the same
wicked man shall die in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at thine hand.
</p><p>
Yet if thou warn the wicked, and he turn not from his wickedness, nor from his
wicked way, he shall die in his iniquity; but thou hast delivered thy soul
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/3/17-19#17">Ezek. 3:17-19</a>).
</p><p>
I regard this commission to declare the saving principle of repentance as a great blessing. I
am grateful to my Father in heaven for it, for there are few things more tormenting to me
than to be faced with a distressing situation about which I can do nothing. The commission
we bear gives us a positive course to follow in meeting the problems we face. It is a
sustaining and comforting feeling to know that the course we are trying to get people to take
is the course the Redeemer would have them take if he were here in person.
</p><p>
NO OTHER WAY
</p><p>
To those who contend that the way of repentance is too slow, I can but reply there is no other
way. Our prophet has so declared in this conference. If we do not come to
ourselves soon and repent, individually and as nations, of our light regard for human life, our
unchastity, our lying and deception, our pride and boastfulness, our covetousness, envying,
greed, and thirst for power, our drunkenness, our lack of humility, reverence, and prayer, our
desecration of the Sabbath day, our lack of faith in the Lord Jesus Christ, and, in short, of all
our unrighteousness, we shall find it is too late, for other proposed remedies to the world's
present predicament will prove futile. There are no armaments, no governmental schemes, no
international organizations, and no mechanisms for the control of weapons which can preserve
an unrighteous people. "Wickedness never was happiness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/41/10#10">Alma 41:10</a>), declared Alma to his wayward son
Corianton; and Samuel, the Lamanite prophet, said to an unrighteous generation of his day,
</p><p>
. . . ye have sought all the days of your lives for that which ye could not obtain; and
ye have sought for happiness in doing iniquity, which thing is contrary to the nature of
that righteousness which is in our great and Eternal Head
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/13/38#38">Hel. 13:38</a>).
</p><p>
Alma has given us compelling evidence of his conviction that repentance is more effectual
than arms in maintaining peace. You will recall that he was the elected chief judge of the
Nephite nation. As such he was the governor of the people of Nephi and commander-in-chief
of their armies. Seeing many of them dissenting and conniving with the enemy, he,
notwithstanding his power to strengthen and command his armies, placed the affairs of state
in other hands that he himself might cry repentance unto the dissenters. The reasons for his
unusual actions are given in the following quotation: 
</p><p>
And now, as the preaching of the word had a great tendency to lead the people to do
that which was just&mdash;yea, it had had more powerful effect upon the minds of the
people than the sword, or anything else, which had happened unto them&mdash;therefore
Alma thought it was expedient that they should try the virtue of the word of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/31/5#5">Alma 31:5</a>).
</p><p>
MESSAGE OF HOPE
</p><p>
Now, my brothers and sisters, there is nothing vindictive in the message of repentance which
we bear. It is a message of salvation and hope, and not of condemnation. It is our purpose to
declare it to our fellow men in charity and love, but we are in no sense apologetic for it. We
know it is of God. We bear it at his command and, we trust, in the power of his spirit.
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to keep in mind the place of repentance in the plan of redemption, the
need for it in the lives of men and nations, and our commission to proclaim it. May he help
us to make it a daily practice in our own living that, when we do proclaim it, we may
effectively hasten the great day envisioned by Alma when there shall be "no more sorrow
upon all the face of the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/2#2">Alma 29:2</a>),
I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ, our Lord. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
