<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Fasting and Prayer</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 122-126</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I rejoice with you for the blessings of this conference. I have
completed one year of service, and I am most grateful for the experiences of this past year. I
want to welcome Elder Marion G. Romney into the Council of the Twelve. For years I have
admired and respected him for his devotion and for his friendly spirit. I am sure we will all
be happy with the quality of the service he is able to give the people of the Church. I also
want to welcome those who have been selected as assistants to the Quorum of the Apostles,
and pledge them my love and support.
</p><p>
I hope, my brothers and sisters, I will not detract from the spirit of this conference. I earnestly
pray for the blessings of our Heavenly Father. Through the sessions of this conference we
have had a tremendous spiritual uplift, and the counsel given to keep the commandments of
God and to stand in holy places has been timely indeed.
</p><p>
FASTING AND PRAYER
</p><p>
As I have traveled about the Church these past few months with members of the general
welfare committee and listened to their talks on fasting and prayer, I have felt this principle
has great spiritual power and opportunity for the blessings of God to the people of the Church
and to the Church itself. I have been impressed by its great spiritual significance. It seems to
me it is a source of strength, a source of power, a source of blessing that perhaps as a people
we are not using enough; that it does have tremendous spiritual value to those who observe
the law, and who apply it faithfully. It also seems to me that fasting and prayer can be
employed to bless others, and if we would faithfully observe the law, the blessings of our
Heavenly Father would collectively be given to the people of the Church.
</p><p>
President Joseph F. Smith said, speaking of the fast, that "the law to the Latter-day Saints as
understood by the Authorities of the Church is that food and drink are not to be partaken of
for twenty-four hours, 'from eve to eve,' and that the Saints are to refrain from all bodily
gratifications and indulgences." Most Latter-day Saints, I think, understand the doing without
two meals in connection with the monthly fast and giving the cash equivalent to the bishop as
fast offerings, but I am wondering along with our fasting do we gather our families together
and pray with them that they may enjoy the blessings of the Lord? Do we also understand
that the true fast presupposes self-restraint and purity of body by refraining from all bodily
gratifications and indulgences? It seems to me that the soul cannot be humbled nor sanctified
for the blessings of God unless this is true.
</p><p>
OBSERVANCE BRINGS BLESSINGS
</p><p>
The Saints by fasting and praying can sanctify the soul and elevate the spirit to Christlike
perfection, and thus the body would be brought into subjection to the spirit, promote
communion with the Holy Ghost, and insure spiritual strength and power to the individual.
</p><p>
By observing fasting and prayer in its true spirit, the Latter-day Saints cannot be overpowered by
Satan tempting them to evil. This morning in the radio address of Elder Cowley, titled, "Man
Cannot Live by Bread Alone," he emphasized the forty-day fast of the Savior
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/1-4#1">Matt. 4:1-4</a>). As I have
thought about the Savior's long fast and prayers unto God, I know his spirit was humbled, his
soul was sanctified, and it gave him the moral strength and the spiritual power to resist the
temptations of Satan. It also prepared him to go forward and complete the great mission that
God had sent him on earth to perform in the interest of mankind.
</p><p>
It was through fasting and prayer that the angel of God appeared to Cornelius, and gained for
him and his household the gospel of Jesus Christ. When Peter came to the home of Cornelius,
he wanted to know for what reason he had been called. Cornelius said: 
</p><p>
Four days ago I was fasting until this hour, and at the ninth hour I prayed in my house
and behold a man stood before me in bright clothing and said, Cornelius thy prayer is
heard and thine alms are had in remembrance in the sight of God (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/3-4#3">Acts 10:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
SONS OF MOSIAH
</p><p>
When Alma was traveling southward from Gideon to the land of Manti, he encountered the
sons of Mosiah returning to the land of Zarahemla. These sons of Mosiah had spent fourteen
years doing missionary work among the Lamanites. Alma in all this time had not seen them
and was overjoyed at this chance meeting. He was made glad because they were still brethren
in the Church and kingdom of God, and says Mormon in his abridgment of Alma's record: 
</p><p>
. . . yea, and they had waxed strong in the knowledge of the truth; for they were men
of a sound understanding and they had searched the scriptures diligently, that they
might know the word of God.
</p><p>
But this is not all; they had given themselves to much prayer, and fasting; therefore
they had the spirit of prophecy, and the spirit of revelation, and when they taught, they
taught with power and authority of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/17/2-3#2">Alma 17:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
This indicates the great blessings that come to those who observe and keep this very sacred
principle of fasting and prayer.
</p><p>
MISSIONARY OBSERVANCE
</p><p>
Recently it was my privilege to tour the Northern California Mission, and as I listened to the
missionaries, your sons and daughters, make their reports and bear testimony, I was so pleased
when they referred time and again to fasting and prayer, and this they resorted to often to
obtain God's blessings for themselves in their work. They fasted and prayed for those who
were sick among them and when they found it difficult to impress people with the gospel
message of the restored Church, they fasted and prayed about it and received great blessings
from such fasting and prayer.
</p><p>
Many of them were fasting and praying that their folk at home, inactive, would become active
in the Church. It seems to me you who are leaders would do well to fast and pray for the
Holy Ghost to guide you in the selection of officers and teachers for Church positions. Let the
Lord give unto you by his Holy Spirit the men and women whom he has chosen.
</p><p>
CALLING OF BRETHREN
</p><p>
We read in the thirteenth chapter of the Acts of the Apostles that there were in the Church at
Antioch certain prophets and teachers, that among these were Barnabas and Saul. The record
says,
</p><p>
As they ministered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Ghost said, Separate me Barnabas
and Saul for the work whereunto I have called them.
</p><p>
And when they had fasted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they sent them
away (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/13/2-3#2">Acts 13:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
We had occasion in the upper room of the temple the other day to witness a similar
experience in the selection of Elder Romney to the Council of the Twelve. As his name was
presented, there was a unanimous feeling that this man had been called of God to the
important position that he now occupies.
</p><p>
NEED FOR SPIRITUAL POWER
</p><p>
I feel, my brothers and sisters, that in our work, and our callings also in our homes, that we
individually need the spiritual power, the strength, the guidance, and the blessings that fasting
and prayer will obtain.
</p><p>
On one occasion when Jesus came to his disciples, he found the scribes asking them
questions. When he inquired as to the nature of their questions, a man stepped forward and
said he had brought his son, possessed of an evil spirit, to the disciples, and they could not
cast him out. He pleaded with the Savior to cast out this evil spirit that was sorely vexing his
son. The Savior asked him if he believed, and he said, "Lord I believe; help thou my
unbelief" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/9/24#24">Mark 9:24</a>).
The Master did cast out the evil spirit from the son and restored him to the father.
As he entered into the house, the disciples came to him and said, "Why could not we cast him
out?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/9/28#28">Mark 9:28</a>).
And Jesus answered, "This kind can come forth by nothing, but by prayer and fasting"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/9/14-29#14">Mark 9:14-29</a>).
</p><p>
It seems to me, my brethren and sisters, particularly my brethren holding the Melchizedek
Priesthood, that when we are called to administer to the sick who are sorely afflicted, if we
would humble our souls through fasting and prayer, we would be close to our Heavenly
Father and have claim upon him for the blessings to those we love and seek to help.
</p><p>
CITY OF NINEVEH
</p><p>
In the interest of saving time (as many other examples showing the great value of fasting and
prayer could be given) may I say that there are great powers, virtues, and blessings in this
divine law. When Jonah was sent to the city of Nineveh to warn them of their destruction
because of wickedness, they repented in sackcloth and ashes, and by decree all in that city
fasted and prayed. Their flocks and herds were also required to do without food and drink.
God accepted this display of repentance and humility through fasting and prayer and turned
aside his anger and the city was not destroyed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jonah/3/5-10#5">Jonah 3:5-10</a>).
</p><p>
It seems to me that if a city could obtain such a blessing by fasting and prayer, a nation also
could be similarly blessed of God. We as a people, by emphasizing this principle, could
obtain great blessings for ourselves and for the Church in general.
</p><p>
Many times during this conference we have been reminded that conditions are serious, that the
affairs of the world are in a muddle, that there are many uncertainties, that men in and of
their own wisdom and learning are not finding the great answers to the problems of humanity
and the world. And as a result, the hearts of men are failing them. Surely in these conditions
of uncertainty, these conditions of wickedness and vice we need the sustaining and guiding
power of Almighty God, which we can obtain from our Heavenly Father through the exercise
of this great principle of fasting and prayer. As a people we need the direction, the
revelations, and the blessings of Almighty God, which we can only obtain by humbling our
souls through fasting and prayer and in keeping God's commandments. Therefore, we should
fast and pray for those in high Church positions, that God will favor them with the revelations
of his mind and will that we may be guided through this period of uncertainty and darkness.
</p><p>
EXAMPLE OF NEPHITES
</p><p>
We read in the Book of Mormon that in the beginning of the fifty-first year of the Judges, the
people of Nephi enjoyed peace, prosperity, and plenty, but yet they were a faithful people in
keeping the commandments of our Heavenly Father
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/33-34#33">Hel. 3:33-34</a>).
However, during this year of the Judges,
pride started to creep into the hearts of the people, and those who had been lifted up in this
pride began to persecute their brethren; therefore it was difficult for the faithful members to
exercise the freedom of their church beliefs. The account reads: 
</p><p>
Nevertheless they did fast and pray oft, and did wax stronger and stronger in their
humility, and firmer and firmer in the faith of Christ unto the filling their souls with
joy and consolation, yea, even to the purifying and the sanctification of their hearts,
which sanctification cometh because of their yielding their hearts unto God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/35#35">Hel. 3:35</a>).
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, if we fast and pray often I am sure that we, too, can wax stronger
and stronger in our faith and in our humility that our hearts will be filled with joy and
consolation; that we will also purify and sanctify our hearts, which sanctification will come
because we do yield our hearts unto God.
</p><p>
May God bless us, may he help us to understand this great principle of the fast, help us to
observe it in its true spirit, help us that we may give to the bishop the cash equivalent of the
meals we do not partake of in the interest of the poor of the Church; and I am sure, and I
promise you that as a people we shall be blessed. You will also be blessed individually in the
observance of this great principle. May this be true, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
