<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1944, pp. 160-161</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is practically the hour of closing, but the time is sufficient for me to say how much I have
enjoyed this conference.
</p><p>
I agree with Brother Joseph Fielding that the keynote of the conference has been repentance. I
agree with him that the Lord told the Prophet at the very beginning that that was his message
to this generation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/9#9">D&amp;C 6:9</a>).
</p><p>
We have been inspired by the principle behind the parable of the lost sheep over whose return
there is greater rejoicing than over the ninety-nine that are safe
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/7#7">Luke 15:7</a>).
</p><p>
I should like to testify to the power of prayer, and to say that it is a wise man who knows
what to pray for. One of the things that we should seek in going before the Lord and in going
upon our knees, is his inspiration and his wisdom to tell us what to ask for
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/30#30">D&amp;C 46:30</a>).
</p><p>
My prayers have been answered.
</p><p>
I want, upon behalf of the First Presidency and of all the brethren, to thank all you brethren
who are here, and those who work with you in your wards and stakes for your loyalty, for
your devotion, for your service to the Lord our God and to his Cause. It is unfortunate that
always we have to speak even the harsh word to those who little need it, because those who
are in dire want thereof are not before us, but we do this in order that you may carry the
message to them.
</p><p>
May the Lord preserve you and bless you for your labors, give you health and strength,
spiritual power to carry on. May he recognize your efforts. May he yield you blessings for
your good desires, yea, and more for your work.
</p><p>
May God be with you till we meet again, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ, His
Son, Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
