<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Book of Mormon a Great Converter</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 85-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I hope all the teachers in the Church will have available to
them, the splendid discourse delivered by Elder Mark E. Petersen. I believe the spirit of the
anti-Christ is rampant in the world and is asserting itself as never before. That places upon the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints a great responsibility because it is our mission to
preach Jesus Christ and him crucified.
</p><p>
In this great conference of the Church at this season we are celebrating two great events, as I
see it. The Easter time, commemorating the resurrection of the Lord Jesus, and the
organization of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints on the 6th day of April, 1830.
I have before me the statement made by Joseph Smith, the Prophet, relative to that first
organization meeting, where six humble men met together and initiated the great movement
which is going forward so rapidly today. The Prophet writes: 
</p><p>
Having opened the meeting by solemn prayer to Our Heavenly Father, we proceeded,
according to previous commandment, to call on our brethren to know whether they accepted
us as their teachers in the things of the Kingdom of God, and whether they were satisfied that
we should proceed and be organized as a Church according to said commandment which we
had received. To these several propositions they consented by a unanimous vote. I then laid
my hands upon Oliver Cowdery, and ordained him an Elder of the "Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints," after which, he ordained me also to the office of an Elder of said Church.
We then took bread, blessed it, and brake it with them, also wine, blessed it, and drank it with
them. We then laid our hands on each individual member of the Church present, that they
might receive the gift of the Holy Ghost, and be confirmed members of the Church of Christ.
The Holy Ghost was poured out upon us to a very great degree&mdash;some
prophesied whilst we all praised the Lord, and rejoiced exceedingly (<i>DHC</i> 1:77-78).
</p><p>
I need not tell you, my brethren and sisters, that the Church, commenced with such a humble
beginning, grew and prospered. The organization was completed with Apostles, prophets, high
priests, seventies, elders, priests, teachers, deacons, patriarchs, and bishops. It was the only
Church on the earth thus organized, even though these callings in the priesthood existed in the
Primitive Church.
</p><p>
I observed that in the account given of this meeting, three important procedures were
introduced: first, the principle of common consent that no man can preside in the Church
without the consent of the membership; second, the introduction of the sacrament of the
Lord's supper which was very appropriate because the first principle of the restored gospel is
faith in the Lord Jesus Christ, and third, the ordinance of laying on of hands for the gift of
the Holy Ghost when a person is confirmed a member of the Church, or, when he is ordained,
or set apart, for any responsibility in the Church.
</p><p>
The Church, organized in this manner, has from its very beginning felt a strong urge&mdash;an
impelling motive to preach the gospel in all the world, and to build up God's kingdom upon
the earth.
</p><p>
Not long ago, in Gordon B. Hinckley's book, What of the Mormons?, I read the dramatic
account of Samuel H. Smith's missionary journey in the region near his home. It was
probably the first missionary undertaking in this dispensation. Samuel was nineteen years old
and a brother of the Prophet Joseph Smith. He carried with him copies of the Book of
Mormon in a knapsack thrown over his shoulders. After walking twenty-five miles the first
day he was refused lodging by the innkeeper. Continuing his journey the next day he called
on Reverend John P. Greene, a Methodist minister. Reverend Greene accepted a book but
refused to buy it. During his absence while visiting his circuit, however, his wife read the
book, and like many others, was deeply impressed. Mrs. Greene urged her husband to read the
book. This he did, and as a result both joined the Church.
</p><p>
Samuel H. Smith returned from his mission, somewhat discouraged, feeling that he had failed.
But, unknown to him, the book had fallen into the hands of Brigham Young. He read it and
began to investigate Mormonism. He did so for two years, and then he, too, joined the
Church. Samuel H. Smith's mission had not been a failure. The book distributed by him and
others also fell into the hands of Dr. Willard Richards of Boston, Massachusetts, who, when
he had read the first page, remarked, "Either God or the devil wrote that book." When he
finished the book, he concluded it had come from God, and he, also, joined the Church.
</p><p>
Later, the volume was read by Parley P. Pratt, a minister in the Campbellite Church. He was
similarly impressed and joined the Church to become one of its outstanding missionaries. I
read his testimony: "As I read, the Spirit of the Lord was upon me, and I knew and
comprehended that the book was true as plainly and manifestly as a man knows and
comprehends that he exists. My joy was now full, as it were, and I rejoiced sufficiently to
more than pay me for all the sorrows, sacrifices, and toils of my life."
</p><p>
Parley P. Pratt took the book to his brother, Orson Pratt, then a young man nineteen years of
age. He, like the others, read the book and became a convert and a great power in the Church.
</p><p>
One of the mission presidents stated yesterday that twenty-five percent of the converts in his
mission were brought into the Church through reading the Book of Mormon. Surely, it is a
powerful book. It is a great converter. It should be read and studied by all Latter-day Saints,
for it will strengthen their faith and give them courage and hope to go forward in the great
work of the Lord.
</p><p>
The Church from its very beginning in this dispensation has put forth every effort, it seems to
me, to tell the world about the restoration of the gospel and the mission of Joseph Smith, the
Prophet. This impression came to me with great force as I read an epistle to the members of
the Church under date of April 7, 1851. This was less than four years after the pioneers
entered the Salt Lake Valley. The epistle was signed by Brigham Young, Heber C. Kimball,
and Willard Richards, and was addressed to the "Saints scattered throughout the earth."
</p><p>
I learned from that epistle that all of the Twelve Apostles were then abroad except Wilford
Woodruff and Ezra T. Benson. Their President, Orson Hyde was in Kanesville, Iowa; Parley
P. Pratt was on his way to Chile, his mission was to all the lands bordering the Pacific Ocean;
Orson Pratt was somewhere in the States on his way to the valley to become associated with
the University of Deseret; John Taylor was in Boulogne, France "preaching, publishing, and
translating"; Lorenzo Snow was in Italy, visiting the Italian states; Erastus Snow was in
Copenhagen, Denmark, where he was translating the Book of Mormon; Franklin D. Richards
was presiding over the British Mission with headquarters in Liverpool, England; Amasa
Lyman and Charles C. Rich were on their way to the Cajon Pass, and George A. Smith was
presiding in Iron County. All of them were preaching the gospel "to every nation, kindred,
tongue and people" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6#6">Rev. 14:6</a>).
What better evidence could they give of their sincerity and integrity? The
best leadership of the Church was surely needed here in the valley, where the foundations of a
great commonwealth were being laid; cities, towns and villages were being laid out and
settled; churches and schools were being erected; and roads and bridges were under
construction. But the paramount obligation resting upon the Church then as now was to
preach the gospel and to proclaim the divine mission of the Prophet Joseph Smith. In this
tremendous responsibility the leaders of the Church have been diligent and determined. May
we be given the faith and the understanding to continue in this great enterprise and thus
discharge the solemn obligation resting upon all of us, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
