<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Work in Great Britain</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1960, pp. 106-110</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brothers and sisters, for these next few moments I seek the indulgence of your
faith and prayers to the end that, guided by the Spirit, I might make some small contribution
to the proceedings of this great conference.
</p><p>
Because of the desire expressed by the Brethren that I say something about the history-making
events of the past week in the British Mission, I have put aside the text of that which I might
have prepared otherwise to say on this occasion. I have determined long since that
the expressed desire of my Presiding Brethren is to me as a command.
Therefore, I trust that I might in some measure, give you a picture of some of the things
which have transpired of a momentous nature in Great Britain.
</p><p>
This assignment from the First Presidency returned us to the scenes of some of the most
soul-stirring incidents and experiences in the history of missionary work in this dispensation.
We were at Preston in the midlands of Great Britain where the first missionary work was
done. As you will remember the history, the first missionaries were submitted to one of the
greatest demonstrations of the power of evil spirits perhaps ever experienced by anyone.
Brother Heber C. Kimball, Elder Willard Richards, Elder Orson Hyde and Elder Isaac Russell
had, for an hour and a half, as they timed the experience, an awful demonstration of that
power.
</p><p>
President Heber C. Kimball, in writing about it afterward, said: "I cannot even now look back
upon the scene without feelings of horror, yet by it I learned the power of the adversary; his
enmity against the servants of God, and got some understanding of the invisible world."
</p><p>
When he returned home, he asked the Prophet Joseph what was the matter with them that they
had to be subjected to such an experience, and the Prophet surprised them when he said
something to this effect: "When I heard of it [your experience] it gave me joy, for I then
knew that the work had taken root in that land [England.]" Then he related some of his own
experiences, and made this significant statement: "The nearer a person approaches the Lord, a
greater power will be manifested by the adversary to prevent the accomplishment of his
purposes" (<i>Life of Heber C. Kimball</i>, 1945 ed., p. 132).
</p><p>
I have no doubt that the Prophet had in mind the terrifying experience he had in the grove
when he prayed for light and was seized upon by this power until he was released therefrom
by the coming of the Father and the Son
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/15-16#15">JS&mdash;H 1:15-16</a>).
He no doubt had in mind the experiences when he
first went to see the plates, when, as he sought to receive them, he again saw a demonstration
of the evil powers.
</p><p>
We were permitted, as we traveled in that same vicinity, to follow the course that Wilford
Woodruff was directed under inspiration to go, from the potteries near Hanley down to
Froomes Hill probably some fifty or sixty miles to the south, where, directed by the Spirit, he
found a people ready to receive the coming of the servants of the Lord. Within two days after
his arrival there, after having met John Benbow and his wife and those who believed in the
sect called the United Brethren, he had baptized six members, and in thirty days he had
baptized forty-five preachers of the United Brethren, and one hundred sixty members, and
obtained thereby the possession of one chapel and forty-five houses for use as meeting places.
In eight months he had baptized over 1800&mdash;all 600 of the United Brethren with one
exception&mdash;and 200 ministers of various denominations in the area.
</p><p>
As a true missionary would, without boasting, he wrote this simple summary: "The power of
God rested upon us and upon the mission in our field of labor. . . . The sick were healed,
devils were cast out, and the lame made to walk."
</p><p>
The work of these first missionaries was not without opposition, and later the
<i>Times and Seasons</i> wrote about the work around Liverpool: ". . . They were so good in general"
(meaning the ministers) "and so pure that they had no room for the gospel. They were too
holy to be righteous, too good to be pure, and had too much religion to enter into the
Kingdom of Heaven" (<i>Times and Seasons</i>, Vol. 2, p. 404).
</p><p>
And then they wrote: "It seemed that it almost required a horn to be blown from the highest
heavens, in order to awaken the attention of the people" (Smith, <i>Documentary History of the Church</i>).
I thought of that when, after elaborate arrangements had been made by President T.
Bowring Woodbury of the British Mission for all the publicity possible through the great
news-gathering wire services throughout the world to get a full coverage, including the local
newspapers, to find the next day, hidden down in an obscure place in one of the two
Manchester papers, this brief reference to our missionary conference where
we created this stake and organized a new mission. This is what the Manchester <i>Guardian</i>
recorded: 
</p><p>
<p>
<b>Mormons Hold a Mass Meeting</b>
</p><p>
"British Mormons formed their first diocese in Europe yesterday at a mass meeting of more
than 2000 members of the Church of the Latter-day Saints in Manchester, the new center to
be built without delay at Wythenshawe, Manchester, at a cost of about 100,000 pounds. The
diocese, or stake covers Manchester, Halifax, Huddersfield, Dewsbury, and Leeds."
</p><p>
I felt like saying what the other missionaries had said, "It seemed as if it almost required a
horn to be blown from the highest heavens in order to awaken the attention of the people."
</p><p>
In one year, 1840 to 1841&mdash;one year and fourteen days, to be exact&mdash;nine members of the
twelve were called to labor in the British Mission. If you remember the history here at home,
those years marked the period of some of the severest persecution that the Church was to
undergo in this dispensation. In that one year and fourteen days the nine members of the
twelve, with their associates, established churches in every noted town and city in the kingdom
of Great Britain. They baptized between 7000 and 8000 converts. They printed 5000 copies of
the Book of Mormon, 3000 hymnbooks, and 50,000 tracts, and they published 2500 volumes
of the <i>Millennial Star</i> and emigrated 1000 souls to America.
</p><p>
These figures of the summary of the missionary work as done in Great Britain might give you
something of an idea of what has happened in the past 123 years in that great country. In
1849 and 1851 over 8000 baptisms were performed in each year, or approximately 1000
converts to each missionary for each of those years. The total number of converts from 1837,
when the work was first started, until the end of 1959 totals 136,026. The recorded number of
emigrants during that same period was 57,149, and we have reason to believe that thousands
of others emigrated without any record being made.
</p><p>
The total number of missionaries who have labored in that field numbers 7398. Twelve
of our General Authorities were British-born, including our own Elder John Longden, who
was born at Oldham, now an organized ward in the new Manchester Stake. It is the estimate
of Elder Richard L. Evans, who has written an excellent history of the Church in Great
Britain during the first one hundred years, that a very large percent of the total membership of
the Church today trace their genealogy to Great Britain.
</p><p>
By assignment of the First Presidency, in company with Elder Alvin R. Dyer, president of the
European Mission, President T. Bowring Woodbury of the British Mission, and President
Bernard P. Brockbank, now president of the new North British Mission, on Sunday, March 27,
we organized the new Manchester Stake with a total membership of 2400 members.
</p><p>
In the afternoon session there were 2026 in attendance, in one of the largest theaters in the
downtown Manchester City. This stake, including all of the Manchester and Leeds Districts of
the mission, and part of the Liverpool District, is now organized with nine wards and two
branches.
</p><p>
It was an interesting thing to discover that the leadership of the stake and wards and the
branches had to be largely composed of brethren who were baptized converts to the Church of
less than five years. Fortunately, and it seemed as though almost by the hand of Providence,
we found a few "anchor" men who had been trained in the stakes here at home, who will
become the trainers of these new, able, but inexperienced leaders. This stake becomes now, a
training ground for leaders of organizations yet to come.
</p><p>
This new stake brings the full Church program into action, so that such an organization will
be a demonstration to the world "to shine forth as a standard unto the nations"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/5#5">D&amp;C 115:5</a>), showing the
work of the Church at full flower. Zion which the Lord declared is "the pure in heart" in that
land now, will "increase in holiness and in beauty." Zion will now begin "to arise and put on
her beautiful garments" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/14#14">D&amp;C 82:14</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/97/21#21">D&amp;C 97:21</a>).
This first stake will provide a pattern for
stakes yet to come from these great missions. We think we have set it up in such a way that
new leaders so trained will shortly be able to take over still other stakes in
that same vicinity, and become a pattern for leaders of stakes in that and the other European
missions.
</p><p>
In truth, then, it now begins to build "a defense, a refuge from the storm, and wrath when it
is poured out with mixture upon the whole earth" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/6#6">D&amp;C 115:6</a>) which as the Lord declared
was the purpose of a stake being organized.
</p><p>
At that same conference, the new North British Mission was organized, with President Bernard
P. Brockbank as the new president. Parenthetically I might tell you that he received his notice
that he had been appointed as the president of that new mission only two weeks before he
actually met us in New York to fly to his new assignment in the North British Mission,
leaving his wife and children to make final preparations and the transfer of his business to
other hands.
</p><p>
We now have organized in the North British Mission eight missionary districts, with nine
missionary districts remaining in the British Mission which will continue to have headquarters
in London, the new mission to have headquarters at Manchester, England. The power of God
is resting again in the missions of Europe, today, as in the century which has passed.
</p><p>
During the month of March alone, in the British Mission they baptized 360 new converts. In
the French Mission, there were another 114 new converts baptized in that mission, which
seems for the first time in our day to give evidence that the work is beginning to take root in
France, after a shocking demonstration of the power of evil in that mission only two short
years ago. And from the North German Mission, to use another example, which we have
usually thought of as being behind the Iron Curtain in part, they baptized in the month of
March alone eighty-five new converts.
</p><p>
So it was likewise, during the three months of last fall, when we toured the Latin American
Missions of South America and in Mexico, we saw evidences of the giant of God's eternal
power, if I might speak of it that way, awakening among those wonderful people, where in
some of those missions they are having 600 to 700 convert baptisms each year, as compared
with only fifty to seventy-five in previous years.
</p><p>
Indeed, in the language of Mark's testimony to the early missionaries of the Apostolic Period
who received the divine commission of the Lord: "Go ye into all the world, and preach the
gospel to every creature.
</p><p>
"He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved, but he that believeth not shall be damned.
</p><p>
"And these signs shall follow them that believe; In my name shall they cast out devils; they
shall speak with new tongues; 
</p><p>
"They shall take up serpents; and if they drink any deadly thing, it shall not hurt them; they
shall lay hands on the sick, and they shall recover"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-18#15">Mark 16:15-18</a>).
</p><p>
And then Mark records
this significant fulfillment: "And they went forth, and preached every where, the Lord
working with them, and confirming the word with signs following"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/20#20">Mark 16:20</a>).
</p><p>
President McKay, I have been a personal witness in these last six months that, as the apostles
of old found, we are finding today that the servants of the Living God are going forth, the
Lord is working with them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/5/72#72">Jacob 5:72</a>)
confirming the work, with the same signs following.
</p><p>
I bear personal witness that the gift of tongues to a whole congregation, which I witnessed, as
in the day of Pentecost, was observed down in one of the Latin American Missions, by which
this congregation understood what was said, although what was being spoken to them was in
a strange tongue. I have witnessed the healing of an impotent and crippled child from birth in
the Brazilian Mission. I have witnessed the healing of a blind child in the Central American
Mission.
</p><p>
And so, enumerating all of these, more important than any of these signs, I have witnessed
the reformation in the personal lives of individuals who accept the gospel and are true to its
principles, which results from a true conversion to the gospel of Jesus Christ. I bear you my
solemn witness to the onrolling of the work of the Lord. The work is awakening everywhere.
</p><p>
I know that God lives. I bear personal testimony to the divinity of the
mission of the Savior, and that this is his work, and that President David O. McKay is his
true representative here upon this earth in our day, and I do it humbly in the name of the
Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
