<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Man Does Not Stand Alone</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1965, pp. 53-55</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
After the earth had been organized and beautified, the Lord created man in his own image and
after his own likeness. And then the Lord God said: "It is not good that the man should be
alone; I will make him an help meet for him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>).
Eve was then created and given to Adam as a companion and wife.
</p><p>
<b>"No man is an island"</b>
</p><p>
The poet Longfellow beautifully expressed this relationship of husband and wife in the
following verse: 
</p><p>
As unto the bow the cord is,<br />
     So unto the man is woman; <br />
     Though she bends him, she obeys him,<br />
     Though she draws him, yet she follows; <br />
     Useless each without the other!<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                    (<i>Hiawatha</i>.)
</p><p>
The Lord's declaration, "It is not good that the man should be alone"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>), has
lofty significance. A babe born into this world is a helpless creature, dependent on its parents
for care, love, and sustenance. Then as his life's cycle expands toward maturity, many other
people affect the course of his life. Association with other youth and participation in their
activities, schools, movies, television, radio, and other media also influence the individual.
</p><p>
One of the most vital forces in this teaching or training process is that of the Church.
Someone has estimated that a boy fourteen years of age, raised in the Church, would have had
approximately seventy-five auxiliary and priesthood teachers and leaders who provided more
than a thousand hours of gospel instruction for his benefit. Added to this there probably
would be another twenty-five persons currently engaged in bringing the full program of the
Church to him.
</p><p>
Although one is born alone and dies alone and is free to live, think, feel and act by himself,
he needs help in reaching his highest possible potential. He cannot do it fully by himself.
</p><p>
As members of the Church, we are traveling along the same highway, each one working out
his own salvation, with exaltation and eternal life in the celestial kingdom as the goal. Yet in
this striving process we are not alone; we gain and give strength and encouragement to each
other. It has been aptly stated: "No man is an island; no man stands alone." (John Donne.)
</p><p>
<b>God in the Solitudes</b>
</p><p>
But there are those who feel that they have no need for anyone else, that they are sufficient
unto themselves. Such persons claim, for instance, that it is not necessary to attend church
meetings and mingle with others. They suggest that they can worship alone in the mountains,
in the canyons, in the out-of-doors.
</p><p>
It is true that momentous events have transpired out in nature. Moses heard the voice of the
Lord from the burning bush on the hillside and also received the Ten Commandments on Mt.
Sinai. Joseph Smith was blessed with the actual visitation from God the Father and the Lord
Jesus Christ in the Sacred Grove. The spirit of worship was surely present on those hallowed
occasions. The Savior taught that secret prayer is efficacious when he suggested: ". . . when
thou prayest, enter into thy closet, and when thou hast shut thy door, pray to thy Father which
is in secret; and thy Father which seeth in secret shall reward thee openly"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/6#6">Matt. 6:6</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Worship for "the perfection of the Saints"</b>
</p><p>
Even though Moses, Joseph Smith, and the Master all worshiped as individuals and prayed
secretly, yet each indicated the need for group worship. The Lord had Moses set up the
magnificent Tabernacle in the wilderness the Prophet Joseph was directed to build churches
and temples and establish a group educational system; and the Savior established his church
organization for the purpose of "perfecting . . . the saints, for the work of the ministry . . ."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12#12">Eph. 4:12</a>).
We have received from God many commandments that require participation
together as church members. The Lord has said: 
</p><p>
"And that thou mayest more fully keep thyself unspotted from the world, thou shalt go to the
house of prayer and offer up thy sacraments upon my holy day; 
</p><p>
"For verily this is a day appointed unto you to rest from your labors, and to pay thy devotions
unto the Most High" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/9-10#9">D&amp;C 59:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
Also remember the instruction: "It is expedient that the church meet together often to partake
of bread and wine in the remembrance of the Lord Jesus"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/75#75">D&amp;C 20:75</a>).
</p><p>
Many blessings come from assembling with other members of the Church. On fast day we are
inspired and uplifted as we hear fervent testimonies borne. In Sunday School and other
meetings we profit by the experiences and expressions of others. Then also consider the value
of the warm smile and hearty handclasp as we associate together, giving us a feeling of
brotherhood and unity, a sense of belonging&mdash;belonging to one another and to the kingdom
of God. The joys we feel are many, many times greater than if we attempted to work and
worship alone.
</p><p>
<b>Fellowship with the Saints</b>
</p><p>
It was not meant that we should stand alone. No one is an island. We need to be in fellowship
with the Saints. By them our lives can be made better and richer. Recently I heard of an
incident which illustrates this point. A boy was extended an invitation to visit his uncle who
was a lumberjack up in the Northwest. For months the boy had looked forward with
anticipation to this trip as an exciting adventure. Finally the time came for his journey to the
vast timber empire of our country. His uncle met him at the depot, and as the two pursued
their way to the lumber camp, the boy was impressed by the enormous size of the trees on
every hand. There was a gigantic tree which he observed standing all alone on the top of a
small hill. The boy, full of awe, called out excitedly, "Uncle George, look at that big tree! It
will make a lot of good lumber, won't it?"
</p><p>
<b>Good Trees Grow in Groves</b>
</p><p>
Uncle George slowly shook his head, then replied, "No, son, that tree will not make a lot of
good lumber. It might make a <i>lot</i> of lumber but not a lot of <i>good</i> lumber. When a tree grows
off by itself, too many branches grow on it. Those branches produce knots when the tree is
cut into lumber. The best lumber comes from trees that grow together in groves. The trees
also grow taller and straighter when they grow together."
</p><p>
It is so with people. We become better individuals, more useful timber when we grow
together rather than alone.
</p><p>
This growing together places a responsibility upon each one of us. We should try fully to
appreciate all our associates, help them, love them, teach them the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ, his plan of salvation for them. We are all the children of God. We can help others;
they can help us. Together we can become valuable timber in effectively building his Church
in which we are blessed to hold membership.
</p><p>
Somewhere out there in the wards and branches and cities where you live are those who are
lonely&mdash;lonely for want of the light of truth; lonely for the association of those who reflect
the Spirit of the Master; lonely, though they may not realize it now to be a part of the body of
Saints that make up the kingdom of God here on the earth. Don't let them stand alone in the
dark. Go to them. Let your life be a lamp to their feet. Guide them till they stand with you
and your associates in the gospel of our Redeemer. This is your responsibility, your
obligation, your mission, your privilege. May you fulfil all of these opportunities humbly and
nobly, I pray in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
