<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Power of Prayer</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President N. Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 50-56</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, brothers and sisters everywhere, it is a joy indeed to be here today in this
historic Tabernacle, here on this beautiful Temple Square, where members of the Church have
been meeting at these regular conferences during the past hundred years; where, as did those
who have preceded us, we enjoy the Spirit of the Lord, listen to words of wisdom, and are
instructed in gospel principles; where we can have our faith renewed and our testimonies
strengthened; from where, as radio and television have made it possible, the great messages of
the leaders of the Church have gone out to all the world.  We wish to extend a warm
welcome to our radio and television audience today.
</p><p>
<b>Centenary of the Tabernacle and of the Choir</b>
</p><p>
We have just heard the beautiful rendition of this great Tabernacle Choir, which was
organized in 1847, and which, with the "Spoken Word" by Richard L. Evans, has been heard
weekly by millions of people since 1929.  The latest tour, which was made about a month
ago, made it possible for thousands and thousands of people in Canada at the exposition, in
New York, Michigan, Nebraska, Oklahoma, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island to enjoy its
magnificent concerts.
</p><p>
On behalf of the First Presidency, those assembled here, and, I feel sure, all members of the
Church, we wish to express our sincere and deep appreciation to President Isaac M. Stewart;
to the conductors, Richard P. Condie and Jay Welch; to our organists, Alexander Schreiner,
Robert Cundick, and Roy Darley; to every dedicated member of the choir, and to others who
have contributed to its outstanding success.  May the Lord continue to bless them with
success.
</p><p>
<b>One hundred years of conferences in the Tabernacle</b>
</p><p>
As we reflect on the many conferences that have been held under the direction of prophets
and inspired leaders, all of whom have been dedicated servants of God, many of whom were
really giants of the Lord, it certainly makes one feel humble to occupy this position.  I do
earnestly pray and ask that I may have an interest in your faith and prayers, to the effect that
the Spirit of the Lord will be with us while I stand before you, that what I may say will be in
keeping with his Spirit and helpful to those assembled here and to those who may be listening
in.  I sincerely pray that the Spirit and blessings of the Lord will attend you,
that those things you desire in righteousness will be given you.
</p><p>
<b>Faith in prayer</b>
</p><p>
I have great faith in prayer, and believe that "more things are wrought by prayer than this
world dreams of." (Tennyson, <i>Morte D'Arthur</i>.) In fact, I have chosen to talk on prayer and
pray that the Lord may help us realize the importance and value of prayer, and what a great
privilege and opportunity every one of us has of going to the Lord in thanksgiving and
supplication.
</p><p>
It is because I have had my prayers answered so many times throughout my life, and because
I feel so keenly the great need of calling upon the Lord, and because I have experienced the
strength and blessings and guidance of the Lord in the position which I now hold, that I have
chosen to discuss this subject with you today.  I pray that those who doubt might be helped to
see and understand that God is our Father, that we are his spirit children, and that he is really
there, and has said: "Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it
shall be opened unto you: 
</p><p>
"For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth; and to him that knocketh it
shall be opened" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7-8#7">Matt. 7:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
I often wonder if we really realize the power of prayer, if we appreciate what a great blessing
it is to be able to call on our Father in heaven in humble prayer, knowing that he is interested
in us and that he wants us to succeed.
</p><p>
As Richard L. Evans has said so beautifully:  "Our Father in heaven is not an umpire who is
trying to count us out.  He is not a competitor who is trying to outsmart us.  He is not a
prosecutor who is trying to convict us.  He is a loving Father who wants our happiness and
eternal progress and who will help us all he can if we will but give him in our lives an
opportunity to do so with obedience and humility, and faith and patience."
</p><p>
To pray effectively, and to feel that one can be heard and have his prayers answered, one
must believe that he is praying to a God who can hear and answer, one who is interested in
his children and their well-being.  The first record we have of anyone praying to the Lord is
that record by Moses in these words: "And Adam and Eve, his wife, called upon the name of
the Lord, and they heard the voice of the Lord from the way toward the Garden of Eden,
speaking unto them, and they saw him not . . .
</p><p>
<b>What hath prayer wrought?</b>
</p><p>
"And Adam and Eve, his wife, ceased not to call upon God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/4,16#4">Moses 5:4,16</a>).
</p><p>
Great and influential men have always prayed for divine guidance. Even this great nation was
founded on prayer.  U.S. Senator Strom Thurmond reminded us of this in May of last year
wherein he said: 
</p><p>
"The Mayflower Compact, written in November of 1620, begins with a prayer, 'In the name
of God,' and goes on to state: 'We . . . having undertaken, for the glory of God . . . do by
these presents solemnly and mutually in the presence of God, and of one another, covenant
and combine ourselves together into a civil body politic.'
</p><p>
"Thus our nation began founded on prayer.  The kneeling figure of George Washington
through that bitter winter in Valley Forge is a part of this country that should never be
forgotten . . .
</p><p>
The Constitutional Convention in June of 1787 had been meeting for weeks without
agreement, when Benjamin Franklin rose to his feet and addressed George Washington: 
</p><p>
"'Mr. President: The small progress we have made after four or five weeks close attention and
continual reasonings with each other . . . is a melancholy proof of the imperfection of the
human understanding . . .  We have gone back to ancient history for models of government
that now no longer exist.  And we have viewed modern states . . . but find none of their
constitutions suitable to our circumstances . . .  How has it happened, Sir, that we have not,
hitherto once thought of humbly applying to the Father of Light to illuminate our understandings?
</p><p>
"'In the beginning of the contest with Britain, when we were sensible of danger, we had daily
prayers in this room for divine protection.
</p><p>
"'Our prayers, Sir, were heard; and they were generously answered . . .
</p><p>
"'I, therefore, beg leave to move:&mdash;
</p><p>
"'That henceforth, prayers imploring the assistance of Heaven and its blessings on our
deliberations be held in this assembly every morning before we proceed to business.'" ("A
Priceless Asset," <i>Spotlight</i>, May 1966.)
</p><p>
<b>Prayer is not unconstitutional</b>
</p><p>
This was done, and now we enjoy the fruits of their labors in answer to prayer.  Prayer has
never been outmoded in this great country.  Lincoln, who prayed to the Lord continually for
guidance, said: 
</p><p>
"It is the duty of nations as well as of men to own their dependence upon the overruling
power of God, to confess their sins and transgressions in humble sorrow . . . and to recognize
the sublime truth that those nations only are blessed whose God is the Lord."
</p><p>
President Dwight D. Eisenhower, at the time of his inauguration, petitioned the Lord: 
</p><p>
"Give us, we pray, the power to discern clearly right from wrong, and to allow all our works
and actions to be governed thereby, and by the laws of this land . . . so that all may work for
the good of our beloved country, and for thy glory.  Amen."
</p><p>
Samuel F. B. Morse, inventor of the telegraph, said that whenever he could not see his way
clearly, he knelt down and prayed for light and understanding.
</p><p>
We have that sweet and simple prayer recorded by astronaut Gordon Cooper while orbiting
the earth: 
</p><p>
"Father, thank you, especially for letting me fly this flight.  Thank you for the privilege of
being able to be in this position, to be up in this wondrous place, seeing all these many
startling, wonderful things that you have created."
</p><p>
<b>Prayer is finite communication with the infinite</b>
</p><p>
I join with Senator Thurmond in his appeal to "our people to pray more, to examine the
religious heritage of our country, and to see the benefit of seeking God's blessings.  Prayer is
the only way in which the finite can communicate with the infinite . . . in which the visible
may be in touch with the invisible.  You may easily see, if you but examine the history of our
Nation, that prayer and communication with God is the cornerstone of our society.  If you a
low it to be abandoned now, you will be casting away the greatest asset this Nation, or any
other nation, has ever known."
</p><p>
All of the prophets, from Adam to our present prophet, have prayed unceasingly for guidance,
and even the Savior prayed continually to God the Eternal Father.  We read, regarding the
Savior: "And it came to pass in those days, that he went out into a mountain to pray, and
continued all night in prayer to God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/6/12#12">Luke 6:12</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has admonished all of us to pray, and through the prophet James has given us this
promise: 
</p><p>
<b>Pray for wisdom</b>
</p><p>
"If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and
upbraideth not; and it shall be given him.
</p><p>
"But let him ask in faith, nothing wavering.  For he that wavereth is like a wave of the sea
driven with the wind and tossed" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5-6#5">James 1:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
This promise is given to every one of us&mdash;high and low, rich and poor.  It is universal,
unrestricted to you and to me and to our neighbors.  He has told us that we must believe and
have faith in God.  We should know that the Lord stands ready to help his children if they
will put themselves in tune through prayer and by keeping his commandments.  In fact, the
Lord has said: "I, the Lord, am bound when ye do what I say; but when ye do not what I say,
ye have no promise" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/10#10">D&amp;C 82:10</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has warned us that we must humble ourselves and not be as the ancient prophet
said: Many men "are lifted up in the pride of their eyes, and have stumbled,
because of the greatness of their stumbling block . . . nevertheless, they put down the power
and miracles of God, and preach up unto themselves their own wisdom and their own
learning" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/26/20#20">2 Ne. 26:20</a>).
</p><p>
Paul said, concerning the proud man of the world: 
</p><p>
"But the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness
unto him: neither can he know them, because they are spiritually discerned" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/14#14">1 Cor. 2:14</a>).
</p><p>
"For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so
the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11#11">1 Cor. 2:11</a>).
</p><p>
As that great student, the late President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., said, if men are to learn of God
and be guided by him, they "must put pride of their learning and their achievements from
their hearts.  And why not?  For how like a drop in the ocean is the knowledge of the wisest
compared with the fullness of the truth of the universe. Men must humbly confess Jesus as the
Christ, 'for there is none other name under heaven given among men, whereby we must be
saved (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>).'" (<i>On the Way to Immortality and Eternal Life</i>, p. 6.)
</p><p>
<b>Recognize the power of God</b>
</p><p>
We must be prepared to recognize God as the Creator of the world, and that he, through his
son Jesus Christ and his prophets, has given us in simple language man's relationship to God,
information regarding our premortal existence, the purpose of our mission here on earth, and
the fact that our post-mortal existence, or our life after death, is real, and that what we do
here will condition us for the world to come.
</p><p>
We must not be misled by the doctrines of men.  All the studies of science and philosophy
will never answer the question: "What is man and why is he here?" But It is answered clearly
and simply in the gospel of Jesus Christ, and we are instructed: "If any of you lack wisdom,
let him ask of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>).
</p><p>
Let us be prepared to do this and not be as those to whom the Savior referred, when he said:
". . . well did Esaias prophesy of you, saying,
</p><p>
"This people draweth nigh unto me with their mouth, and honoureth me with their lips; but
their heart is far from me.
</p><p>
"But in vain they do worship me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/7-9#7">Matt. 15:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Humility and meekness foster the spirit of prayer</b>
</p><p>
Yes, it is important, and the Lord emphasizes that we must humble ourselves and accept the
teachings of Jesus Christ and keep his commandments if we would expect him to hear and
answer our prayers.  We should all be prepared to say truthfully, as Paul did, in speaking to
the Romans, "For I am not ashamed of the gospel of Christ: for it is the power of God unto
salvation to every one that believeth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
It is difficult to understand why some cannot believe, or find it very hard to believe, that God
can hear and answer our prayers, and yet they believe that astronauts can leave the earth and
travel in outer space at thousands of miles per hour and still be directed from home base; that
they can keep in touch with home base and receive instructions and be led in their activities
and then be brought back to a safe landing here upon the earth.
</p><p>
How can we question God's ability to hear and answer our prayers and direct us in all things
if we will but keep in tune with him and at the same time have no doubt that Surveyor III, a
mechanical instrument, can be sent out from the earth to the moon and there be directed by
mere man here upon the earth? It followed instructions as it was directed to dig, to stop
digging, to make a report, to send back pictures, and to dig again.  As long as it was in tune,
it could be directed.
</p><p>
We are as astronauts, or the Surveyor, sent out by God to fill our missions here upon the
earth.  He wants us to succeed.  He stands ready to answer our prayers and
assures us a safe landing as we return if we will but keep in touch with him through prayer
and do as we are bid.
</p><p>
As we pray, however, are we prepared to ask the Lord to bless us as we answer his call or
acknowledge and serve him?
</p><p>
Are we prepared to ask the Lord to forgive us as we forgive one another? For the Lord has
said: ". . . if ye forgive men their trespasses your heavenly Father will also forgive you; But
if ye forgive not men their trespasses neither will your Father forgive your trespasses"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/13/14-15#14">3 Ne. 13:14-15</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Prayer in emergencies</b>
</p><p>
We may well stop and analyze our own situation.  Do we wait until we are in trouble and
then run to the Lord?  As we pray, do we give orders to the Lord by saying, "Bless this," and
"Bless that," "Give us this," and "Give us that," "Do this," and "Do that"?
</p><p>
Or do we pray that we might be led to do that which is right, or be blessed with those things
which are for our best good? We should always pray for the desire and strength and
determination to do the will of our Heavenly Father, and always stand ready to do his
bidding.
</p><p>
Men pray for different reasons. Many are driven to their knees out of fear, and then only do
they pray. Others go to the Lord when in dire need of immediate direction for which they
know of no other place to go. Nations are called by their governments in case of a national
tragedy, drought, or plague, famine or war, to call upon God for his blessings, for his
protection, and for his direction. Some people ask to be healed, others to be strengthened. 
They ask for the blessings of the Lord to attend their families, their loved ones, and
themselves in all their righteous endeavors. This, I am sure, is all good in the sight of the
Lord.
</p><p>
<b>Pray to express gratitude</b>
</p><p>
It is most important, however, that we take time to express our gratitude to our Father in
heaven for the many blessings we receive.  I was deeply touched one day following our
family prayer when one of our little daughters said, "Daddy, I don't think we ought to ask for
more blessings.  The Lord has been very good to us, but I do think we should ask him to help
us to be worthy of the blessings we receive." Since then we have tried more diligently to
express our gratitude to our Father in heaven and pray for guidance that we might be worthy
of that which he has given us.
</p><p>
As we express our appreciation for our many blessings, we become more conscious of what
the Lord has done for us, and thereby we become more appreciative.  We all know what it
means to hear or receive an expression of gratitude for anything we might have done.  Our
forefathers set aside a day of thanksgiving.  I fear that some of us even forget that day.
</p><p>
I wonder if we are sometimes guilty of not expressing to the Lord our gratitude, even as the
lepers who were healed.  We all remember so well the story of Jesus healing the ten lepers,
who cried: ". . . have mercy on us.
</p><p>
"And one of them, when he saw that he was healed, turned back, and with a loud voice
glorified God,
</p><p>
"And fell down on his face at his feet, giving him thanks: and he was a Samaritan.
</p><p>
"And Jesus answering said, Were there not ten cleansed? but where are the nine?
</p><p>
"There are not found that returned to give, glory to God, save this stranger"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/13,15-18#13">Luke 17:13,15-18</a>).
</p><p>
And as Mark Antony said when referring to Caesar, who recognized his friend Brutus among
his assassins: 
</p><p>
"This was the most unkindest cut of all; <br />
      For when the noble Caesar saw him stab,<br />
      Ingratitude, more strong than traitors' arms,<br />
      Quite vanquished him: then burst his mighty heart."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;      (William Shakespeare, <i>Julius Caesar</i>, Act 3, sc. 2.)
</p><p>
<b>The will to do right</b>
</p><p>
I am sure that the Lord expects us to express our gratitude for our many
blessings as we ask for his continued blessings, and to ask forgiveness for our failings and the
desire and strength to do right.
</p><p>
When we pray, it is important that we set about to do all in our power to make it possible for
the Lord to answer our prayers.  As my father said to me when I was just a boy, "My son, if
you want your prayers to be answered, you must get on your feet and do your part."
</p><p>
I often think how much more effective it would be, when the country's president calls upon
his people to set aside a day of prayer, if we were all living righteous lives and were prepared
to acknowledge God as our Creator and to keep his commandments. It seems that many have
lost belief in God entirely, and others question his ability to answer our prayers.  Others have
faith and confidence in their own learning and in their own strength and power.
</p><p>
Then there are those who are as the chief rulers referred to in John: 
</p><p>
"Nevertheless among the chief rulers also many believed on him; but because of the Pharisees
they did not confess him, lest they should be put out of the synagogue: 
</p><p>
"For they loved the praise of men more than the praise of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/42-43#42">John 12:42-43</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Serve "the God of this land"</b>
</p><p>
Let us all pay heed to the warning of the Lord himself, wherein he said, regarding the
American continent: 
</p><p>
"Behold, this is a choice land, and whatsoever nation shall possess it shall be free from
bondage, and from captivity, and from all other nations under heaven, if they will but serve
the God of the land, who is Jesus Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>).
</p><p>
With this warning from the Lord, we have this promise: ". . . seek ye first the kingdom of
God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
We should all have the courage and determination to say as did Joshua: ". . . choose you this
day whom ye will serve . . . but as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has instructed parents to teach their children to have faith in Christ, the Son of the
living God, and to pray and to walk uprightly before the Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25,28#25">D&amp;C 68:25,28</a>). There is no doubt that our
children, if they are taught to pray to a living God in whom they have faith, can more easily
walk uprightly before the Lord.
</p><p>
I shall never be able to express fully my appreciation to my parents for teaching me to pray
secretly and to participate with them in family prayer. My mother taught me at her knee. She
made me feel and know that I was talking to the Lord, to our Maker, our Father in heaven,
and that he was conscious of my acts and my wishes and my needs.  I was taught that I
should express my sincere thanks, ask for forgiveness, and ask for strength to do the right. 
This has always been a great strength to me throughout my life, and today I pray even more
diligently than I ever did before that the Lord will guide and direct me in my activities, that
whatever I do will be acceptable to him.
</p><p>
As I think back to when we used to kneel as a family in prayer every morning and every
evening, I realize what it meant to us as children to hear our father call upon the Lord and
actually talk to him, expressing his gratitude and asking for the blessings of the Lord on his
crops and flocks and all of our undertakings.  It always gave us greater strength to meet
temptation when we remembered that we would be reporting to the Lord at night.
</p><p>
<b>The power of family prayer</b>
</p><p>
Family prayer in any home will draw the family closer together and result in better feelings
between father and mother, between parents and children, and between one child and another. 
If children pray for their parents, it makes them more appreciative of their parents, and as
they pray for one another, they feel closer to one another and part of each other, especially as
they realize that they are talking to their Father in heaven while on their knees in family or
secret prayer.  Then is when we forget our differences and think of the best
in others, and pray for their well-being and for strength to overcome our own weaknesses.
There is no doubt that we are better people when we try to tune in to the spirit of our Father
in heaven so that we might communicate with him and express our desire to do his will as we
pray for his blessings.
</p><p>
The Lord has admonished us to "pray always, lest you enter into temptation and lose your
reward.
</p><p>
"Be faithful unto the end, and lo, I am with you.  These words are not of man nor of men,
but of me, even Jesus Christ, your Redeemer, by the will of the Father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/31/12-13#12">D&amp;C 31:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has also said: ". . . the effectual fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/16#16">James 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
I have often asked myself and tried to answer the question, "Why do some people refuse to
pray? Is it because they feel they have not the time?" I remember very well a father coming
to me one day regarding his oldest son, with whom he was having some difficulty. The boy
was a good boy, but he was getting out of hand.  I asked the father if they had regular family
prayers in their home.  His answer was, "Well, no, but sometimes.  You know, we are too
busy and we go to work at different times, and therefore it is most difficult for our family to
get together for family prayer."
</p><p>
I asked: "If you knew that your boy was sick nigh unto death, would you be able to get your
family together each night and each morning for a week to pray that his life might be
spared?" He said, "Why, of course."
</p><p>
I tried then to explain to him that there are other ways of losing a boy than by death.  I also
explained that where families pray together, they usually stay together, and their ideals are
higher, they feel more secure, and they have a greater love for one another.
</p><p>
Next, do they feel too independent, too smart, and that they can go it alone? Or are they
ashamed to call upon God?  Do they think it shows a weakness?  Or do they not believe or
have faith in God?  Or is it that they do not appreciate their many blessings? Or do they not
feel worthy?
</p><p>
If one does not feel worthy, he should acknowledge his weaknesses, express regret, repent,
covenant to do right, and ask for guidance.
</p><p>
Is it because some do not know how to pray?  If that is true, I suggest that you go to your
Heavenly Father in secret.  Pour out our heart to him. Pray regularly so that you can feel at
home and comfortable while communing with him.  All one needs to do is express his
feelings, which the Lord understands.  He has invited all of us to call on him regularly and
has promised that he will hear our supplication.
</p><p>
<b>The promise of Moroni</b>
</p><p>
The ancient prophet Moroni, referring to the Book of Mormon, said: 
</p><p>
"And when ye shall receive these things, I would exhort you that ye would ask God, the
Eternal Father, in the name of Christ, if these things are not true; and if ye shall ask with a
sincere heart, with real intent, having faith in Christ, he will manifest the truth of it unto you,
by the power of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
"And by the power of the Holy Ghost ye may know the truth of all things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4-5#4">Moro. 10:4-5</a>).
</p><p>
This promise applies to all of us if we will but repent and go to the Lord, knowing that he
can hear and will hear and answer our prayers.  We should all realize that we are God's
children and that he is still as interested in us as he ever was.  He still answers the prayers of
the righteous and those who diligently seek him.
</p><p>
This is my testimony to you.  May we all humble ourselves and diligently seek him through
prayer, and then walk uprightly before him, that we may be led to immortality and eternal
life, I sincerely and humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
