<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">In the Service of Our Father</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Sterling W. Sill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Sterling W. Sill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 118-119</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I here have been a number of circumstances that have combined themselves together this
morning to produce in my heart great humility, accompanied by a feeling of inadequacy to
discharge properly the responsibilities of this appointment.  I pray that I might receive the
necessary strength to fulfil those obligations.  I am grateful for the confidence of the brethren
who are responsible for this appointment.  I also appreciate very much your sustaining vote.  I
promise the General Authorities of the Church, as well as the general Church membership,
and Him whose name the Church bears, that I will do the very best I can.
</p><p>
Many times I have prayed to my Father in heaven that he would help me to do my work.  I
hope that I may pray more and more effectively that I may help him to do his work, and by
that means express to him the appreciation that I feel for all of the blessings of my life.
</p><p>
I am very grateful for my wife and family.  I am grateful for my parents, grandparents, and
great-grandparents. As my great-grandfather marched with the Mormon Battalion to assist in
the war with Mexico, my great-grandma marched with her little family across the plains to
establish herself and her posterity in this valley.  The wagon containing her earthly
possessions was drawn by a team of oxen. Before reaching her destination one of the oxen
died.  My great-grandmother lifted the yoke of the fallen oxen to her own shoulders and
continued the march. I pray that I may draw from her strength and determination.
</p><p>
I appreciate the great opportunity of being a part of this Church, both for what it has meant to
me in the past, and for what it will mean in the future. The real worth of a man is not in
himself alone, but in what he stands for.  It is an inspiring thing to me that the most humble
of us may stand for the most important things.  Joseph Smith was great because of what he
stood for.
</p><p>
When Joseph Smith arose from his knees, after his first vision, and walked across the fields to
his father's house, and went into the kitchen where his mother was working, and leaning
against the fireplace for support, said in substance, "Mother, I have seen God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/20#20">JS&mdash;H 1:20</a>), at that instant
he did not know a bit more surely than I know or than you know that it is right to be honest,
that it is right to be virtuous, and that all the other principles for which this Church stands are
right.  It is right to spend our strength in the service of our Father in heaven to help to bring
about his purposes.
</p><p>
The great psychologist, William James, said that the greatest use of life is to spend it for
something that outlasts it.
</p><p>
In a Sunday School class which I visited recently I heard a Sunday School teacher recount
that thrilling story of creation, that "God created man in his own image"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>), and I found myself
wishing that I might have been there to have witnessed this great beginning, and then it
occurred to me, as it has occurred many times since, that the creation of man is not something
that was finished and done with in the Garden of Eden.  The creation of man is still going on,
and in a very real sense each of us is a creator&mdash;that is, the attitudes, the enthusiasms, the
faith, the determination to serve God, that are so important to our eternal exaltation, are
being currently within us and in others.
</p><p>
It is more important to build a great character than to build a great skyscraper.  We know that
the worth of souls is great, but mostly we are not great for what we are, we are great or what
we may become, and it is my hope and prayer in my own behalf that I may develop those
qualities that will enable me to accomplish the duties of this assignment as is expected of me
by my Father in heaven and those who preside over me in the Church.
</p><p>
May the blessings of our Father in heaven be with us that we may understand our
opportunities, I pray in Jesus name.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
