<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Behold the Man</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Sterling W. Sill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Sterling W. Sill, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 136-138</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
In Austria there is an interesting bridge spanning a beautiful river. As one crosses the bridge,
he passes 12 statues of Christ spaced a few paces apart. Each of these likenesses represents
the Master in his relationship to some occupational or special-interest group. As herders cross
over this bridge with their flocks, they usually tarry for a few moments before that statue
picturing Christ as the Good Shepherd. Farmers stop and meditate before the statue depicting
him as the sower. Fishermen stand in reverence before the representation of Christ stilling the
tempest. And those travelers who are sick, either in body or in spirit, bow before the image of
Christ the healer.
</p><p>
<b>The great teacher</b>
</p><p>
A wonderful uplift can come to a worshiper as he rethinks these inspiring thoughts with the
knowledge that Christ understands his occupational as well as his personal problems. One of
the statues on the Austrian bridge represents the Great Teacher. Jesus was the greatest teacher
because he looked with the clearest insight into human lives; and better than anyone else, he
understood the effects of those common everyday events on which our success continues to
turn. As the Great Teacher, he used the simple experiences of people to illustrate those
profound truths which still determine our accomplishment. As George A. Barton says: 
</p><p>
"He spake of lilies, vines and corn,<br />
     The sparrow and the raven,<br />
     And the words so natural yet so wise<br />
     Were on men's hearts engraven.<br />
     "And yeast and bread and flax and cloth<br />
     And eggs and fish and candles&mdash;<br />
     See how the most familiar world<br />
     He most divinely handles."
</p><p>
And he presented his lessons with as much confidence to the wise men in the temple as to the
unlearned fishermen working at their nets.
</p><p>
<b>Help for businessman</b>
</p><p>
Now just suppose that as we cross our own bridge of life, we utilize the various
representations of the Master to inspire us in the places of our own greatest need. A few years
ago an article was written about the Bible as "The Book That Has Helped Most in Business."
Most of the scientific books written 15 years ago are now out of date. While the Bible was
written when the camel was our most modern means of communication, yet it is still the most
helpful book in creating our business success. And in our meditations we ought to stop before
the Master to absorb his honesty, his industry, his fairness, and his faith. What an upsurge our
economy would receive if we pruned out all of our unrighteousness and fully devoted
ourselves to those goals that he indicated were the most worthwhile.
</p><p>
Beginning in his youth, Jesus was engaged in that greatest of all enterprises which he
characterized as "my Father's business" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>). That is the business of building character, integrity,
and eternal life into the lives of God's children. As Thomas Carlyle once pointed out, "A
man's religion is the most important thing about him. That is what he thinks about and
believes in and works at and fights for and lives by." God has invited each of us to have as
large a share as we desire in the affairs of this important family concern. And when we feel a
little bit discouraged and are tempted to do less than our best, we might listen to this young
"businessman of the centuries" as he went around saying to people, "Be of good cheer." "Be not afraid" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/27#27">Matt. 14:27</a>).
"Why are ye troubled? and why do thoughts arise in your hearts?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/38#38">Luke 24:38</a>). "Rejoice and be
exceedingly glad" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/22#22">D&amp;C 128:22</a>).
</p><p>
The Golden Rule (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/12#12">Matt. 7:12</a>), made up of 17 words, is probably the greatest formula for any business
success that has ever been known in the world. And as we pass along our own bridge of
accomplishment, we might learn from Jesus about being a more responsible worker, a more
effective planner, a wiser judge of our human values, and more dependable in our own
self-discipline. One of the greatest of all business lessons is that "man does not live by bread
alone" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/4#4">Matt. 4:4</a>). We need a good dose of inspiration occasionally. We need to build up our faith and
recharge our love of life. But above all other interests, we need to learn to identify
effectively. We must remember that we are the children of God, formed in his image,
endowed with his attributes, and heirs to his glory. And we should be constantly reaffirming
our destiny through our daily duties.
</p><p>
<b>The great physician</b>
</p><p>
As we cross this river of life, we need to stop occasionally before the representation of Christ,
the Great Physician. Each of us has an important occupational responsibility for his own
health, and we can perform some of the greatest cures if we understand the possibilities of his
command that says, "Physician, heal thyself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/23#23">Luke 4:23</a>).
</p><p>
The world is presently making itself sick by wrong thinking, and yet there is available to us a
great power that is capable of making us well physically, mentally, morally, and socially.
Jesus gave his greatest success formula in just two words when he said, "Follow me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/8/22#22">Matt. 8:22</a>). And if
we pause before him long enough and meditate about him effectively enough, we can actually
follow him in his faith, in his righteousness, in his doctrines, and in his obedience to God.
</p><p>
Christ has some higher titles than those of physician or shepherd or businessman. He is also
the King of kings, and we must not repeat that ancient mistake when nineteen hundred years
ago one group announced their own downfall by proclaiming: "We have no king but Caesar"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/19/15#15">John 19:15</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Christ of the latter days</b>
</p><p>
To serve our own best interests we might erect upon the bridge of life a special representation
to be designated as "the Christ of the latter days." The scriptures tell us a great deal about
Christ's occupational assignment for the cleansing of the earth, the destruction of the wicked,
the universal resurrection, the millennial reign, and the final renewal and glorification of the
earth. The scriptures make clear that the miracles and wonders of the latter days will be
among the most important events ever to take place.
</p><p>
Many people place a very serious handicap upon themselves when they think of Christ only in
his ancient settings of sowing and teaching and suffering. For in describing the Christ of the
latter days, the scripture says, "Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the
way before me: and the Lord, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the
messenger of the covenant, whom ye delight in: behold, he shall come, saith the Lord of
hosts.
</p><p>
"But who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is
like a refiner's fire and like fuller's soap" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/1-2#1">Mal. 3:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The second coming</b>
</p><p>
On our bridge of life there should be a representation of the Christ who will come to cleanse
the earth of its sins. This has more than ordinary interest for us, inasmuch as the sins
mentioned will be our own sins. Someone once painted a famous picture entitled "Christ
Before Pilate." It represents Jesus being judged and condemned by the people of the world he
came to save. But someday another picture may be painted entitled "Pilate Before Christ."
This will involve his second coming, when, with his mighty angels in flaming fire, he will
return to judge the world and take "vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not
the gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/1/8#8">2 Thes. 1:8</a>).
</p><p>
About this event the apostle Paul said, "But I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren,
concerning them which are asleep. . . .
</p><p>
". . . so them also which sleep in Jesus will God bring with him.
</p><p>
"For this we say unto you, by the word of the Lord, that . . .
</p><p>
". . . the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the
archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first: 
</p><p>
"Then we which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to
meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we ever be with the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_thes/4/13-17#13">1 Thes. 4:13-17</a>).
</p><p>
What a great day to look forward to, and what a disaster will involve those who are still
unprepared. Even nineteen hundred years ago Jesus knew a great deal about our personal and
community needs. He looked forward to our day and was greatly concerned for our welfare.
He gave a comparative appraisal of our times when he said, ". . . as the days of [Noah] were,
so shall also the coming of the Son of man be" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/37#37">Matt. 24:37</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Our primary concern</b>
</p><p>
Then he projected our greatest opportunity when he said, "And this gospel of the kingdom
shall be preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
In the latter-day fulfillment of his own promise he has reestablished his Church
and has revealed anew a fulness of his original doctrines, including the greatest of all truths,
that God lives and that the God of Genesis, the God of Sinai, and the God of Calvary is also
the God of the latter days.
</p><p>
As we pass along the bridge of our lives, we ought to understand that our greatest latter-day
need is not for bigger industries or more oil wells or greater power plants or a more ample
gold supply. Our most critical problems are not our population explosions or our projected
food shortages. Our primary concern should be centered in getting a sufficient love of God
and truth enshrined in our hearts, that we will obey all of his commandments.
</p><p>
Christ is the Good Shepherd (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/14#14">John 10:14</a>) and the Great Teacher, but he is also the Savior of the
world. He is the rock of our eternal salvation. He is the Lord of truth, the Prince of Peace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>), the
Son of God, and the giver of all good things. We must not forget that he is also the Christ of
the latter days, and as we meditate before him, may we be inspired to make the best and the
most of that great life which he has given us to live, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
