<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Gospel Plan</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1944, pp. 84-89</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
As an example of the doubts and the vain philosophies in the minds of some of our young
people I want to read you a few statements contained in an article that appeared in a
publication from our own state university during the last few weeks:
</p><p>
A YOUNG STUDENT'S IDEA
</p><p>
Heaven is for children. To the child's mind it is real. For the adult it belongs to the world of
fantasy and make-believe. If we have become adults we have left the idea of heaven behind.
Perhaps the only mature individual who finds the everyday exhilarating and promising is the
one who has supplanted his childhood beliefs in another worldly heaven with confidence in a
heaven on earth. . . The modern world is concerned chiefly with ethics rather than with
theology, with better living than with the methodical analysis of the hereafter.
</p><p>
I suspect that that young student was thinking of the kind of heaven that too frequently is
pictured, which requires much hymn singing and ever so much praying with rows and rows of
saints kneeling in perpetual adoration as a continuous occupation; and perhaps his idea of God
and the Creator is similar to that which has been expressed by one writer who
spoke of God as "a sleepless active energy that actuates all things, so small and yet so
complex as to dwell in the wonderful energies of life and sound and electricity, in the vital
processes of human and animal form, in the motivating influences of the human heart," and so
on. Such a one, who believes thus, would have no faith in the teachings of the scriptures or
an understanding of their import. To one such the Church of Jesus Christ would be relegated
to a mere organization of man, lacking either the reason for or the authority to administer the
ordinances of salvation.
</p><p>
HEAVEN A REALITY
</p><p>
Heaven, as we have usually conceived it, is the dwelling place of the righteous, after they
have left this earth life, and the place where God and Christ dwell. Of this happy state the
Apostle Paul said, "Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of
man the things which God hath prepared for them that love Him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/9#9">1 Cor. 2:9</a>). The location of the place
was made clear by the revelations of the Lord to us in this day when he said that the earth
was to be the abiding place of those who were to inherit the celestial glory and that it would
be cleansed from impurity in order to become that holy place. How the earth was to be
prepared for that condition is indicated in brief Visions recorded by a prophet who said he
"saw a new heaven and a new earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/1-4#1">Rev. 21:1-4</a>).
Another said "and the end shall
come and the heaven and the earth shall be consumed and pass away, and there shall be a
new heaven and a new earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/23#23">D&amp;C 29:23</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph, speaking of the condition in which the earth would then be, after that
cleansing and that purification, in its immortal state, declared that the earth would be as a
crystal and a Urim and Thummim unto those who would dwell upon it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/1#1">D&amp;C 77:1</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/9#9">D&amp;C 130:9</a>). The interim dwelling
place of the spirits, while this great change is taking place, is indicated in the revelation where
the Prophet speaks of "a place of happiness called paradise, a state of rest, a state of peace,
where they shall rest from all their troubles and from all care and sorrow"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/2#2">D&amp;C 77:2</a>). This rest spoken
of was not to be a condition of inactivity but rather was to be what the Lord called it, a place
where men and women were to enjoy the "fullness of his glory"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/24#24">D&amp;C 84:24</a>). To say that there would be
no such a place as the state where one could have rewards or punishments for the things done
in the flesh, would be to say that there would be no such a thing as a judgment; and to say
that there would be no judgment would be to deny that there was atonement for the sins of
mankind or that Jesus Christ was the author of salvation, the plan by which man could be
sanctified for that holy state. To say that there was no such a thing as the atonement would be
to define sin merely as a philosophical formula. If one were to doubt in a life after death or in
a resurrection from the dead, as such a belief would imply, then man would be of all men
most miserable (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/19#19">1 Cor. 15:19</a>),
because he lacks faith in that which would follow after her life here upon this
earth.
</p><p>
I have tried to think how a man would guide his life if he had this sort of feeling and this 
disbelief in heavenly things. Life, with its fleeting opportunities, it seems to
me, would be a mad scramble for the satisfying of one's selfish ambitions and the seeking of
worldly gain. Against that the Master declared himself in a parable where He spoke of the
man of affluence who was seeking about for a place wherewith to bestow his goods:
</p><p>
And he said, This will I do: I will pull down my barns, and build greater; and there will I
bestow all my fruits and my goods. And I will say to my soul, Soul, thou hast much goods
laid up for many years; take thine ease, eat, drink, and be merry. But God said unto him,
Thou fool, this night thy soul shall be required of thee: then whose shall those things be,
which thou hast provided? So is he that layeth up treasure for himself, and is not rich toward
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/12/18-21#18">Luke 12:18-21</a>).
</p><p>
FAITH IN HEAVENLY THINGS AN ANCHOR
</p><p>
Without the discipline of the rewards and punishment that are spoken of in the plan of life 
and salvation, passions and appetites would go on unbridled; vice and crime would go on
unchecked and wickedness would stalk our days. If the Church is but man-conceived, then our
care of the needy would not be for the spiritual and temporal welfare of those who are to be
assisted, but our care would be extended, as is the case with so many public institutions,
merely with the political or the social or the economic welfare of the state or of the
individuals who administer it as the chief consideration.
</p><p>
I have a feeling that whenever we have among our leaders those who would say that the care
of the needy should be left to public institutions and not to the Church, there we have men
who lack the spiritual insight into the spiritual values involved in caring for the unfortunate.
</p><p>
In the parable of the Savior at the close of the great Sermon on the Mount He taught very
plainly the doctrine that the storms of life would descend upon the wise as well as the foolish
and by inference, upon the good as well as the bad, upon the rich and the poor, and that only
those would survive, when those tests and trials should come, who had built their house upon
the rock, because they had listened to the things which the Lord had taught them concerning
the Gospel plan (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/24-27#24">Matt. 7:24-27</a>).
</p><p>
In battle those with faith in heavenly things forbid a dangerous fatalism that ofttimes induces
carelessness and recklessness in combat as well as in private conduct. The kind of difficulty in
which our young men today find themselves, the terrible struggles through which they are
passing in battle, is revealed in an interesting bulletin we have just received from one of our
chaplains down in the Italian area. He starts this bulletin by quoting from President Grant's
great blessing to the boys in the military service some time ago. As I heard President Grant
declare again a blessing upon our boys, I thought how well it would be if the bishops of
wards and the presidents of stakes who have chaplains or our Coordinators from their stakes
now serving with the armed forces would write out that message and ask that they include it
in their publications so that every boy in the service might have the chance to have the words
and the power of that blessing.
</p><p>
EXPERIENCES OF BOYS IN THE ARMY
</p><p>
Here was the description of some of the conditions of four hundred fifty of our boys who
were in that African and Italian area:
</p><p>
Two of our brethren in the infantry were killed during the month on the beachhead. The base
censor has informed us that their names may not yet be divulged. I recall the last time I saw
them. It was at a sacrament service in a make-shift medical dispensary in a town taken a short
time previously. One of them administered the sacrament. Our pioneer forefathers used to
sing, "And should we die before our journey's through, happy day, all is well. We then are
free from toil and sorrow, too, with the just we shall dwell." Those appropriate words,
"Come, Come Ye Saints," seem to particularly apply to our day. It probably will be welcome
news that *** who was formerly reported missing in action is now definitely known as a
prisoner of war in Germany *** is in the hospital convalescing from a shell
fragment wound in his leg. Lieutenant *** who was referred to last month as being
grateful for escaping with his life when a German one hundred fifty millimeter shell struck
his truck and failed to explode, is this month spending time in a hospital recuperating from
the after-effects of the thunderous jolt. *** has been released for duty again after
recovering from an encounter with a shell fragment. *** is still  having his injured foot looked
after by the medics but expects to be returned to duty shortly. *** had a brief career on
white sheets while getting over the effects of a mortar  shell piece that crashed through his
helmet and grazed his scalp. *** fell down an eight-foot well shaft one dark night recently
while under the range of enemy guns. *** is being treated for shrapnel under the arm.
*** is being treated for frozen feet. Three other L.D.S. men have been hospitalized for
minor illness and so on.
</p><p>
Then he quotes two brief statements from two of our boys who have written from distant
stations:
</p><p>
An artillery shell landed where I had most recently been. I don't know whether it was luck or
inspiration that caused me to move, but whatever it was I am mighty thankful.
</p><p>
And another said this:
</p><p>
I have one of those pocket editions of the Book of Mormon. I have just completed reading it
and let me say it is the best book I have ever read. I was astounded at the wonderful
prophecies it contained. My testimony has certainly been increased since I read the Book of
Mormon. I can sincerely say the Gospel means more to me than anything else in all the
world.
</p><p>
When I see the faith that such of our young men are exhibiting I say likewise, thank the Lord
for the power of the Gospel that they have had to guide them and keep them safe. I contrast
the words written into this statement of the young student, in expressing a disbelief in a
heavenly reward, with the picture of a young man who stood on the prow of the vessel going
over toward the invasion coast. As the ship neared the coast within two hours' distance the
men were becoming very nervous. The commanding officer was anxious as to the results of
the mental strain upon the men. This young man stepped forward and said,
</p><p>
"Would you mind if I talk to the boys a few minutes?" And one who heard his voice wrote
home to his father, a business man in the east, not a member of the Church and said, "Father,
that boy talked to us for two hours, just a young man. He told us that even if our lives were
taken and we had lived good clean lives, we need not be concerned, because God had a
reward for the faithful, and we weren't dead actually, but we lived again and our spirits were
more active than they could be here in mortality." He said, "Father, when I inquired of that
young man as to who he was, I found that he was a member of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints."
</p><p>
In my home the other night, I had a young man who spent eleven months in the Aleutian
Islands, discharged because of shell-shock and injuries, recently baptized a member of the
Church. He told of having met some of our boys up in the Aleutians, who invited him to
come to their Sunday School. He said to me:
</p><p>
Brother Lee, the nearest thing I can describe in comparison to my feelings as I stood with
those boys and worshipped with them, was a feeling I used to have as a little child when I
clung to the knees of my mother so that I wouldn't fall. Now the Gospel has meant just that
to me. I cling to it as I used to cling to my mother, so I will not fall.
</p><p>
As I saw this young man shattered somewhat and in a highly nervous state, because of the
recent shell-shock, and in his physical disability I thought of the many thousands of our boys
who may come home to us, some of them maimed and wounded as he, many of them
wounded in their hearts, hurt in their thinking, and all of them needing sympathetic
understanding and direction. I am asking this body of Priesthood&mdash;are we recognizing our
responsibility as Priesthood quorums of the Church to be the stay and the guide of these boys
as they are now in service and to be that agency that will welcome them back into the
fraternity of civilian life?
</p><p>
A PLEA FOR MORE SPIRITUAL FOOD
</p><p>
As I thought of my own childhood experience and that which induced faith within me, I
remember that in our sacrament meetings we didn't expect those from outside the ward to
come and speak to us except on special assignment. Every man was expected to prepare
himself so that when called he could stand up, as they said, "and give a reason for the hope
that was within him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/15#15">1 Pet. 3:15</a>),
and I remember their testimonies. I remember their doctrinal discourses.
I remember how I as a boy, grew upon that kind of spiritual food. I am asking today, are we
partaking of a modern trend that makes of our sacrament meetings little else sometimes than a
place for political discussions or for concerts? This is a place and a time when we ought to do
more to teach the plain simple doctrines of the Gospel than we have ever done before. Our
ward teachers should be prepared to go out into the homes of those who have not been
privileged to come to sacrament meetings. So in all our activities may we be faithful. May we
be as the teachers of Zion. May we be as the Apostle Paul said to the Corinthians:
</p><p>
And I, brethren, when I came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom,
declaring unto you the testimony of God.
</p><p>
For I determined not to know anything among you, save Jesus Christ, and Him crucified.
</p><p>
And I was with you in weakness, and in fear, and in much trembling.
</p><p>
And my speech and my preaching was not with enticing words of man's wisdom, but in
demonstration of the Spirit and of power:
</p><p>
That your faith should not stand in the wisdom of men, but in the power of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/1-5#1">1 Cor. 2:1-5</a>).
</p><p>
As the leaders of Israel, may we so study and prepare ourselves that we, like the Apostle
Paul, may preach the doctrines not of the world but the doctrines of the Lord Jesus Christ,
that the faith of Israel might not be builded on the wisdom of man but on the power of the
Lord Jesus Christ, I humbly pray in His name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
