<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas E. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas E. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 75-80</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Smith, brethren and sisters, it is a delight to welcome our sisters into our midst
again. I was thrilled, and I am sure all of you were, with the splendid tribute that our
President, in his wonderful opening remarks, paid to the mothers and daughters of our
Church. It was also refreshing in the meeting in the temple, with the mission presidents, to
hear nearly all of them express appreciation for the work their wives are doing in helping
them in their great responsibilities. I wish their wives could have been there to hear them. I
commend the example of these mission presidents to all the men of the Church, to feel
appreciative not only of what our wives are doing for us but also to express that appreciation.
I am sure there would be more sunshine and love in our homes, and in the world generally, if
all, not only felt but expressed such appreciation.
</p><p>
A TRIBUTE TO THE BRETHREN LEFT IN CHARGE IN EUROPE
</p><p>
In the early spring of 1940 the last of the missionaries, American missionaries, left Europe.
Sister McKay, our daughter, Louise, and four very choice missionaries sailed from Italy and
came home by way of Gibraltar. Brother Gaston Chappuis and his bride sailed from Lisbon.
Since that time, nearly six years now, our missions, nine of them in Europe, have been
directed by local elders; and at this time I wish to pay tribute publicly and express
appreciation for the work that these fine brethren have done. They have been working under
unusual and very difficult conditions but they have carried on. They've held their meetings
nearly all of them, including branch, district, and annual conferences. The missions have been
self-supporting. The tithing, in fact, has increased from year to year. They have visited the
branches as often as possible under the trying conditions. Many of them have attempted to
maintain a missionary system, and most of the missions have had a few missionaries, and
some of them quite a large force. The British at one time, Brother Anastasiou reported, had
three hundred and twenty-five part-time missionaries. Brother Anastasiou, his wife, and two
children are here now. The British Mission is again presided over by President Hugh B.
Brown, who is doing a wonderful work, not only as president of the mission but also and
especially among the servicemen. He writes that he needs more missionaries. Our acting
mission presidents are also looking forward to the time when missionaries will be again in
their midst.
</p><p>
In a recent letter from President Brown he states: "We need missionaries, experienced men,
preferably older men such as ex-bishops or men who have had experience in presiding."
</p><p>
THE DANISH MISSION
</p><p>
In the Danish Mission, Address: Priorvej 12, Copenhagen F,
Brother Orson West is in charge. He is a very fine man. He writes and
speaks English quite fluently, although he was born and has always lived in Denmark. In a
recent letter he states:
</p><p>
We are all looking forward to receiving missionaries again in the Danish Mission. . . A
problem which has been a serious one during the war is the coal and fuel situation. For the
time being it is worse than ever. Peat is not the best fuel, but we will have to do with that
during the coming winter. I am sure it is not good for our central heating plant to use only
peat, which deposits so much soot. Regarding help to families and persons in our mission, I
beg to inform you that as far as food is concerned we can get along. Our people in Norway
and Finland need it much more than we do. We would be more than happy, however, to
receive, underwear, shirts, stockings, and socks. Especially the babies need these things very
much. It is almost impossible to buy babies' clothing.
</p><p>
THE EAST-GERMAN MISSION
</p><p>
In the East-German Mission when we left&mdash;I happened to be in Berlin when war was
declared&mdash;Brother Herbert Klopfer was placed in charge, another fine young man who speaks
English fluently. In fact, all of our mission presidents except two speak or write English, and
those two have secretaries who can translate for them. Brother Klopfer, before we left
Switzerland, was called into the service, not as a soldier, but to do secretarial work. The next
we heard of him after we returned home was through Sweden; he was in Denmark and had
attended services there and had taken part in their testimony meeting. The last word is that he
is reported missing on the Russian front. The members are carrying on, however, and his
counselors, Elder Richard Ranglack, now acting mission president, and Elder Paul
Langheinrich are doing a splendid work. A letter dated August 19, 1945, states:
</p><p>
Had two wonderful meetings today. At two p.m. just a priesthood meeting with forty-five
present. At four we held a memorial service in honor of President Grant. There were at least
two hundred fifty to three hundred present in a hall big enough to hold one hundred
seventy-five. It was just as full of spirit as it was of people. The old mission home at
Händelallee is a pile of rubble. A sign in front gives the information that the office is now at
Rathenower Str. 52, Berlin N.W. 21, only two blocks north and east of the old location.
</p><p>
THE FRENCH MISSION
</p><p>
The French Mission, as you know, is divided into three districts, Belgium, France, and
French-Switzerland. This mission was not left in charge of one acting president, but three
district presidents, very fine young men who have been carrying on in the same effective way
as have our acting presidents. They are Brother Paul Devignez of the Belgium District,
Brother Leon Fargier for France, and Brother R. Simond for the French-Swiss District.
Brother Simond has managed in some way to send a monthly report during the entire war.
</p><p>
THE NETHERLANDS MISSION
</p><p>
In the Netherlands Mission the branches are also carrying on. Brother J. Schipaanboord
writes:
</p><p>
During the war years we have endeavored to keep the right course. Our old buildings, and the
rented halls, too, we have improved if possible so that they have become more valuable for
our services. In the Rotterdam Branch we have built a baptismal fount. . . A new organ was
also secured. Owing to the food scarcity, many of the faithful Saints had to be supported by
money or in kind. You no doubt know that the mission house in The Hague had to be
evacuated, and we finally moved and rented a place in Utrecht, Maarten Harpertzoon,
Trompstraat 36.
</p><p>
THE NORWEGIAN MISSION
</p><p>
In Norway, Address: Osterhougs Gt. 27, Oslo,
Brother O. Sonsteby, also a very fine man, has been carrying on. He writes:
</p><p>
I have been on a visit to North Norway and saw the Saints there. We held three meetings at
Narvik, probably the most northern branch in the world. The branch has scarcely been visited
during the war, but the Saints there have kept together in faithfulness and held their meetings
regularly. The branch has been visited in the past by some of the leading authorities from
Zion during their stay here in Norway, among others, Apostles David O. McKay, and Joseph
F. Merrill. As travel conditions are today, the trip was very strenuous, but it was a great joy
to me to see the Saints.
</p><p>
THE SWEDISH MISSION
</p><p>
From the Swedish Mission we have received letters and reports all during the war, and
Brother Fritz Johansson has done a splendid work, not only in keeping us in touch with the
Swedish Mission, but also the sister missions of Denmark and Norway. August 7th to the
22nd he also made a trip in the north up to Finland. Two people were baptized, and they
organized a Relief Society. "I discern," he says, "the awful poverty that prevails in Finland.
They need food as well as clothing in order to keep them from freezing this winter."
</p><p>
THE SWISS MISSION
</p><p>
We have heard from the Swiss Mission, also a neutral country, occasionally. Brother Max
Zimmer, Sr., Leimenstr. 49, Basel, is the acting mission president; he has been especially
helpful to our servicemen who were interned in Switzerland and in prison camps in Germany.
A conference held at Easter time in their own chapel in Basel, the only Church-owned chapel
in Switzerland, is reported as being of the largest conferences ever held in the Swiss Mission.
</p><p>
THE WEST-GERMAN MISSION
</p><p>
In the West-German Mission, the home and office is one of the few buildings still standing in
beautiful Frankfort on the Main.
</p><p>
It is only slightly damaged with a few broken windows; a bomb had hit near the building but
only cracked the walls slightly and left a large crater where it struck. Most of the rest of
Frankfort on the Main is just piles of rubble. Our meeting place was completely burned out.
Brother Friedrich Buhl, Jr., was left in charge; a very fine young man, but he was called into
the service before we left, and Brother Christian Heck, another young man, was called to take
his place. Brother Heck was also called into the service, and Brother Anton Huck, an elderly
brother, was called to preside and is doing so now. It is reported that the two young men who
had been called into the armed service were both killed.
</p><p>
AUSTRIAN REPORT
</p><p>
In Austria, our meeting places have not been damaged except in Vienna but our members are
still meeting in No. 20 Seidengasse. A Russian cannon grenade struck high in the rear of the
church building, breaking only a few windows in the chapel part, but inflicting a good-sized
hole in the upper region of the apartment building. When the occupying Russians looked over
the building, our Church occupying about one-third of it, they were told it was an American
church and so they left it alone. Later, when the Americans came, they in turn, looked over
the building but when they saw the work of the grenade they also left, and so the members
continue to meet in their accustomed place. "Vienna," our correspondent continues, "is a
hungry city, a city with ever so little food, fuel, light, housing, and transportation.
</p><p>
"These are difficult times, and I fear that the coming winter will be one long to be
remembered. Just recently, I visited the Allgemeine Krankenhaus, the largest and most famous
hospital in Vienna, and there the situation was the same, even in a hospital."
</p><p>
WORD FROM CZECHOSLOVAKIA
</p><p>
"In Czechoslovakia," Brother Joseph Roubiek, Trysova ul-c 8, Prague 2, writes, "I wish to
inform you that after six years of war, all members of the Church have remained well and
alive. It has been a terrible time. We have remained faithful however, and we await you."
(This letter was written to Wallace F. Toronto, last president of this mission.) "The work of
the Lord here has not been disturbed. We often think of you and the missionaries. Here there
is great need and distress, great hunger among the people. The Saints, however, have
continued to enjoy the blessings of the Lord. Their testimonies of the truthfulness of the
gospel have not wavered, even in the worst moments of the great conflict."
</p><p>
The two branches in the Palestine-Syrian Mission are carrying on as usual, and food is also
scarce there. In fact, it always is.
</p><p>
OUR SERVICEMEN PRAISED
</p><p>
Much of this information that has been received has come from our servicemen and several of
our chaplains assigned to these European countries; and I should like to take this opportunity
to express appreciation publicly for these servicemen. They have done, and are doing, a
wonderful work. Our members are also very thankful for the kindness and help of our
servicemen. I will take time to quote from one letter. It is typical of many others. After
referring to the splendid work that President Brown did in his recent visit to Belgium, the
writer says:
</p><p>
Our good friend and brother, Chaplain Howard C. Badger, has reported to you about activities
in this country but he failed to point out the successful mission that he filled in our branches.
Not only did he deliver stimulative sermons supported by a strong background, but although a
serviceman, he assisted the needy and was somewhat like Father Christmas to our children,
some of whom never knew chocolates or sweets before. We will surely remember him over
here for his attractive character, personifying the successful missionary. It was also my
privilege to welcome and to greet a great many servicemen since September 1944. Although
we never met before, we felt immediately like best brothers ready to help each other with all
our might.
</p><p>
He speaks of going to a cemetery and with reference to that I should like to read a paragraph
from a young French sister. She says:
</p><p>
On October 19, 1944, I copied a dedication from the tomb of a military Mormon which is
found in the cemetery of Henri-Chapelle in Belgium. We have promised to visit the
cemeteries and search out the tombs of our brother Mormons who died to liberate us, and we
will do all we can to place flowers on their graves just as though they were our own beloved
sons.
</p><p>
I just cannot say too much for our servicemen. I have heard directly from more than a score
of them, and indirectly from more than a dozen others. Several of our chaplains, as I stated,
are also in these occupied countries and are also doing an outstanding work. We have had
letters from them from the Scandinavian missions, the Netherlands, Belgium, France, and
quite a large number from Germany and Austria.
</p><p>
The only way we can get letters and help to Germany and Austria is through these
servicemen. We are permitted, however, to send eleven pound packages by parcel post to the
other missions, but these must be mailed to some person direct. We have now received from
our acting mission presidents several hundred names and addresses and we had hoped to get
these packages over before Christmas. There has been some delay, however, but the names
are on file in the welfare office and are awaiting the go-ahead signal from a special committee
appointed by the First Presidency to supervise this matter. In all the missions, as you have
noted, shoes, underwear, and other warm clothing, especially for babies and young children
are needed I do hope and pray that we can get help to them so that they will not suffer too
much from cold and hunger this coming winter.
</p><p>
THE WAY TO PEACE
</p><p>
May our servicemen and our members in these war-torn countries, and all of us, live lives of
Latter-day Saints. May we cultivate tolerance and love for one another and for all mankind.
This war is but an awful chapter written in the eternal-long struggle between right and wrong,
between love and hate, chastity and unchastity, greed and unselfishness. As long as hate and
lust for power control the hearts of men, real peace can find no resting place in the world.
Only love can bring peace. Anyone who permits himself to hate any person, or any people,
makes his own small but vital contribution towards the discord and trouble, while he who
seeks to love others, even his enemies, makes his own priceless contribution to peace. True,
lasting peace, when it comes to the world, will be made up of the many tricklets of love
flowing from the hearts of the people to a common understanding and a common goal. The
gift of peace on earth and good will to men was offered to the world in the gospel of living
taught by our Savior in his earthly ministry. He made love of God and love of mankind
fundamental (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37-39#37">Matt. 22:37-39</a>),
and declared, "On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/40#40">Matt. 22:40</a>). The
power of love alone can permanently disarm the world.
</p><p>
May our Father in heaven help us to realize this and to govern our lives accordingly, I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
