<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Keep the Commandments</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President George Albert Smith</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Albert Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 157-164</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It falls to my lot as the President of the Church to make some concluding remarks.
</p><p>
I would like to ask all of you, could you imagine any other place that we could have been
during the past three days, where we would have been nearer to our Heavenly Father than we
have in this great conference? Is there any place in the world where you could gather together
a group of men who, one after another, would stand on their feet and bear witness that they
know the gospel is here and that we are partakers of it and testify of the blessings that result
from keeping the commandments of our Heavenly Father?
</p><p>
SMOKER FAILS TO GET JOB
</p><p>
The brethren have reminded me of one or two little incidents that I think I will relate. One
has to do with a cigarette. One of our missionaries who filled a good mission came home and
sought employment and was unable to find it here. He had been a smoker before he went on
his mission, but he had quit, so when he came back and became a little bit discouraged, he
took up his habit of smoking again. About that time a non-Latter-day Saint businessman
spoke to one of the prominent men of the Church, also in business, and said, "I need a man to
come into my business, one that is capable and able to grow to take my place, because I want
to retire after a while. I can pay him a good salary, and I have concluded that, while I am not
a member of your Church, I would like to have one of your returned missionaries. They have
had such wonderful experiences, many of them. I've heard some of them talk. If one of them
comes home and you know of him, you don't need to tell him what it is all about, just send
him to me with the understanding that there may be a position. I'd like to interrogate him."
</p><p>
Not long after that the young man who had been seeking work visited the office of the
brother who told me this story. He said to the young man: "I think I know where you can
find employment." He sent the returned missionary to the individual who had told him
without hesitation what he wanted. This returned missionary was a fine, intelligent, young
fellow, and he supposed it meant a job for him.
</p><p>
Our Church businessman said, "I met the young applicant on the street two or three days
after, and asked him, 'How did you come out?" The young man said, 'I didn't succeed. The
man asked me a few questions and then remarked, "I think we had better not try it out
together."
</p><p>
Sometime later the two businessmen met, and the member asked the non-member why the
young man had not been employed. He replied, "When the missionary came into my office,
he told me you had sent him. I thought to myself, this is my opportunity. He was a
fine-looking young fellow and appeared satisfactory to me. As he entered the office, I was
smoking my pipe, and all at once he took a cigarette out of his pocket and lit it, and we started
to talk. I said to him, 'I thought you were a member of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints.' He replied, 'I am,' and I said, 'I thought you were a returned missionary.'
'I am,' he answered.
</p><p>
" 'I'm sorry, I wanted just such an individual as I thought you might be, but what are you
smoking for?' and the young man said, 'You are smoking; why shouldn't I smoke?' I said,
'The difference is this: You have been taught that it is not a proper thing to smoke; I was
never taught that. You are violating the advice and desires of those who love you, and I think
there is no use discussing this matter any further. I will just say that I haven't any position
ready for you, and we'll part.'"
</p><p>
That young man lost a fine position because he had that filthy habit, and that's the only word
I can think of just now that exactly fills the bill.
</p><p>
RETURNED MISSIONARY WHO LACKED COURAGE OF CONVICTION
</p><p>
Another instance that may be of interest: one of our missionaries returned from the Eastern
States where he had become acquainted with a shop foreman in a large manufacturing
establishment, and after returning home he tried for some time to secure employment but was
not successful. Finally he said to himself, "Well, I believe if I go back East, my friend there
will give me a job."
</p><p>
He was a very fine, capable young fellow, but the friend that he spoke of did not know that
he was a member of the Church. So when he went to him and said, "I've come back. I
wonder if you will give me something to do?" the foreman said, "Certainly I will; come right
in." So the young man began work in the very city where he had been laboring as a
missionary. He avoided the members of the Church; he didn't go to meeting; he kept away
from them because he was afraid the men who employed him who were not members of the
Church would not give him the same kind of opportunity for advancement if they knew who
he was. But he was a good worker and kept at it for some time.
</p><p>
One day, after he had been there about three months, the shop foreman called him and said,
"You had better go upstairs; the president wants to see you." The president had told the shop
foreman that he needed a young man for another department who had ability. He wanted a
young man with a good education. He said, "Look around, and if you can find such a man as
that, let me know."
</p><p>
The foreman replied, "We have just such a man working for us right now."
</p><p>
"Already in our employ?" the president asked.
</p><p>
"Yes." The president said, "That pleases me. Send him up to see me." So the young man, not
knowing what the circumstances were reported to the president's office and said, "I
understand, Mr. Grant, that you want to speak to me."
</p><p>
He answered, "Yes. Have you been sent up by the shop foreman?"
</p><p>
The young man replied, "Yes, sir."
</p><p>
"Please sit down. I want to know something about you; I'd like to know where you are from."
</p><p>
"Well," the young man said, "I live away out in the Rocky Mountains." That was the first
hedge.
</p><p>
"But, what part of the Rocky Mountains?" "Well," he replied, "not very far from Idaho." "But
what are you doing here?"
</p><p>
"Well," he said, "I'm here working as one of your employees." "Were you ever here before?"
"Yes."
</p><p>
"Do you know anybody here in the city?" "Not very many, just two or three."
</p><p>
"Well, I don't quite understand why you came back here for employment."
</p><p>
I want to say before going any further, the president knew all about this boy. He had had
somebody check his record, and so when he kept hedging, the president asked, "But who are
your friends here?"
</p><p>
"Oh," he replied, "they're just people that work around town."
</p><p>
"But," the president continued, "do you belong to any church?"
</p><p>
"Well, not here."
</p><p>
"Did you ever belong to a church?"
</p><p>
He said, "Yes, I did at one time," and he began to be afraid the president did know who he
was, and he didn't want him to find out now, so he kept on hedging and said, "At one
time I was a member of a church, but I didn't take much interest in it, and I'm not
doing much at it now."
</p><p>
"What church was it?"
</p><p>
"Well, you'd call it the Mormon Church."
</p><p>
The president said, "Do you mean to tell me that you are a son of a Mormon family?"
</p><p>
The boy knew the man was up with him then; so he answered, "Yes, sir."
</p><p>
The president queried, "Do you mean to tell me that you would desert the faith of your
parents, when you had known that they were Mormons and desired you to be one?"
</p><p>
"Well, not exactly that."
</p><p>
"I'm afraid," the president said, "you're not much credit to them. If you haven't the
courage to stand up for your faith, what good are you? Now," he said, "I will be plain with
you. I thought you were the man I was seeking for this position, but I want to say to you that
if you would betray your parents and go back on the Church you belong to; I'd be afraid to
give you any kind of a job where you have to handle money." And so the young man lost his
opportunity because he did not have the courage to do his duty by his Church and his family.
</p><p>
These things happen so many times; while on the contrary our boys and girls who keep the
commandments of the Lord, and observe the advice of our Heavenly Father, need not be
afraid anywhere.
</p><p>
ADVANTAGES OF CHURCH MEMBERSHIP
</p><p>
I have traveled considerably in the world, myself. I have covered approximately a million
miles. I have been in the homes of the rich and the poor, in many parts of the world, and I
never have found one instance among the better class of people where I have been, where if
they knew I was a member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, it was any
detriment to me. But I have known many cases where it has opened the way and offered
opportunity that I couldn't have had before. You know, it is a strange thing that it is possible
for an individual to belong to the Church, not just a church, but to belong to the Church, to
have had a witness and a testimony that the Lord himself established this Church, to know
that he spoke by the power that he had, in his wisdom, and gave to us in this day the gospel
of Jesus Christ, again, and to belong to just such an organization. No other church in the
world makes such a claim as we do. When I see this wonderful group of young folk, behind
us here, and the choir, and those that we had from Provo yesterday, and others that we meet
all the time, I know of no other place in the world where you can find such young people as
the Lord gives to us in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Where can you go, in
all the world, and find such companionship as you can have in the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints? It is his Church. He gave it his name,
and he advised us that it should be
so called (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/4#4">D&amp;C 115:4</a>). Again I want to mention that fact to some of our brethren. Don't let the Lord down
by calling this the Mormon Church. He didn't call it the Mormon Church. It is all right for us
to believe in the Book of Mormon. He expects us to do that but he told us what to call this
Church. The Lord has said:
</p><p>
THE NAME OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
And how be it my church save it be called in my name? For if a church be called in Moses'
name then it be Moses' church; or if it be called in the name of a man then it be the church
of a man; but if it be called in my name then it is my church, if it so be that they are built
upon my gospel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/8#8">3 Ne. 27:8</a>).
</p><p>
This is <i>his</i> Church, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. I sometimes feel
disappointed that so many of us seem to be timid, if I may use that term, and give this
Church that the Lord has permitted us to be identified with rather a casual reference. I am so
proud of membership in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, when I think that all
the blessings of the world may be mine as a member of his Church, and if I were not a
member how many blessings there may be lost for me. Think of the wonderful people in the
world and in all these various churches. I want to tell you that there are thousands of them, I
think I would be safe in saying millions of them who, if they knew what we know and had
the testimony that God has given to us, wouldn't hesitate to join the Church. They would be
afraid not to take advantage of the opportunities that he has given to us. In this wonderful
conference where we have been assembled the past three days, think how we have mingled
together. I have shaken hands with people all the way from Australia, to Portland, Maine, and
from Europe to Hawaii, who have come here, happy to make these long journeys, delighted to
be permitted to associate and to shake hands with the membership of this Church.
</p><p>
I feel it is a great compliment to you, my brothers and sisters, that so many of you find in the
lives of one another the things that make you proud and grateful to be identified with this
organization. When we think of what the Lord has done for us&mdash;think of the thousands of our
young men and women who have had an education that they could obtain in no other way
except in the missionary field, and that we have more than four thousand out in the world
today&mdash;what a privilege it is! This is not a Church to criticize, to find fault with others. The
Lord doesn't advise us or counsel us to make it uncomfortable for other people who don't
understand, but the Lord in every way encourages us to set an example that others seeing our
good works will be constrained to glorify his name
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE
</p><p>
I am so proud and grateful for the young people of this great organization as I meet them in
different parts of the country, and I am so thankful for their fathers and mothers who have
given them the training that encourages them to pray and to walk uprightly before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>),
encourages them to avoid bad habits and not partake of things that otherwise would hurt
them. Think of it. Do you realize, my brethren and sisters, that there isn't a blessing, a real
blessing in any church in the world that is enjoyed in that church that you may not enjoy as a
member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints? You can't think of a thing that is
worthwhile in preparation for eternal life that we do not have and while we are only a small
organization compared with the great ones in the world, all that they have, all together, that is
necessary for eternal life in the celestial kingdom, we have, plus the authority of our
Heavenly Father and the promise of eternal happiness if we will obey his commandments.
</p><p>
This is not a man-made organization. It is not just a small fraternal department in this great
world; this is the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Think what that means, a
Church of the Son of God, who gave his life that we might live again. So today as I worship
here with you I am thankful for my birthright, thankful for parents who taught me the gospel
of Jesus Christ and set the example in their home. If I did anything that I should not do in my
life, it would be something that I could not have learned in my mother's home. There were
sweetness and kindness and love always. With a large family of children it took a mother with
a good deal of patience, but she was always patient with us.
</p><p>
KEEPING COMMANDMENTS BRINGS JOY
</p><p>
It will not be very long, in the natural course of events, till the summons that took Father and
Mother and other loved ones to the other side, will reach me. I look forward to that time with
pleasant anticipation. I have lived a long time, as contrasted with the average of human
beings, and I have had a happy life. I can think of nobody who has had a fuller life than I
have had, and I don't say that boastfully, but gratefully; and I want to say to you that every
happiness and every joy that has been worthy of the name has been the result of keeping the
commandments of God and observing his advice and counsel. So, as we go forward, each of
us, each having an influence with our neighbors and our friends, let us not be too timid. We
do not need to annoy people, but let us make them feel and understand that we are interested,
not in making them members of the Church for membership, but in bringing them into the
Church that they may enjoy the same blessings that we enjoy.
</p><p>
WORLD IN CRITICAL CONDITION
</p><p>
This world is in a critical condition. It is a pitiable situation that faces us, and not anything in
the world but the power of our Heavenly Father can preserve the civilization of our day and
the people who live upon the earth at the present time. The adversary is having his innings
because the people of the world have refused to listen to their Heavenly Father. Now it is our
privilege, not only to set the example but also to encourage others to take advantage of it.
Nobody knows, when we pick up a paper today, what the headlines may read. So many lives
destroyed here, so many there, some from accident, some from warfare, some from
wickedness, and the greatest destruction of all that is going on in the world today is the result
of immorality. There was a time, as we have been reminded, when, the people of Sodom and
Gomorrah could not produce, in those two cities, ten individuals who were worthy to live
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/18/32#32">Gen. 18:32</a>).
They had been so wicked that they were not fit to live any longer, and so they were
consumed by fire.
</p><p>
Now, brethren and sisters, somebody said in this conference that the same laws apply, the
same rules govern today, and it is just as necessary for us to keep the commandments of our
Heavenly Father. today as it was for any of the prophets of old or any of his faithful sons and
daughters who have lived upon the earth, who have earned a right to a place in the celestial
kingdom. We can't gain our exaltation by the good lives of our neighbors, but we can profit
by their good example, and we can improve ourselves.
</p><p>
With love in my heart for every one of you, may I say I am grateful. I haven't any way of
expressing my thanksgiving to the people of this Church and many people out of the Church,
where I have traveled in the world, for their kindnesses to me, one of the humblest of our
Father's sons. I wish I could return in full measure all the good which has been done for me
wherever I have been.
</p><p>
RICHES OF ETERNAL LIFE
</p><p>
And now, brothers and sisters, it is not so important how many valuables you may have, how
much property you may possess, and how many of the honors of men you may acquire, and
all those things that are so desirable in the world, the thing that God has given to you that is
worth more than all the rest is the opportunity to obtain eternal life in the celestial kingdom
and have as your companions, throughout the ages of eternity, sons and daughters, husbands
and wives with whom you have associated here on earth. That is what the Lord teaches us,
and when the world is so distressed and uncertain, we ought to be grateful, we ought to be
thankful for our blessings. I can think of no people in the world who have so much reason to
be thankful for their blessings as right here in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
BLESSINGS OF CONFERENCE
</p><p>
This will be the conclusion of a remarkable conference. It has been delightful to me, these
wonderful choirs that have made us so happy with their singing, the fine advice and counsel
that we have received from our brethren, the opportunity even to sit in the room and feel the
influences that are here, because everyone who is here, I am sure, has felt as I have felt the
inspiration of our Heavenly Father and the spirit of love and kindness and a determination to
do better than we have ever done before.
</p><p>
This is God's work. It is for the salvation of all the human family if they will accept it, and
we who have received it and know it is true should be ever alert and watchful to share with
others the things that we know. Let our homes be the abiding place of prayer and
thanksgiving and gratitude. Every day when we go out from our homes, let us leave a place
that has been sanctified by the righteousness of our own lives, and when we return to it that
we may feel that influence that is always there when the Spirit of God is present.
</p><p>
I pray that these fine boys and girls who have come to sing to us, along with the other
visitors, may go home from this conference, that you may return to your various homes in
safety and in peace, and take with you a renewed desire to be real members of the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, worthy to be called members. Now, I pray that the Lord
may add his blessing, that his peace may be upon you and in your lives, and in your home.
Let us pray for the great men and women of the world who need the Lord but do not
understand his interest in them. Pray for the President of the United States who, at the present
time, so much needs guidance from our Heavenly Father. Pray for our representatives in
Congress, our governors, our mayors of cities, the men who have influence in politics in our
various communities, that they may do the things that will be better for all of us and make us
happier, and please our Heavenly Father. That is our privilege. I say to you that the power of
prayer is something that cannot be measured. If there were time, I could tell you many
instances where prayer has been answered in a marvelous way. People have risen from beds
when they have been told they could not live, that it was not possible, and yet they have lived
and performed a great work. This is the kind of Church that you belong to. This is the kind
of organization the Lord has offered to all people. Think of our great educational institutions,
the opportunities which are given to our children to learn all that the world can teach them,
plus the glorious truths that are necessary for us to absorb and make a part of our lives in
order that we may gain an exaltation in the celestial kingdom.
</p><p>
ADMONITION TO LOVE ONE ANOTHER
</p><p>
God bless you, my brothers and sisters. I feel I want to be with you. I am so grateful for the
privilege of being here, and now I am anxious that you may all go to your homes and carry
with you love unfeigned, love for your boys and your girls, for your husbands and wives, for
your neighbors and friends, and let that love abound wherever you may be. If we will do that,
when the returns come from this conference and we hear from the various stakes and missions
of the world, where people have gone from here, we will discover that we did receive a
blessing and that the Lord did magnify us and give us our opportunities, and we will go on
keeping his commandments.
</p><p>
I pray that every one of us will remember that to be a member of the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints is an honor beyond all price in comparison, and that we may so live that
our neighbors and friends who know us, who may not be members of the Church, will be
grateful for our fellowship. Peace be with you. May you go to your homes in peace and
safety and continue to live in love and happiness as long as you are upon the earth. And when
the time comes for us to depart this life, may each of us find our names recorded in the
Lamb's book of life, not one missing, entitling us to an inheritance in the celestial kingdom,
right here upon this earth, in the companionship of those we love, I humbly pray in the name
of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
