<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Faith of a Child</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Matthew Cowley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Matthew Cowley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 93-95</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I would like very much to welcome my friends who have come from far-off Hawaii, to
this conference, <i>Aloha mai, aloha nui loa.</i>
</p><p>
Yesterday morning, had I been called upon to speak, I would have attempted to speak about
the integrity of the home. Had I been called upon yesterday afternoon, I would have talked
about this nation under God. Had I been called upon last night in priesthood meeting, I would
have urged the brethren to keep in training with respect to the priesthood which they hold.
Had I been called upon this morning, I would have talked about John the Baptist who was the
forerunner of Christ, whose resurrection we commemorate this day. But I was told this
morning that an inquiry had been made about when I was going to speak so that a little friend
of mine could listen in, and so I am going to talk about my little friend, my little friend, Joe,
who is in the polio ward of the county hospital.
</p><p>
A few weeks ago I went with a young bishop to visit Joe. I did not know how old he was, I
could not see how large he was, all I could see was his head protruding from an iron lung. He
was unconscious. He was afflicted with polio and double pneumonia. When we went in, the
nurse placed robes on us, and we had to put masks over our faces. We prayed over little Joe.
Two weeks later we called again at the hospital and asked if we could see the little lad. The
nurse said, "yes," and when she called him, he came running up the hall to meet us.
</p><p>
I said, "Do you know who I am?" He replied, "Are you Brother Cowley?" I said, "Yes." He
then said, "I was unconscious when you came before, wasn't I?" "You certainly were," I said
and then he replied, "No wonder I don't recognize you."
</p><p>
He took us into his room, and lying in an adjoining bed to his was another young chap, twice
the age of Joe. And after visiting for awhile, we were about to go when little Joe said, "Wait
a minute, don't forget my partner." I said "What do you mean?" And he said, "You pray over
my partner, and then he can thank you for a prayer the same as I did."
</p><p>
And so we turned to his companion, a young lad sixteen years of age, stricken with polio, and
he said, "I would like a blessing. I am a teacher in the Aaronic Priesthood in my ward." And
so we blessed Joe's partner. Two weeks later we called back again. On this
visit little Joe was rather sad, and we asked him what was the matter. He said, "I am lonely.
Maybe I shouldn't have asked you to bless my partner. He got well too soon and has gone
home."
</p><p>
Well, little Joe is probably listening in, and maybe he can see me on television as I speak, so
I want to say to you, little Joe, we are thinking about you. We are praying for you. We have
been told here by the great leaders of this Church that we should have a simple faith. Christ
himself says that we should have faith like yours, the faith of a little child, and unless we
have your faith, we cannot enter the kingdom of heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/3#3">Matt. 18:3</a>). Joe, you are of the kingdom of
heaven because yours is a faith which has not been tarnished by learning, by the wisdom of
men. It is simple. And there are many of your companions down there with you. We are
thinking of them. There are the little Joes and the little Janes who are there, some in iron
lungs and some on rocking beds, some being fed with a spoon. We are thinking about them,
and I know, my little friend, that your faith can do much to make them whole. And over in
the other ward there are others adults, those who are old enough to be your parents, who are
reaching out for help because they feel that medical science may fail. And with your faith
they can know that when medical science has to lay the burden down, the power and
priesthood of God can pick that burden up and restore them to health and strength.
</p><p>
Up there in another ward of that hospital there is another sweet friend of mine. She is almost
ninety-three years of age, still clear in her mind. I visited her on one of her birthdays, and at
the side of her bed was a little vase of flowers. I read the card, "Many happy returns of the
day from the Moose Lodge." She did not know anything about the Moose Lodge. All she
knew about was the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. All she knew about was the
years that she had spent in the temple of God, saying as the Master said to that thief upon the
cross, "Today shalt thou be with me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/43#43">Luke 23:43</a>),
as she worked for the dead.
</p><p>
Joe remind me that I must not forget her birthday this coming July. There must not only be
flowers from the Moose Lodge, but there must also be flowers from the ward to which she
belongs.
</p><p>
I also have another friend about whom I am thinking. She is not in the hospital. She is at a
home. Her limbs are rigid. She cannot use her hands. She cannot walk. Her eyeballs appear to
be frozen in their sockets. She has been that way for twenty-five years, and yet when I call on
her, she laughs, or tries to; she tries to joke; she asks me to take her to a dance.
</p><p>
And so, Joe I am talking to you. I hope you are listening. There are many others like you,
and we remember them, too. We may not have the time to call often. I know others who must
not be forgotten. Oh, I am thinking of the sisters who live on the top floor of the Constitution
Building, over here on Main Street. Some of them near unto ninety, who cannot get out, but
who love the Church, who appreciate the blessings of the priesthood, and who are praying for
you and for me and for the brethren of this Church.
</p><p>
God bless the eight-year-olds of this Church, those who have been baptized. When you were
baptized, Joe, you were not sprinkled; water was not poured upon you; but you, like the
Master, to commence to fulfil all righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/15#15">Matt. 3:15</a>),
were taken down into the water; and you
were immersed; and now yours is the opportunity to follow in the footsteps of your Savior
and be like unto him.
</p><p>
God bless you, my young friend, with the power of the priesthood of heaven. God grant that
his Spirit may be and abide with you and with your partners down there in that polio ward.
Thank your doctors and your nurses for me, they who are so kind and so gentle and so
concerned about the restoration of health to you and your companions.
</p><p>
But, Joe, continue to rely upon your God. Whatever the results may be, you are of the
kingdom of heaven. God grant that we may all have your faith, I pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
