<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Meet Joseph Smith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Paul H. Dunn</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Paul H. Dunn, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 70-73</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, both seen and unseen throughout the world, this is a wonderful
occasion.
</p><p>
Sister Dunn and I are currently residing in Cambridge, Massachusetts. It is steeped in American
tradition. It was the dwelling place for the Washingtons, the Franklins, the Reveres, the
Hancocks. The story is told there of a dialogue that was supposed to have occurred between Mrs.
Paul Revere and her husband. It is reported that she said: "I don't care who's coming tonight. It's
my turn to have the horse."
</p><p>
I am grateful, my brothers and sisters, for my turn here, to bear solemn witness to things that are
very close to my heart, and which I believe completely.
</p><p>
<b>Birthplace of Joseph Smith</b>
</p><p>
One hundred thirty miles north of Boston is one of the most beautiful places I have ever seen.
Nestled in the rolling green hills of Windsor County, Vermont, is the birthplace of a prophet of
the Lord&mdash;Joseph Smith. On the grounds of the original homesite stand two buildings housing a
bureau of information and a religious display center.
</p><p>
Recently on one of our trips to the memorial we had our young daughter Kellie with us. She has
been there many times and is always noticeably affected by the inner peace and spirit that
prevails. She never leaves that building without signing her name in the guest book provided for
visitors and giving her evaluation in the column provided for comments. (Incidentally, another
column asks if you would like more information about the Church. We have received over forty
referrals from her already.)
</p><p>
On this particular day she wrote: "The Church is the greatest thing in my life." My wife and I
were obviously filled with joyful emotion. Why? Because the Church and the gospel with its
ordinances is a "way of life," and by following its teachings we as a family are finding the true
joy and happiness we all seek.
</p><p>
<b>150 years ago</b>
</p><p>
It was just 150 years ago this spring that a young lad with simple faith asked a very important
question: "Which church is right?" That beautiful spring morning in 1820, God the Father and
his Son Jesus Christ revealed themselves to a young boy whose name will never perish. That boy
was Joseph Smith, the first prophet of this dispensation.
</p><p>
For the past two years we have been living in New England and have spent a great deal of time
at the birthplace of the Prophet. The Lord has hallowed that spot, and each time we gaze upon
the granite shaft that pierces the sky over the place where he was born, our hearts fill with joy
and the Spirit whispers to us, "He was indeed a prophet."
</p><p>
One of the best gifts I could give you this morning is an opportunity to know the Prophet Joseph
Smith a little better. I shall not undertake to explain to you the accomplishments of Joseph
Smith, but I want to tell you about the man, the Seer, and the Prophet. I think it is important that
we know the how and why of his life, for to do so is to increase our understanding and
appreciation of this "prince of our present dispensation," even Joseph Smith, the man of whom
Brigham Young said: "Jesus Christ excepted, no better man ever lived."
</p><p>
<b>Life of Joseph Smith</b>
</p><p>
A life that has become a candle of the Lord is a life that all would wish to see more clearly. Such
a life was Joseph Smith's&mdash;a life given in the service of others and a life of love. We declare that
he was, without a doubt, one of the most noble sons of our eternal Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
He was a tall, well-built man, over six feet in height and about 210 pounds. He had a light skin,
light hair, and blue eyes that could gaze into the heart of any man. He was as quick as a squirrel,
strong as a lion, and mild as a lamb. One young man said of him that "he wore no whiskers, and
that altogether, he presented a very formidable appearance, being a man of gentlemanly
bearing." A young lady said that there were no pictures of him in existence that can compare
with the majesty of his presence. His wife said no one could capture his true countenance
because his expression and countenance changed with his moods.
</p><p>
<b>Remarkable blend of qualities</b>
</p><p>
As one looks more deeply into his personality, experiences, and character, one can see a
remarkable blend of Christ-like qualities. His peers spoke of his solemnity in sacred moments,
yet are much pleased at his prophetic wit, his love of music, poetry, drama, and, very notably, his
hearty laughter. They were continually amazed at his versatility in changing pace. He could
move from studying the scriptures or any of his four foreign languages to playing ball, wrestling,
jumping at a mark, and back again to studying. All people could recognize his easy jovial
appearance when he was engaged in activities of fun, but they were quick to note his dislike of
anything that was degrading or vulgar.
</p><p>
He could reprove betimes with sharpness and always showed forth afterwards an increase of
love. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/43#43">D&amp;C 121:43</a>) "I am determined," he said, "while I lead this church to lead it right."
</p><p>
Joseph Smith was a rugged and free outdoor man. He delighted in physical work and taught that
it was a God-given principle to keep our bodies strong. During the building of the Nauvoo
Temple, he would often work in the rock quarry. Many people learned of the restoration of the
gospel while working at his side in quarry, in the forest, or the hayfield.
</p><p>
<b>Spiritual gifts</b>
</p><p>
Joseph Smith had a strong and abiding testimony of Jesus the Christ and never let an opportunity
pass in which he could tell others of the knowledge he had. When he spoke, he seemed to shake
the very earth, and the people said that he had the appearance of one that was heaven borne
while preaching. Not only did he speak with the Spirit, but the records show that at one time or
another in his life he possessed every spiritual gift, and one of his most profound teachings was
uttered in these words when he said, "I have made this my rule: When God commands, do it."
</p><p>
In carrying out God's commandments, Joseph possessed the rare Christ-like combination of what
Carl Sandburg called "velvet and steel," which can move people with gentleness, meekness, and
love unfeigned, without threat or force. If the world would only learn God's commandments and
live like Joseph Smith, what a wonderful world this would be.
</p><p>
President McKay often told us that we become like what we love. Joseph loved Christ and
became like him. He said, "I want to become a smooth shaft in the quiver of the Almighty," "My
voice is always for peace," and "Jesus Christ is my great counselor."
</p><p>
<b>Endured unspeakable persecution</b>
</p><p>
He was a man, like any of us, but unlike us today, he endured unspeakable suffering and
persecution. He was driven from four states, lost six children in birth, was tarred and feathered,
was poisoned; yet he led his people with great courage and said, "I cannot deny what I know to
be true."
</p><p>
Brigham Young said that he lived one thousand years in 38, and although he was mobbed and
beaten, Lydia Bailey said, "His face shown with the mellow radiance of an astral lamp."
</p><p>
He led like Moses, spoke like Peter, and wrote like Paul. Wilford Woodruff said, "His mind, like
Enoch's, expands as eternity, and God alone can comprehend his soul."
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge of gospel unsurpassed</b>
</p><p>
In knowledge and understanding of the gospel, he was unsurpassed. Joseph Smith left on record
fifteen hundred statements that spoke of the future. Many hundreds of these have already come
to pass, and in our own lifetime we will see the fulfillment of many more. You may pick at
random any of his writings and find more about the last days than in the entire Bible. His
writings, letters, and, spoken words are so extensive that it seems almost impossible that one
man could do so much in so little time. The Book of Mormon, the books of Moses and Abraham,
and the Doctrine and Covenants, all of which he recorded under revelation, total 830 pages, and
his own history, speeches, and minutes total over 3,200 pages.
</p><p>
We have been called the happiest people on earth, and much of our happiness comes from living
the truths revealed to us by Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
If any man was taught by God and angels, Joseph Smith was that man. He was a spiritual
amphibian, with one foot on earth and one foot in heaven. Edward Stevenson says, "He
possessed an infinity of knowledge." And Wilford Woodruff said, "He seemed a fountain of
knowledge from whose mouth streams of eternal wisdom flowed." Parley P. Pratt said, "He
could gaze into eternity, penetrate the heavens, and comprehend all worlds."
</p><p>
<b>America, a choice land</b>
</p><p>
Joseph Smith taught that this great nation of America was a choice land that came into being
under the Lord's direction, and he bore a strong testimony of the divine importance of the work
done by the founding fathers of this great country. He said, "The Constitution of the United
States is a glorious standard; it is founded in the wisdom of God. It is a heavenly banner; it is to
all those who are privileged with the sweets of its liberty, like the cooling shades and refreshing
waters of a great rock in a thirsty and weary land. It is like a great tree under whose branches
men from every clime can be shielded from the burning rays of the sun." (<i>Documentary History</i>
<i>of the Church</i>, Vol. 3, p. 304.)
</p><p>
He never asked for a light load, but rather he prayed for a strong back; and he was indeed a
prophet, for his constant plea was: "Oh Lord, what shall I do?" Those who listened to his prayers
marveled at the spirit he presented and learned in their own lives that the heavens could literally
be opened. They understood what he meant when he taught: "It is the first principle of the gospel
to know for a certainty the character of God, and to know that we may converse with Him as one
man converses with another." (<i>DHC</i>, Vol. 6, p. 305.)
</p><p>
<b>True nature of God</b>
</p><p>
Someone has said that the greatest of all discoveries is when a man discovers God. Joseph Smith
made available to the world, with no exceptions, the true nature and knowledge of God, a
personal and loving Father. He taught that God is our Father and that Christ is not only his Son,
but also our elder brother. The Christian churches of the day said, "We believe in God," but
Joseph Smith said, "I saw God and Christ and they did in reality speak to me." He was
persecuted for saying that he had seen a vision, yet it was true. Not only has he made known to
us that God exists, but also that he is ever willing to answer our prayers.
</p><p>
<b>Martyrdom</b>
</p><p>
Prayer is the soul's sincere desire, says a great hymn, and if Joseph Smith gave us nothing else,
he set the example whereby we could have our desires fulfilled and our hearts made clean and
pure. Thus, on his way to Carthage before he was martyred, he said, "My conscience is void of
offense." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4#4">D&amp;C 135:4</a>) "I am not afraid to die." He spoke as a man whose life could stand inspection before
the Master.
</p><p>
On that fateful day in 1844, he was killed by a mob of about 150 men with painted faces. At the
time of his death it was written, "The blow that subdued Joseph Smith has palsied the arm of
Mormonism. They will now scatter in the four winds and gradually merge in the great mass of
society." (<i>Boston Globe</i>, June 27, 1844.) This congregation today and the millions in our
listening audience refute those words.
</p><p>
The enemies of God were sure that by killing the Prophet, they had destroyed the truth; yet it
lives, greater and stronger with each passing year. It is indestructible, for it is the work of God,
and knowing that it is the work of God, we know that Joseph Smith, who was God's chosen
servant, is a prophet, holy and true, for he said, "I obtained power or the principles of truth and
virtue, which will last when I am dead and gone."
</p><p>
It is my personal witness that he was and is a prophet. His mantle fell upon succeeding prophets
and rests upon the shoulders of Joseph Fielding Smith today. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
