<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Mormon Astronaut</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Don Lind</p>
<p class="gcbib">Don Lind, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 99-100</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
(Dr. Don Lind, LDS astronaut, missionary, jet pilot, scientist, was called on and spoke
extemporaneously at the priesthood meeting at general conference, April 1967. These are his
remarks.)
</p><p>
Brethren, it is an honor to be with you this evening.
</p><p>
It is amazing what irrelevant ideas come to your mind as you are walking up that flight of
stairs. The thing I was thinking about was the fact that a great amount of our training is
involved in such things as riding centrifuges, when you have a great variety of sensors
attached rather painfully to your body to give the doctor a monitor of your pulse rate, heart
beat, and general physical condition. As I was climbing the stairs I was grateful that I wasn't
being monitored, because I think I exceeded a number of limits. If lying on an Apollo couch
is as disturbing as sitting in that little green chair, we may have to postpone a launch.
</p><p>
Brethren, it is a pleasure to be with you. I enjoyed greatly the first half of this meeting, as
well as the afternoon session. I was grateful for the opportunity to come and be with you for
conference. It has been inspiring.
</p><p>
When I was in grade school, a number of movies were made about great square-rigged
whaling vessels. I always felt at that age in my life that I had been born at the wrong time,
that I should have been born back in the days of the whaling vessels; but
since I have grown a bit older, and hopefully a little wiser, I have decided that this is the time
in the world's history that I am most grateful for being alive, not only for having the
opportunity of participating in one of the most exciting adventures I think mankind has
attempted, but also the opportunity of being born at a time when the Gospel is here upon the
earth, in going to the particular home to which I was assigned.
</p><p>
I would not be here today if it were not for my parents.
</p><p>
The words that were spoken about the responsibility of fathers and parents in general this
evening touched my heart in my responsibility to my family, but I also marvel at the
wonderful job that my father and my mother did for me. I, with Nephi, can say that I have
come of goodly parents (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/1/1#1">1 Ne. 1:1</a>). I would never have made the astronaut program, nor would I be a
priesthood bearer in the Church, if it had not been for my father and my mother, and I thank
them for it.
</p><p>
I am grateful for this gospel. I have been in situations when religion was not necessarily the
most popular topic of conversation. I have been in situations involving my schooling when
people expressed openly the idea that religion was fairy-tale, was legend, was myth, was only
for those who were not sufficiently well educated to get along without it; and obviously I did
not agree.
</p><p>
I have been in situations where the principles that we hold have not been lived, if even
believed, and I have been grateful for the strength that I received in my home, and grateful
for the strength that a testimony of the gospel gave me in those situations. The gospel means
more to me than my life, more to me than anything that I would be capable of describing. I
don't know how to express in words the feeling of what my testimony of the gospel means to
me.
</p><p>
Brethren, it is an honor to be with you as a member of this priesthood. I have marveled at the
strength it can give one in various situations. I have a testimony that God lives, and that
strangely enough, is a fact I am afraid most of the world do not share with us. There are a
great many who wonder whether God really lives at all.
</p><p>
I wasn't in the Sacred Grove with Joseph Smith, but I have just as strong a conviction of the
fact that he saw God and talked with him face to face as I have the conviction of something I
got my doctoral dissertation on, the existence of pi-mesons. I haven't seen pi-mesons either,
but I accept their existence on secondary evidence. And on secondary evidence I believe that
Joseph Smith saw God in the Sacred Grove; and that is a great strength in my life.
</p><p>
I believe that Joseph Smith was a prophet, that he received revelations. Scientifically I believe
it because I think it would be just too difficult to forge the Book of Mormon, if for no other
reason. I do not think it could be done by a man with Joseph Smith's education. So I believe
the Book of Mormon is an evidence that Joseph Smith has to be a prophet of our Lord. I am
grateful too that we have a prophet living today to guide and direct the Church.
</p><p>
Brethren, let me repeat once more, it is a pleasure to be with you, because I couldn't be with
you if I did not hold the priesthood, which I hold dear. Brethren, I bear you my testimony
that the gospel is true; I am grateful to be a member of this Church, and I do this in the name
of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
