<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Great Work</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Rudger Clawson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">President of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Rudger Clawson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 23-24</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, at the set time Columbus appeared, and the new world was born. At the set time
Joseph Smith appeared, and it was predicted that a great and marvelous work was to
commence (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/21/9#9">3 Ne. 21:9</a>).
Both characters were here and had their part to play among the children of men.
Columbus discovered the new world on October 12, 1492. Joseph Smith organized the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints April 6, 1830, and it is destined to fill the whole earth.
</p><p>
A VISION IN THE KIRTLAND TEMPLE
</p><p>
I am impressed this afternoon to read a few words froth the D&amp;C, Section 110:
</p><p>
The veil was taken from our minds, and the eyes of our understanding were opened.
</p><p>
We saw the Lord standing upon the breastwork of the pulpit, before us; and under his feet
was a paved work of pure gold, in color like amber.
</p><p>
His eyes were as a flame of fire; the hair of his head was white like the pure snow; his
countenance shone above the brightness of the sun; and his voice was as the sound of the
rushing of great waters, even the voice of Jehovah, saying:
</p><p>
I am the first and the last; I am he who liveth, I am he who was slain; I am your advocate
with the Father.
</p><p>
Behold, your sins are forgiven you; you are clean before me; therefore, lift up your heads and
rejoice.
</p><p>
Let the hearts of your brethren rejoice, and let the hearts of all my people rejoice, who have,
with their might, built this house to my name.
</p><p>
For behold, I have accepted this house, and my name shall be here; and I will manifest 
myself to my people in mercy in this house. Yea, I will appear unto my servants, and speak
unto them with mine own voice, if my people will keep my commandments, and do not
pollute this holy house.
</p><p>
Yea, the hearts of thousands and tens of thousands shall greatly rejoice in consequence of the
blessings which shall be poured out, and the endowment with which my servants have been
endowed in this house.
</p><p>
And the fame of this house shall spread to foreign lands; and this is the beginning of the
blessing which shall be poured out upon the heads of my people. Even so. Amen.
</p><p>
After this vision closed, the heavens were again opened unto us; and Moses appeared before
us, and committed unto us the keys of the gathering of Israel from the four parts of the earth,
and the leading of the ten tribes from the land of the north.
</p><p>
After this, Elias appeared, and committed the dispensation of the gospel of Abraham, saying
that in us and our seed all generations after us should be blessed.
</p><p>
After this vision had closed, another great and glorious vision burst upon us; for Elijah the
prophet, who was taken to heaven without tasting death, stood before us, and said:
</p><p>
Behold, the time has fully come, which was spoken of by the mouth of Malachi&mdash;testifying
that he [Elijah] should be sent, before the great and dreadful day of the Lord come&mdash;
</p><p>
To turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the children to the fathers, lest the whole
earth be smitten with a curse&mdash;
</p><p>
Therefore, the keys of this dispensation are committed into your hands; and by this ye may
know that the great and dreadful day of the Lord is near, even at the doors
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/1-16#1">D&amp;C 110:1-16</a>).
</p><p>
It is shown here very clearly that before this marvelous work and wonder
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/14#14">Isa. 29:14</a>) should be
accomplished certain keys should be given to the earth, and I have read in your hearing
concerning these keys, and it throws a great deal of light on this subject. It emphasizes the
responsibility resting upon Latter-day Saints to familiarize themselves with these keys and
laws and testimonies that are given.
</p><p>
A TESTIMONY
</p><p>
I testify to you, my brethren, that this revelation was given for our profit, and I express to
you my testimony in these words, that I know the Lord is with us, that Jesus is the Christ,
and that Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of God. We are engaged in a glorious work. It is
a marvelous scene to look out upon this gathering of Priesthood.
</p><p>
I trust that I may never lose this testimony that I have.
</p><p>
God bless you, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
