<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Unity for the Welfare of the Church and the Nation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1942, pp. 85-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
This has been a gathering that might accurately have been described as a Church leadership
conference. President Grant, at the opening session of this conference, bore testimony to the
divine calling of those who have presided over the Church in this dispensation. In his
testimony he has given us the key by which we may be safely guided in our own presidency
and leadership responsibility, and he sounded the keynote that has carried through this entire
conference. I am persuaded that any presiding officer who does not have such a testimony is
not qualified to preside as an officer in the Church.
</p><p>
From the beginning of time, as recorded in sacred scripture, the prophets of the Lord have
sounded the warning note to the world and to the membership of the Church. There have
always been those with apostate leanings who have ridiculed, and have stood on the side-lines
and made light of the efforts of those who sought to follow that counsel. It was so in the days
of Noah, and that history is repeating itself at the present time.
</p><p>
In 1831, the Lord gave a revelation to this Church, in which He declared that "the time was
not yet, but soon, when peace should be taken from the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/35#35">D&amp;C 1:35</a>). That time, we all recognize, is
here. In that same revelation the Lord declared:
</p><p>
Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the
earth, called upon my servant Joseph Smith, Jun. and spake unto him from heaven, and gave
him commandments (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
Again He has declared, "whether by mine own voice, or by the voice of my servants, it is the
same" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/38#38">D&amp;C 1:38</a>).
Not all of His commandments have been given to the Church in the
writings of the scriptures.
</p><p>
This conference has convened on the sixth anniversary of the launching of what we have
styled the Church Welfare plan which was given to the Church by our leaders as they were
inspired by the Lord. The activities of the Welfare plan have provided the greatest
opportunities for spiritualizing this Church that perhaps have ever been given this people in
our generation and as we have watched it unfold and its purposes be more fully revealed, we
have come to see therein a building for not only the temporal salvation but also the spiritual
salvation of the Church as well. Priesthood quorums everywhere who have rallied to that call,
and have joined together as a group, have bound themselves in love and unity that has blessed
this Church beyond our fondest expectations.
</p><p>
We have come to understand, and it is my firm conviction that the thing most needed in the
Church today is a membership stimulated to action by a fervent conversion to the divinity of
the calling of the brethren who preside as leaders of this Church. We have been a most
blessed people above all other peoples. We have been given the power of the Priesthood. We
have been blessed with a divine leadership and an inspired organization, and a great
pioneering heritage and experience. The Lord will hold us responsible for the blessings that
He has given us, and if the calamities that have been foretold come upon this people, they
will come because we have not done our full duty, and we have not made the most of our
opportunities, nor have we discharged the responsibilities we bear before our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
We have had many evidences of the power manifesting itself from the united team work of
Priesthood quorums. We have witnessed that wherever stake welfare groups have followed the
counsel of the leaders, and have banded together as regional organizations, when there was a
disaster or an emergency as was the case in southern Arizona during a serious flood situation,
we have discovered to our delight that the way was provided by which true brotherhood was
fostered. We have noted how Priesthood quorums have made large contributions, with but
very little effort when they worked unitedly together. We have seen how great amounts of
produce have come from those who saw in their assignment not merely an out and out
contribution, but a chance to work together and to develop together, on a permanent
foundation, some project of which their community was capable.
</p><p>
We have been delighted to observe throughout the Church an attempt to study the basic
reasons for our economic difficulties, and in farming communities we have noticed that
farmers have set their goals to two prime objectives, namely, first to produce all they can on
their own farms, for their own living; and second, to make an all-out war on debt. The
analysis of how that work should be done has been something that I am sure would provide
intelligent and profitable reading for those who are struggling with these problems.
</p><p>
The general Church Welfare committee would have me say to you, that from the standpoint
of organization there is no other way to carry forward this work except by the Ward Welfare
committees properly supervised by the stake Welfare committees. It cant be done without an
intelligent analysis of problems as revealed in the survey that you have been asked to make.
The only ones who are objecting to the carrying forward of that survey, or to the organization
as now set up, are those who have never organized or who have never made the survey.
</p><p>
We are pleased that in the Salt Lake region we have received the report that at least
seventy-five percent of the wards are functioning according to program.
</p><p>
We have been asked today to be patriotic. This Church, as has been read by President McKay,
has a record of accomplishment that is a delight to all of us, and a testimony to the world of
the patriotism of this people. We have been sending our boys into the army, and will continue
to do so. We will buy war bonds and stamps. We will pay inordinate taxes, for the carrying
on of the work for the buying of planes and munitions of war. We will produce and conserve
foodstuffs, that there may be sufficient of the necessities to carry on, as we have been
requested by our government.
</p><p>
But beyond all that, the Latter-day Saints have a responsibility, that may be better understood
when we recall the prophecy of Joseph Smith who declared that "the time would come when
(the destiny and) the Constitution of these United States would hang as it were by a thread,
and that this people, the sons of Zion, would rise up and save it from threatened destruction"
(<i>Journal of Discourses</i>, 7:15).
</p><p>
I want to ask you to consider the meaning of that prophecy, in the light of the declaration of
the prophets of the Book of Mormon times, who declared that this land was a choice land
above all other lands, and would be free from bondage and from captivity, and from all other
nations under heaven, if they will but serve the God of this land, even our Savior, Jesus
Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>).
</p><p>
This is a people whom the Lord has chosen to preach the gospel of righteousness. We talk of
security in this day, and yet we fail to understand that here on this Temple Block we have
standing the holy temple wherein we may find the symbols by which power might be
generated that will save this nation from destruction. Therein may be found the fulness of the
blessings of the Priesthood. Yesterday morning, as we assembled and heard the broadcast
from that place, broadcasting to the world a message, it to me was significant of the prophecy
that from this place "the law shall go forth to the world, and the word of the Lord from
Jerusalem" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/3#3">Isa. 2:3</a>).
The spires on the eastern towers of the temple are to represent the presidency of
the Melchizedek Priesthood; the spires to the west, the presidency of the Aaronic Priesthood;
the gilded figure of the angel Moroni symbolizes the preaching of the gospel to the world.
The gospel must be preached as a witness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>)
under the direction of the holy Priesthood: "Fear
God and give glory to him; for the hour of his judgment is come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/7#7">Rev. 14:7</a>). Therein
lies the responsibility of this Church in sanctifying this people and this nation, that they might
be spared the judgments that otherwise might come upon them, were it not for the preaching
of the humble elders of this Church.
</p><p>
The Prophet Isaiah comforted his struggling people with these words:
</p><p>
Peace, peace to him that is far off, and to him that is near, saith the Lord; and I will heal
him.
</p><p>
But the wicked are like the troubled sea, when it cannot rest, whose waters cast up mire and
dirt.
</p><p>
There is no peace, saith my God, to the wicked
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/57/19-21#19">Isa. 57:19-21</a>).
</p><p>
May we return home and teach our people the way of peace &mdash; peace because they are willing
to live the commandments of the Lord Jesus Christ, I humbly pray, in His name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
