<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Immortality and Eternal Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 65-72</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is indeed a sobering experience, my brethren and sisters, to occupy this position and to look
into the faces of this vast multitude of Latter-day Saints who have come here to worship the
Lord. I humbly trust and pray that the Spirit of the Lord will attend me in what I say this
morning.
</p><p>
I, like the other brethren who have spoken, have a testimony of this great work. I appreciate
the privilege I have of being a member of the Church of Jesus Christ. It is my one great
desire in life to serve the Lord to the best of my ability and always to do what he wants me
to do.
</p><p>
IMMORTALITY OF MAN
</p><p>
Deep in the heart of practically every person who has lived in this world, God has implanted
a hope&mdash;yes, more than that&mdash;even a strong desire, that he will live on after death. The
immortality of man is an unusual concept. The study of ancient religions reveals the fact that
any religion that was popular with its devotees and became a religion of prominence attained
that popularity and prominence as a result of assuring its members that following their sojourn
on this earth they would experience a happy, glorious, and blessed immortality. The same fact
holds true today.
</p><p>
When Father Adam and Eve were upon this earth, through his Only Begotten Son, God
revealed to them the gospel of Jesus Christ; and as one of the most important doctrines in that
gospel he gave them the assurance that if they and their posterity would live in accordance
with all the teachings, doctrine, and ordinances revealed to them that some day they would be
able to come back into his presence. There they would not only experience immortality but
they would also enjoy the great blessing of eternal life.
</p><p>
Throughout the various ages when God has revealed gospel principles to his holy prophets, he
has always given them that one great idea that men will live on throughout the eternities.
</p><p>
A little over a hundred years ago when the gospel plan of salvation was being restored to the
Prophet Joseph Smith in our dispensation, the various Christian denominations held the
concept that men would live on after death, and yet their understanding of the unseen world
was very hazy and vague. They had little, if any, information regarding our pre-mortal life,
and their post-mortal life concepts were very erroneous in many respects. It became necessary,
therefore, for our Father in heaven to reveal again to earth an abundance of knowledge
relative to the immortality of man and point out the pathway to follow in order to gain eternal
life. As a result of God's concern over his children, the Prophet Joseph Smith translated the
Book of Mormon. It contains much doctrine pertaining especially to post-mortal life. He also
received the wonderful revelations recorded in the D&amp;C. Section seventy-six is the greatest
revelation regarding post-mortal life to be found recorded in any book in the world. Joseph
received the Pearl of Great Price in which we find much information on the council of the
gods and our pre-mortal existence.
</p><p>
RESURRECTION OF JESUS CHRIST
</p><p>
We not only have the teachings of the prophets and revelation regarding the immortality of
man, but we have a lot of absolute evidence. The greatest of all evidence that you and I are
immortal, that we will live on after we leave this life, is the fact that Jesus Christ, following
his crucifixion, rose from the grave. He appeared to many people in and around Jerusalem,
thereby establishing the fact that he was immortal and extending the promise to humanity that
as he had risen from the grave so would all men.
</p><p>
We read in the book of Matthew that at the time of the Savior's resurrection the graves of
saints who had lived godly lives while in mortality were opened, and they appeared to many
people in and around Jerusalem (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/27/52-53#52">Matt. 27:52-53</a>).
These saints could have been such characters as Father
Abraham, Isaac, Jacob, Joseph, Noah, and the other holy prophets and their wives who
belonged to "the Church of the Firstborn"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/22#22">D&amp;C 93:22</a>).
</p><p>
Following his resurrection, Jesus Christ also appeared to the Nephites who lived in this land.
On one of those occasions he told them to bring their records to him. As he read that record,
he asked them if Samuel the Lamanite had not prophesied that when Christ was resurrected
the graves of the ancient saints would be opened and that they would appear to these Nephite
people. He was informed that such had been the prophecies and that those prophecies have
been fulfilled. Thereupon he instructed the Nephite historian to write that great prophecy and
its fulfillment in their records (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/23/6-13#6">3 Ne. 23:6-13</a>)
in order that you and I in the latter days might know for a
surety that we would live on after death; that we are immortal beings as well as mortal.
</p><p>
LATTER-DAY TESTIMONY
</p><p>
Over one hundred years ago Jesus Christ appeared to Joseph Smith on several occasions.
Christ was a resurrected, glorified celestialized God when he made those appearances.
Interspersed among those visitations, other beings who had lived upon this earth in ancient
days appeared to the Prophet Joseph. Such persons as the Angel Moroni, Peter, James, and
John, John the Baptist, Moses, Elias, Elijah, Michael, Raphael, and others visited Joseph
Smith. Each appearance, of course, added testimony upon testimony regarding the immortality
of man and the eternal life that the righteous ones who live upon this earth will eventually
attain.
</p><p>
In the doctrines of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints we have a rather
comprehensive understanding of our pre-mortal life. We are taught that you and I are brothers
and sisters; in fact, all the men, women, and children who have ever come into this world are
brothers and sisters, and they were all sons and daughters of God the Eternal Father and our
Eternal Mother in that celestial spirit realm before we came into mortality. We are taught that
we were born into that spirit realm as babies, and that we grew to maturity there, undergoing
the various experiences which were there for us prior to our coming to mortality. Also
through revelation we have learned that the gods held a council preparatory to the peopling of
this earth in which the plans for mortality were discussed and proclaimed.
</p><p>
OUR DESTINATION
</p><p>
Probably of all the human beings who have lived upon this earth, at least a vast majority of
them have asked this question of themselves: "Where do we go when we die?" I would say to
all Latter-day Saints on this occasion that the place to which you and I go when we die will
be determined, to a great extent, upon how we live while we are here&mdash;I mean our ultimate
destination, the goal that we are striving for. We have the true plan of salvation, the gospel of
Jesus Christ, with all the ordinances of the gospel, all the teachings, including the Holy
Priesthood after the Order of the Son of God. All of these things which are necessary to bring
us back into the presence of God and exalt us in celestial glory are ours. We know, therefore,
what will be our destination as members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints if
we will live by every word that comes from the mouth of God. On the other hand, with all
the power, priesthood, ordinances, doctrines, opportunities, and blessings that are ours, we
also know that if we sin sufficiently, we have the power to condemn ourselves to the greatest
of depths, even to cast our souls down to hell. The prophets have proclaimed that where much
is given much is required at our hands.
</p><p>
To the Latter-day Saints death is not such a serious thing. It doesn't make a lot of difference
how long we live in this world. The thing which is of vital importance, however, to you and
me is how we live. Are we prepared to meet the. Eternal Father and his Only Begotten Son?
If death should come upon us any minute, are we prepared to go into the other world and
eventually come into the celestial kingdom of God? That should be your goal and that should
be my goal. We should live such a clean and pure life each day, rendering obedience to all
the principles and ordinances of the gospel to such an extent that we would be ready to die
whenever death comes upon us.
</p><p>
SPIRIT WORLD
</p><p>
Every person who dies will go into a world known as the spirit world. Those who have lived
righteous lives here in mortality will find there a paradise, a heaven, a place of peace, of joy,
of opportunities, of progression. On the other hand, those who have lived wicked lives will
find themselves in the spirit world somewhat as if they were in prison. In fact, the prophets
speak of that world as a prison. We read in Second Peter that at the time the Savior's body
lay in the tomb, his spirit went to the spirit world and opened the doors of the gospel to those
who were drowned in the flood at Noah's time
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/18-20#18">1 Pet. 3:18-20</a>).
Those people had been detained from hearing
the gospel, being in prison during that long period of time of more than two thousand years.
</p><p>
Some people that I have talked to have the concept that when they die that suddenly, their
sins will all be washed away, and they will become white and glorious, pure and clean, in
somewhat of an automatic or miraculous way. Such is not the case. According to the ancient
prophets, especially the Book of Mormon, sustained by modern revelation, when we die, if we
are filthy, we are filthy still
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/16#16">2 Ne. 9:16</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/14#14">Morm. 9:14</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/35,102#35">D&amp;C 88:35,102</a>).
The fact that we die doesn't change us one iota. You and I are
dual personages, possessing a spirit body which dwells in a physical body. Death is the
separation of that spiritual body from the physical body. All of our good deeds, our bad
deeds; the knowledge we have attained; our habits, our evil and good inclinations, are resident
in the spirit. The spirit personage contains the personality, or, in other words, the spirit is the
real individual. Having an understanding of this doctrine, therefore, we know that when we
die we take with us to the other world exactly what we have made of ourselves while living
in mortality. There is only one way that I know whereby you and I can purify ourselves, and
that one way is through repentance. The things that we should repent of here in mortality will
probably be easier to repent of now instead of putting them off until we go to the other world
and have to overcome those handicaps at that time; and so I would say, "today is the day to
prepare to meet God. Permit me to quote the words of an ancient Nephite prophet on that
subject:
</p><p>
For behold, this life is the time for men to prepare to meet God; yea, behold the day of this
life is the day for men, to perform their labors.
</p><p>
. . . if we do not improve our time while in this life, then cometh the night of darkness
wherein there can be no labor performed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/32-33#32">Alma 34:32-33</a>).
</p><p>
A PROBATIONARY STATE
</p><p>
Every person after he or she leaves this life will stay in the spirit world a certain length of
time in order to continue to prepare himself to come into the presence of God. In that spirit
world there is a lot of activity. The gospel of Jesus Christ is being taught to those who have
not received the plan of salvation here in mortality, and especially to those who previously
have not had opportunity. When those people in the spirit world have received the gospel, the
temple work that mortals do for them consummates the work for their acceptance of Jesus
Christ and the plan of salvation there in the spirit world. The spirit world, then, is another
probationary state in order that the sons and daughters of God who will, might prepare
themselves to meet him.
</p><p>
UNIVERSAL RESURRECTION
</p><p>
Following our sojourn in the spirit world comes the resurrection. There will be a universal
resurrection of every man, woman, and child. Just as we all die, so must we all rise from the
grave. Amulek declared:
</p><p>
. . . I say unto you that this mortal body is raised to an immortal body, that is from death,
even from the first death unto life, that they can die no more; their spirits uniting with their
bodies, never to be divided; thus the whole becoming spiritual and immortal, that they can no
more see corruption (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/45#45">Alma 11:45</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus Christ came into the world and died for the sins of the world. He broke the bands of
death and was resurrected, being the first fruits of the resurrection. He set into operation the
law of resurrection and thereby gave as a free gift to every man, woman, and child,
resurrection, or, in other words, immortality. Thus we will all, the wicked as well as the
righteous, enjoy immortality.
</p><p>
THE GREAT JUDGMENT
</p><p>
Following the resurrection comes the great judgment. Every person who has lived and shall
live in this world&mdash;every man, woman, and child&mdash;shall stand before the judgment seat
judgment seat of God to answer for the life he or she lived here in mortality, and also to
answer for the life lived in the spirit world.
</p><p>
Alma, that great Nephite prophet, was preaching this doctrine one day to his people. He
explained to them that every man, woman, and child, "both bond and free . . . both the
wicked and the righteous" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/44#44">Alma 11:44</a>),
would be resurrected and required to stand before the judgment
seat of God. There they would be held accountable for the lives they lived while in mortality,
for every act they committed, yea for every word they spoke, and for every thought that they
thought. You and I are responsible beings, accountable for the things that we think. To quote:
</p><p>
For our words will condemn us, yea, all our works will condemn us; we shall not be found
spotless; and our thoughts will condemn us
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/14#14">Alma 12:14</a>).
</p><p>
Alma also explained on that occasion that God would divide the people into two groups. He
would look upon the members of one group and smile. They are the righteous. He would
proclaim to them that they could enter into his presence. Great would be their joy. And then
he would look upon those who composed the other group, and they should be so ashamed
because of the lives they had lived in mortality that they would cry to the mountains to come
down and hide them from the presence of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/14-15#14">Alma 12:14-15</a>).
But such would not be the case. They would
have to stay in his presence while being judged, and every knee would bow and every tongue
would confess that he was the Christ; that his judgments were true and just
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/27/31#31">Mosiah 27:31</a>). And then they
would hear the voice of God tell them to depart from him because of the sinful lives that they
had lived. This is the group spoken of in the scripture, declaring that they would weep and
wail and gnash their teeth because they had lost the great blessing of celestial and eternal life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/40/13#13">Alma 40:13</a>).
</p><p>
THREE DEGREES OF GLORY
</p><p>
Following the judgment, according to modern revelation, a vast majority of the inhabitants of
this earth will be assigned to one or another of three kingdoms, worlds, or degrees of glory.
These are termed the telestial, the terrestrial, and the celestial. The law by which we are
quickened at the time of resurrection will determine the world to which we shall be assigned.
Let us hear the word of the Lord on that subject:
</p><p>
For notwithstanding they die, they also shall rise again, a spiritual body.
</p><p>
They who are of a celestial spirit shall receive the same body which was a natural body; even
ye shall receive your bodies, and your glory shall be that glory by which your bodies are
quickened.
</p><p>
Ye who are quickened by a portion of the celestial glory shall then receive of the same, even
a fulness.
</p><p>
And they who are quickened by a portion of the terrestrial glory shall then receive of the
same, even a fulness.
</p><p>
And also they who are quickened by a portion of the telestial glory shall then receive of the
same, even a fulness.
</p><p>
And they who remain shall also be quickened; nevertheless, they shall return again to their
own place, to enjoy that which they are willing to receive, because they were not willing to
enjoy that which they might have received
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/27-32#27">D&amp;C 88:27-32</a>).
</p><p>
CELESTIAL GLORY
</p><p>
To the Latter-day Saints our interests lie in the celestial glory. In fact, we don't have much
interest in the other two degrees because we are assured through revelation that those who go
to the celestial degree of glory and receive exaltation are members of the Church of the
Firstborn (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/54,94#54">D&amp;C 76:54,94</a>)
who have lived by every word that has come from the mouth of God, being humble,
and faithful in all of their activities here in life. We are heirs, therefore, of celestial glory. The
gateway into celestial glory is faith, repentance, baptism, and confirmation; and then, of
course, as the Saints enter the kingdom of God by compliance with the foregoing
requirements, they make their calling and election sure by rendering obedience to all the
ordinances and doctrines of the gospel of Jesus Christ from day to day throughout the entire
course of this mortal life. These are they who shall dwell in the presence of God.
</p><p>
EXALTATION
</p><p>
In the celestial degree of glory there are three kingdoms or three degrees. The highest of these
constitutes those who receive exaltation or eternal life. They are they who live the law of the
priesthood or the new and everlasting covenant of marriage, known as celestial marriage. The
Latter-day Saints, as well as the people throughout the various ages of the world who have
belonged to the true Church of Jesus Christ, who have been married by the power of the
priesthood and have obeyed all the priesthood covenants that they have entered into, having
lived in accordance with all the teachings of the gospel, these are they who shall be exalted in
the celestial realm. The Lord has given his law on this doctrine as follows:
</p><p>
. . . verily I say unto you, if a man marry a wife by my word, which is my law, and by the
new and everlasting covenant, and it is sealed unto them by the Holy Spirit of promise, by
him who is anointed, unto whom I have appointed this power and the keys of this priesthood;
[and if they commit no sin to break that seal]; . . . they shall pass by the angels and the gods,
which are set there, to their exaltation and glory in all things, as hath been sealed upon their
heads, which glory shall be a fulness and a continuation of the seeds forever and ever.
</p><p>
Then shall they be gods
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/19-20#19">D&amp;C 132:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith explained that this continuation of "the seeds" forever and ever,
meant the power of procreation; in other words, the power to beget spirit children on the same
principle as we were born to our Heavenly Parents, God the Eternal Father and our Eternal
Mother. Therefore, a man cannot receive the highest exaltation without a woman, his wife,
nor can a woman be exalted without her husband
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/11/11#11">1 Cor. 11:11</a>).
That is the fulness of the gospel of Jesus
Christ, the plan of salvation. Eternal life is the greatest gift that God has in store for those
who love him and keep his commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>),
and you and I know how it can be attained.
</p><p>
In the celestial degree of glory there are two other divisions. They are occupied by angels of
God. These angels are the ones who did not abide by the law of celestial marriage; however;
they accepted Christ and lived good lives, but they did not accept all the gospel ordinances.
This is the word of the Lord on that subject:
</p><p>
For these angels did not abide my law; therefore, they cannot be enlarged, but remain
separately and singly, without exaltation, in their saved condition, to all eternity; and from
henceforth are not gods, but are angels of God forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/17#17">D&amp;C 132:17</a>).
</p><p>
ETERNAL LIFE
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters, where do we go when we die? As Latter-day Saints we hope someday
to go not only to the celestial degree of glory but also to receive exaltation in his
kingdom, i.e., to receive eternal life. If we accept all the ordinances of the gospel of Jesus
Christ and obey all of the teachings of the gospel; if we abide by the law of celestial
marriage; if we pay our tithes and offerings to the Lord; if we are clean and pure in thought
and habit, thereby keeping our bodies as temples of God, clean and pure as he wants us to do;
if we live virtuously and in every way serve him, then at the great judgment day we will hear
the voice of God say to us, words to this effect: "Well done, my beloved servants. You were
faithful in the few, small things that I gave you to do in mortality, you may, therefore, now
come into my presence." And to continue to paraphrase the D&amp;C, "Then shall they pass by
the angels and gods who are stationed there to their exaltation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/19#19">D&amp;C 132:19</a>), and they shall become priests
and kings to the Most High God. They shall become as he is." In other words, they shall have
eternal life. Then shall the oath and covenant of the priesthood be brought into effect which
you and I have made, each of us who holds the Melchizedek Priesthood. All that God has will
be ours (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>).
He will share with us.
</p><p>
May this be the lot of the Latter-day Saints, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
