<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Debt&mdash;a Great Hazard</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Clifford E. Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Clifford E. Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1956, pp. 115-117</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Someone suggested in his opening prayer that this had been  the most outstanding conference
he had ever attended.  I think we all feel that way as we come to the end of this very
impressive service that has now been held for these three days.  What I say this afternoon, my
brethren and sisters, I hope will not in any way detract from the sweetness of spirit that we all
feel.
</p><p>
I desire to make a few comments, and they could be enlarged upon if time would permit,
prompted by the inspired address of President McKay in the opening session of this
conference in which he gave us a great ideal, an ideal of what a home and
our lives ought to be. I do not know how you felt about it, but after President McKay had
finished, I felt in my heart that I would from now on like to be just a little kinder and a little
more considerate, less impatient, less impulsive.  I would like to be able to offer counsel, and
I would like to be worthy to offer that counsel to our boys and girls, our youth.
</p><p>
I would like them to feel as we felt that in a home of a Latter-day Saint may be found the
finest concepts of life, a pattern of life, that when our young people take upon themselves the
responsibilities of a home, they may lay such a foundation that will ultimately give them the
same type of home as President McKay so impressively portrayed to us.
</p><p>
As our leader spoke, he spoke authoritatively.  We had that demonstrated Saturday in the
impressive address of Brother Thomas E. McKay, my colleague.  I have been in his home; I
know the sweetness of spirit there.  And he reflected yesterday in his address those high
ideals and great virtues as he told of the home life from which he came.  We knew again of
the power of example that we have had demonstrated to us by these two of our beloved
brethren.
</p><p>
I have a little concern for our young people.  Last night I read some figures in the <i>Deseret News</i>.
I want to call attention to these figures and some of the comments of the writer of the
editorial.  I quote from the editorial entitled "Lengthening Debt's Shadow": 
</p><p>
"Economists and economizers&mdash;home, business and government&mdash;have reason to raise an
eyebrow over the fact that the nation has posted a record increase of $660 million debt for
installment buying of goods other than autos since a year ago.
</p><p>
"For types of goods, Americans are now in debt $6 1/4 billions.
</p><p>
"This is not all they owe, either. Americans have also increased their pay-by-the month
personal loans to 5 1/2 billions.  This is a gain of $733 millions, or 15% in the space of 12
months."
</p><p>
This does not include the purchasing of homes.  This just refers to consumer debts.
</p><p>
The danger there, my brethren and sisters, as I see it, lies in our young people undertaking
obligations they cannot meet.  It has always seemed to me that a young man was justified in
going in debt for a home, provided that obligation did not exceed his ability to pay.  A young
man should not feel that when just starting out in life he should have as good a home as his
father.  His father probably has struggled for many years to get his home.  But a young man
and woman starting out should take into consideration the fact that his parents had little to
start with and that they are starting from the beginning, and theirs should be a humble home. 
The tendency today, however, is to build and buy extravagantly, frequently beyond the ability
to pay.
</p><p>
And that is not the only difficulty. In addition to the obligations incident to a home are the
obligations incident to this consumer buying. We think we must have all of the gadgets, all of the
conveniences that are advertised.  They are desirable to have.  They are convenient. No one
would refuse a mother an electric washer, an electric dryer, a freezer, if we could afford them.
No one would refuse his children television or a radio or a good car, if he could afford them. 
But brethren and sisters, if we are going to maintain the high standard, the spiritual standard
of our homes, we must safeguard ourselves and our children against obligations that will bring
sorrow and friction into the home and that will upset the high standards that we want to
preserve for them.
</p><p>
This is the reason that I mention these things, and much more could be said about them. I
have seen so many cases of sorrow and suffering incident to too much debt.  It has been my
experience now for over forty years to be connected with financing.  I have seen young
couples start out happily in life and finally bring to themselves distress, not only financially,
but also spiritually and emotionally, all because their debts had reached a point where they
could not pay them. They became upset, and friction and quarreling ensued, which brought
about a condition in the home that is in contravention to the spirit and the ideals taught us in
this conference.
</p><p>
I hope you will not consider it presumptuous on my part if I offer a word of caution to our
young people against these practices.  We should teach our boys and girls to
have honor above everything else, honor in paying their debts.
</p><p>
Someone in this conference spoke of bonds, not government bonds, but a bond of integrity
and honor. We need to teach that to our children and to ourselves.  Somewhere I read of an
old Chinese practice.  If a young man wanted to borrow money (I do not know how it is
now) but in the days of the older civilization, if a Chinese boy wished to borrow money, he
would go to the banker and tell him, "I am a son of Lu Sing.  I would like to borrow a
thousand dollars." And the banker, knowing the integrity of Lu Sing, would lend the boy the
thousand dollars without a scratch of a pen.  There was nothing but a verbal contract because
the banker knew of the integrity of the family, the honor of the family, and he knew that the
family would not let him down, even if the boy should fail, and rarely did the boy fail.  It is
a striking example of the value of one's word, and we can well adopt it in our lives&mdash;not
necessarily the practice of it, but the intrinsic value of honor and integrity that our word is as
good as our bond.
</p><p>
Young people, do not go into debt beyond your ability to pay.  Let us as parents help them to
avoid these pitfalls.
</p><p>
Now, one other thought. As President McKay spoke of the ideal home and the love of home,
I thought of an ideal home back in 1820, of a boy who came into that home one spring
morning to tell his father and mother of a great revelation, and the father and mother believed
the boy. His brother Hyrum believed him, and his brother Alvin. Hyrum was twenty, six years
older than the Prophet, and Alvin was eight years older, he being over twenty-two.
</p><p>
It is significant, my brethren and sister&mdash;a fourteen-year-old boy telling his father and mother
of the greatest revelation of all time since the birth of the Savior and having parents and
brothers and sisters believe him.  From that time on there was loyalty and devotion in that
home.  The boy was to instruct his father, not in unkindness but in love, because his father
believed in him, his mother believed in him. If there had been any element of fraud, if the
boy had been inclined to tell an untruth, the parents would have known it; his brothers would
have detected it, and the mother, above all others, would have known it.  She would not have
talked about it, but she would have known it, keeping the boy's weakness wrapped up in her
own soul.  Mothers generally protect their children regardless of their weaknesses.
</p><p>
I repeat, they believed in their boy, and to me that has always been an example of a perfect
home, an ideal home.  Confidence, faith, love and devotion were to be exemplified throughout
the life of the boy.  Hyrum was to give his life as a witness of his confidence in his younger
brother and the divinity of his calling. His father, too, was to suffer persecution that was to
cause an early death.
</p><p>
You will recall the night the Angel Moroni appeared to Joseph Smith and revealed to him the
sacred record from which the Book of Mormon was to be translated.  In the morning, Joseph,
somewhat weary, having been awake most of the night, went to the field to assist his father.
"You look weary, my boy, go back to the house and rest." As he reached the edge of the
field, the Angel again appeared to Joseph and instructed him to tell his father.  He returned to
his father in the field and rehearsed the whole matter to him. His father replied to him, "It
was of God. Do as commanded by the messenger"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/48-50#48">JS&mdash;H 1:48-50</a>).
</p><p>
And there was no failure, and I submit to you, my brethren and sisters, that here we have an
example of a perfect trust between father and son, an example of what should be in an ideal
home. That home was a humble one, probably with candlelights, certainly no modern
conveniences, but a home in which abounded love, trust, confidence, and faith, and from that
faith and that home was to come the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
I bear you my witness in the name of Jesus.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
