<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Fulfilment of Prophecy</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 58-62</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
With my dear wife and missionary companion, we are most grateful for the privilege of being
invited to return at this conference time to be refortified with the spirit and the strength of
these wonderful gatherings. I want to say to the First Presidency of the Church that the
inspiration of their direction that has come to us during the past nine months has been in large
measure the reason for the expanding of the gospel of Jesus Christ among the people of
Europe. We have been in almost constant contact by telephone, by letter, and by other means,
with the inspiration and direction of the First Presidency of the Church. In standing here this
afternoon, I do so for and in behalf of the thirteen mission presidents who are now laboring in
Europe, and I bring to this conference their greetings, as well as to the parents of their
missionaries, and to all who have served in these many missions of Europe.
</p><p>
These mission leaders are President and Sister T. Bowring Woodbury of the British Mission;
President and Sister Levi B. Thorup of the Danish Mission; President and Sister John D.
Warner of the Finnish Mission; President and Sister Edgar B. Brossard of the French Mission;
President and Sister J. Henry Volker of the Netherlands Mission; President and Sister Ray
Engebretsen of the Norwegian Mission; President and Sister Bernard P. Brockbank of the
North British Mission; President and Sister Percy K. Fetzer of the North German Mission;
President and Sister A. Gideon Omer of the Swedish Mission; President and Sister William S.
Erekson of the Swiss Mission; and the new mission recently organized, President and Sister
W. Whitney Smith of the Austrian Mission; President and Sister T. Quentin Cannon of the
South German Mission; and President and Sister Stephen C. Richards of the West German
Mission. And with them also I bring the greetings of 1700 missionaries who are now laboring
in Europe. I am happy to report that I have had the opportunity during these past months to
look into their faces, to feel their spirit, and once again to say within my heart and to
proclaim aloud that I have confidence in the youth of this Church.
</p><p>
I am grateful to say that there is a unification in the programs of our missionary work in
Europe. Each and every mission is pursuing the work of proselyting in the same manner, and
the faith and the testimony of the missionaries who are carrying the gospel to the peoples of
these ancient lands are in evidence. Presaged by the visits made to Europe by President
McKay at the time of the temple dedications, followed by other visits by members of the
Quorum of the Twelve and by President Moyle, the visit by Elder Harold B. Lee at the time
of the organization of the Manchester Stake&mdash;these have presaged an awakening among the
people of these ancient lands.
</p><p>
In August 1959 all of the European missions combined were responsible for ten percent of the
converts of that month. In the month of August of this year, the European missions were
responsible for thirty-five percent of the converts of the Church for that month, and I only
re-echo the faith and the testimony of the mission presidents who are there when I say that we
haven't even scratched the surface. God is touching the hearts of the people, they are
listening, and are receiving answers to their desires and their prayers. I only wish that I had
the time to tell of the many personal cases of conversion that have come to these thousands of
people in the past year, and to reassure you, my brethren and sisters, that these people are
converted to the gospel of Jesus Christ. They have answered a call that has come to them
under the power and the influence of the Spirit of God. I have always felt in my heart that
when the Holy Ghost bears record to anyone that he ought to do something about that, and
we are encouraging our missionaries in all of these lands to be alert to the reaction of the
power of the Spirit in the minds and the hearts of these people, and in that very moment to
persuade, to encourage, to teach, to testify, and to challenge that they may be willing to
accept the gospel message that has come to them.
</p><p>
I would be insensible to what is taking place in these ancient lands if I did
not say that we are witnessing the fulfilling of a prophecy&mdash;a prophecy made by
President McKay at the time I was called to go into the lands of Europe, wherein he stated to
me that the time had come for the gospel of Jesus Christ to be expanded in these lands. The
people are ready for the gospel, and we are finding them responding to the efforts of the
missionaries as they bear record by the power of faith and testimony of the truths of the
gospel unto those with whom they make this contact.
</p><p>
One of the instructions that the First Presidency gave to me was to go into all of the lands of
Europe, to go into every mission, and I think it was President Moyle who said to me that I
might well go to the French Mission first. We heeded this counsel, and with my good wife I
went into the land of France and in association with President and Sister Brossard, spent some
three weeks there last February&mdash;a land where ninety-two percent of the population belong to
the Catholic Church. We found our splendid missionaries responsive to motivation and a new
method of contacting the people and teaching them by the power of the Spirit and testimony.
</p><p>
We labored in that land, and under the inspiration of God the hearts of the missionaries were
touched, and I shall never forget a meeting held in Brussels at the close of the tour of that
mission with the missionary leaders, who went from that meeting with such faith that it
engendered itself into the hearts of every one of the missionaries. We said to them, "We want
you to go back to the people you have been meeting with, and where they have not listened
to you before, to bear your testimony to them, and to do it with all the strength and the power
that you have." From that day to this in that mission the Lord has awakened in the hearts of
many hundreds the desire to receive the gospel of Jesus Christ. For here in a land rich with
great cathedrals have come over 600 converts to the Church already this year, to meet in
rented halls, but who now are looking forward to the time when they can associate with their
brethren and sisters in the erecting of beautiful chapels to better serve the needs of old and
new members alike. As of today there is not a single LDS
chapel in all of France, and anyone who would question the faith of these people who have
come into the Church would need only to be there and see the transition that they have made
from cathedrals of worship to halls on second and third floors, and who now are laboring as
stated with our other Saints to help in the erection of our own chapels. This has been true in
all of the missions of Europe.
</p><p>
I think one of the greatest testimonies that has come to me in these past months has been the
responsiveness of the local members of the Church in Europe, where we have nearly 60,000.
We transferred Church leadership to these local members. While in February of this year there
were nearly 600 of our full time missionaries engaged in branch, district, and auxiliary
activity, today there are fewer than a hundred, and it is the avowed determination of these
wonderful mission presidents to see to it that local leaders be called in these also. This
accomplished two things: It has relieved the missionaries that they can do more proselyting,
and it has strengthened the branches of the Church in these countries.
</p><p>
Let me tell you of one example which is typical. In the tour of the French Mission, when we
visited the city of Nice, we had several missionaries there all engaged in branch work. One
was the branch president, one was a counselor, another a superintendent of Sunday School, all
were engaged. The thought had been that local brethren were not worthy or capable, but we
sought out and called the best man we had. That afternoon we interviewed four or five of the
local elders, and with Brother Brossard selected the one to be president of the branch. We
called in his wife and asked her to support him. That night we set him apart and others of the
local brethren into other positions thus relieving missionaries, and in the very next month
these missionaries baptized twenty-one people, two of whom were doctors, one an attorney,
and the other a schoolteacher.
</p><p>
The Nice Branch today is strong, and since that meeting there have been approximately sixty
people come into the Church in that one branch, and they are attending their meetings.
</p><p>
I stood on the street at Trondheim in Norway where Elder John A. Widtsoe lived and
played as a boy, and who later said that the day would come when many of the people of that
land would accept the gospel, and we are witnessing the continuing of this prophecy in that
land. We are seeing again the surge of conversions in Great Britain&mdash;a land that has seen
more than 160,000 converts to the Church. Why would it be incredible that under the
inspiration of God there could be more of these wonderful people accept the gospel and come
into the Church?
</p><p>
And in all of the lands of Europe there have been men and women of great strength and
character that have added to the stability of this Church, and how grateful now to be there in
the midst of this new time of awakening that will see more than ten thousand converts come
into the Church in these lands this year; and in consultation with my brethren, these mission
presidents, we feel that there is no end to where we can go under the impetus of the power of
God as he reaches and touches the hearts of the people.
</p><p>
These new converts are telling their neighbors about the gospel. They are letting their friends
know about it. Let me tell you of one typical case. When I was in Denmark, I shook hands
with a good sister by the name of Dagmar Petersen, who had been baptized a month
previously. She had heard the gospel, but she said, "I am too old. All of my family would
turn against me. I know Joseph Smith is a Prophet of God, but I do not think I'd better take
the step."
</p><p>
But thank the Lord for a missionary who had the courage to go to her one day when there
was a baptismal service and say to her, "Sister Petersen, today is the day of your baptism. The
font is filled. Will you come with me?" She hesitated for a moment, then went with the
missionaries, walking the six or seven blocks to our beautiful little chapel and was there
baptized.
</p><p>
In this conference meeting she sat with one neighbor on one side and two neighbors on the
other side of her. The one on the one side already had been baptized, and the other two were
to be baptized the following Saturday, and she said, "I will never be happy until all my
friends and all my neighbors have been baptized," and this wonderful soul left the chapel and
then came back. She said, after entering the chapel again, "I cannot leave, the spirit is so great
in this building. I must shake hands again," and then she went off down the street with her
friends.
</p><p>
Every Latter-day Saint desires to be a missionary. I think that this is in the heart of almost
every member; but why is it, my brethren and my sisters, that we are so afraid to bear our
testimonies to our neighbors? I think it was the Apostle Paul who said this:
</p><p>
"For though I preach the gospel, I have nothing to glory of: for necessity is laid upon me;
yea, woe is unto me, if I preach not the gospel!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/9/16#16">1 Cor. 9:16</a>).
</p><p>
Then another great prophet of Israel has said this: "So thou, O son of man, I have set thee a
watchman unto the house of Israel; therefore thou shalt hear the word at my mouth, and warn
them from me.
</p><p>
"When I say unto the wicked . . . thou shalt surely die; and if thou dost not speak to warn the
wicked from his way, that wicked man shall die in his iniquity; but his blood will I require at
thy hand.
</p><p>
"Nevertheless, if thou warn the wicked of his way to turn from it; if he do not turn from his
way, he shall die in his iniquity; but thou hast delivered thy soul"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/33/7-9#7">Ezek. 33:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
I have often said to the Latter-day Saints, "If you cannot be a missionary, then at least be a
Latter-day Saint, that you will not stand in the way by your manner of living, of those who
will want to come into the Church."
</p><p>
Now there are many wonderful things going on in Europe. Under the inspiration of the Lord
we have called thirty-four translators in the various countries. I wish I could tell you the story
of each one, like Sister Charrier down in a little village in France. She heard the gospel,
accepted it. We learned that she had a class of pupils whom she was teaching English. Her
preparations have enabled her to help us with the translations into the French language. And
she now is working diligently.
</p><p>
I am thinking of Immo Luschin Ebengreuth of Graz, Austria, a man who
heard the gospel message from two missionaries, and said to them before they got into a
lengthy discussion on the gospel, "I would ask you only five questions before you go further."
He was a confirmed member of the Catholic Church, and these are his questions:
</p><p>
"1. Does this Church believe in marriage for all eternity?<br />
"2. Does this Church believe in the punishment for infants who are not baptized?<br />
"3. Do, in this Church, the rich and the poor have equal opportunity?<br />
"4. In this Church, do you baptize by immersion for the remission of sin?<br />
"5. In this Church do you lay on hands for the receiving of the Holy Ghost?"
</p><p>
This man had never met the missionaries before, and we inquired as to where he got such
questions. His answer was, "We have not been satisfied with our faith. My wife and I
determined that through prayer and the desire to know that we would find out the true
Church." The missionaries said, "Why, these are our teachings," and thus Brother Ebengreuth
was baptized with his wife. This brother is a skilled interpreter. He speaks English, I am
confident, better than I do, and he now will become a translator for the Church of the German
language.
</p><p>
This has been how the Lord has opened the way for us, so that by the end of this year nearly
one hundred textbooks and manuals combined in six languages will have been translated. This
has been a tremendous task and could not have been done without the help of the Lord.
</p><p>
There is a wide program of micro-filming going on in Europe. This is better known by others
than myself, although I have kept an eye on it, and have had some indirect connection with it.
I have seen the advantages to this work from heeding the counsel of the brethren. They
instructed me to meet the ambassadors, the leaders of nations, and this has been my purpose,
and in each and every country have I taken the time to meet these men when I could.
</p><p>
In Norway when the head bishop of the state church carried a personal campaign to the press
and elsewhere to prevent us from microfilming in that land, and succeeded also in getting it
before the Parliament and when it appeared as though we might lose these privileges, the
Minister of Education of the country of Norway, who is also the Minister of Religious
Instruction, rose to his feet and said, "You cannot stop the Mormon people from doing this
work." He said, "I have been to Salt Lake City. I have met these people. I know what they do
with these films," and he made a defense for us largely because of the association that had
been had with him here and in the land of Norway, and even the head bishop of the state
church had to acknowledge defeat in his effort to prevent us from continuing with this work.
</p><p>
And so the Lord is watching over the things that are being done. I am most grateful, my
brethren and sisters, to report to you that these wonderful members in the lands of Europe are
substantially true to the gospel of Jesus Christ. I have witnessed in their youth conferences
their adherence to our Church customs and patterns and how they revere the ideals and the
standards which have been set for them by our general youth organizations. I have been near
to their Relief Society meetings and have seen how the influence of our Relief Society
organization finds its way into their thinking, and they have a desire to do the will of the
Lord. I do not know to what extent we may go in these lands when they have the
instrumentation and the facility of proper buildings which they do not have now.
</p><p>
I want to say to President McKay and President Clark and President Moyle and the brethren
how grateful these people are for the coming building program that will see many chapels go
up in places where they are so sorely needed to further the Church program and which also
will provide greater tools of missionary work to carry on this great responsibility given to us
as a Church to proclaim the gospel of Jesus Christ unto the people.
</p><p>
Let me tell you just briefly of my two visits behind the Iron Curtain to be in attendance with
the Saints at Leipzig where other of our brethren have been. These members live under
hardened conditions. I said to one brother, "How do you stand it here?" He said, "We
learn to follow the paths and the trails that are laid out for us. We
learn to do what we are told, then we have no difficulty. Our children are picked up in the
morning by bus at 8 a.m. and are delivered home at night. We have no control over their
schooling nor over what is taught them: referred to by Brother Buehner in the morning
session. I was greatly moved to hear the testimonies of our members there.
</p><p>
One of the district presidents testified what to me is the greatest testimony I have heard in
Europe: Under such conditions "no man," said he, "can tell me how to worship God in my
own heart. Although there are nearly five thousand members in some thirty-nine branches we
keep in contact with them as much as we can." I thought as we enjoyed this wonderful
presentation of music here today, that but a few weeks ago, I listened to a combined chorus of
the Leipzig and Dresden districts sing, "Shall the Youth of Zion Falter." The look on the faces
of these young people was most stirring. All that day in our priesthood and leadership
meetings, we gave encouragement to safeguard to the fullest extent possible our youth to
cause them to remain true to the gospel because there are inroads being made.
</p><p>
How grateful Sister Dyer and I have been to be associated with these people and with our
wonderful missionaries, who with clear faces are bearing their testimonies to the peoples of
Europe, and who are receiving these wonderful responses, and I know with all my heart that
all this is but the fulfilment of prophecy.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony in all humility that this is the work of God. I have seen it in the
lives of people. I have witnessed it as it causes men and women to change their lives, I have
seen it become a motivating force for good, and I bear record that Jesus Christ is the Son of
God, the Redeemer of the world, the Mediator&mdash;not as it is preached by these predominant
countries of the lands of Europe. And do you know that this is the message we declare when
we go to the doors of the people the first time? It is through the testimony of our missionaries
that the veneer of false concepts and the antiquities of these people are being laid aside for
the acceptance of the gospel. It is more powerful than all other things that we do in our
missionary work as we look into their faces and bear record that God has raised up a prophet,
and they are listening to this message.
</p><p>
We had a family of seven visited recently by the missionaries where the woman was about to
close the door when the elder said, "I can see you are going to close the door. I am very
sorry. We have such a wonderful message," and we have told them, "Before any door is
closed, you bear your testimony." He said, "Before you close that door I want to bear my
testimony to you of these brief things we have stated today,"  and he bore his testimony. The
door closed, and the missionaries started for their home to their room, and it was raining.
They had reached about a half a block when they heard a voice, it was the young boy of the
home, fourteen-years-old, who said, "Dad wants you to come back," and they went back and
the father said, "I listened to your message at the door on the other side as you spoke to my
wife, and I did not think much of it until that young man bore his testimony, and then
something came over me that I have never experienced before, and now I have to know what
this is."
</p><p>
I had the privilege of shaking hands with this family of seven and hearing them testify that
God had made known to them that these things are true. This is the reason why so many are
accepting the gospel in the lands of Europe. We are proclaiming the message by testimony
and through the Spirit.
</p><p>
I ask the blessings of our Heavenly Father upon the great missionary work and upon our
beloved brethren who lead us, without whose inspiration and direction we could not go
forward in these lands and throughout the world, I pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
