<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Render Unto Caesar..."</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1955, pp. 77-79</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I assure you at the outset that I will keep my eyes on the clock.  I
know my brethren will also keep their eyes on the clock.  I ask you for an interest in your
faith and prayers.  There is so much to say on an occasion like this, and there are so many to
say it that time becomes very precious.
</p><p>
A week ago I stood before a group of high school students in one of the stakes not far from
here. I urged them on that occasion to accept as a project the reading of the Gospel according
to Matthew in order to familiarize themselves with the life of Jesus Christ.  I recall years ago
reading about Lew Wallace who wrote the great story, Ben Hur. It appears that while he was
writing this book, he was visited by a certain well-known and gifted agnostic. The agnostic
encouraged him to write the book. "But," said he, "do not emphasize the divinity of Jesus
Christ.  Treat this character as you would any other character in history." But Lew Wallace
had studiously read the Gospels and formed his opinions of the Master on the record left by
Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John.
</p><p>
We have heard many things during this conference, and during this Easter time, about Jesus,
the Christ.  His perfect life has been extolled.  His teachings have been expounded.  His
resurrection has been explained in the light of modern and ancient scriptures, and his divine
mission has been emphasized by everyone who has spoken from this stand during the
conference.
</p><p>
Someone has said, "Jesus is still loved, but he is also hated, among men." There are those
who would crucify him the second time, this time in the hearts of men.  Yet there is no
explanation offered for his marvelous life and his perfect record except the one he himself
gave. "I came forth from the father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/28#28">John 16:28</a>),
and, "If ye have seen me ye have seen the father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/9#9">John 14:9</a>). In his
prayer of intercession for his Twelve Apostles, he said: "This is life eternal&mdash;that they might
know thee, the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou has sent"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
In the same prayer he said, "Glorify thou me with the glory which I had with thee before the
world was" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/5#5">John 17:5</a>).
He left no room for equivocation and argument on the question of his divinity
and his Sonship, and I am happy today as I stand here, that I belong to a Church which
accepts that teaching as very fundamental.
</p><p>
It was William Jennings who stated in his famous lecture called, The Prince of
Peace, "It is easier to believe him divine than to explain in any other way what he said and
did and was." There are marks of distinction which set him apart from all others who have
lived upon the earth.  He was the master of every situation which confronted him.  He
answered all questions put to him where an answer would enlighten the questioner.
</p><p>
Albert J. Beveridge, a Senator from Indiana, stated many years ago: "The Son of Mary is the
prince of public speakers." He was right, for the Sermon on the Mount is the greatest sermon
ever preached.  It has endured nineteen centuries of criticism.  It has survived the apostasy,
the Dark Ages, the Renaissance, and the Reformation, and its powerful message is still
reverberating through the world.  It will never die.
</p><p>
Yesterday I know you were touched, as I was, when our great choir sang "The Lord's
Prayer." "The Lord's Prayer," says someone, "is perfect in its diction. It is comprehensive in
its scope." It covers the essential phases of human existence.  His stories and parables will
live forever.  "The story of the Prodigal Son," said Charles Dickens, "is the most beautiful
story ever told."
</p><p>
There is another one like unto it.  It is the story of the Good Samaritan, and I think of one
more with which you are very familiar.  It begins, "A sower went out to sow"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/8/5#5">Luke 8:5</a>).
What a lovely statement that is!  All of these stories called parables charm and captivate the
reader.  They are timely today, as fresh as they were nineteen hundred years ago when they
were given. They stir the heart to better and nobler living.  They are a force for righteousness
in the world.
</p><p>
And there is another thing which I called to the attention of the young students a week ago,
when I said, "Jesus is the most compelling personality in human history." He spoke two words
to his followers: "Follow me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/8/22#22">Matt. 8:22</a>),
and strong men gave up their fishing nets and
followed him even to death.
</p><p>
Pilate was uneasy and disturbed before him.  When you enter the great Salt Lake Temple, and
as you go into the Assembly Room, I wish you would do as I have frequently
done&mdash;examine that magnificent painting of the Lord Jesus standing before Pontius Pilate&mdash;Jesus so
calm and unruffled; Pilate so deeply disturbed.  The contrast is impressive.
</p><p>
I recall another incident.  It happened in the Garden of Gethsemane when the Roman soldiers
came to arrest the Master.  As they entered, Jesus said to these hard-faced men, "Whom seek
ye?" They answered, "Jesus of Nazareth." "I am he," replied Jesus, and those men, in silent
tribute, "went backward and fell to the ground." He asked again "Whom seek ye?" They
answered, "Jesus of Nazareth." "I am he," responded the Lord, and then, characteristic of his
great soul, he said, "If therefore ye seek me, let these go their way," referring, of course, to his
disciples (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/4-8#4">John 18:4-8</a>).
</p><p>
The writer of that circumstance gives one more sentence, which reads, "And Judas stood with
them" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/18/5#5">John 18:5</a>).
I wonder what the thoughts of Judas were as he stood there
witnessing the courage and love of Jesus, whom he had already betrayed.  The moral side of
Christ's character has no parallel. In it we find absolute perfection.  No flaw, no blemish, no
weakness is discovered.  He is without sin. He was as great as the gospel he preached. He met
every situation perfectly.  He said and did the right thing at the right moment.
</p><p>
I am reminded of the spies who were sent out by the chief priests to trip and trap him if they
could.  "Is it lawful to pay tribute to Caesar?" they asked. Jesus asked for a coin.  They
produced what happened to be a tax coin with which the Jews paid taxes to the Roman
government.  "Whose image is on the coin?" asked Jesus.  "It is the image of Caesar." Then
said the Lord, "Render unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's, and unto God the things
which are God's" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/17-21#17">Matt. 22:17-21</a>).
I submit that it was the best answer that could
possibly be given under the circumstances.  Not only that, it was a great sermon, although
very brief, on the matter of honesty.
</p><p>
May we worship the Lord and Master in spirit and in truth.  May each of us have the
conviction that he is the Redeemer of the world and the promised Messiah, and may we join
hands in carrying forward his work and in explaining the restored gospel which has come to
earth in these, the last days, through the instrumentality of Joseph Smith, the Prophet, I pray
most humbly in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
