<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Our Glorious Destiny</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Charles A. Callis</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Charles A. Callis, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 80-83</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
As I witnessed that impressive vote sustaining the General Authorities of the Church, a Latin
phrase came to my mind which runs as follows: "The voice of the people is the voice of
God." While this does not hold strictly true in all cases, yet yesterday morning the voice of
God was heard in this great tabernacle. It is a wonderful thing, a blessing of comfort that we
have the more sure word of prophecy in this Church. In fact this Church is the treasure house
of all the gifts of God, and gives the knowledge that will make men eligible for entrance into
the celestial kingdom of God. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is a universal
Church; it is not only a worldwide Church, but it is as wide as eternity.
</p><p>
THE DAWNING OF A NEW ERA
</p><p>
The prophet Isaiah&mdash;and of this prophet, Jesus said that his words were
great (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/23/1#1">3 Ne. 23:1</a>)&mdash;had
a vision so glorious and splendid that in heavenly rapture he exclaimed:
</p><p>
Who hath heard such a thing? who hath seen such things? Shall the earth be made to bring
forth in one day? or shall a nation be born at once?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/66/8#8">Isa. 66:8</a>).
</p><p>
We are on the threshold of remarkable events. If God, centuries ago, could incline the hearts
of the people to seek him so that they had no disposition to do evil
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/5/2#2">Mosiah 5:2</a>), why cannot he do that
today? The inhabitants of the earth are his children, and God loves mercy more than
judgment. I believe that we are entering upon an era of conversion so great that the human
mind cannot conceive its magnitude. We are told in holy writ that every knee must bow and
every tongue confess that Jesus is the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/10-11#10">Philip. 2:10-11</a>).
With all my heart I believe that divine prediction
will come true, for Jesus Christ is the King of kings and the Lord of lords
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/16#16">Rev. 19:16</a>).
</p><p>
THE APPEARANCE OF JESUS TO THE JEWS
</p><p>
Orson Pratt and Charles W. Penrose declared that prior to the glorious coming of the Son of
God, the Jews are going to be beleaguered by the nations who threaten the very existence of
the Jewish race. Then, according to Zechariah, down through the gates of heaven shall come
the Lord Jesus Christ, the Captain and King for whom the Jews have wept and prayed so
long, and he shall set his feet upon the Mount of Olives, and the Mount shall cleave asunder,
and the Jews shall escape destruction (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/14/4-5#4">Zech. 14:4-5</a>).
The God of heaven shall then, with the armies of
heaven, have judgment upon the wicked, and the wicked shall be destroyed. When Jesus
stands before the Jews, they will see the wounds in his hands and, recognizing their Lord and
God, they shall say: ". . . What are these wounds in thine hands?" And then Jesus shall break
the hearts of the Jews by saying: "Those with which I was wounded in the house of my
friends" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/13/6#6">Zech. 13:6</a>).
And that nation then, and not until then, shall be born in a day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/66/8#8">Isa. 66:8</a>). By
the authorized servants of God they shall receive the baptism of repentance; they shall receive
the gift of the Holy Ghost, and become the children of God their Father and the servants of
the great Jehovah. At that time a fountain shall be opened up unto the Jews and the
inhabitants of Jerusalem (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/13/1#1">Zech. 13:1</a>),
a fountain for the cleansing of sin and iniquity, and that fountain
shall be as it always has been, the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
We read in the Book of Mormon:
</p><p>
. . . because of the Spirit of the Lord Omnipotent, which has wrought a mighty change in. . .
our hearts, . . . we have no more disposition to do evil, but to do good continually
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/5/2#2">Mosiah 5:2</a>).
</p><p>
THE DESTINY OF THE LATTER-DAY SAINTS
</p><p>
And if the elders of Israel will preach the gospel in its plainness, not worldly philosophy, but
the gospel of faith, repentance, baptism by immersion for the remission of sins, and the laying
on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost, then shall the hearts of the people be changed by
the almighty power of God and they will press into the kingdom of God. This Church is
destined to evangelize the whole earth. That is its mission, and by the grace of God we are
going to accomplish it.
</p><p>
There is a wonderful prophecy in First Nephi, fourteenth chapter, uttered about the time that
Isaiah delivered his great prophecy. Listen to it:
</p><p>
And it came to pass that I, Nephi, beheld the power of the Lamb of God, that it descended
upon the saints of the church of the Lamb, and upon the covenant people of the Lord, who
were scattered upon all the face of the earth; and they were armed with righteousness and
with the power of God in great glory
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/14/14#14">1 Ne. 14:14</a>).
</p><p>
How rapidly this wonderful prophecy is being fulfilled! President Joseph F. Smith in Bern,
Switzerland, declared that "there will be churches built here [that is, in Europe], and temples
built here and there all over Europe."
</p><p>
What a glorious destiny God sent us here to perform. Brethren and sisters, how can we be
dilatory, how can we be negligent, when, shining as the sun in heaven, is the purpose and the
destiny of this people? A people that has not an ideal or a noble purpose is like a painted ship
on a painted ocean, but we must cherish and nourish these wonderful ideals that God has
given and press on to the mark of eternal perfection. And the elders in the field ought not to
be kept coddling the Saints, but they should be sent out among the Gentiles and derive that
strength and power which comes from preaching the everlasting gospel.
</p><p>
RIGHTEOUSNESS REQUIRED TO MAKE A MIGHTY NATION
</p><p>
God be praised for this mighty republic! Oh, if the leaders of this
nation could realize the purpose for which this nation is created, a might nation, the greatest
in the world, that stands preeminent among
all the nations, I believe that they would highly resolve in their hearts that corruption,
extravagance, infidelity, Sabbath-breaking, and all the evils which form the accursed things in
this nation, would be removed. I believe that this nation would then receive such a mighty
uplift that it would be the wonder of all the world, that it would go forth assisting God and
Jesus in establishing the religion which can bring permanent and perpetual peace and lasting
glory to this nation.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, let us go forward. We are trying to awaken the world for the conflict of
justice, preaching the gospel as a special witness for the second coming of the Son of God.
Standing in the front ranks of this battle, we shall know, we do know now, that we are
battling for the Lord through rendering service for our fellow creatures.
</p><p>
"O God, our help in ages past, our hope for years to come," be thou our guide we pray thee,
lead us on to victory in this great spiritual battle. May we be thy humble instruments in
bringing repentance into the world and salvation to our fellow beings, we humbly pray in the
name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
