<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Obligations of the Priesthood</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 94-99</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is my purpose tonight to plead with our brethren who hold the responsibility of conducting
the priesthood for a better supervision of priesthood quorums. In a revelation given to the
Prophet for the benefit of the first elders of this Church he said: ". . . thou shalt not idle away
thy time, neither shalt thou bury thy talent that it may not be known"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/60/13#13">D&amp;C 60:13</a>). Too
many of those who hold the priesthood have idled away their time and have buried their
talent. We would like to have a revival among all the quorums of the priesthood.
</p><p>
ORGANIZATION ESSENTIAL TO PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
In that great revelation known as section one hundred seven, the priesthood revelation, there
are three expressions I would like to read, first from the twenty-first verse:
</p><p>
Of necessity, there are presidents, or presiding officers growing out of, or appointed of or
from among those who are ordained to the several offices in these two priesthoods
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/21#21">D&amp;C 107:21</a>).
</p><p>
Then in the sixtieth verse the Lord says:
</p><p>
Verily, I say unto you, saith the Lord of Hosts, there must needs be presiding elders to
preside over those who are of the office of an elder
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/60#60">D&amp;C 107:60</a>).
</p><p>
And then again in the eighty-ninth verse:
</p><p>
Again, the duty of the president over the office of elders is to preside over ninety-six elders,
and to sit in council with them, and to teach them according to the covenants
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/89#89">D&amp;C 107:89</a>).
</p><p>
Organization is an essential requirement in the government of the Church. The entire universe
is organized on a divine plan. Without organization there would be confusion, chaos, and that
would lead to disorganization and destruction. The quorums of the priesthood are organized
for a definite purpose. I've jotted down several of these: first, to keep the members holding
the priesthood active and alert in the performance of every duty which the priesthood requires
at their hands; second, to teach the members how to assume responsibility and magnify their
callings; third, to train them in methods by which they may effectually teach others and
officiate in their behalf; fourth, to encourage them in their responsibilities pertaining to the
salvation of the dead as well as for the living.
</p><p>
A quorum, properly appointed, must seek out the needs of every individual member and
attempt to supply these needs that may be discovered, both temporally and spiritually. No
quorum of the priesthood is assuming the full obligation placed upon it by the Lord which
does not sufficiently extend temporal need. Each member should dedicate himself and use his
talent to advance the cause of Zion. He must be loyal and faithful to the Church, to the
quorum, to the priesthood in general, to his family and to every divine principle of eternal
truth.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY OF PRESIDENT OF QUORUM
</p><p>
The responsibility of the quorum president is, as stated in this revelation, to sit in counsel, to
advise and instruct and teach those who are under his direction. The Lord has placed the
responsibility for the training and the conduct of the members of the quorum upon the
shoulders of the president of the quorum. He has given him two counselors to assist him in
that work. This direction and care of the quorum may not be transferred to the shoulders of
some other. Men who are the most capable for these positions of presidency should be sought.
Too frequently it is thought that the supervision of a quorum, especially of elders, is not of
great importance, but the Lord thinks otherwise. There should be, however, a division of
responsibility among the presidency. The presidency should see that the quorum is fully
organized, and that every man is performing his duty. If there are delinquent or wayward
members, these should be labored with until brought to repentance and full fellowship.
</p><p>
The stake presidency and the high council have supervision over the quorums of the
Melchizedek Priesthood. It is their duty to see that the quorums are fully organized and
properly functioning. The stake Melchizedek Priesthood committee is to act as an aid to the
stake presidency. It is recommended that such a committee be maintained. It must be
understood, however, that the stake Melchizedek Priesthood committee does not preside, but is
to supervise and counsel quo-rum members, under the direction of the stake presidency. It is
proposed that a member of the stake presidency be the chairman of this committee. He may
have as many members of the high council on that committee as it is deemed wise, but not
less than three. It is further understood that this committee has authority in the supervision of
the elders, seventies and high priests within the stake, under the direction of the stake
president.
</p><p>
The presidency of a quorum of priesthood should hold weekly council meetings. They must
not wait for something to arise which they deem important to be considered. If they will
meet, many things will arise for their consideration which were previously not thought of.
</p><p>
There are three great needs of a quorum. We believe that the work falls naturally into three
divisions: first, the need to help every bearer of the Melchizedek Priesthood to attain to the
degree of economic independence and material well-being that will assure adequate food,
clothing, fuel, housing, and other needs, physical and educational, for himself and family as
well as spiritual; second, the need to establish a feeling of true brotherhood should
characterize the work of priesthood quorums. There should be the endeavor to provide
through the quorum activities, including socials and outings, the feeling of fellowship, faith,
and love that shall meet all the needs of the membership; third, a need to search out the facts
and make available all the information and statistics concerning the quorum and its members.
</p><p>
DIVISION OF RESPONSIBILITY
</p><p>
We suggest that the responsibility having to do with personal welfare be assigned to the
quorum president. It would naturally follow that the other divisions would be assumed by the
counselors, one taking the quorum activity and Church service, the other fact-finding and
statistical responsibility. These responsibilities must not be shifted to the shoulders of others,
but it is very proper that help be obtained from standing committees as the presidency of the
quorum may determine. It is suggested that these responsibilities may be designated as
follows: one, personal welfare; two, quorum activity and Church service; three, fact finding
and statistics.
</p><p>
In the past we have had four standing committees but our observation and the information
coming from stake priesthood committees lead us to conclude that these three committees may
be all that are required. However, the presidency, if they desire, may call task committees
whenever the occasion seems to warrant it.
</p><p>
MONTHLY LEADERSHIP MEETING
</p><p>
There should be in each stake a monthly Melchizedek leadership meeting at which the stake
presidency and the stake Melchizedek priesthood committee shall meet with the officers and
leaders of quorums and groups, including quorum presidencies, quorum secretaries, group
leaders, committee members, and class instructors. It is suggested that the secretaries meet
with the fact finding and statistical group of counselors. It is also recommended that a special
department to take care of instructors be conducted under the leadership, or at least the
direction of a member of the stake Melchizedek Priesthood committee. In this department
teacher-training helps and assistance should be given, lesson material enlarged and developed.
It should be borne in mind that class instruction and related problems are the responsibility of
the member of the quorum presidency assigned.
</p><p>
On the day of the monthly priesthood leadership meeting, the stake committee should hold a
preliminary meeting with the presidencies of the Melchizedek quorums. We recommend that
separation be had on a department, not quorum, basis. At the time of separation, brief opening
exercises should be held. In the matter of reports, it is to be hoped that attention will be given
to the instructions which are sent to the quorums. More detailed information and an outline of
procedure and instruction will, within a short time, be furnished each stake president and
quorum president.
</p><p>
THE COURSE OF STUDY
</p><p>
The course of study that will be considered by the priesthood quorums for the year 1946 was
prepared by Elder Milton R. Hunter of the First Council of the Seventy. The title is,
<i>The Gospel Through the Ages</i>. I have read this manuscript and some of the other brethren have
read it, and I can assure you brethren that we are going to have a very profitable time in
considering a subject of this nature.
</p><p>
Now, if I may spend a little time, after giving these details and stating that more information
will soon be furnished, I would like to say a few things about our responsibilities as men
holding the priesthood. On the one hundred and twenty-first section of the D&amp;C, the
quotation that we have heard so many times from the lips of President Heber J. Grant, I
would like to make a comment.
</p><p>
THE WORD OF THE LORD
</p><p>
Behold, there are many called, but few are chosen. And why are they not chosen? Because
their hearts are set so much upon the things of this world, and aspire to the honors of men,
that they do not learn this one lesson&mdash;That the rights of the priesthood are inseparably
connected with the powers of heaven, and that the powers of heaven cannot be controlled nor
handled only upon the principles of righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/34-36#34">D&amp;C 121:34-36</a>).
</p><p>
Now who are those who are called? I take it that every man who is ordained to an office in
the priesthood has been called. The Lord is willing that any man should serve him.
</p><p>
In the early revelations given to some of the brethren who came asking of the Lord what he
would have them do he told them to bring forth the cause of Zion
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/6#6">D&amp;C 6:6</a>), to thrust in their sickles
with their might that they might lay up in store
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/4#4">D&amp;C 4:4</a>).
</p><p>
I think a great deal of this short section, section four, for two good reasons: first, it was given
to my great-grandfather, but it wasn't given to him alone, and I have said many times it was
also given to me; and second, it was given to you, each one of you, and in this revelation the
Lord says:
</p><p>
Therefore, O ye that embark in the service of God, see that ye serve him with all your heart,
might, mind and strength, that ye may stand blameless before God at the last day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/2#2">D&amp;C 4:2</a>).
</p><p>
Then it follows that if we don't serve him with all our heart, might, mind, and strength, if
we're not loyal to this calling which we have received, we are not going to be blameless
when we stand before that judgment seat. It is a very serious thing to hold the priesthood. I
wish when our young men were called and ordained, that is, recommended to be ordained to
the office of elder in the Church, they could be impressed before they were ordained with the
importance of the calling which they are about to receive.
</p><p>
In section eighty-four of the D&amp;C, the Lord has this to say:
</p><p>
For whoso is faithful unto the obtaining these two priesthoods of which I have spoken, and
the magnifying their calling, are sanctified by the Spirit unto the renewing of their bodies;
They become the sons of Moses and of Aaron and the seed of Abraham, and the church and
kingdom, and the elect of God; And also all they who receive this priesthood receive me,
saith the Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33-35#33">D&amp;C 84:33-35</a>).
</p><p>
And if we receive the Lord, then, surely the Lord receives us, and we are in fellowship with
him.
</p><p>
For he that receiveth my servants receiveth me; and he that receiveth me receiveth my Father
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/36#36">D&amp;C 84:36</a>).
</p><p>
Now, here is the great blessing, which I think many of us have overlooked, and especially
these young men when they are called and sustained to be ordained to the office of elder:
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth my Father"&mdash;and of course we receive the Father through our
faithfulness and our obedience, "receiveth my Father's kingdom; therefore all that my Father
hath shall be given unto him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>).
</p><p>
Can you think of a greater blessing the Lord could offer to any man holding the priesthood?
But this is based upon faithfulness and the magnifying of the calling.
</p><p>
In other revelations, you know, the Lord says:
</p><p>
And [they] who overcome by faith, and are sealed by the Holy Spirit of promise, . . . They
are they into whose hands the Father has given all things . . . they are gods, even the sons of
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/53,55,58#53">D&amp;C 76:53,55,58</a>).
</p><p>
And this according to the oath and covenant which belongeth to the priesthood. Therefore, all
those who receive the priesthood, receive this oath and covenant of my Father, which he
cannot break, neither can it be moved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/39-40#39">D&amp;C 84:39-40</a>).
</p><p>
Here is a definite, positive statement that every man who receives the priesthood, receives it
with an oath and covenant that he will magnify his calling, that he will be faithful and true,
and his reward will be to become a son of God and a joint heir with Jesus Christ in having
the fulness of the Father's kingdom. No greater blessing could be offered. And then the Lord
has said:
</p><p>
Therefore all those who receive the priesthood, receive this oath and covenant of my Father,
which he cannot break, neither can it be moved
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/40#40">D&amp;C 84:40</a>).
</p><p>
Now, these promises were not made to high priests alone, but to all who receive the
priesthood. And then the Lord is promising us everything that he has if we will be faithful.
Isn't it only fair, that the punishment for violation of that covenant and the trampling of that
priesthood under our feet should bring a punishment, on one hand, as severe, as glorious will
be the reward on the other? And so the Lord says:
</p><p>
But whoso breaketh this covenant after he hath received it, and altogether turneth therefrom,
shall not have forgiveness of sins in this world nor in the world to come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/41#41">D&amp;C 84:41</a>).
</p><p>
Oh, if we could only impress that upon the mind of every man when he is called to receive
the priesthood! Now, only those who magnify their callings will be chosen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/34#34">D&amp;C 121:34</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord bless you, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
