<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 101-102</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, it seems to me that the circumstances under which we meet and the stirring
messages to which we have listened give rise to many reflections. I rejoice with you in the
strength and stability of the Church. I rejoice with you in the zeal and the enthusiasm of the
leaders of this Church, and I rejoice with you in the faith and the integrity and the unswerving
devotion of the membership of this Church. I say to you that God is at the helm. He is
directing this people. He will continue to inspire the leaders of this Church. I
appreciate more than I can tell my membership in the Church, my testimony of the truth, the
great privileges, and the great opportunities which have come to me because of that
membership.
</p><p>
ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
Reference has been made frequently to the greatness of the Church. The Church is great, not
necessarily great in number, because there are many churches which outnumber us in
members, but our Church, the Church of Christ, is great in purpose, in plan and objectives. It
is great in leadership, past and present, local and general. It is great in historical background;
its history forms a big part in the drama of American accomplishments. Our history is
colorful, interesting, stirring, full of romance, full of tragedy, and yet full of achievement. The
membership of this Church have built villages, cities, commonwealths, churches, schools, and
temples&mdash;and the end is not yet. The organization and the movement characteristic of the
Church have always been surcharged with a constructive spirit. Past leaders have subdued the
desert. They have set up high standards for you and me to follow. They have developed a
literature that will live in the world, a literature that explains and interprets the teachings of
Jesus, of Paul, of Moses, and of other great men who stand as the pivots of history. What
would these men say if they came back today with a message? What would Moses, the
lawgiver of Israel say? He would teach, as he taught when he lived, the divinity of the Ten
Commandments. So important are these commandments that neither men nor nations can
violate them, if they want to live and achieve. What would Paul, the apostle, say? He would
say to the skeptics as he did to King Agrippa, "Why should it be thought a thing incredible
with you, that God should raise the dead?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/8#8">Acts 26:8</a>), virtually saying, "You ask me to
explain the resurrection. I call upon you to substantiate the denial of this great doctrine." He
would say, as he did to King Agrippa, ". . . believest thou the prophets?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/27#27">Acts 26:27</a>). I tell
you the world has gone astray because they have failed to believe the prophets.
</p><p>
What would Jesus say? He would preach again his wonderful, unparalleled Sermon on the
Mount and tell the nations to heed the teachings, because in it are the elements of salvation.
What would Joseph Smith say? He would give his testimony as he gave it when he was alive.
He would tell you and me and the world that he saw God the Father, that he gazed upon him
and heard the voice of the risen Redeemer. I testify to you that God's work has been
established upon the earth. It will grow and increase until it reaches the hearts of men
everywhere. It will not fail. God help us to discharge our responsibilities and to introduce into
our lives the saving principles of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, I pray in his name.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
