<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">This Same Jesus</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Sterling W. Sill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Sterling W. Sill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 40-43</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Many years ago someone published a picture Bible in which it was attempted to make the
great scriptural messages more memorable, by presenting them in visual form. Our natural
tendency is to see things more clearly when they are presented in pictures. Mere ideas are
often too abstract for the mind to deal with effectively.
</p><p>
One of the visual portrayals in this interesting Bible was a colored picture of the ascension. It
showed the Resurrected Jesus standing in the air above the Mount of Olives as he was
ascending to his Father. And standing slightly below the master were two angels dressed in
white clothing. Over the years I have drawn great strength from the thrilling ideas represented
by this picture. Christ's ascension to heaven marked the end of an important period. He had
finished one part of the work assigned to him in the grand council of heaven. He had
organized the Church and had left ordained apostles to carry on its work. He had taught them
the doctrines of salvation and had given them the priesthood, with the power to bind in
heaven what they did on earth. He had shed his own blood to pay the penalty of our sins.
Then in the last words spoken just before his ascension, Jesus said to the Twelve ". . . ye
shall be witnesses unto me both in Jerusalem, and in all Judea, and in Samaria, and unto the
uttermost part of the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/8#8">Acts 1:8</a>).
</p><p>
The ascension picture is completed by the interesting scriptural statement which said, "And
when he had spoken these things, while they beheld, he was taken up; and a cloud received
him out of their sight.
</p><p>
"And while they looked stedfastly toward heaven as he went up, behold, two men stood by
them in white apparel; 
</p><p>
"Which also said, Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? this same Jesus,
which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go
into heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/9-11#9">Acts 1:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
During World War II, I added another impressive mental picture to my collection. This one
shows General Douglas MacArthur about to take flight from Corregidor under the military
pressure of Japanese conquest. To those who were forced to remain behind, General
MacArthur said, "I shall return." I like to imagine the hope that this promise must have
brought to the people of the Philippines during those long months in which they awaited their
liberation from the bondage of the Japanese. They knew that MacArthur would not forget.
They knew that just as soon as possible he would come back to set them free and punish their
oppressors. His promise may have had more than ordinary significance to
me, inasmuch as some of the members of my own family were among those awaiting
MacArthur's return. They hid in the hills until they were captured and sent to a Japanese
concentration camp in Manila.
</p><p>
The general's promise to return must have had a disturbing significance for the invaders
themselves, for they must have known that MacArthur would never rest until they had been
driven from the islands or annihilated during their resistance. This "I shall return" picture was
given its happy ending some two years later when the general's promise was finally and fully
kept.
</p><p>
However, the world still awaits this more significant "I shall return" promise that had been
made some nineteen hundred years earlier from above the Mount of Olives. It is very
important to remember that the Savior of the world was only bidding the earth and its people
a temporary farewell. Many times before his death, he himself had foretold his own glorious
second coming to judge the world.
</p><p>
On that last Tuesday before his death on Friday, Jesus had been teaching his followers about
his second coming. Near the end of the day he left the temple and led the Twelve across the
Mount of Olives. As he sat down to rest near the summit, his disciples said to him, ". . . Tell
us, when shall these things be, and what shall be the sign of thy coming, and the end of the
world?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/3#3">Matt. 24:3</a>).
Then Jesus told them of the wars and contentions that should
characterize the last days, and as one of the important signs that should precede his second
coming, he said, "And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the world for a
witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
As the people of the Philippines awaited their liberation, they probably wondered whether or
not General MacArthur had the ability to fulfil the conditions involved in his promise to
return. There are also a great many in our world who discount both the possibility and the
probability of the second coming of Christ. Yet we may be certain that God's program has
never been abandoned and will not be forgotten.
</p><p>
In those last sad hours just prior to his death, Jesus said to his disciples, "Let not your heart
be troubled: ye believe in God, believe also in me.
</p><p>
"In my Father's house are many mansions: if it were not so, I would have told you. I go to
prepare a place for you.
</p><p>
"And if I go and prepare a place for you, <i>I will come again</i>, and receive you unto myself; that
where I am, there ye may be also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/1-3#1">John 14:1-3</a>), italics added).
What a thrilling, frightening
thought when we understand the conditions under which he will come again. And what
tremendous consequences are involved in the message of ascension day. As the Resurrected
Son of God stood there between the heavens and the earth, holy angels from God's presence
made a firm promise, that he would personally return. The angels said, ". . . this same Jesus .
. . shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
Since ascension day,
some nineteen wide centuries have come and gone, and many important events have taken
place. According to tradition with one exception, the apostles that Jesus appointed to carry on
his work, were all subjected to violent deaths. Peter, Philip, Simon, and Andrew were
crucified; James and Paul were beheaded; Bartholomew was flayed alive; Thomas was run
through with a lance; James, the son of Alphaeus, was beaten to death; Thaddaeus was shot
through with arrows; Barnabas was stoned; Matthew was slain with a battle axe in Ethiopia;
and Mark was dragged to death in the streets of Alexandria. Then John, the sole survivor,
was banished to the lonely isle of Patmos in the Aegean Sea. Jesus had built his Church upon
the foundation of apostles and prophets. When the foundation was destroyed, the building
crumbled. In time what had once been a divine organization became merely a human
institution. Many of the Christian doctrines were misinterpreted; the ordinances were changed;
the authority was lost; the apostasy grew; and the world slipped gradually into the long black
night of the Dark Ages. Then some said that the heavens were forever
sealed, that the canon of scripture was full, and that no voice from God would ever again be
heard upon the earth. The spirit of those who crucified Christ, destroyed his organization, and
disbelieved his doctrines, still have a numerous following among us.
</p><p>
One of the most serious problems of our present world is that there are so many people who
disbelieve in a Supreme Being. To some, man is the highest authority and the greatest
intelligence in the universe. Others believe that God has gone out of business and that the last
words that we will ever hear from the Savior of the world were spoken at the ninth hour of
that awful Friday afternoon, when from Calvary's cross the dying Christ said, "It is finished"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/19/30#30">John 19:30</a>).
The last memory that some have of their Redeemer pictures him hanging upon the cross.
Recently the world has been flooded with the crucifix, but Jesus did not remain upon the
cross. Some remember him lying in the garden tomb of Joseph of Arimathaea, but Jesus did
not remain in the tomb. Nothing in the scriptures could be plainer than the fact that the life of
Christ did not begin in Bethlehem, neither did it end on Calvary. He said, "I came forth from
the Father, and am come into the world: again, I leave the world, and go to the Father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/28#28">John 16:28</a>).
In his prayer in Gethsemane while contemplating his own death, he said, "And now,
O Father, glorify thou me with thine own self with the glory which I had with thee before the
world was" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/5#5">John 17:5</a>).
</p><p>
Long before our earth was created, Jesus lived and ruled with his Father as a part of the
presidency of the universe. Under the direction of the Father, he was the Creator of the earth.
In the first chapter of Genesis, God is recorded as saying, ". . . Let <i>us</i> make man in <i>our</i>
image, after <i>our</i> likeness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26#26">Gen. 1:26</a>, italics added).
The use of these plural pronouns
indicates that the Son also took part in the creation. But even then he was no novice as a
Creator. In one of the great revelations given to Moses and revealed anew in the latter days,
God said, "And worlds without number have I created; . . . and by the Son I created them,
which is mine Only Begotten" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33#33">Moses 1:33</a>).
</p><p>
We think of greatness partly in terms of what it has already accomplished and partly in terms
of what it promises for the future. As I rerun my mental picture of ascension day, I like to
think of the Redeemer in terms of his tremendous background. Not only had he created
worlds without number, but in his pre-mortal existence he was that magnificent personage of
great authority and power known in the scriptures as Jehovah, the God of Abraham, Isaac,
and Jacob. He was the first Begotten Son of God in the spirit and was chosen to be the Savior
of the world because he was the best qualified for that important calling. Then as a part of his
own progression, he took upon himself a body of flesh and bones, and became the Only
Begotten Son of God in the flesh. There are some who discount the value of a body so far as
eternity is concerned. There are those who in their teachings seek to deprive God of his body.
Many do not believe in their own resurrection. But next to the human spirit the human body
is the most marvelous of God's creations. If the body was not necessary, God would never
have created it in the first place. If it was not necessary for eternity, God would never have
instituted the resurrection. If a body was not necessary for God the Father, certainly there
would have been no reason why God the Son should have been resurrected. The spirit and the
body inseparably connected constitutes the soul. The spirit can never be perfect without the
body. There can never be a fulness of joy until the spirit and the body are inseparably joined
together (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/33#33">D&amp;C 93:33</a>).
</p><p>
The Resurrected, Glorified Jesus, like Elohim, his Eternal Father, has a body of flesh and
bones as tangible as man's (see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/22#22">D&amp;C 130:22</a>).
When Jesus appeared to the eleven after his
resurrection, they were frightened and supposed that they had seen a spirit. Jesus corrected
them by saying, "Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I myself: handle me, and see; for a
spirit hath not flesh and bones, as ye see me have"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/39#39">Luke 24:39</a>).
Jesus did not lose his body
after his resurrection. In some mysterious way it did not evaporate, neither
did it expand to fill the immensity of space. Jesus had his body as he ascended to his Father
from the Mount of Olives, and the record is perfectly clear that he will still have that same
body when he comes in glory to judge the world.
</p><p>
In addition to the information given in the Bible, we now have some new evidence of
universal importance which has been given to the world on this subject in our own day. In the
early spring of 1820, in upper New York state, God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ
reappeared upon the earth to re-establish among men a belief in the God of Genesis, a belief
in the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and a belief in the God of Mount Olivet. The
Prophet Joseph Smith describes his part of this experience by saying, ". . . I saw two
personages whose brightness and glory defy all description, standing above me in the air. One
of them spake unto me, calling me by name and said, pointing to the other&mdash;<i>This is My</i>
<i>Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
Then there followed the great message of the restoration.
</p><p>
The same Jesus who healed the sick and walked upon the waves has spoken again in our day
and has reaffirmed the fact that he is still interested in our success. The same Jesus said to his
disciples, ". . . Go ye into all the world, and preach the gospel to every creature.
</p><p>
"He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved; but he that believeth not shall be damned"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-16#15">Mark 16:15-16</a>).
This same Jesus has informed us anew that he has not changed his mind
about the importance of this and the other great Christian doctrines.
</p><p>
The same Jesus who upon the Mount of Olives said, "And this gospel of the kingdom shall be
preached in all the world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>), has,
under the direction of his Father, restored <i>that</i> gospel, in preparation for <i>that</i> day. He himself
looked forward to that day saying, "For the Son of man shall come in the glory of his Father
with his angels; and then he shall reward every man according to his works"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/27#27">Matt. 16:27</a>).
What a tremendous day that will be. That is also the day foretold by Malachi who said "For
behold, the day cometh that shall burn as an oven, and all the proud, yea, and all that do
wickedly shall burn as stubble; for they that come shall burn them, saith the Lord of Hosts,
that it shall leave them neither root nor branch"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/37#37">JS&mdash;H 1:37</a>). That tremendous event
is fast approaching, and we must work while it is called today, for the night cometh, wherein
no man can work (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/4#4">John 9:4</a>).
</p><p>
I would like to bear to you my personal witness that God has not gone out of business, that
the heavens are not sealed, that the Redeemer of man has not forgotten his promises, nor is he
any less interested in our welfare now than when in Gethsemane and upon Mount Calvary he
suffered for our sins. And to close, I would again like to take you out to the sacred top of the
Mount of Olives, and again hear the angels say, ". . . this same Jesus, which is taken up from
you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have seen him go into heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>).
May God help us to be ready for that important event I pray in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
