<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Elijah's Mission to the World</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 131-136</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I need your assistance and the guidance of the Spirit of the
Lord. I would like to read a little from the book of Malachi, whom I may designate as a
prophet of the restoration, for he has a great deal to say about the restoration.
</p><p>
In the third chapter we read:
</p><p>
A PROPHET OF THE RESTORATION
</p><p>
Behold, I will send my messenger, and he shall prepare the way before me: and the Lord,
whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple, even the messenger of the covenant, whom
ye delight in: behold, he shall come, saith the Lord of hosts
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/1#1">Mal. 3:1</a>).
</p><p>
Throughout the world the idea prevails that this prediction has reference to the first coming of
Christ in the days of his ministry, but this is not the case, it has reference to his second
coming, for the predictions which follow were not fulfilled at his first coming, but are to be
fulfilled when he comes in power, at and preceding the second coming. We read:
</p><p>
But who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is
like a refiner's fire, and like fuller's soap:
</p><p>
And he shall sit as a refiner and purifier of silver: and he shall purify the sons of Levi, and
purge them as gold and silver, that they may offer unto the Lord an offering in righteousness.
</p><p>
Then shall the offering of Judah and Jerusalem be pleasant unto the Lord, as in the days of
old, and as in former years.
</p><p>
And I will come near to you to judgment; and I will be a swift witness against the sorcerers,
and against the adulterers, and against false swearers. and against those that oppress the
hireling in his wages, the widow, and the fatherless, and that turn aside the stranger from his
right, and fear not me, saith the Lord of hosts
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/2-5#2">Mal. 3:2-5</a>).
</p><p>
Now we understand, and the whole world could understand, that the offering of Judah in the
days of Christ's ministry, was not pleasant. Levi was not at that time cleansed, but Judah and
Levi turned away from the Lord. It is in the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times that these
things are to be fulfilled.
</p><p>
In the fourth chapter Malachi speaks again of the coming of the Son of God, in these words:
</p><p>
For, behold, the day cometh, that shall burn as an oven; and all the proud, yea, and all that do
wickedly, shall be stubble: and the day that cometh shall burn them up, saith the Lord of
hosts, that it shall leave them neither root nor branch
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/1#1">Mal. 4:1</a>).
</p><p>
This will happen when our Savior comes in his glory to take vengeance upon the ungodly
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/97/22#22">D&amp;C 97:22</a>) and
take his place as King of kings and Lord of lords
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/16#16">Rev. 19:16</a>).
Then this prophet Malachi goes on to say
that before that day can come, which will be terrible, Elijah the prophet was to come, and
these are the words as we have them in this King James translation:
</p><p>
Behold, I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and dreadful day of
the Lord:
</p><p>
And he shall turn the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their
fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6#5">Mal. 4:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
GREAT AND DREADFUL DAY NEAR
</p><p>
The whole world ought to take notice of this prediction, but the world does not understand it.
Surely the signs of the times point to the fact that the great and dreadful day is near, even at
our doors. The fig tree, figuratively, is putting forth her leaves
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/32#32">Matt. 24:32</a>). The turmoil, trouble, the war
and bloodshed that we have seen, and which we still see, all point to the fact that this day for
the coming of the Son of God is near. Therefore, Elijah the prophet is due to appear. I am
sure you agree with me that he has already appeared, for we have it so recorded by the
testimony of witnesses. It was on the third day of April, 1836, when he came to the Kirtland
Temple, to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery, and conferred upon them the keys of his
priesthood and told them that he came in fulfillment of the prophecy of Malachi, to turn the
hearts of the fathers to the children, and the children to their fathers, lest the whole earth be
smitten with a curse (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/11-15#11">D&amp;C 110:11-15</a>).
</p><p>
Therefore, the keys of this dispensation are committed into your hands; and by this ye may
know that the great and dreadful day of the Lord is near, even at the doors
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/16#16">D&amp;C 110:16</a>).
</p><p>
RESTORATION BY ELIJAH
</p><p>
Well, of course, the world does not believe that Elijah came to Joseph Smith and Oliver
Cowdery; but they have no record in the world that he has come to anyone else. There has
been no appearance and no claim of an appearance, and a restoration of his priesthood to
anyone else. May we not, then, with perfect consistency, put forth the claim that he did come
on that occasion and that he did restore his keys of authority to these two humble men, which
turned the hearts of the fathers to their children and the hearts of the children to their fathers?
No one else has ever disputed this claim by the giving of another claim. And why could he
not come to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery as well as to anybody else?  I testify to you
that he did come, and if the world want to know it also, they can. We have an abundance of
evidence that this story is true. If Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery had lied, it would have
been impossible for them to have turned the hearts of the fathers to their children and the
hearts of the children to their fathers. Surely, they would not have any power to do that. It is
true that following the declaration by them that Elijah did come, the hearts of the children
commenced to turn to their dead fathers. There is strong presumptive evidence that this was
because these keys were restored. This is a demonstrative fact, that the hearts of children have
turned to their fathers.
</p><p>
ACTIVITY IN GENEALOGY
</p><p>
I have a little information here that I think is important, and this coming of Elijah is one of
the vital things in the history of this world. It is vital to me and to you and to every other
soul upon the face of the earth. Before the days of the coming of Elijah in 1836, there was no
endeavor of any import to search the records of the dead. What was done, here and there, was
usually where some estate was involved. The people were not turning their hearts to their
dead fathers. They were not searching the records. They were not compiling them. There were
no organizations or societies on the face of the earth, as far as I can learn, gathering records
of the dead, before the year 1836. In 1837, however, one year later, Great Britain passed laws
providing for and compelling the preservation of records of the dead. In the year 1844, the
New England Historical and Genealogical Society was organized in Boston, and I think this
was the first organization of the kind in the world. In 1869, the New York Genealogical and
Biographical Society in the city of New York was organized. Then followed rapidly other
societies up and down the Atlantic coast of the United States, from Maine to Georgia. Then
these organizations began to spread inland, and this spirit took hold of the people in other
parts. I have visited some of these societies in various parts of the United States, and they
have extended now from the east to the Pacific Ocean. In Great Britain, genealogical societies
have been organized in practically every county in that land and in Scotland. These records
have been kept and flied also in other countries in Europe, the countries from which the
Latter-day Saints have come. The spirit has taken hold of the people, not only in the Church,
but also of many who are not of the Church, and they, too, are searching the records,  and
compiling them, of the dead.
</p><p>
PREVALENCE OF GENEALOGICAL RESEARCH
</p><p>
In the year 1902, I had the privilege of going east on a genealogical mission. My father
wanted me to go because there was some confusion in our family line in those early days,
which he wanted me to straighten out. I went back to Essex County, Massachusetts. At
Topsfield, where our ancestors first settled in the United States, I became acquainted with Mr.
George Francis Dow, a very prominent gentleman of Massachusetts. I told him the purpose of
my visit to that part of the country. He invited me to his home. I asked him where I could
find the best sources for information in my search. He said: "You do not have to go
anywhere. I have all that information. I have compiled it." So he put in my hands this record,
and I found it already prepared. He was working on many other lines also. While there I met
a Mr. Perley, a prominent lawyer of Salem, Massachusetts. He likewise was engaged in
genealogical research. I had a long conversation with him. He told me that he had undertaken
a great work for the benefit of the descendants of people who settled in Essex County. "It is
my ambition," he said, "if I can do it, to search out the records of every individual who came
to Essex County before the year 1700. I said to him, "Mr. Perley, you have cut out for
yourself a big work, haven't you?" He replied, "Yes, and I am afraid I'll never finish it."
Then I said to him, "Why are you doing this work?" He thought a moment and looked rather
puzzled and then replied, "I do not know why, but I got started, and I cannot stop." I said, "I
can tell you why you are doing this and why you cannot stop, but if I did, you would not
believe me and would laugh at me." "Oh," he said, "I don't know. If you can tell me, I am
sure I will be interested." Then I told him of the prophecy concerning Elijah and the
fulfilment of this promise to the Prophet Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery, April 3, 1836, in
the Kirtland Temple, and how this spirit of research had taken hold of many people, and they
had turned their hearts to the seeking after the dead in fulfilment of this great promise which
was to come before the second coming, so that the earth would not be smitten with a curse.
Now the children were turning their hearts toward their fathers, and we were doing the
ordinance work for the dead that they might find redemption and have the privilege of coming
into the kingdom of God, although dead.
</p><p>
When I got through, he laughed and said, "It is a very pretty story, but I do not believe it."
Yet he admitted that there was something compelling him to carry on this research, and he
could not stop. I have met a great many others who also started and could not stop, men and
women who are not members of the Church. So we find today thousands of men and women
searching out the records of the dead. They do not know why, but it is so that we can obtain
these compiled records and go into our temples and do the work for our dead.
</p><p>
President Clark told us that the Church is putting forth considerable sums for the purpose of
collecting records in Europe that we might search out our ancestors and go into the house of
the Lord and do work for them.
</p><p>
Now here is something which I think is interesting. In 1935, Mr. T. B. Thompson published
A Catalogue of British Family Histories. It included the titles and years of publication of
some two thousand seventy-one families and was supposed to be a complete list of all such
published records up to that date. Here are his figures from the date of the invention of
printing:
</p><p>
From 1450 to 1600, were published 2 family histories.<br />
From 1600 to 1700, were published 18 family histories.<br />
From 1700 to 1800, were published 72 family histories.<br />
From 1800 to 1836, when Elijah came, were published 100 family histories.<br />
From 1837 to 1935, were published 1,879 family histories.
</p><p>
THE KEYS OF SEALING POWER
</p><p>
These were records in Europe, and since the year 1836, there have been published in Great
Britain and the United States thousands of records of the dead. I have some other things I
would like to present but cannot at this time. Let me call your attention to the fact, however,
my good brethren and sisters, that Elijah restored to this Church and, if they would receive it,
to the world, the keys of the sealing power; and that sealing power puts the stamp of approval
upon every ordinance that is done in this Church and more particularly those that are
performed in the temples of the Lord. Through that restoration each of you, my brethren, has
the privilege, of going into this house or one of the other temples (I believe most of you have
done so) to have your wife sealed to you for time and for all eternity, and your children
sealed to you also, or better, have them born under that covenant. What a glorious privilege it
is to know that the family organization will remain intact. It is not destroyed. It does not
come to an end wherein we have complied with the divine law by virtue of the keys which
are held by the President of the Church. We may go into the house of the Lord and do these
things and be baptized for our dead, those who have died, the scriptures say, and we have
heard it repeated at this conference, who died without the knowledge of the gospel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/5#5">D&amp;C 128:5</a>). Our duty
is to search out our dead, and I am very grateful that the Church is helping us in these matters
by securing the records of the dead that we might have them, and our duty is to perform the
necessary ordinances in their behalf in our temples.
</p><p>
STATEMENT OF PROPHET JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith has said:
</p><p>
The Bible says, "I will send you Elijah the prophet before the coming of the great and
dreadful day of the Lord; and he shall turn the hearts of the fathers to their children, and the
hearts of the children to the  fathers, lest I come and smite the earth with a curse"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6#5">Mal. 4:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
Now the word <i>turn</i> here should be translated <i>bind</i> or <i>seal</i>. But what is the object of this
important mission? or how is it to be fulfilled? The keys are to be delivered, the spirit of
Elijah is to come, the Gospel to be established, the Saints of God gathered, Zion built up, and
the Saints to come up as saviors on Mount Zion
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/obad/1/21#21">Obad. 1:21</a>).
</p><p>
But how are they to become saviors on Mount Zion? By building their temples, erecting their
baptismal fonts, and going forth and receiving all the ordinances, baptisms, confirmations,
washings, anointings, ordinations and sealing powers upon their heads, in behalf of their
progenitors who are dead, and redeem them that they may come forth in the first resurrection
and be exalted to thrones of glory with them; and herein is the chain that binds the hearts of
the fathers to the children, and the children to the fathers, which fulfills the mission of Elijah
. . .
</p><p>
The Saints have not too much time to save and redeem their dead, and gather together their
living relatives, that they may be saved also, before the earth will be smitten, and the
consumption decreed falls upon the world.
</p><p>
I would advise all the Saints to go with their might and gather together all their living
relatives to this place, that they may be sealed and saved, that they may be prepared against
the day that the destroying angel goes forth; and if the whole Church should go to with all
their might to save their dead, seal their posterity, and gather their living friends, and spend
none of their time in behalf of the world, they would hardly get through before night would
come, when no man can work . . . (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/4#4">John 9:4</a>).
</p><p>
The question is frequently asked: "Can we not be saved without going through with all these
ordinances, etc.?" I would answer, No, not the fullness of salvation. Jesus said, "There are
many mansions in my Father's house, and I will go and prepare a place for you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/2#2">John 14:2</a>). <i>House</i> here 
named should have been translated kingdom; and any person who is exalted to the highest
mansion has to abide a celestial law, and the whole law, too (<i>DHC</i> 6:183-184).
</p><p>
I call your attention to these things. The Lord bless you, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
