<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"...and if Ye Receive Not the Spirit Ye Shall Not Teach"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 20-22</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I realize my weakness and the need of your faith and prayers
and the help of the Spirit of the Lord.  I am grateful for the nature of the remarks made by
President McKay in the opening session of this conference and for the prayer that has just
been offered by President Pugmire in which a plea to our Father in heaven was made in
behalf of the faith of the young people of the Church.
</p><p>
I, too, am concerned over the faith of our young people, for that matter, of all the members of
the Church in this day when there are so many prevailing notions, ideas, and philosophies. I
have realized for a long time the need of spiritual protection, protection in the teachings that
we give to our young people in our organizations, to save them from the false doctrines and
teachings of the world.
</p><p>
About three days ago I received a letter from one of my very dearest friends, a brother who is
a teacher and who has been a teacher for nearly a half century, one who sat in the councils of
the Church in stakes of Zion and in whom I have a great deal of confidence.  He expressed in
his letter his solicitation for our young people, and in fact, for all the members of the Church
and the need of giving them proper protection and guidance in the teachings that are placed
before them.
</p><p>
I copied from his letter one paragraph, and asked him if I might use it. He said I might, and I
am going to read it to you: 
</p><p>
"There are in our community, and I suspect in other places, men who are instructing in our
quorums and other organizations who teach false doctrine, and the craziest imaginations, and
almost invariably they are brethren who are not in line.  They have brilliant, trained minds,
sometimes with pleasing, influential personalities, but lacking the spirit of truth that comes by
obedience.  You cannot give what you do not possess.  In my humble opinion only those who
believe in, and can prove their teachings by their works, should be instructing in our quorums
and other organizations."
</p><p>
That remark of his I fully endorse, and so I am expressing these thoughts particularly to our
bishops, presidents of stakes, superintendents of Sunday Schools and Mutuals, and those who
have charge of priesthood quorums, and the other organizations of the Church, to see to it that
in the choosing of teachers they use wisdom and seek for the guidance of the Spirit of the
Lord that these men spoken of here in this communication, brilliant, outstanding personalities,
but without faith, are not called to teach in our Sunday Schools, our Mutual Improvement
Associations, and in the priesthood quorums of the Church. We want men who are trained in
the principles of the gospel and who have faith and a testimony of the truth. We have them.
</p><p>
Because a man has great schooling, is educated according to the ideas of the world, is not
sufficient reason why he should be called to take charge of a class in any of the organizations
or priesthood quorums within the Church. Now, if he has scholastic ability and training, and
along with it has faith in the principles of the gospel and in the mission of the Lord Jesus
Christ, and of the Prophet Joseph Smith, all well and good.  But if he is filled with all kinds
of philosophy and notions and cannot accept the doctrines in the standard works of the
Church, we do not want him, whether it is in our auxiliaries or the priesthood, or in our
seminaries or institutes, that are given for the teaching of religious principles and to instill
faith in the hearts of our young people.
</p><p>
"Remember," the Lord has said, "the worth of souls is great in the sight of God; 
</p><p>
"For, behold, the Lord your Redeemer suffered death in the flesh; wherefore he suffered the
pain of all men, that all men might repent and come unto him.
</p><p>
"And he hath risen again from the dead, that he might bring all men unto him, on conditions
of repentance.
</p><p>
"And how great is his joy in the soul that repenteth!
</p><p>
"Wherefore, you are called to cry repentance unto this people.
</p><p>
"And if it so be that you should labor all your days in crying repentance unto this people, and
bring, save it be one soul unto me, how great shall be your joy with him in the kingdom of
my Father!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/10-15#10">D&amp;C 18:10-15</a>).
</p><p>
In the early days of the Church men came out of the world and received the testimony of the
gospel, but they had been trained in the traditions of the world, the religious world, and they
brought in with them some of those religious notions.  The Lord had to
correct them, and he said: 
</p><p>
"Let us reason even as a man reasoneth one with another face to face.
</p><p>
"Now, when a man reasoneth he is understood of man, because he reasoneth as a man; even
so will I, the Lord, reason with you that you may understand.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I the Lord ask you this question&mdash;unto what were ye ordained?
</p><p>
"To preach my gospel by the Spirit, even the Comforter which was sent forth to teach the
truth.
</p><p>
"And then received ye spirits which ye could not understand, and received them to be of God;
and in this are ye justified?
</p><p>
"Behold ye shall answer this question yourselves; nevertheless, I will be merciful unto you; he
that is weak among you hereafter shall be made strong.
</p><p>
"Verily I say unto you, he that is ordained of me and sent forth to preach the word of truth by
the Comforter, in the Spirit of truth, doth he preach it by the spirit of truth or some other
way?
</p><p>
"And if it be by some other way it is not of God.
</p><p>
"And again, he that receiveth the word of truth, doth he receive it by the Spirit of truth or
some other way?
</p><p>
"If it be some other way it is not of God.
</p><p>
"Therefore, why is it that ye cannot understand and know, that he that receiveth the word by
the Spirit of truth receiveth it as it is preached by the Spirit of truth?
</p><p>
"Wherefore, he that preacheth and he that receiveth, understand one another, and both are
edified and rejoice together.
</p><p>
"And that which doth not edify is not of God, and is darkness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/11-23#11">D&amp;C 50:11-23</a>).
</p><p>
It makes no difference who the teacher is, if he teaches false doctrine, if he teaches that which
has been condemned by the Lord, that is contrary to what is written in the revelations given
to the Church, then he should not teach.
</p><p>
In the forty-second section of the Doctrine and Covenants the Lord declares that he who hath
not the Spirit shall not teach (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/14#14">D&amp;C 42:14</a>).
I call upon you brethren in the stakes and in the wards to be
alert to find men who have faith in their hearts and a love of the truth of the gospel of Jesus
Christ and do not choose men simply because they have a personality or worldly wisdom.
Find if they have in their hearts a love of divine truth. If a man cannot accept the revelations
in the Bible, in the Book of Mormon, the Doctrine and Covenants, the Pearl of Great Price,
which we have received as standards, if he has reservations in his mind in regard to the things
that are there recorded, which have come to us by the word of the Lord, then he ought not be
teaching in any organization, any class, anywhere in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us one and all, guide us in righteousness, help us through the study of the
scriptures to know his will, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
