<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Scientific Proof for the Word of Wisdom</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph F. Merrill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph F. Merrill, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 135-141</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren and Sisters:
</p><p>
Conferences of this kind are primarily for members of the Church, but nonmembers are
welcome to attend the public sessions and of course to listen to the broadcast proceedings.
However, it is to members that most of us who speak direct our remarks. This I shall do
during the few minutes I occupy.
</p><p>
A PRACTICAL RELIGION
</p><p>
We teach that our religion is a very practical one and, being a way of life, touches every
phase of our daily living. We believe with the Apostle James that faith without works is dead.
We also believe with the Apostle Paul that ". . . by grace are ye saved through faith; and that
not of yourselves: it is the gift of God: Not of works, lest any man should boast." Some
readers seem to stop here, but let us read the next verse which says:
</p><p>
For we are his workmanship, created in Christ Jesus unto good works, which God hath before
ordained that we should walk in them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/8-10#8">Eph. 2:8-10</a>).
</p><p>
This statement of Paul's is in harmony with that made by Jesus in his great Sermon on the
Mount, when he said:
</p><p>
Wherefore by their fruits ye shall know them. Not every one that saith unto me, Lord, Lord,
shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father, which is in
heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/20-21#20">Matt. 7:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul also wrote, as you also know, these words:
</p><p>
Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the spirit of God dwelleth in you? If any
man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy, which
temple ye are (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
A LAW OF HEALTH
</p><p>
As a means of preserving our bodies from certain types of defilement (destruction) the Lord
gave to the Church in its very beginning, and to the human family generally, what has been
properly called a law of health, better known among us as the Word of Wisdom. Qualified
specialists in the field of science and medicine have said that food and drinks are the things
that have more to do with bodily health than any other ordinary factor. So in recent years the
science of dietetics&mdash;the science and art of feeding&mdash;has come into prominence and is based
upon an immense amount of experimentation and research. The health of the individual and
the health of the people in mass are extremely important, not only to the individuals
themselves but also to the public. Hence civil governments, private humanitarian
organizations, the Church, etc., are vitally concerned with problems of health.
</p><p>
It is my purpose now, however, to make some remarks relative to only one of the many
problems in the big field of things that affect human health. In section eighty-nine of the
D&amp;C we find a revelation given to the Prophet Joseph Smith in February 1833, less than
three years after the organization of the Church
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/1-21#1">D&amp;C 89:1-21</a>),
in which abstinence from wine, strong drinks,
tobacco, and hot drinks is enjoined, because they are not good for man. By hot drinks was
meant primarily tea and coffee, though subsequent researches found that any drinks at high
temperatures, such as hot water and soups, are harmful. The ideas voiced in the Word of
Wisdom were expressed in words having the meaning current at the time. In those days hot
drinks were commonly understood to be tea and coffee. The Church now interprets the words,
wine and strong drinks, as meaning all alcoholic beverages, of which there are many varieties.
</p><p>
In passing, it may be well to remark that the revelation on the Word of Wisdom was given at
a time when scientific men knew but little, if anything, about basic facts of the science of
dietetics. Since those days, and within the last fifty years, a vast amount of research has been
done, and that pertinent to matters spoken of in the Word of Wisdom is confirmatory of the
truths therein revealed. This fact should give joy and satisfaction to all Saints, for it is
irrefutable testimony of the divinity of that great document. Time will not permit me now to
go into detail concerning this testimony. I repeat, however, that a multitude of scientifically
discovered facts support the Word of Wisdom, and, so far as I know, none refute it.
</p><p>
MISLEADING ADVERTISEMENTS
</p><p>
Among these is the irrefutable fact that liquor and tobacco are not good for man. Science,
experience, and revelation are in agreement on this statement. Then, why do people continue
to use liquor and tobacco? Ask Satan, he knows. Satan is a deceiver, the father of lies, the
inspiration of avaricious men engaged in promoting evils and cunning designs calculated to
mislead the people, particularly the youth, into habits of drinking and smoking. To this end
huge sums of money are continually spent in advertising propaganda material, much of it
honeycombed with misleading and partially or wholly falsifying statements. A few years
before the great global war began, an able investigator found that more than sixty million
dollars was spent annually in the United States for advertising cigarettes and alcoholic
beverages. Since all of us have some idea of the power of money, is it any wonder that
publicity agencies that accept liquor and tobacco advertisements, such as newspapers,
magazines, and radios, are opposed to prohibition?
</p><p>
Let me say here that smoking and drinking in this country have become so general that the
enormous sum of ten and one-half billion dollars was spent during 1944 for liquor and
tobacco, so it was authoritatively reported.
</p><p>
I have just said that science, experience, and revelation agree that liquor and tobacco are not
good for man. Let me specify a little.
</p><p>
INJURIOUS EFFECTS OF TOBACCO
</p><p>
Concerning the use of tobacco, it affects injuriously the heart and circulatory system, the
lungs and respiratory system, the brain and mental powers, the nervous system, the kidneys
and elimination organs, the muscular system, etc., thus weakening the body with the result
that it is less resistant to diseases of various kinds. Recently there came from the press a new
book relative to tobacco and its effects written by Dr. Frank Leighton Wood, entitled
<i>What You Should Know About Tobacco</i>. Dr. Irving Fisher of Yale University wrote a foreword for
the book in which he said:
</p><p>
The tobacco problem has for years engaged my attention, both as to its economic and hygienic
aspects. As treasurer of the Committee for the Scientific Study of the Tobacco Problem and as
chairman of the Hygienic Reference Board of the Life Extension Institute, which has
contributed more perhaps than any other agency toward solving the basic problem of tobacco,
I have had unusual opportunities to become familiar with this many-sided problem. . . The
evidence now exists sufficient to show that no one who smokes can achieve the best of which
he or she is capable, whether this be a foot race, a prize fight, a golf game, tightrope walking,
a rifle score, bombing the Reich, writing, speaking, singing,
acting, performing on a violin, piano, or typewriter, attainment of health, strength, endurance,
working power, beauty, glamour, or any other excellence on which men and women set their
hearts. Prize fighters and acrobats know this. It is time that those ambitious in all other lines
of work should learn it.
</p><p>
Relative to the effect on the muscular system I give this illustration found in the 1938 edition
of the standard book <i>How to Live</i> by Fisher and Emerson:
</p><p>
Some years ago Dr. W. P. Lombard, professor of physiology in the University of Michigan,
conducted a series of observations for the purpose of determining the influence of smoking
upon muscular work. He reported: "The record of these successive observations shows that the
effects of one cigar of moderate strength was to lessen the work of which the subject was
capable from seventy-five foot-pounds to fifteen foot-pounds, the number of times that the
weight could be lifted being reduced from eighty-six to twelve, over eighty percent. These
figures indicate how seriously tobacco cuts down one's strength and endurance!"
</p><p>
In his book, after pointing out many deleterious effects of the use of tobacco, Dr. Wood says:
</p><p>
There is an aspect of the tobacco habit which, to some, is more important than its effect on
life itself. A large number of people, including many doctors, are quite indifferent concerning
their health or the possibility of dying prematurely. When confronted with facts concerning
the life-shortening effects of tobacco or other habit-forming drugs, they may accept them but,
in a spirit of bravado, may add that they would rather live their fifty years than exist for one
hundred. In saying this they assume that the smoker lives a more happy, contented, and useful
life than the nonsmoker. But does he? In the following chapters we shall show that, on the
average, not only does the smoker die at a much earlier age than the nonsmoker but that he is
more often afflicted with painful and disabling diseases of long duration and that in addition
to this, he experiences various minor ills, such as annoying coughs, hoarseness, rawness of the
throat, heartburn, shortness of breath, and many other disagreeable symptoms or diseases
which are peculiar to those who use tobacco in any form. We shall show that he cannot excel
in sports, as most people already know; that he will be handicapped in acquiring an education
and for this reason may be likewise handicapped in satisfying his other aspirations in life. We
shall show that even his character may be unfavorably affected. . . . We shall show that girls
and boys and men and women who begin to smoke with the avowed intention of smoking in
moderation and quitting the habit when they find that it is becoming harmful to them, nearly
always smoke to a great excess and seldom quit the habit. No one can be at his best if he uses
tobacco any more than the boxer, the runner, or the ball player can, for the use of this drug
interferes with the blood supply, not only of the heart muscles but of every organ and part of
the body, including the brain, the liver, the stomach, and the reproductive organs, as we shall
show.
</p><p>
The use of tobacco shortens life. This fact was demonstrated satisfactorily to the whole
scientific world on the appearance of a report by Dr. Raymond Pearl of Johns Hopkins
University, published in the journal Science, March 4, 1938. Dr. Pearl and his associates made
complete life tables on 6,813 white men between the ages of thirty to seventy. He divided this
group into three&mdash;2,095 nonusers of tobacco; 2,814 moderate smokers; 1,905 heavy smokers.
He found that between the ages of thirty and seventy the heavy smoker died, on an average,
ten years younger than nonsmokers; that moderate smokers, on an average, also died from one
to five years sooner. And as I have already quoted, smokers are less free from bodily ailments
than are nonsmokers. So I repeat, the fact is that smokers die earlier than nonsmokers.
</p><p>
May I quote a few words from the late Dr. A. L. Warner, who devoted a long life to the
study of the evil effects upon the mind, body, and character of tobacco and was widely known
for his writings on the subject? He wrote:
</p><p>
A large majority of the young men of the United States have used tobacco. We are breeding a
race of tobacco degenerates. The children inherit the narcotic craving from tobacco-using
ancestors, making them as they grow older, easy addicts to tobacco, liquor, and other dope.
Juvenile crime, vice, and degeneracy, steadily increase with the increased use of tobacco. The
average age of crime in the United States has come down in sixteen years from age
twenty-eight to nineteen.
</p><p>
Extremely regrettable as it is, young women in the last few years have taken up smoking and
the habit is rapidly growing among them. From an article written by Alonzo L. Baker,
associate editor of the magazine <i>Good Health</i>, and entitled "Should Women Smoke?" I make
a few quotations as follows:
</p><p>
Here are two facts that should be borne in mind by every girl and woman in America:
</p><p>
1. Tobacco harms women more physically than it does men.
</p><p>
2. Tobacco does more damage to the race through mothers than through fathers.
</p><p>
Naming some bad effects, he continues:
</p><p>
A vital question is the effect of tobacco in pregnancy. These two facts are indisputable: (1)
Nicotine is one of the few substances that passes through the placenta to the fetus; (2)
Nicotine passes to the infant in its mother's milk. In view of the virulence of the poison that
nicotine is, damage both to the unborn child and to the nursing child is inevitable when he is
nicotinized before and after birth. . . The smoking habit has become widespread among
women of recent years only in America. Preliminary reports . . . thus far made indicate that
the number of still-births and premature children born to habitually smoking mothers is
markedly higher than for mothers who are abstainers from tobacco. . . .Just cause for alarm is
the rapidly growing number of girls who form the tobacco habit before they have come to
physical maturity. Smoking on the part of girls during their teen years is nothing less than a
tragedy, for those are the years when nicotine does its greatest damage to the growing nerve
and glandular systems of the female body.
</p><p>
Dr. D. H. Kress, another well-known objector to smoking, wrote on this particular point
saying:
</p><p>
For both man and wife to be addicted to smoke inhalation is destructive of everything that is
good. Children born to such a pair had better never been born; . . . anything that is injurious
to the child after its birth is equally injurious to it before its birth when indulged in by the
pregnant mother.
</p><p>
United States Surgeon General Hugh S. Cummings once wrote:
</p><p>
When women generally contract the smoking habit (as they are now doing) the entire nation
will suffer. The physical tone of the whole nation will be lowered. This is one of the most
evil influences in American life today. The habit harms a woman more than it does a man.
</p><p>
President Charles W. Eliot of Harvard University once in talking to his freshman class on the
subject of tobacco gave the following advice:
</p><p>
My dear freshmen, I want you to remember that tobacco in any form destroys the brain, and
you have none to spare.
</p><p>
ALCOHOL A CURSE
</p><p>
Time will not permit my saying much relative to liquor. It is perhaps unnecessary to do so
since the effects of drinking are more or less widely known. However, I ask your indulgence
while I give two or three quotations from keen observers.
<i>The Journal of the American Medical Association</i> said:
</p><p>
Alcohol is a poison inherently, absolutely, essentially; in a drop or in a gallon, in all
quantities and in every quantity, it is a poison. Plainly the quantity cannot effect its chemical
constitution.
</p><p>
And from the eloquent pen of the late keen-minded Robert G. Ingersoll, who knew how to
describe alcohol in all its hellish effects on humanity, I give the following:
</p><p>
Alcohol is the blood of the gambler, the inspiration of the burglar, the stimulus of the
highwayman, and the support of the midnight incendiary. It suggests the lie and countenances
the liar, condones the thief, and esteems the blasphemer. It violates obligation, reverences
fraud, turns love to hate, scorns virtue and innocence. It incites the father to butcher his
helpless offspring, and the child to sharpen the patricidal ax.
</p><p>
Alcohol burns up men, consumes women, destroys life, curses God, and despises heaven. It
suborns witnesses, nurses perversity, defiles the jury box, and stains the judicial ermine. It
bribes voters, disqualifies votes, corrupts elections, pollutes our institutions, endangers the
government, degrades the citizen, debases the legislature, dishonors the statesman, and disarms
the patriot. It brings shame, not honor; terror, not safety; despair, not hope; misery, not
happiness; and, with the malevolence of a fiend, calmly surveys the frightful desolation, and
reveling in havoc, poisons felicity, destroys peace and ruins morals, wipes out national honor,
curses the world, and laughs at the ruin it has wrought. It does that and more. It murders the
soul; it is the sum of all villainy, the father of all crime, the mother of all abominations, the
devil's best friend, and God's worst enemy.
</p><p>
And from the inspired voice of the Church&mdash;that of the First Presidency&mdash;the following was
said three years ago in this conference:
</p><p>
Drink brings cruelty into the home; it walks arm in arm with poverty; its companions are
disease and plague; it puts chastity to flight; it knows neither honesty nor fair dealing; it is a
total stranger to truth; it drowns consciousness, it is the bodyguard of evil; it curses all who
touch it.
</p><p>
Drink has brought more woe and misery, broken more hearts, wrecked more homes,
committed more crimes, filled more coffins than all the wars the world has suffered.
</p><p>
Yes, in accordance with the divine will, the Church stands absolutely and continuously
opposed to smoking and to the consumption of all kinds of alcoholic beverages. It persistently
calls to its members and to all others to abstain from the use of these body, mind, and soul
destroying poisons. May the Lord give us all the desire and the strength to do so, I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
