<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Individual Commitment in Sustaining Freedom</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 96-98</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We have already had quoted the passage of scripture with which I desire to start. "But blessed
are your eyes, for they see: and your ears, for they hear"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/16#16">Matt. 13:16</a>). And Matthew
further tells us that "The light of the body is the eye: if therefore thine eye be single, thy
whole body shall be full of light.
</p><p>
"But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of darkness. If therefore the light that is
in thee be darkness, how great is that darkness!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/22-23#22">Matt. 6:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
Matthew further says: "Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments,
and shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven: but whosoever
shall do and teach them, the same shall be called great in the kingdom of heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/19#19">Matt. 5:19</a>).
</p><p>
To us the prophecy of Daniel has great significance, as was pointed out by President McKay
in his inspired message to the world yesterday. Daniel says, "And in the days of these kings
shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom, which shall never be destroyed: and the kingdom
shall not be left to other people, but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms,
and it shall stand for ever.
</p><p>
". . . and the dream is certain, and the interpretation thereof sure"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/44-45#44">Dan. 2:44-45</a>).
</p><p>
The world needs the restored Church and kingdom of Jesus Christ, of which David spoke.
The world needs the help of those who have recognized and received the gospel of the
kingdom. The world needs their inspiration and active participation in the affairs of life. We
are an inspired people. That I know as well as I know that I live. We are responsible for the
proper use of this inspiration. This inspiration is not confined to our spiritual lives but carries
over into all temporal responsibilities, and included therein is our moral, our civic, our
political, our social, our financial responsibilities. We stand ready to exercise this divine
guidance together with the power of our priesthood in behalf of a neighbor, as well as in our
own behalf. We look upon the children of our Heavenly Father as our brothers and sisters, no
matter where they live, or what they believe, or what their ancestry may be. We cannot expect
to do our full duty as we are inspired to do unless we can live and work in
an environment of love, of peace, of freedom&mdash;freedom at home and throughout the world.
</p><p>
Plato has put into words that the spirit of freedom is not a matter of laws and constitutions.
"Only he is free," Plato says, "who realizes the divine order within himself, the true standard
by which a man can steer himself." And I say true standards, ideals that lift life up, mark the
way of true progress. Such ideals followed will never permit our light to be extinguished.
</p><p>
Pericles said: "But we regard him who holds aloof from public affairs as useless." They called
the useless man a "private" citizen, <i>idiotes</i> from which our word <i>idiot</i> comes. The citizens of
the kingdom of God should set the pattern for the citizens of the kingdoms of men.
</p><p>
A reflective Roman traveling in Greece in the second century, A.D. said, "None ever throve
under democracy save the Athenians. They had self-control and were law-abiding." That is
what Athenian education aimed at, to produce men who would be able to maintain a
self-governed state because they were themselves self-governed, self-controlled, self-reliant. It
is said of the Athenians, "We yield to none in independence of spirit and complete
self-reliance."
</p><p>
This is not much different from conditions found in the Church in the Meridian of Time.
Brother James L. Barker, in his history of the early Church, which is soon to be printed,
writes: "In the Church organized by the Savior two important principles were
reconciled&mdash;divine authority and individual liberty."
</p><p>
The Father sent his Son, Jesus Christ, into the world; the Son chose his apostles, gave them
authority, and they chose the presiding elders, bishops, and other local officers, always
seeking the guidance and approval of the Holy Spirit. In the Church of Jesus Christ there
must always be this divine leadership. Any church without his leadership is not his, as
President Stephen L Richards so beautifully demonstrated yesterday. However, the Lord has
always safeguarded human liberty. There can be no progress without liberty. The great
purpose of this life is that man shall gain experience and strength in freely making his own
choices. Divine guidance will be given, but man must be free to choose obedience or
disobedience, otherwise his actions have no ethical or religious value. "God has always
preserved freedom and the powers of self-government in man," wrote Irenaeus when he wrote
against heresies in the third century.
</p><p>
"The Church organization carefully safeguarded this freedom," Brother Barker continues.
"Nominations were made by authority," just as they have been made here this morning in our
presence, and in which we have participated, "but the members of the Church were given the
right to accept or reject those nominated. The Lord has never forced the acceptance of his
prophets. If the Lord sends a prophet, he will be a prophet, even if no one accepts his
message, but the Lord has at no time forced the acceptance of a prophet's message on the
people; nor has he forced a prophet on the people as president of his Church, nor a bishop on
his congregation.
</p><p>
"In the Church he organized, the members were an important part of the organization: they
were free and responsible, because the Holy Ghost was not given to their leaders, the apostles,
bishops, and elders, alone, but to every worthy member of the Church. Both leaders and
members were free to obey or disobey the inspiration of the Spirit, and both were equally
responsible for their individual choices and the consequences entailed by their choices. Thus
each member of the Church was made, in part, responsible for the government and conduct of
the Church," says Brother Barker.
</p><p>
We read in Acts of the council of Jerusalem: "Then pleased it the apostles and elders, with the
whole church, to send chosen men of their own company to Antioch . . ." and the next verse
is again repeated, "And they wrote letters by them after this manner; The apostles and elders
and brethren" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/15/22-23#22">Acts 15:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
What is our position today? Take, for example, public affairs. I read recently a comment of
one of our national statesmen, Adlai Stevenson, "Our condition has nothing to do with any
deficiency of technology or resources. It is a matter of people forgetting that
political freedom can be sustained only by continuing individual commitment." As he
continues: "The great German poet Goethe, who also lived through a crisis of freedom, said to
his generation 'What you have inherited from your fathers, earn over again for yourselves or
it will not be yours.' We inherited freedom. We seem unaware that it has to be remade and
re-earned in each generation of man."
</p><p>
Stevenson says, "The natural government of man is servitude. Tyranny is the natural pattern
of government." If that be true, it is in direct opposition to the government of God. "We do
not slip into freedom or happiness. It is strenuously sought and earned."
</p><p>
When will we realize that the very power and success of US society demand more not less
individual dedication for its citizenship. It is interesting to note that the concern of our leaders
today is not expressed in terms of security but in terms of survival. What else but individual
dedication can stay the Soviet assault on free civilization?
</p><p>
In an oft-quoted passage from Shakespeare there is a warning given which we might well
heed: 
</p><p>
"There is a tide in the affairs of men<br />
Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune; <br />
Omitted, all the voyage of their life<br />
Is bound in shallows and in miseries."
(<i>Julius Caesar</i>, Act. IV, Sc. 3).
</p><p>
When in the course of life one arrives at a fork in the way, a decision must be made and a
course selected often results in a choice that later becomes completely irrevocable. President
McKay told us yesterday of the 231,000 teachers in the Church. I say they stand as watchmen
at the crossroads to direct us aright in the course we pursue. Our decisions, once executed,
can never be erased. This is because such selections introduce a new series of conditions,
setting in motion events which cannot later be recalled. The good done, the evil accomplished,
are all there. It is a faithful axiom that he who would not when he might, shall not when he
would.
</p><p>
Happy is he who profits by the experiences of the past, like those of the Athenians in ancient
times so that he may make right decisions in the present and face the future with confidence,
divinely assured that his hope concerning things to come will have full and lasting
realizations. Faith in Jesus Christ our Lord, and obedience to his restored gospel assures
inevitably this glorious result&mdash;the enjoyment of that peace which passeth understanding
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/4/7#7">Philip. 4:7</a>) now
as in all prior time.
</p><p>
Let us all live in all that we do, guided and directed by the inspiration which comes to the
faithful as a gift of the Holy Ghost. "But blessed are your eyes, for they see: and your ears,
for they hear" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/16#16">Matt. 13:16</a>).
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us all, I pray humbly in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
