<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Responsibility of Latter-day Saints in Building for Peace</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1946, pp. 12-15</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters: With you I have listened with great interest and profit to the
address of the man who stands at the head of the Church at this time. I am always glad, with
you, to be under the leadership of inspired men. The world is hungering, I believe, for that
kind of leadership.
</p><p>
DISTURBED CONDITION OF WORLD
</p><p>
The world is in a disturbed condition. There is discouragement everywhere. No man seems to
see the end from the beginning. I have pondered in my heart for some time what my
obligation is in this state of worldly confusion. What is the obligation of my Church, the
restored Church of Christ in these latter days? Perhaps all of us have entertained such
thoughts in these unhappy days.
</p><p>
There is a world cry for peace; everybody wants peace. In newspapers, magazines, books,
from the public platform come cries for peace. As far back as I can remember, there has
never been such a worldwide appeal for peace among the children of men. Yet it begins to
look as if we are farther away from peace today than we were during the heavy and difficult
war years.
</p><p>
It is a curious commentary on human nature that men who cry for peace look upon peace as
something that may be picked as an apple from a tree, something that lies about within easy
reach of humanity. If I pick an apple from a tree, I have first planted the tree, cared for it,
watered it, brought it to maturity. Then in due time I may have the fruit.
</p><p>
So with peace. It is not a thing by itself to be picked up casually; but it is the fruit of
something precedent. Like the tree, something must be planted and nourished and cared for, if
we are to obtain peace.
</p><p>
PEACE RESULT OF OBEDIENCE TO GOSPEL
</p><p>
It is a marvel to thinking men that those who write on peace fail to understand that it can be
obtained only by the use of a body of principles which, if obeyed, in time would give us
peace. We cannot begin with peace; we must begin with the philosophy or the system which,
if accepted and honored, will lead to peace. Failure to understand that seems to be the error of
the nations at this time, of the organizations and conventions of nations, assembled in great
meetings on this side and the other side of the Atlantic. They have so far failed to touch upon
the foundations of peace, upon the issues which are the aids to peace. They clamor for the
peace they want, without yielding obedience to the methods by which that peace may be
obtained.
</p><p>
The Latter-day Saints, from the beginning of our history, have taught that the good things of
life, above all, peace, can come only through acceptance of the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ. He was the Prince of Peace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>).
He is the Prince of Peace. It is only as the men and
women of the world, all children of God, accept the gospel of the Son of God that peace shall
come to rule and reign and be established upon earth. That has been our message from the
beginning of the restoration of the gospel in this day. We still proclaim without hesitation,
that there is only one way to peace, one way to the perfect human happiness, the way of the
gospel, paved with the principles that constitute the gospel.
</p><p>
We make a further claim, brethren and sisters. It is a claim that often makes us hesitant in
stating it, because it is so vast in its meaning, in its implications. We claim that this people,
this Church, organized by God's own voice in this generation, possesses the only system of
truth containing all of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30#30">D&amp;C 1:30</a>). Then, by that token, there can be
no full peace, no complete happiness upon earth, until the men and women of the world
accept the great latter-day message. We stand humbly before this claim, I know, but it is our
claim. The Lord has said so.
</p><p>
He has said further, that the time shall come in these latter days when every ear shall hear and
every eye shall see, and every heart be penetrated by the eternal message of the gospel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/2#2">D&amp;C 1:2</a>), and
that this great message shall be delivered by "the mouths of my disciples, whom I have
chosen in these last days"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4#4">D&amp;C 1:4</a>),
those spoken of by President Smith in his opening
address to this conference.
</p><p>
OUR OBLIGATION TO TEACH THE TRUTH
</p><p>
Now, then, if all this be true, in my thinking about these things, there lies
my obligation. It is my divine obligation somehow, through my feeble efforts, and through
yours, and through all the members of the Church, to teach all the world the truth of the
restored gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ. I must try to plant this truth in the hearts of men and
women. I must contribute every day in my way, as best I can, toward the teaching of the truth
which alone can bring peace to our unhappy world. It is a tremendous obligation when we
view it as a whole; but with the help of the Lord easy to meet, if we take the tasks one by
one, always keeping our obligation in mind, as we travel through life.
</p><p>
Missionary work must grow in foreign fields, as never before; missionary work at home must
increase as never before. We shall employ every modern device&mdash;the telephone, telegraph, radio,
printing press, the short wave systems as mentioned by President Smith, and the other devices
that are coming. We shall use them all in our attempt to win men and women from
wickedness to righteousness, from untruth or near truth to full and complete truth which is the
gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
This Church is not merely for me and for you who are in the Church. I must begin with
myself, undoubtedly. My own salvation comes first; but unless I give of my strength to the
winning of other souls for God, my own salvation will be incomplete. That applies to all of
us. It cannot be otherwise if we follow the message given us this morning by our prophet and
leader. We have a calling, not merely to build the Church of Christ, and to save ourselves
therein, but also a commission to save the whole world. We are, as it were, set apart,
consecrated for that great purpose. All of Israel must remember, every man or woman who
enters the waters of baptism must keep in mind, and every child that comes into the Church
must be taught that by the ordinance of baptism we accept the great and divine commission to
serve the Lord in building his Church. It will then be easy to keep the commandments of
God, to lay aside or meet courageously the temptations that face us. To stand alone, saying
selfishly, "I have received the gospel; it is good to be a Latter-day Saint" will not be doing
our duty; but, when we say, "Now, I have received this great blessing. I shall pass it on to
others"; there comes the flowering in the hearts of men of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
COMMISSION TO SUPPLANT EVIL WITH GOOD
</p><p>
We are not as other people; we are different. We are humble acceptors of the truth, yielders
to God's will and word, under a commission to change the whole world, from evil to good. It
is a great commission. It has been our commission from the beginning.
</p><p>
The great men who led this Church from the beginning have voiced this commission or
calling to which we are consecrated. When we talk about this commission, about our duty or
obligation, let us not forget the lesson of these mighty men. In the midst of confusion
let us look back to the labors of those who have gone before us, our fathers
who founded the Church under God's direction, who toiled from city to city, across the plains
and the desert to build a commonwealth. They left behind them, not necessarily the heritage
of their methods, for the world has changed, but the heritage of their undaunted, unchanging
spirit. We must be as eager to fulfill God's word as they were in their day. We must do that,
my brethren and sisters, if we are to fulfill and meet our full obligation in this difficult age.
To those who catch the spirit of this obligation, of this commission, of this calling to a great
people will come strength to resist, as I have said, the temptations of the world. It will be
easy to reject the cocktail; the cigar can be laid aside easily; to divide with the Lord in tithing
will not seem difficult; to converse with the Lord in prayer will be a joyful experience. Men
are changed and transformed who enter into partnership with God in helping to establish his
great cause upon the face of the earth.
</p><p>
GOD'S WORK IS ETERNAL
</p><p>
This work is not an ordinary cause. It is God's cause. It is not a cause for a day. It is a cause
for the eternities, both gone and coming. We are working out an eternal project, you and I, all
of us. We of today must do as well as those who went before us, a bit better perhaps, for new
opportunities have come to us in our day. We should do better in this Church in the cause of
righteousness than grandfather or great-grandfather. More light has come, more opportunity is
given, more means are at our command. We should do better. And we all, especially the
youth of the Church, should dream about the future of the Church, and give our own earnest
endeavors to the fulfilment of our commissions.
</p><p>
These are the thoughts that have been running through my mind, and crystallized during
President Smith's address this morning.
</p><p>
I want to bear this testimony to you that as I have traveled through the world, and while I
have not traveled as much as President Smith, I have traveled far and wide, I have found
thousands of people not acquainted with the gospel; good, clean, wholesome people, walking
in darkness, who are looking for light, who, misled by untruths, are looking for truth, and
unhappy because of the untruths handed to them by tradition. There are a vast congregation of
men and women throughout the world, in every country, of every creed and color, waiting for
us and our great message. The field is ripe unto harvest.
</p><p>
Now I pray, my brethren and sisters, that we may rise in our strength, the strength of Zion,
and fill and fulfill our commission. Let us forget at least a part of the time the daily duties that
hold us down, and give ourselves to thoughts and actions, in building actively under our great
obligation, the great latter-day kingdom of God, the Almighty Father. May it be so, I pray in
the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
