<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">&ldquo;Blessed Is the Nation whose God Is the Lord&rdquo;</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 11-16</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"Blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord, and the people whom he hath chosen for his
own inheritance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/33/12#12">Ps. 33:12</a>).
So said the Psalmist. This saying it would be well for the
people of America to remember.
</p><p>
OUR COUNTRY UNDER DIVINE GUIDANCE
</p><p>
No nation has been more greatly blessed than has the United States. We live in a land which
has been called choice above all other lands by divine pronouncement
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/19#19">2 Ne. 10:19</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/7#7">Ether 2:7</a>).
The Lord has watched
over it with a jealous care and has commanded its people to serve Him lest His wrath be
kindled against them and His blessings be withdrawn. Our government came into existence
through divine guidance. The inspiration of the Lord rested upon the patriots who established
it, and inspired them through the dark days of their struggle for independence and through the
critical period which followed that struggle when they framed our glorious Constitution which
guarantees to all the self-evident truth proclaimed in the Declaration of Independence, "that all
men are created equal: that they are endowed by their Creator with certain inalienable rights:
that among these are life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness." That is to say, it is the right
of every soul to have equal and unrestricted justice before the law, equal rights to worship
according to the dictates of conscience and to labor according to the individual inclinations,
independently of coercion or compulsion. That this might be, the Lord has said, "I established
the Constitution of this land, by the hands of wise men whom I raised up unto this very
purpose and redeemed the land by the shedding of blood"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/80#80">D&amp;C 101:80</a>).
</p><p>
The founders of this nation were men of humble faith. Many of them saw in vision a glorious
destiny for our government, provided we would faithfully continue in the path of justice and
right with contrite spirits and humble hearts, accepting the divine truths which are found in
the Holy Scriptures. The appeal of these men has echoed down the passing years with
prophetic warning to the succeeding generations, pleading with them to be true to all these
standards which lay at the foundation of our government. This country was founded as a
Christian nation, with the acceptance of Jesus Christ as the Redeemer of the world. It was
predicted by a prophet of old that this land would be a land of liberty and it would be
fortified against all other nations as long as its inhabitants would serve Jesus Christ; but
should they stray from the Son of God, it would cease to be a land of liberty and His anger
be kindled against them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/1/7#7">2 Ne. 1:7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>).
</p><p>
DANGER IN FORSAKING RIGHTEOUSNESS
</p><p>
It is a sad reflection, but one that cannot be successfully refuted, that we have forgotten the
admonition which has come down to us, just as Israel forgot the commandments which would
have blessed that nation in the land of Canaan forever had they been observed. In forsaking
these laws we stand in danger of punishment as the people of Israel stood in danger of
punishment because they forsook the Lord and failed to repent and accept the warnings of
their prophets.
</p><p>
Since the days of our fathers there has been a gradual straying froth the sacred teachings
which we have received. In later years we have, in fact, fulfilled the prophecy of Paul:
</p><p>
This know also, that in the last days perilous times shall come.<br />
For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers,
disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,<br />
Without natural affection, trucebreakers, false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those
that are good,<br />
Traitors, heady, highminded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God;<br />
Having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/1-5#1">2 Tim. 3:1-5</a>).
</p><p>
This is a very severe indictment made by Paul; but can we honestly deny the charge? The Ten
Commandments (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3-17#3">Ex. 20:3-17</a>)
are just as much the word of the Lord today as they were when written by
the finger of God on Sinai. They have not been abrogated; they have not been modified and
are binding upon the people with all the force which accompanied them when first uttered. As
sure as we live, we are to be judged by them and all other divine commandments, for God
will not permit us to mock Him and hold His laws in contempt with impunity
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/7#7">Gal. 6:7</a>).
</p><p>
Have not the people of this land ignored the first commandment?
</p><p>
Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy
mind.<br />
This is the first and great commandment.<br />
And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.<br />
On these two commandments hang all the law and the prophets
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37-40#37">Matt. 22:37-40</a>).
</p><p>
In other words, all that has been revealed for the salvation of man from the beginning to our
own time is circumscribed, included in, and a part of these two great laws. If we love the
Lord with all the heart, with all the soul, and with all the mind, and our neighbors as
ourselves (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36-39#36">Matt. 22:36-39</a>),
then there is nothing more to be desired. Then we will be in harmony with the total
of sacred law. If we were willing to live in harmony with these two great
commandments&mdash;and we must do so eventually if we are worthy to live in the presence of
God&mdash;then wickedness, jealousy, ambition, covetousness, bloodshed, and all sin of every
nature would be banished from the earth. Then would come a day of eternal peace and
happiness. What a glorious day that would be! We have been endowed with sufficient reason
to know that such a state is most desirable and would establish among men the Fatherhood of
God and the perfect brotherhood of man.
</p><p>
But as a people have we not forsaken these commandments? Can we say that we love the
Lord with all the soul? Can we say we are as Solicitous for the welfare of our neighbor as we
are for our own? As we look about us, we cannot fail to see the selfishness, the unbelief,
blasphemy, and love of evil which are found everywhere among the people, all revealing to
us our weakness and unwillingness to obey these laws. We are not ignorant of the things of
God, for they have been made known to us from the days of Adam until now and are
recorded in the Holy Scriptures. Messengers from the presence of God have been sent to the
earth from the beginning to establish in the hearts of men and to reveal to them all that is
essential for man's salvation. If any among us is ignorant of these things, it is due to wilful
rebellion. The Son of God came to earth Himself to show us by example the way to eternal
life, and was Himself free from all sin. We cannot excuse ourselves for the violation of the
laws of God on the ground of ignorance. With all of these commandments before us, we are
moral agents responsible to the Most High and under obligation to be obedient. Nevertheless,
because of the love of the things of the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/2/15#15">1 Jn. 2:15</a>)
and the enticing influence of the powers of
darkness, we have departed from the strait path which leads to life and which our Lord has
said few men find because they love darkness rather than light, their deeds being evil
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/19#19">John 3:19</a>). We
have permitted the philosophies of men, which deny the divinity of Jesus Christ and mock at
the sacred ordinances of the gospel, to enter into our schools, our businesses, and our homes,
thus weakening our faith and our reverence for our Creator. We have forgotten that man was
created in the image of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26-27#26">Gen. 1:26-27</a>),
that the scriptures declare that we are His offspring
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/29#29">Acts 17:29</a>), and that we
are commanded to seek first the kingdom of God and His righteousness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
LAWS OF GOD TO BE OBEYED
</p><p>
Are we keeping our bodies clean and free from all contaminating influences? We are
informed that no unclean thing can inherit the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/40/26#26">Alma 40:26</a>), that "he that is unjust, let him
be unjust still: and he which is filthy, let him be filthy still: and he that is righteous, let him
be righteous still: and he that is holy, let him be holy still"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/22/11#11">Rev. 22:11</a>). So it will be
in the judgment. Every man shall receive a reward according to his works
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/27#27">Matt. 16:27</a>). Unfortunately
there are many selfish, greedy agencies at work playing upon the credulity and ignorance of
the people, enticing them to indulge in many evil habits which weaken and impair their
vitality and drive them from the spiritual guidance promised them through their humility and
faith.
</p><p>
Have we observed the Sabbath day and kept it holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>)? Is it not a fact that we have looked upon
this law as being obsolete; something suited, perhaps to the needs of a primitive people, who,
like little children, need special care, but not necessary for us to observe in this modern world
of superior wisdom? Is it not the fact that through the length and breadth of our land, this
sacred commandment has been treated, and is being treated, with absolute contempt? Have we
not made of it a day of pleasure, of indulgence, and have we not lost all love for its
sacredness? How can we expect the Lord to bless us when we ignore so universally this holy
law?
</p><p>
Have we not forgotten to pray and to thank the Lord for His mercies and for His guidance in
all that we do? If at times we have been requested to seek the help of the Lord in this great
struggle which has deluged the world, have we prayed in the true spirit of prayer? What good
does it do for us to petition the Lord, if we have no intention of keeping His commandments?
Such praying is hollow mockery and an insult before the throne of grace. How dare we
presume to expect a favorable answer if such is the case? "Seek ye the Lord while he may be
found, call ye upon him while he is near: Let the wicked forsake his way, and the unrighteous
man his thoughts: and let him return unto the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to
our God, for he will abundantly pardon." So said Isaiah
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/55/6-7#6">Isa. 55:6-7</a>). But is not the Lord
always near when we petition Him? Verily no! He has said, "They were slow to hearken unto
the voice of the Lord their God; therefore, the Lord their God is slow to hearken unto their
prayers, to answer them in the day of their trouble. In the day of their peace they esteemed
lightly my counsel; but, in the day of their trouble, of necessity they feel after me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/7-8#7">D&amp;C 101:7-8</a>).
If we draw near unto Him, He will draw near unto us
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/63#63">D&amp;C 88:63</a>), and we will not be forsaken;
but if we do not draw near to Him, we have no promise that He will answer us in our
rebellion.
</p><p>
Are we free from all covetousness? Do we refrain from desiring to possess unjustly the
property of others? Have we permitted the lusts of the flesh and the desire to possess that
which is not our honest due, to canker our souls?
</p><p>
Have we not come to look upon the sacred and holy bonds of matrimony as merely a civil
contract which may be broken at will on the slightest whim by either covenanting party? Has
not divorce become a blot upon the nation? How can we reconcile our practices and the
statutes of many states with the commandments given us by Jesus Christ in relation to the
marriage covenant? The home is the foundation of civilization and vital to the safety of our
country. When the home is destroyed, the foundation of the country is in danger of
destruction. Such has been the history of the past among nations. Marriage is a sacred
ordinance instituted before death came into the world when the Lord said, "It is not good that
the man should be alone; I will make him an help meet for him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>).
</p><p>
SUFFERING COMES THROUGH LOSS OF BLESSINGS
</p><p>
Throughout our land we see the tragedy of broken homes, fathers and mothers separated,
children denied the natural affections. Children have a right to the blessings coming from this
sacred union. They are entitled to the love and care of faithful parents and the happiness and
devotion which true worship brings. When these blessings are lost, the whole community
suffers and the integrity of government is weakened. It is a shame and a disgrace that so
much evil is coming out of broken homes, and this comes largely because we have forgotten
God and our obligations to serve and honor Him. Truly we have much room for repentance
and a return to the simple worship of true Christianity.
</p><p>
THE NEED FOR RELIGION
</p><p>
President Calvin Coolidge once said:
</p><p>
Our government rests upon religion. It is from that source that we derive our reverence for
truth and justice, for equality and liberality and for the rights of mankind. Unless the people
believe in these principles they cannot believe in our government. There are only two main
theories of government in the world. One rests on righteousness and the other on force One
appeals to reason, the other appeals to the sword. One is exemplified in a republic, the other
is represented by a despotism.
</p><p>
The government of a country never gets ahead of the religion of a country. There is no way
by which we can substitute the authority of law for the virtue of men. Of course we can help
to restrain the vicious and furnish a fair degree of security and protection by legislation and
police control, but the real reform which society in these days is seeking will come as a result
of religious convictions, or they will not come at all. Peace, justice, charity&mdash;these cannot be
legislated into being. They are the result of Divine Grace.
</p><p>
It is true that a country cannot get ahead of its religion. The higher our ideals, the nearer we
observe divine law, and the stronger are our spiritual forces. No Christian country can forsake
the divinity of Jesus Christ and not suffer. In those lands in Europe where paganism has
superseded the Christian ideals, there is bound to come decay and eventually, if there is no
repentance, their former greatness will be forgotten. Jesus said: "And why call ye me, Lord,
Lord, and do not the things which I say?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/6/46#46">Luke 6:46</a>).
</p><p>
Here is another inspiring thought. It was copied from a panel on the wall in the chapel at
Stanford University.
</p><p>
There is no narrowing so deadly as the narrowing of man's horizon of spiritual things. No
worse evil could befall him in his course on earth than to lose sight of heaven; and it is not
civilization that can prevent this; it is not civilization that can compensate for it. No widening
of science, no possession of abstract truth, can indemnify for an enfeebled hold on the highest
and eternal truth of humanity.
</p><p>
What shall a man give in exchange for his soul? (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/26#26">Matt. 16:26</a>).
</p><p>
But some one will say: "Are we not living in the most enlightened age the world has ever
seen? Is it not true that great progress is being made to lessen the burdens and increase the
happiness of man?" Yes, this is true in regard to many material things. Great progress has
been made in mechanics, chemistry, physics, surgery, and other things. Men have built great
telescopes that have brought the hidden galaxies to view. They have, by the aid of the
microscope, discovered vast worlds of microorganisms, some of which are as deadly as are
men towards their fellow men. They have discovered means to control disease; they have, by
the aid of anesthesia, made men insensible to pain, thus permitting major and delicate
operations which could not otherwise be performed. They have invented machines more
sensitive than the human touch, more far-seeing than the human eye. They have controlled
elements and made machinery that can move mountains, and many other things have they
done too numerous to mention. Yes, this is a wonderful age. However, all of these
discoveries and inventions have not drawn men nearer to God! 
</p><p>
Nor created in their hearts humility and the spirit of repentance, but to the contrary, to their
condemnation. Nearly everything, it seems, which has been given that should be a blessing to
men, has been turned to evil. Many of these discoveries and inventions are now being used
to bring destruction to the human race. They are being used in the most cruel, most inhuman,
godless war this world has ever seen. They are employed by criminals to aid them in their
crimes, by the ambitious in their efforts to destroy the agency of man, and by despots who
are endeavoring to subjugate the world to an unholy, wicked rule. 
</p><p>
Faith has not increased in the world, nor has righteousness, nor obedience to God. What the
world needs today is to draw nearer to the Lord. We need more humble, abiding faith in our
Redeemer, more love in our hearts for our Eternal Father and for our fellow men. Yes, this is
a good time, a vital time&mdash;if we are to survive the forces of evil&mdash;for every man every man to
forsake the paths of sin and turn unto the Lord who will abundantly pardon
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/55/7#7">Isa. 55:7</a>). If we will do
this, we may in confidence call upon the Lord and He will be near. He will help us fight our
battles (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/14#14">D&amp;C 105:14</a>)
to cleanse the world of despotism and make it a fit abode for all who love the
principles of truth and righteousness.
</p><p>
"Blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/33/12#12">Ps. 33:12</a>).
Let us make our nation all that
it was destined to be, and this will come if we will humble ourselves and learn to be obedient
to divine law.
</p><p>
May the peace and blessings of the Lord be ours, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
