<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 95-99</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I stand before you this afternoon, my brethren, with mingled feelings of joy and sadness. I am
glad that the absence of President Hardy and President Bennion has been mentioned here this
afternoon. They were both men who were very, very dear to me, and I want you all to know
that I miss them very keenly. As I sit here on the stand today, I feel their absence because I
used to go to both of them for support in the questions that so frequently arose, and I used to
sit next to Brother Bennion in all of our conference gatherings. I hope that God will comfort
Sister Hardy and Sister Bennion, and that he will give us the power to give them some aid in
their trials and make it easier for them. On the other hand, I rejoice in the fine quality of the
men who have been selected to take their places. I want to make public acknowledgment of
my esteem for them and tell them that they have my support in the work that they shall have
to do.
</p><p>
THE COMPORT A TESTIMONY GIVES
</p><p>
I am glad for the testimony I have of the gospel of Jesus Christ and for the faith that it gives
me, faith that the work which God initiated in this dispensation, through the instrumentality of
the Prophet Joseph Smith, shall go on and on and on. I feel very insignificant as one of the
cogs in the great machine which is to carry it forward, but I have gained through my
observation and experience the faith that God will see it go forward, regardless of the fact that
those of us who are here now will eventually lay down the burdens of life. I like to think of
life as something that began before mortality and something that will go on after it; that death
is but an incident in life, just as is birth, and I like to think that these companions of mine
now are exercising an influence just as they did here. The sun rises in the morning, and we
feel its warmth during the day. For us it sets in the evening, but when it sets for us, it warms
another land. I feel that those fine men are doing that very thing, that through their
personalities and the power that they gained through their experiences here, they are warming
another land and helping another group of men and women. I am thankful for that faith, for it
helps me over many difficult problems in life.
</p><p>
THE RESPONSIBILITY OF LEADERSHIP
</p><p>
We who are here, this afternoon, represent the leadership of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints. We come together for inspiration and to learn better how to do the various
things that we have to do in administering the work of the Church. We have a great and grave
responsibility because we stand at the head of this large group of people, and it is expected of
us that we will show them the way to go. It is true, as has been said, that he who holds a
lantern to light the footsteps of his friends, lights his own. In leading the people we see more
clearly our own duties, our own responsibilities, and the pathway that we should follow. It is
a great obligation, and I stand in fear and trembling before you and before God when I think
of my responsibility in the position I occupy. I hope that I may have your faith and prayers as
my life carries on, to do it properly.
</p><p>
Man is the crowning creation of God, who spent a long time fashioning the world and the
plants and the animals that grow upon it. As his crowning effort he placed man to rule and
reign over them. Man is the great workmanship of God. To bring about the eternal life of
man is his great objective. He starts us out as almost the weakest of all of the animal
creations which he has placed upon the world. There are few of the animals that are born as
weak and puny as we, and all of them grow more quickly to maturity and to independence
than we. We are the most dependent of all the creations, I believe, but we grow, if we are
properly nurtured and cared for, into the crowning glory of the work of God. To take that
new soul and tiny body as it comes into the world and develop it into a
personage who will eventually attain to the qualities of godhood is a responsibility that few of
us appreciate in its enormity. We talk a great deal about the delinquency of this present day,
juvenile delinquency and the delinquency of others, but we seem to be startled mainly with
what we term juvenile delinquency. The other night I sat and listened to a discussion by one
of our prominent educators on that question and one of the things that I gained from his
discussion was this statement, "Back of every delinquent child, there is a responsible and
frequently a delinquent adult." Now if we will think of it that way, think what a responsibility
we have. It isn't their fault, if that is true, there is delinquency in the world, but it is our fault
and the fault of our grandfathers, because we respond to influences down through all these
generations, the present generation being the product of the past. When we think, too, of a
child whose career is changed by some careless act or teaching of ours and that he becomes
an undesirable member of society passing his undesirable qualities down to future generations,
which pyramid as a great fan beyond him, how can we think of the end of that evil influence
and how can we determine the enormity of the offense; thus it is not surprising that we read
in Matthew and in Mark and in Luke the statement of the Savior that "he who shall offend
the least of these little ones who believe in me, it were better for him that a millstone had
been tied about his neck and he had been drowned in the sea" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/6#6">Matt. 18:6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/9/42#42">Mark 9:42</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/2#2">Luke 17:2</a>).
Verily, that is true, for had that been done before his evil influence was
felt, it had been better for the world.
</p><p>
THE PROPER WATCHCARE OF CHILDREN ENJOINED
</p><p>
Now, brethren, the children of this Church are our children. God has entrusted us with their
care, and ours is the problem to see that they are properly taught and led. I am very, very
sure that there are many homes, and perhaps most of the homes of the Latter-day Saints,
where this obligation is properly appreciated and where the parents do what is within their
power properly to lead as well as direct their children, and I give you in testimony of it the
fact that I have seen many young men and women come out of these homes with a faith that
is fine and holy. At the same time, it is quite possible that some of us do not attend to these
responsibilities as we should. We have frequent cases reported to us where children are on the
streets at all hours of the day and night, while their parents are off on some errand, perhaps
for pleasure, perhaps for gain, a questionable gain when you consider the sacrifice they make
for it. So there may be among us some cases which should have attention, and we who are
here are the ones who are charged with that part of it, to see that our people are properly
taught and properly led.
</p><p>
It isn't every parent that has the tact to do those things as he should, and it isn't every parent
whose children go astray who is responsible for that, because they come
under the influence of people outside the family as well as within it, but when we expose
them to those external influences we should do everything within our power to protect them
from within. Perhaps we who are here in this section of the country have felt so secure in the
past that we haven't done as much as we should in preparation and in protection.
</p><p>
I remember visiting an outlying stake established in a large community. When I suggested to
the president of the stake that we at home were worried over the temptations that are now
being presented to our young people, he said, "President Ivins, we have had to contend with
temptation since we came into this section. Our children have developed a method of
withstanding it, and we can trust them." So it seems possible to build up a resistance to those
things. That is our charge and that is our task. I wonder how many of us get close enough to
our children, so that when they come in in the evening, they come to our bedside and tell us
where they have been, and how many of us get close enough to them that they will come and
confide in us their problems as their advancing years come upon them? Too many of us, I am
sure, as parents, are backward in teaching them some of the principles of life which they
should learn, and there develops between father and son, between mother and daughter, a
barrier that seems hard to surmount; but when we recognize that, at its very first appearance,
we should consciously attempt to break it down, tactfully, nicely. Let us see if we can't gain
the confidence of these children that we are producing, and let us who are the fathers in the
wards and the stakes of the Church see if we can't so gain the confidence of the fathers and
mothers that we can talk to them in the same spirit, that we can teach them the value of
family prayer. It is astonishing how many people in this last report that we received have
admitted that they don't practice regularly family prayer. Now there is no greater safeguard in
the family, and there is no greater protection to a child than that habit which he should
develop. The principles of integrity, righteousness, and upright living should also be taught
them. If it is true that back of every erring child there is an erring parent or other adult, there
is a grave responsibility resting upon us, and we shouldn't shirk it; we shouldn't evade it
because we are backward or bashful with our children. We should face it fairly and squarely
with our arms around them, bringing them close to our hearts and talking confidentially with
them. Some of the greatest pleasures of my life have been the sessions that I had with my
father, under the stars of heaven, sleeping side by side with him. We should get close to those
children; we should love them. We would give our lives for them, but frequently we are so
embarrassed and bashful that we won't even talk plainly to them in love and good will. I
don't mean a dominating spirit or anything of that kind. I remember one time in going
through a mission we attempted to teach a father that he should put his arms around his child,
his boy, and bring him close to him. The man who made the appeal in the
public address said, "You must hang on to your children," and the man who translated into
Spanish, said, "You must govern them with a hand of mail." You can imagine how far we
got. That isn't what I mean, brethren. "We must put our arms around them; we must love
them; we must teach them; we are the leaders of the people, the heads of the wards and
stakes; and what are we doing for them? Let every man of us look himself in the eye, and see
if he can say, "I have done my full duty, I am satisfied and happy." If he can't, I call him to
repentance.
</p><p>
May God give us the strength to do it, I ask in the name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
