<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Repentance Worketh Salvation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion G. Romney</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion G. Romney, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1955, pp. 123-125</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brothers and sisters: President McKay began this great conference on a note of
gratitude.  My soul immediately responded to the theme. The spirit of it has inspired the
proceedings of every session of the conference.  In harmony with it, let me say that I am
grateful for the peace that has come into my heart during the conference, and for the peace of
this moment as I stand before you to express my feelings.
</p><p>
Among the many things for which I am thankful is the sanctifying process of repentance.  I
am grateful to the Lord Jesus Christ who, through the atonement he wrought, gave us the gift
of repentance.  I am grateful that he was willing voluntarily to give his life for us.  That is
literally what he did. He did not have to give it; he did not have to die.  Because he was the
Son of God, he was not subject to the Fall, as were men.  Within him was power to live
forever.  ". . . I lay down my life for the sheep"&mdash;he said.  "No man taketh it from me, but I
lay it down of myself.  I have power to lay it down, and I have power to take it again"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/15,18#15">John 10:15,18</a>).
He inherited power over death from his divine Father.
</p><p>
It took a person with power over death to pay the debt to justice to bring men forth in the
resurrection.  It took a sinless one, a god, even the sinless Son of God, to satisfy the
demands of justice for men's sins.  They themselves could not make an atonement which
would either bring about their resurrection or pay for their sins and bring about their spiritual
rebirth.
</p><p>
And so I repeat, I am grateful for my Redeemer, grateful that he paid the debt and brought
about the means of repentance so that by repenting of my transgressions I can bring my soul
within the reach of his atoning blood and thereby be cleansed of sin; for, after all, it is by the
grace of Christ that men are saved, after all they can do
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/25/23#23">2 Ne. 25:23</a>). The thing they can and must do is
repent.  I love the doctrine of repentance.
</p><p>
During the past few months I have seen the need of it&mdash;oh, how I have seen the need of it. I
have seen missionaries, saints, and non-members of the Church, in far-off lands sorrowing
with a godly sorrow for sin.  I have heard them say, "Oh, Brother Romney, do you think
there is any hope for me, any chance for me to get on even the bottom rung of the gospel
ladder?"
</p><p>
And as I have witnessed their sorrowing, I have remembered the sorrowing of repentant men
in days of old; Zeezrom, for example, whose "soul," after he realized what he had done in
opposing the ministry of Alma and Amulek,". . . began to be harrowed up under a
consciousness of his own guilt; yea, he began to be encircled about the pains of hell"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/14/6#6">Alma 14:6</a>). So
severe were his sufferings that he ". . . lay sick at Sidom, with a burning fever, which was
caused by the great tribulations of his mind on account of his wickedness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/15/3#3">Alma 15:3</a>).
And Alma, who said of the suffering he endured for "seeking to destroy the church of
God": 
</p><p>
I was racked with eternal torment, for my soul was harrowed to the greatest degree
and racked with all my sins.  Yea, I . . . was tormented with the pains of hell . . .
with inexpressible horror . . . even with the pains of a damned soul (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/36/12-14,16#12">Alma 36:12-14,16</a>).
</p><p>
But then I also remembered the rest which came into their souls when, through repentance,
they found forgiveness.  "Yea, I say unto you," said Alma to his son Helaman, that as "there
could be nothing so exquisite and so bitter as were my pains"&mdash;so ". . . on the other hand,
there can be nothing so exquisite and sweet as was my joy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/36/21#21">Alma 36:21</a>).
</p><p>
And so I was comforted and encouraged those who confided in me, and I encourage all
sorrowing, repentant men to be comforted&mdash;comforted by the experience of Alma and by
Paul's assurance that ". . . godly sorrow worketh repentance to salvation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/7/10#10">2 Cor. 7:10</a>).
For today, as well as in days of old, there is hope, there is peace, there is rest in Christ for all
whose godly sorrow brings them to that repentance which worketh salvation. Forgiveness is as
wide as repentance. Every person will be forgiven for all the transgression of which he truly
repents. If he repents of all his sins, he shall stand spotless before God because of the
atonement of our Master and Savior, Jesus Christ; while he that exercises no faith unto
repentance remains ". . . as though there had been no redemption made, except it be the
loosing of the bands of death"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/41#41">Alma 11:41</a>).
Such is the gist of God's merciful plan of
redemption.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, there are many among us whose distress and suffering are
unnecessarily prolonged because they do not complete their repentance by confessing their sins. 
You will recall the following words of the Savior,
</p><p>
I command you to repent . . . and that you confess your sins, lest you suffer these
punishments of which I have spoken
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/20#20">D&amp;C 19:20</a>).
</p><p>
In another revelation he said,
</p><p>
By this ye may know if a man repenteth of his sins&mdash;behold, he will confess them and
forsake them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/43#43">D&amp;C 58:43</a>).
</p><p>
Repeatedly he says that he forgives the sins of those who confess their sins with humbleness
of heart, ". . . who have not sinned unto death" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/2#2">D&amp;C 61:2</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/7#7">D&amp;C 64:7</a>). And he adds,
</p><p>
. . . he who of his sins, the same is forgiven, and I, the Lord, remember them no
more (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/42#42">D&amp;C 58:42</a>).
</p><p>
But how are we to fulfil this commandment?  To whom are we to confess our sins?  In the
fifty-ninth section of the Doctrine and Covenants, the Lord, with other directions concerning
his "holy day," says,
</p><p>
. . . remember that on this, the Lord's day, thou shalt offer thine oblations and thy
sacraments unto the Most High, confessing thy sins unto thy brethren, and before the
Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/12#12">D&amp;C 59:12</a>).
</p><p>
I would assume that we are to confess all our sins unto the Lord.  For transgressions which
are wholly personal, affecting none but ourselves and the Lord, such confession would seem
to be sufficient.
</p><p>
For misconduct which offends another, confession should also be made to the offended one,
and his forgiveness sought.
</p><p>
Finally, where one's transgressions are of such a nature as would, unrepented of, put in
jeopardy his right to membership or fellowship in the Church of Jesus Christ, full and
effective confession would, in my judgment, require confession by the repentant sinner to his
bishop or other proper presiding Church officer&mdash;not that the Church officer could forgive the
sin (this power rests in the Lord himself and those only to whom he specifically delegates it,
see [<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/9/2-6#2">Matt. 9:2-6</a>];
[<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/2/7-10#7">Mark 2:7-10</a>]),
but rather that the Church, acting through its duly appointed officers, might with full
knowledge of the facts take such action with respect to Church discipline as the circumstances
merit.
</p><p>
One having forsaken his sins and, by proper confession, cleared his conduct with the Lord,
with the people he has offended, and with the Church of Jesus Christ, where necessary, may
with full confidence seek the Lord's forgiveness and go forth in newness of life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/6/4#4">Rom. 6:4</a>), relying upon
the merits of Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/19#19">2 Ne. 31:19</a>).
</p><p>
Let us in this manner clear for righteous living the decks of our own lives, and get on our
way to eternal life. Only by so doing can we rid ourselves of those guilty feelings of
unworthiness, depression, fear, uncertainty, and self-condemnation which block our upward
climb.  So long as we put off either the forsaking or confessing of our sins, just so long do
we delay the day of our redemption.
</p><p>
Let not the past hang heavy as a millstone to thy heels,<br />
     To drag thee downward as each upward impulse to thy nobler self appeals; <br />
     But as the joyous butterfly from its chrysalistic shell breaks free,<br />
     So from the past must thou rise jubilant, thine own true self to be.
</p><p>
This we may do today if we will, for Amulek assures us that
</p><p>
. . . if [we] will repent and harden not [our] hearts, immediately shall the great plan of
redemption be brought about unto [us] (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/31#31">Alma 34:31</a>).
</p><p>
And President Joseph F. Smith spoke these comforting words: 
</p><p>
. . . none of the children of the Father who are redeemed through obedience, faith,
repentance, and baptism for the remission of sins, and who live in that redeemed
condition, and die in that condition, are subject to Satan . . .  They are absolutely
beyond his reach just as little children are who die without sin. (Gospel Doctrine, p.
570.)
</p><p>
God grant that it may be so with us all, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ, our
Redeemer.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
