<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">On Sustaining Authority</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 41-46</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
One day an ancient prophet called his son to his side and talked with him about liberty. They
discussed the free agency which God has given to us all, which permits every man to choose
his own course in life, whether good or bad. The father told his son that it is impossible for a
man to exercise his right of choice unless alternatives are placed before him: virtue and vice,
light and darkness, the bitter and the sweet. Then he said, "Man could not act for himself save
it should be that he was enticed by the one or the other." Therefore, "it must needs be that
there is an opposition in all things." The ancient prophet told his son that this opposition in all
things had existed from the beginning of time and that even in the Garden of Eden the
forbidden fruit stood in opposition to the tree of life (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/11-16#11">2 Ne. 2:11-16</a>).
</p><p>
THE RIGHT TO CHOOSE GIVEN TO MANKIND
</p><p>
When Jesus began his ministry, he also dealt with this opposition in all things. He recognized
that evil is in the world, and he acknowledged that all men have their free agency and have
the right to choose between the good and the evil. All through his ministry he taught men to
choose the right and told them of the many blessings they would receive if they would do so.
</p><p>
Again he said that if men were to choose the evil they would be condemned; that their
offences would bring sorrow, not only upon other men but upon themselves. Therefore, he
said:
</p><p>
Woe unto the world because of offences! for it must needs be that offences come; but woe to
that man by whom the offence cometh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/7#7">Matt. 18:7</a>).
</p><p>
As he went about in his ministry, Jesus was met with varied reactions. There were some who
gladly accepted him, followed him wherever he went and tried to live his teachings. There
were some who were indifferent, and then there were others who openly opposed him. So the
people of that day had before them a clear working example of the law of opposition in all
things. On the one hand was Jesus preaching the way of life; on the other were the Scribes
and the Pharisees who fought him at every step. Then there were the
indifferent ones. Can we say that they were for the Lord or against him, or were they merely, as
we say, indifferent? I call to your mind that the indifferent ones did not keep the
commandments, and by their indifference they encouraged others to be indifferent, and as the
others became indifferent, they also refused to obey the commandments of the Lord their
God.
</p><p>
These indifferent ones built up a barrier against the Christ, and as they spread the example of
disobedience they became a hindrance to him in his work, and for that reason the Lord said:
</p><p>
He that is not with me is against me; and he that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/30#30">Matt. 12:30</a>).
</p><p>
At another time he said, "Ye are my friend, if ye do whatsoever I command you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/14#14">John 15:14</a>); and then
again he said, "He that loveth me not keepeth not my sayings"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/24#24">John 14:24</a>).
</p><p>
His attitude regarding the indifferent ones is further shown by the message of the Lord to the
seven churches as given to John on Patmos; and you remember what was said to one of those
churches:
</p><p>
I know thy works, that thou art neither cold nor hot: I would thou wert cold or hot. So then
because thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will spue thee out of my mouth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/3/15-16#15">Rev. 3:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
So with the Lord we take sides. We are either for him or we are against him. We are
strengthening his work or we are weakening his work. Every Latter-day Saint should ask
himself whether he is for the Lord or whether he is against the Lord; whether his deeds are
sustaining and strengthening the work of God or whether his deeds, even his indifference, are
weakening the work of the Lord.
</p><p>
MEN ARE AUTHORIZED TO CARRY ON GOD'S WORK
</p><p>
Then there is another lesson which the Lord taught in those days, and that lesson was this:
that we cannot be for the Lord and at the same time be against his authorized servants.
</p><p>
Jesus well understood that he would not remain long in mortality and that his ministry would
necessarily be limited, and so he planned to follow the age-old example of the Lord in raising
up and calling to the ministry living prophets, authorized men of God, to carry on the work.
</p><p>
But in doing so it was necessary for the Lord to warn these servants in the ministry of the
attitude of the people. He remembered that in the ages past there had been a tendency on the
part of the people to resist, reject, persecute, and even slay the prophets of God, and Jesus
knew that that tendency continued even in his own day because he had felt it. And now, as he
was about to send forth his authorized servants to minister among the people, and having in
mind this tendency, he said to them, "I send you forth as lambs among wolves"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/3#3">Luke 10:3</a>).
</p><p>
What a commentary upon those who reject and resist and persecute the
authorities of the Church. What a rebuke from the Lord himself to those who stand in
opposition to the servants of the Lord.
</p><p>
He tried to comfort these disciples. He told them that whosoever would receive his authorized
servants would receive him; and whosoever received him would receive him who sent the
Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/40#40">Matt. 10:40</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/20#20">John 13:20</a>). But then he said:
</p><p>
. . . he that despiseth you, despiseth me; and he that despiseth me despiseth him that sent me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/16#16">Luke 10:16</a>).
</p><p>
Remember, he was speaking to the authorities of the Church. Then he said further:
</p><p>
. . . whosoever shall not receive you, nor hear your words, . . Verily I say unto you, It shall
be more tolerable for the land of Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of judgment, than for that
city (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/14-15#14">Matt. 10:14-15</a>).
</p><p>
MODERN AUTHORITIES ON SAME BASIS
</p><p>
Then with his warning these chosen servants of the Lord, these authorities of the early day
Church, went forth as commanded by the Lord, and they tasted of the opposition in all things.
There was opposition within the Church, and there was opposition out of the Church.
Persecution both within and without increased. The spirit of apostasy spread, and finally
apostasy overcame the Church. The leaders of the Church were destroyed, and taken out of
the ministry. The people were left in darkness, and gross darkness covered their minds
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/23#23">D&amp;C 112:23</a>), and
we had a complete apostasy from the truth.
</p><p>
It was decreed, however, that in the last days there should be a restoration of the Church, and
we who are here are witnesses of the fact that the Church of Jesus Christ has been restored in
these last days. But it has been restored upon the same basis that the Church was built upon
in ancient times and is founded upon a foundation of apostles and prophets
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20#20">Eph. 2:20</a>). In other words,
the authorities of the present day Church were especially appointed by the Lord to represent
him in these last days because he could not be here always in person any more than he could
in the days of Paul. Therefore, the Lord spoke to his modern authorities in the same way in
which he spoke anciently, and he said:
</p><p>
And as I said unto mine apostles, even so I say unto you, for you are mine apostles, even
God's high priests; ye are they whom my Father hath given me; ye are my friends. Therefore,
as I said unto mine apostles I say unto you again, that every soul who believeth on your
words, and is baptized by water for the remission of sins, shall receive the Holy Ghost. And
these signs shall follow them that believe&mdash;In my name they shall do many wonderful works:
In my name they shall cast out devils; In my name they shall heat the sick; In my name they
shall open the eyes of the blind, and unstop the ears of the deaf; And the tongue of the dumb
shall speak; And if any man shall administer poison unto them it shall not hurt them; And the
poison of a serpent shall not have power to harm them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/63-72#63">D&amp;C 84:63-72</a>).
</p><p>
While speaking in these last days, the Lord remembered again the tendency
of the people to resist the living prophets of God, and to persecute them, to say all manner of
evil against them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/11#11">Matt. 5:11</a>)
and to undermine the work they are doing. The Lord remembered that there
were people in his own day and in earlier days who possessed such a tendency, and he knew
in these last days there would be men and women who would continue to fight against the
living prophets of God. But he comforted these modern living prophets and said to them, He
that receiveth you, receiveth me, and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that sent me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/36-37#36">D&amp;C 84:36-37</a>); but
conversely he taught," . . . Wo unto that house, or that village or city which rejecteth you, or
your words, or your testimony concerning me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/94#94">D&amp;C 84:94</a>).
</p><p>
So you see, he placed the modern authorities of his Church on the same basis as that on
which he placed the ancient authorities of the Church, and he again preached the doctrine that
if the people receive you, the living prophets, whether you live in 1945 or whether you live in
A.D. 30, "they receive me, and whosoever rejecteth you, rejecteth me." That was the doctrine
of the Church anciently. It is the doctrine of the Lord himself in these days, and whosoever
rejects or receives the living authorities of his Church rejects or receives the Lord himself.
</p><p>
DISLOYALTY TO AUTHORITY WEAKENS THE CAUSE
</p><p>
Now, recall the scripture I read to you earlier in this discussion: "He that is not with me is
against me; and he that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/30#30">Matt. 12:30</a>). Keeping in mind the
doctrine of the Lord with respect to his servants, that if we, the people, reject the servants of
the Lord, we reject the Lord, and that if we receive the servants of God we receive God, we
are fully justified in interpreting this scripture, that I have just read to you, in this way: "He
that is for the living prophets of God is also for the Lord; and he that is not for the living
prophets of God is against the Lord." We may interpret it also in this way: "He that is loyal
to the living authorities of the Church is loyal to God; and any Latter-day Saint who is
disloyal to the authorities of the Church is disloyal to God." Or we may read it this way and
still be within the truth: "He that sustains the authorities of the Church sustains the Church
and the Lord, but any Latter-day Saint who does not sustain the authorities of the Church
places himself in a position where he weakens the cause of God instead of lending it
strength."
</p><p>
Now look at the other part of that scripture. "He that gathereth not with me scattereth abroad."
When we speak of "gathering with" the Lord, or assisting him in gathering in the souls of
men, gathering them into the fold of Christ, we speak of an organized effort, and we speak of
an organized program. We speak of the fold of the Church of God and therefore, if we are
"gathering with" him, we are working with him, working in his Church, working in his
program, accepting his program and lending our strength to it.
</p><p>
And then there is another thought in connection with it, that if we are "gathering with" him
we engage in a cooperative effort, cooperation on the part of us, the Latter-day Saints,
cooperating with the leaders of the Church, cooperating with the Lord in gathering into the
fold of Christ the souls of men.
</p><p>
Now, are we gathering with the Lord, or are we, by our efforts, scattering abroad the sheep
that he is trying to gather into the fold? Are we cooperating with the authorities of the
Church, are we gathering with them: are we assisting them in bringing into the fold of Christ
the people the Lord would save? Are we gathering with them, cooperating with them in the
prosecution of the program of the Church, or are we criticizing the authorities of the Church
and undermining them and their efforts?
</p><p>
I call to your minds the words of the Prophet Joseph Smith in this connection:
</p><p>
I will give to you one of the keys of the mysteries of the kingdom. It is an eternal principle
that has existed with God from all eternity. That man who rises up to condemn others, finding
fault with the Church, saying that they are out of the way while he himself is righteous, then
know assuredly that that man is on the high road to apostasy, and if he does not repent, will
apostatize, as God lives. The principle is as correct as the one that Jesus put forth in saying
that he who seeketh a sign is an adulterous person
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/39#39">Matt. 12:39</a>); and that principle is eternal, undeviating
and as firm as the pillars of heaven.
</p><p>
So spake the Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
I ask you again, my brethren, and my sisters on the air, are you for the Lord and his program
or are you against them? Are you for the authorities of the Church or are you against them?
Are you gathering with them, or are you scattering abroad? Are you on the Lord's side
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/32/26#26">Ex. 32:26</a>)?
</p><p>
Who's on the Lord's side? Who? <br />
Now is the time to show;<br />
We ask it fearlessly,<br />
Who's on the Lord's side? Who?
</p><p>
The pow'r of earth and hell<br />
In rage direct the blow<br />
That's aimed to crush the work; <br />
Who's on the Lord's side? Who?
</p><p>
We serve the living God;<br />
And want his foes to know <br />
That if but few, we're great; <br />
Who's on the Lord's side? Who?
</p><p>
We're going on to win,<br />
Nor fear must blanch the brow; <br />
The Lord of hosts is ours, <br />
Who's on the Lord's side? Who?
                               &mdash;H. Cornaby
</p><p>
There is an opposition in all things. You have your free agency. Are you using that free
agency to strengthen or to weaken the cause of God? And if you are weakening the cause of
God, I say to you with Joshua of old, "And if it seem evil unto you to serve the Lord, choose
you this day whom ye will serve." I earnestly pray, also in the words of Joshua, that each one
of us will say, "...as for me and my house, we will serve the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/24/15#15">Josh. 24:15</a>), and this I
pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
