<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Communication</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 41-44</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved President, and my beloved brethren and sisters:
</p><p>
For more than a third of a century it has been my privilege to speak to many of you many
times through my association with the Tabernacle Choir and its remarkably long series of
broadcasts and through other organizations and activities. But I feel a weighty responsibility
this morning in speaking to you of some things that are close to my heart and important to
my life, and which are vitally a part of the principles and convictions of the Church to which
I have the honor to belong&mdash;The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, sometimes
inaccurately referred to as the "Mormon" Church, whose head and lawgiver is our Lord and
Savior, Jesus the Christ, who with his Father&mdash;the Father of us all&mdash;is the foundation of our
faith.
</p><p>
It is God the Father and his Son our Savior whom we worship. This places us on common
ground with all sincere worshiping Christians, through our belief in the divinity of the Lord
Jesus Christ. It places us on common ground with all other men also who believe in God the
Father and Creator of us all, in whose image, as scripture testifies, men are made
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26-27#26">Gen. 1:26-27</a>).
</p><p>
Now since we have this literal relationship with our Father in heaven and his Son, our Lord
and Savior, the matter of communication between God and man, between a loving Father and
his children, becomes a matter of primary importance&mdash;for life is a search for all of us&mdash;a
search for its purpose and meaning&mdash;a search for the answers to questions, to
problems&mdash;answers that will satisfy the yearnings of our hearts, the reaching of our minds. These are
answers that can only come from a divine source.
</p><p>
This brings us to the question of communication between God and man, between a loving,
all-knowing Father and his searching, seeking children. This communication includes prayer,
inspiration, impressions from the divine source upon the mind of man, the findings of truth
through earnest seeking and research, and also what is called revelation, to which the ninth
Article of our Faith refers in these words: "We believe all that God has revealed, all that He
does now reveal, and we believe that He will yet reveal many great and important things
pertaining to the Kingdom of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
Who knows all the answers or any of the ultimate answers? Since no one
does, they must come from continued revelation&mdash;from continued prayerful seeking and
search.
</p><p>
There has been among men some suggestion that the heavens are closed, that scripture is
closed; that God revealed his mind and will to his prophets in the far past, but for some
reason does not do so today.
</p><p>
Do we need his guidance less today than men once did? Do we have fewer problems? Would
a just and loving Father love us less than he did his children of the past? What kind and
loving father would fail or refuse to respond to his children if they approached him with
urgent need and humble hearts?
</p><p>
What gracious and all-wise Administrator of heaven and earth would ignore the problems of
the present or leave his children to grope alone in life?
</p><p>
The comforting answer to these questions is that the channels of communication <i>are</i> open; that
our God and Father is still interested in all our affairs; that he has his prophet on earth; that
he gives to his children what in his wisdom they need and seek and are prepared to accept.
</p><p>
"Surely the Lord God will do nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the
prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>).
"Where there is no vision, the people perish"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/29/18#18">Prov. 29:18</a>).
</p><p>
This need for prophets and their vision&mdash;lest the people perish&mdash;prompts us to quote another
Article of Faith: "We believe in the same organization that existed in the Primitive Church
(i.e. the Church founded by our Savior in the Meridian of Time), viz., apostles, prophets,
pastors, teachers, evangelists, etc." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/6#6">A of F 1:6</a>).
Would not our Savior's Church today be organized as when he was on earth?
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints sustains in this conference President David O.
McKay, who has stood before us this morning in his ninety-first year, in his kindly wisdom
and far-seeing perception; sustains him as a prophet of God in this latter day, with the same
divine commission that was given to the prophets of the past.
</p><p>
Some have asked about our belief in the Book of Mormon. The Book of Mormon is not a
substitute for the Bible. We accept the Bible and use the King James Version. But we do not
believe that the Lord God confined his communications to the people of ancient Palestine or
to any place or period of the past. He has had prophets in other places. The Book of Mormon,
which supplements the Bible and is compatible with it, is an account of the counsels and
communications of God, as is the Bible, and contains sacred and secular history, given to and
preserved by the prophets of ancient America, among whom were some of the ancestors of
the American Indians.
</p><p>
God is no respecter of persons (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/34#34">Acts 10:34</a>)
and has not confined his communication to one part of his
family, to one time of history, or to one land.
</p><p>
Now not only does our Father in heaven communicate by revelation, by inspiration, but he
reveals truth also to earnest searching, seeking men in many fields of truth. Knowledge has
been poured out upon the earth, the evidences of which are too numerous to dwell upon.
</p><p>
And not only does he reveal his will to his servants the prophets and to sincere searching
men, but he responds to a child's simplest prayer&mdash;the simplest, sincere desire of the soul.
He is mindful of every one of us in all our needs, in all of our decisions, in all our uses of
life, in the thoughts of our innermost hearts, and our outermost actions. And aside from
revelation as such, there is the impression within&mdash;the whisperings of the Spirit to the hearts
and consciences of men.
</p><p>
And not only do we need communication with our Father in heaven, but we need
communication and understanding with one another. So often we misjudge men. We misjudge
motives; we believe rumors, and not only believe them, but sometimes add to them and pass
them on. We sometimes believe what gossip and prejudice says of others, rather than going to
factual sources of information. We often reach conclusions based on sheer assumptions. "O
mortal men," said Dante, "be wary how ye judge."
</p><p>
Parents need better communication with their children, and children with parents. They need
to counsel and respect each other and confide in each other and share with each other the
thoughts of their hearts. What more important charge could anyone have in life than to care
for and nourish and understand and teach and love a child whom God has given? What
greater loyalty can a child have than to confide in a father and a mother with respect and
love, sharing hopes and dreams and plans and experiences. And there is safety in this&mdash;safety
in doing nothing that we would not be willing and proud to confide to parents or to our
Father in heaven, who in fact knows all things whether or not we confide.
</p><p>
There is safety in a mother and a father waiting for children to return at whatever
hour&mdash;safety in these close confidences.
</p><p>
Husbands and wives need to confide and communicate with each other and not withdraw
themselves within themselves, but to keep always open between them a gentle and frank and
kindly communication.
</p><p>
Those who don't communicate sometimes sit in brooding silence, and let small things seem
large, and imagine offenses that were never intended, and misjudge minds and hearts and
motives, and pull apart and sever the most sacred ties, and break hearts and homes.
</p><p>
There is so much of misunderstanding that could be cleared with communication, with talking
things out&mdash;suspicions, offenses, misjudging motives, much of which would disappear with
communication and the sincere sharing of confidences with those who have a right to expect
us to confide. As a poet so long ago expressed it&mdash;
</p><p>
"Not understood. We move along asunder,<br />
      Our paths grow wider as the seasons creep<br />
    Along the years; we marvel and we wonder<br />
      Why life is life, and then we fall asleep,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;              Not understood.
</p><p>
"Not understood. We gather false impressions<br />
      And hug them closer as the years go by,<br />
    Till virtues often seem to us transgressions;<br />
      And thus men rise and fall and live and die,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                    Not understood.
</p><p>
"Not understood. Poor souls with stunted vision<br />
      Oft measure giants by their narrow gauge.<br />
    The pointed shafts of falsehood and derision<br />
      Are oft impelled 'gainst those who mould the age,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                    Not understood.
</p><p>
"Not understood. The secret springs of action,<br />
      Which lie beneath the surface and the snow,<br />
    Are disregarded; with self-satisfaction<br />
      We judge our neighbors as they often go,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                 Not understood.
</p><p>
"Not understood. How trifles often change us.<br />
      The thoughtless sentence or the fancied slight<br />
    Destroys long years of friendship, and estranges us,<br />
      And on our souls there falls a freezing blight:<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                 Not understood.
</p><p>
"Not understood. How many breasts are aching,<br />
      For lack of sympathy? Ah! day to day,<br />
    How many cheerless, lonely hearts are breaking!<br />
      How many noble spirits pass away,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                 Not understood.
</p><p>
"O God, that men would see a little clearer,<br />
      Or judge less harshly where they cannot see!<br />
    O God, that men would draw a little nearer<br />
      To one another! They'd be nearer Thee<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                 And understood."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;                   &mdash;Thomas Brecken
</p><p>
I would leave my witness with you that there is purpose in life, that there is
a Father in heaven who made us in his own image; that he did send his Son, our Savior, to
redeem us from death; that God has revealed himself to man through the prophets of the latter
days even as through the prophets of the far past; that he is interested in his children; that he
responds to prayer; that he gives the revelations of his mind and will; that men are immortal
and eternal; and that there is everlasting purpose and reason for the righteous living of life,
for keeping his commandments, for cherishing, serving, and loving one another.
</p><p>
We would share with you these words from King Benjamin from the Book of Mormon:
</p><p>
"Believe in God; believe that he is, and that he created all things, both in heaven and in earth;
believe that he has all wisdom, and all power, both in heaven and in earth; believe that man
doth not comprehend all the things which the Lord can comprehend.
</p><p>
"And again, believe that ye must repent of your sins and forsake them, and humble yourselves
before God; and ask in sincerity of heart that he would forgive you; and now, if you believe
all these things see that ye do them . . .
</p><p>
"And ye will not suffer your children . . . that they transgress the laws of God, and fight and
quarrel one with another, and serve the devil, who is the master of sin . . .
</p><p>
"But ye will teach them to walk in the ways of truth and soberness; ye will teach them to love
one another, and to serve one another
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/9-10,14-15#9">Mosiah 4:9-10,14-15</a>).
</p><p>
". . . I say unto you, that there shall be no other name given nor any other way nor means
whereby salvation can come unto the children of men, only in and through the name of
Christ, the Lord Omnipotent
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/17#17">Mosiah 3:17</a>).
</p><p>
". . . O remember, remember that these things are true; for the Lord God hath spoken it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/41#41">Mosiah 2:41</a>).
</p><p>
The answers men so much seek are to be found, and to the aching, yearning loneliness of
human hearts, and to the anguished agony of the world there can come direction, revelation,
comfort, guidance, inspiration, and a finding of the way to the purposeful, happy living of life
with the peace and cleanliness of a quiet conscience, and with the blessed assurance of an
everlasting life with limitless opportunities, and with our loved ones with us.
</p><p>
May God be with you, my beloved friends, and give you every needed blessing in life, and
your loved ones, in peace and health and happiness, in prayerful searching and seeking, in
pursuit of the divine purpose, with the assurance that the answers are there. May you have
help in your daily pursuits, and in your homes, and in all relationships with your loved ones,
and with wise and good choices in all the living of life.
</p><p>
God does live! He is real and reachable and not indefinable. He is mindful of us. He hears us.
He is interested in us. He is ever ready to communicate with us. He is our Father and made
us in his own image, and as we seek him he will not leave us groping and lonely and alone.
His word, his Church, his purposes are here and now on earth. The Creator is still in
command. May God bless you and peace be with you&mdash;always, I pray in the name of the
Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
