<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Rufus K. Hardy</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Rufus K. Hardy, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 54-56</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am impressed, my brethren, today with the great gathering which is here and which was
here yesterday, and I am thinking that perhaps there will never come into the lives of men
that they may build a thing so perfect even as we now see it constructed before us&mdash;I speak of
the organization of the Church. Here, according to President McKay this morning, is every
officer of the two Priesthoods, the Aaronic and the Melchizedek, represented in this building.
</p><p>
PRIESTHOOD A CHOICE GIFT
</p><p>
This Priesthood is referred to as "being without father, without mother, and without descent,
and has neither beginning of days or end of life." Each of us is called with a peculiar calling,
each in his respective calling to do vastly different things. Every appointment and calling in
the Priesthood is of such importance that all of the time devoted by each man to his
designated sphere, in close application to his work, will not begin to encompass the greatness
and eternal decrees of God.
</p><p>
One thing, however, of which we must ever be wary is the warning which God has given.
That warning is that "all other authorities or offices in the church are appendages to this
priesthood" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/5#5">D&amp;C 107:5</a>),
and then again, God gave a revelation to the Prophet Joseph
and told him this: "For I have conferred upon you the keys and power of the priesthood,
wherein I restore all things, and make known unto you all things in due time"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/45#45">D&amp;C 132:45</a>).
And, yet, I am sure, my brethren, that we zealous and energetic laborers in the work
of God are tempted at times to exaggerate our own importance, to accomplish personal
ambitions, but we should adopt the humble attitude of standing still "to see the glory of the
Lord pass by" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/33/22#22">Ex. 33:22</a>);
this would accomplish a great deal more. We grow despondent with what we
think is delay, forgetting momentarily that since the very beginning of time God has planned
and wrought with patience, and has seen afar the very time in which we now find ourselves.
</p><p>
Let us remember that we are blessed with the choicest of God's gifts, the inestimable calling
in the Priesthood which we ourselves hold; "that the rights of the priesthood are inseparably
connected with the powers of heaven, and that the powers of heaven cannot be controlled nor
handled only upon the principles of righteousness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/36#36">D&amp;C 121:36</a>).
</p><p>
It is a revealing and marvelous thing that God has brought about the many miracles that we
see performed in our midst this day.
</p><p>
A LAND BLESSED OF THE LORD
</p><p>
When we consider the early sending forth of the Priesthood bearers and the scattering of the
membership of this Church and Priesthood, which then we looked upon as a calamity, to the
various parts of the earth, and the gathering of it all here and concentrating its executive
power in this locality, and then to look at the beauty of our land compared with what it was,
to realize that it has become an inviting, charming place, and behold these buildings, now in
our midst, we must give fervent thanks to God. This surely is the land of Joseph, the land
which God gave and blessed in the beginning that all men who came here might enjoy it who
would lend ear to that which God has given us, the Gospel of Jesus Christ. It is the only land,
my brethren, which is surrounded on all sides by friends and not enemies, God's blessed land.
</p><p>
PRESENT NEED FOR MISSIONARIES
</p><p>
Now, in this turmoil through which we are passing, we have a need, a great calling, to put to
work that thing which God has given us, the Priesthood. We need missionaries to teach these
hungry, eager people, strangers within our midst, something of the Gospel, to let 
them know how it came about and was restored, and why God's children are here doing what
they are.
</p><p>
I am very sure that in our council, the First Council of the Seventy, every man is keenly alert
to this situation. Notwithstanding the two thousand-odd who were baptized last year by our
stake missionaries, we have not touched the surface.
</p><p>
God will bless us in this work if we will put our mind and attention to it, and I sincerely 
trust and hope and pray that this may be the case, and that we may recognize in this strained
and trying condition that besets us the privileges which are ours now, and that will be, for
they were given by the Lord, even as He says: "Wherefore, now let every man learn his duty,
and to act in the office in which he is appointed, in all diligence"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99#99">D&amp;C 107:99</a>).
</p><p>
I pray that God will give a keen desire to each man to serve in his own sphere to the best of
his ability, that His work may roll on and that these blessings which are ours may be given to
others, which I do in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
