<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Consciousness of God: Supreme Goal of Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">(Read by his son, Robert R. McKay)</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 84-88</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren of the priesthood, and esteemed fellow workers, my heart is full of gratitude tonight
for the privilege of participating in this meeting with you. There is a concentration of power
in these priesthood meetings that is inspiring. No one who attends can escape that influence,
and the responsibility of giving a message to you is overwhelming. I, therefore, pray for your
sympathy, your faith, and prayers that the message given may be divinely directed.
</p><p>
<b>"Beloved associates"</b>
</p><p>
It has always been my nature to enjoy the company of my associates. I love to be with my
friends, and the older I grow the more intense becomes my appreciation of fellowship in the
brotherhood of Christ, and I sense that tonight more deeply, more sincerely than ever before.
As I feel of your spirit, I picture those of you who are gathered in the Assembly Hall, and in
the 478 other meetings being held at this hour across the United States and in Canada. I have
nothing but blessing in my heart for you. I like to call you my beloved associates and fellow
workers, and that love is akin to the love we have for our families. If we can keep this unity,
this confidence, nothing in the world can stop the progress of this work.
</p><p>
<b>Comfort of close relationship with God</b>
</p><p>
The greatest comfort in this life is the assurance of having a close relationship with God, and
I believe in the statement that "the greatest battle of life is fought within the silent chambers
of your own soul." It has been said that "consciousness of God is the highest achievement in
human experience and is the supreme goal of human life. This is true religion. It is a mental,
spiritual experience of the highest order." Many of you priesthood members know what that
experience is. It is a good thing to sit down and commune with yourself, to
come to an understanding with yourself and decide in that silent moment what your duty is to
your family, to your Church, to your country, and what you owe to your fellowmen.
</p><p>
<b>Need for spirituality, meditation, communion</b>
</p><p>
In view of the responsibilities facing this body of priesthood holders and leaders in the
Church, especially during these uncertain and crucial times, I should like to emphasize the
need for more spirituality, for more meditation and communion with our Father in heaven. I
ask that you men of the priesthood&mdash;you stake presidents, you bishops, and other leaders in
stakes and wards&mdash;see to it that a spirit of reverence is maintained in our homes and houses
of worship.
</p><p>
Our houses of worship furnish a wonderful opportunity to commune with one's self and to
commune with the Lord, especially during the sacrament period. Sunday is a day of worship,
which we turn over to him. We may rest assured that he will be there in that house of
worship to inspire us if we come in proper attunement to meet him.
</p><p>
We are not prepared to meet him if we bring thoughts regarding business affairs, and
especially if we come knowing we have been disloyal to our wives and other members of our
families, and bring feelings of hatred, enmity, and jealousy toward our fellowman. Most
certainly no individual can hope to come into communion with the Father if that individual
has such disloyalty or entertains any such feelings, as they are foreign to worship and are
particularly out of tune with the partaking of the sacrament.
</p><p>
<b>Value of meditation</b>
</p><p>
I think we pay too little attention to the value of meditation, a principle of devotion. In our
worship there are two elements: One is spiritual communion arising from our own meditation;
the other, instruction from others, particularly from those who have authority to guide and
instruct us. Of the two, the more profitable introspectively is meditation.
</p><p>
<b>Meditation, spiritual language</b>
</p><p>
Meditation is the language of the soul. It is defined as "a form of private devotion or spiritual
exercise, consisting in deep, continued reflection on some religious theme." Meditation is a
form of prayer. We can say prayers without having any spiritual response. We can say prayers
as the unrighteous king in <i>Hamlet</i>, who said: "My words fly up, my thoughts remain below:
Words without thoughts never to heaven go." (William Shakespeare, <i>Hamlet</i>, Act III, scene
3.)
</p><p>
The poet Robert Burns, contrasting the outward form of worship and the prayer of the soul,
said: 
</p><p>
"The Power, incens'd, the pageant will desert.<br />
         The pompous strain, the sacerdotal stole; <br />
         But haply, in some cottage far apart,<br />
         May hear, well-pleas'd, the language of the soul,<br />
         And in His Book of Life the inmates poor enroll."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        (Robert Burns, "The Cotter's Saturday Night.")
</p><p>
<b>Sacred door to the presence of the Lord</b>
</p><p>
Meditation is one of the most secret, most sacred doors through which we pass into the
presence of the Lord. Jesus set the example for us. As soon as he was baptized and received
the Father's approval&mdash;"This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>)&mdash;
Jesus repaired to what is now known as the Mount of Temptation where, during forty days of
fasting, he communed with himself and his Father and contemplated the responsibility of his
own great mission. One result of this spiritual communion was such strength as enabled him
to say to the tempter: "Get thee hence, Satan: for it is written, Thou shalt worship the Lord
thy God, and him only shalt thou serve" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/10#10">Matt. 4:10</a>).
</p><p>
Before he gave the beautiful Sermon on the Mount, he was in solitude, in communion. He did
the same thing after that busy Sabbath day, when he arose early in the morning after having
been the guest of Peter. Peter undoubtedly found the guest chamber empty, and when he and
others sought Jesus, they found him alone (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/1/35-36#35">Mark 1:35-36</a>). It was on that morning that they said: "All men
seek for thee" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/1/37#37">Mark 1:37</a>).
</p><p>
Again, after Jesus had fed the 5,000, he told the Twelve to dismiss the multitude. Then Jesus,
the historian says, went to the mountain for solitude; and "when the evening was come, he
was there alone" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/23#23">Matt. 14:23</a>). Meditation! Prayer!
</p><p>
<b>Meditation at the Lord's Supper</b>
</p><p>
I believe the short period of administering the sacrament is one of the best opportunities we
have for such meditation, and there should be nothing during that sacred period to distract our
attention from the purpose of that ordinance.
</p><p>
One of the most impressive services I have ever attended was a group of over 800 people to
whom the sacrament was administered, and during that administration not a sound could be
heard except the ticking of the clock&mdash;800 souls, each of whom at least had the opportunity
of communion with the Lord! There was no distraction, no music, no singing, no speaking.
Each one had an opportunity to search himself introspectively, and to consider his worthiness
or unworthiness to partake of the sacrament. His was the privilege of getting closer to his
Father in heaven. That is ideal!
</p><p>
<b>More reverence during meditation</b>
</p><p>
I strongly urge that this sacred ordinance be surrounded with more reverence, with perfect
order; that each one who comes to the house of God may meditate upon and silently and
prayerfully express appreciation for God's goodness. It is up to you bishops to see to it that
the sacrament is administered only by boys and young men who are worthy to attend to this
sacred ordinance, and that it is done reverently with a full understanding of its significance to
them and to the audience. Let the sacrament hour be one experience of the day in which the
worshiper tries at least to realize within himself that it is possible for him to commune with
his God.
</p><p>
<b>Response to inspiration of the Almighty</b>
</p><p>
Never forget that great events have happened in this Church because of such communion, and
because of the responsiveness of the soul to the inspiration of the Almighty. I know it is real!
You will find that when these most inspirational moments come to you, you are alone with
yourself and your God. They come to you probably when you are facing a great trial, when a
wall is across your pathway and it seems that you are facing an insurmountable obstacle, or
when your heart is heavy because of some tragedy in your life. I repeat, the greatest comfort
that can come to us in this life is to sense the realization of communion with God.
</p><p>
Great testimonies have come in those moments. It is just such an experience as that which
came to my father in the north of Scotland when he prayed to God to remove from him a
spirit of gloom and despondency that overwhelmed him. After a night of worry and
restlessness, he arose at daylight and repaired to a cave on the shore of the North Sea. He had
been there before in prayer. There, just as the rays of the morning light began to come over
the sea, he poured out his soul to God, as a son would appeal to his father. The answer came:
"Testify that Joseph Smith is a Prophet of God." The cause of his discouragement flashing
upon his mind, he said aloud: "Lord, it is enough!"
</p><p>
Those who knew my father could testify as to his integrity and his honesty. A testimony of
that kind has one hundred percent value.
</p><p>
These secret prayers, these conscientious moments in meditation, these yearnings of the soul
to reach out to feel the presence of God&mdash;such is your privilege and mine!
</p><p>
<b>Reverence, manifestation of spirituality</b>
</p><p>
Inseparable from the acceptance of the existence of God is an attitude of reverence. The
greatest manifestation of spirituality is reverence; indeed, reverence is spirituality. Reverence
is profound respect mingled with love. It is a "complex emotion made up of
mingled feelings of the soul." Carlyle says it is "the highest of human feelings." If reverence
is the highest, then irreverence is the lowest state in which a man can live in the world. Be
that as it may, it is nevertheless true that an irreverent man has a crudeness about him that is
repellent. He is cynical, often sneering, and always iconoclastic.
</p><p>
Reverence embraces regard, deference, honor, and esteem. Without some degree of it,
therefore, there would be no courtesy, no gentility, no consideration of others' feelings or of
others' rights. Reverence is the fundamental virtue in religion. It is one of the signs of
strength; irreverence, one of the surest indications of weakness. "No man will rise high," says
one man, "who jeers at sacred things. The fine loyalties of life must be reverenced or they
will be foresworn in the day of trial."
</p><p>
<b>Your attitude toward the Infinite Presence</b>
</p><p>
Churches are dedicated and set apart as houses of worship. This means that all who enter do
so, or at least pretend to do so, with an intent to get nearer the presence of the Lord than they
can on the street or amidst the worries of a workaday life. In other words, we go to the
Lord's house to meet him and to commune with him in spirit. Such a meeting place, then,
should first of all be fitting and appropriate in all respects, whether God is considered as the
invited guest, or the worshipers as his guests.
</p><p>
Whether the place of meeting is a humble chapel, or a "poem in architecture" built of white
marble and inlaid with precious stones, makes little or no difference in our approach and
attitude toward the Infinite Presence. To know that God is there should be sufficient to impel
us to conduct ourselves orderly, reverently. Presiding authorities in stake, ward, and quorum
meetings, and especially teachers in classes, should make a special effort to maintain better
order and more reverence during the hours of worship and study. Less talking behind the
pulpit will have a salutary effect upon those who face it. By example and precept, children
should be impressed with the inappropriateness of confusion and disorder in a worshiping
congregation. They should be impressed in childhood, and have it emphasized in youth, that it
is disrespectful to talk or even to whisper during a sermon, and that it is the height of
rudeness, except in an emergency, to leave a worshiping assembly before dismissal.
</p><p>
<b>The language of reverence</b>
</p><p>
Reverence for God's name should be dominant in every home. Profanity should never be
expressed in a home in this Church. It is wrong; it is irreverent to take God's name in vain
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/7#7">Ex. 20:7</a>).
There is no provocation that will justify it. Let us apply that quality and that virtue of
reverence at all times.
</p><p>
If there were more reverence in human hearts there would be less room for sin and sorrow,
and there would be increased capacity for joy and gladness. To make more cherished, more
adaptable, more attractive this gem among brilliant virtues is a project worthy of the most
united and prayerful efforts of every parent, every officer, and every member of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>My testimony</b>
</p><p>
My soul is stirred with deep emotions when I think of what the gospel has done for this
people, and what it will yet do if we will but keep in tune with his Spirit and commandments.
I love the gospel and believe in it with all my soul; I know it is the power of God unto
salvation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>). I bear witness that the gospel of Jesus Christ was revealed in its completeness to the
Prophet Joseph Smith, and I pray that our young people, and all people everywhere, will be
led to know of its truth.
</p><p>
God bless you men of the priesthood, you teachers of youth, you parents, and all good people
everywhere. May the ecclesiastical groups of the Church be blessed with the spirit of unity
and harmony. May there be banished from their hearts the spirit of enmity, backbiting, and
evil speaking, and may they keep in their hearts the truth expressed by Jesus when he said, ".
. . if ye are not one ye are not mine" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/27#27">D&amp;C 38:27</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Live for the companionship of the Holy Spirit</b>
</p><p>
I pray we may have the strength so to live that we may merit divine guidance and inspiration;
that through worship, meditation, communion, and reverence we may sense the reality of
being able to have a close relationship with our Father in heaven. I bear you my testimony
that it is real; that we can commune with our Heavenly Father. And if we so live to be
worthy of the companionship of the Holy Spirit, he will guide us unto all truth; he will show
us things to come (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13#13">John 16:13</a>); he will bring all things to our remembrance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>); he will testify of the divinity
of the Lord Jesus Christ and restoration of the gospel. God bless you all for your faith and
loyalty, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
