<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1944, pp. 66-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am very happy to be with you here today, my brethren, and bring you the good news that
President Hardy of our Council is better today and continually improving, and to elicit upon
his behalf faith and prayers that his recovery may be rapid and complete.
</p><p>
As I came into the building, I met a very dear brother who has feted something similarly to
him, for a number of years, who now that he has been completely healed through the
blessings of the Lord. We know that it is possible, and if we unite our prayers in behalf
President Hardy we feel sure that he can come back to service and our companionship.
</p><p>
One feels a sense of responsibility in occupying the time of group of men, and I pray that
God may give me His spirit, the few moments that I stand here, that I may say something that
may possibly helpful to a few of us. Before I start out, however, I want to my very great
pleasure at the presence on the stand of the President the Church, my venerable uncle, and tell
him that our constant prayer in our family is for his well-being.
</p><p>
OUR DAILY CONDUCT
</p><p>
We are a missionary group, the First Council of the as we go forth, we constantly have in
mind the dissemination of God, the bearing of testimony as to the restoration of the Gospel
in the latter dispensation. We study the D&amp;C for themes to use in approaching the people. I
remember that when some of the brethren in early days asked the Prophet to ask the Lord
what they best do for their own welfare, the Lord told them, through the Prophet Joseph
Smith, that they could do nothing better than to call the world to repentance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/15/6#6">D&amp;C 15:6</a>); and as I came to
the stand, President Young suggested that I talk about this subject.
</p><p>
I have come to the conclusion that there is never a day in my life when it is not essential to
my well-being. I think sometimes some of us think of repentance in a rather narrow way, but
I am coming to feel that it applies to everything we do in life, whether its purpose be
temporal or spiritual. The Lord has told us that there is nothing purely temporal, that in all we
do there is a spiritual aspect (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/34#34">D&amp;C 29:34</a>).
I believe that is true, that every activity, every
honest and honorable activity of life should be directed toward the well-being of the sons and
daughters of God; and if it is, it is spiritual in its nature.
</p><p>
As we meet each other in our daily walks, we strive to help each other to live better, more
successfully, that we may prosper. Some of us are not particularly careful in our dealings with
each other, to be honest, and to give all a fair chance. I believe that in all of our dealings
there is something to be gained, that a fair exchange is justified; for a fair exchange is no
robbery, and that men can deal honestly and honorably with each other, so that there may be
profits on both sides of the deal. I believe that we should strive to that end and purpose in all
our labors.
</p><p>
I believe that all of us, when we view our own conduct, and can see that we have taken
undue advantage of another, have reason to repent. I believe that all of us who, when we
think of our sons and our daughters, feel that we have not given them the type of teaching
and leadership that they should have had, have reason to repent. There is nothing on earth that
is of greater value to us than our children, and there is little that has less care at certain times
from certain people. We travel around from place to place, we see frequently children who
are allowed just to grow up; they have no leadership in their homes, they have no guidance,
and they have no care. Fortunately, that is a condition which is not prevalent in the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE A PRINCIPLE OF GROWTH
</p><p>
I do feel, however, that there are occasions and instances in which even our children do not
have the type of leadership that they should have, and the prominence of certain sins among
us indicates that very thing.
</p><p>
I think that when we go to our rest at night, we should thank God for any success we have
had during the day, and ask Him for faith in guiding our children. We should do the same
thing when we start upon the duties of the day in the morning. We should ask God for faith
in caring for them. Now, if we have not done so, we have reason for repentance.
</p><p>
If we have misrepresented any act, anything in our business activities of the day, we have
reason for repentance.
</p><p>
We are constantly repenting of the practical things that we do in life. Whenever a man comes
to us and tells us that we can grow more wheat by changing our system, we repent, although
we do not call it that. We abandon an old practice that was not good, and take on a new one
which is better, but we are not so prone to adopt the suggestions of people who are inspired
of the Lord when they come to us and tell us how we can better our spiritual lives. We ought
to pay attention to those suggestions because they are prompted by the Spirit of God.
</p><p>
Now, we are daily confronted with the task of deciding what we would like to do, and what
we can best do, from the many things we would like to do. None of us can do everything we
would like; we have to make that decision. We have to decide what is the
worthwhile thing, and what is not. If we have been in the habit of doing things that our
better judgment tells us are not quite the best thing that we might do for our good and the
good of those depending upon us, we have there a chance for repentance.
</p><p>
Let us inspect our lives and see if we do not, all of us, have room to change our way of
living. I feel that many of us do. We, who are here, are the priesthood of God. We are the
leaders of the people; we have a charge; we have a duty; and if we can feel that we have
fully acquitted ourselves of that duty and responsibility, all is well and good.
</p><p>
Perhaps, as leaders of wards and branches and priesthood quorums, we have need to repent,
because we have not fully done our duty. I feel sure that many of us have not. If we all had,
perhaps our quorums would be in better condition than they are.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY OF LEADERSHIP
</p><p>
When we accept these offices, we accept a definite responsibility, very, very definite, one to
lead. Now, people like leadership when it is good and just, and they approve of it. They
follow it. But it is not a common thing for a man to be able to guide a community according
to a program that he himself will not subscribe to. Perhaps some of us need to repent of some
of our priesthood leadership practices, so that we may be able to say: "Come, let us go in this
direction."
</p><p>
I think that is one of our greatest responsibilities as leaders of this Church, that we should be
honest and true, absolutely honest and true to the standards of the Church and the obligations
of leadership which we assume.
</p><p>
There is no place in all our activities for us to forget this responsibility, and to forget that 
from day to day we should better our way of living. We should increase our power of
leadership; we should be more eager to serve and better qualified to serve. If we cannot gain
through the experience of today more power for tomorrow, we are unfortunate. If we should
see in the work we do today wherein we have failed, we, as leaders of the priesthood, have
reason to repent, to abandon the bad of today, and to replace it with a better system for
tomorrow.
</p><p>
Brethren, do not get the idea that repentance is something that is only for the man who does
not belong to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, because it is a thing that applies
to us every hour, and every day, and every year of our lives. We will never be perfect, and
the last act of our lives may be one of repentance. We should remember it, and apply it.
</p><p>
I pray that God will bless us, that He will make us strong, that we, the leaders of Israel, will
have the inspiration of His holy spirit in leading this people, that they can honestly support us
and follow us in the things we ask them to do. God bless you. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
