<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Significance of World Trends</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 115-121</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and to the
rest of the apostles, Men and brethren, what shall we do?
</p><p>
Then Peter said unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus
Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37-39#37">Acts 2:37-39</a>).
</p><p>
APPRECIATION OF UTAH CENTENNIAL COMMISSION
</p><p>
Before commenting on the thought expressed in this scripture, may I take one moment, in
behalf of the Utah Centennial Commission, and so far as I may, the governor and other state
officials who have sustained the commission, to express to the people of Utah heartfelt
commendation for their cooperation and united effort during this centennial year.
</p><p>
I wish to name especially the county committees, the public school teachers, President Olpin
and the University of Utah, President McDonald and the Brigham Young University, President
Harris and the Utah State Agricultural College, President Dixon and the Weber College, and
the Utah State Teachers' Association&mdash;these must be added to the director and to the scores of
committees heretofore publicly recognized, to whose united and devoted effort is due all
credit for whatever success has been achieved during the 1947 celebration.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR BLESSINGS
</p><p>
Meeting with you this morning in this great conference, I am deeply grateful for my
knowledge of the existence of God, our loving Father, and of his Beloved Son, our Savior in
very deed. I am grateful for the restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ. In the depths of my
soul I know it is true.
</p><p>
I am happy in my love for my immediate associates, President George Albert Smith and
President J. Reuben Clark, Jr., and for these noble men of the Council of the Twelve, the
Assistants to the Council of the Twelve, the Council of the Seventy, the Presiding Bishopric,
the Patriarch. I find it a joy to work with you loyal men who preside in stakes and wards and
branches. It is a privilege to have the opportunity to labor with you, to recognize your
unselfish devotion to the Church.
</p><p>
Life, though freighted with great responsibilities and a consciousness of my inability, and
regrets for failures, is still wholesome and sweet.
</p><p>
The world is full of honorable men and women who, as those men who accosted Peter on the
day of Pentecost, desire to know what to do&mdash;what to believe.
</p><p>
A man who has reached the four score mark in years hailed me yesterday morning with the
comment: "The world is in a terrible condition, isn't it?"
</p><p>
I replied: "It certainly is and greatly in need of wise, steady guidance."
</p><p>
EPOCH-MAKING PERIOD
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, we are living in what may be the most epoch-making period of all time.
Scientific discoveries and inventions, the breaking down of heretofore approved social and
moral standards, the uprooting of old religious moorings all give evidence that we are
witnessing one of those tidal waves of human thought which periodically sweep over the
world and change the destiny of the human race. I call attention to world conditions because
the mission of the Church of Christ is worldwide. Its responsibility and commission is to:
</p><p>
. . . teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son,
and of the Holy Ghost: Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have
commanded you (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
SCIENTIFIC PROGRESS
</p><p>
Last September 23, Colonel James M. Gillespie, commander of the robot C54 Skymaster,
made a flight of twenty-four hundred miles from. Newfoundland to Brise, Norton Airfield,
England, demonstrating that a pilotless plane can be sent three thousand miles from the
United States and back again from one radio station.
</p><p>
Fourteen men crossed the ocean without touching a button or a wheel!
</p><p>
Imagine what could happen if, instead of fourteen passengers, that robot plane carried two
thousand five hundred pounds of atom bombs. Then imagine not only one such plane, but
fifty, all bent on destruction, and guided accurately by mechanical brains!
</p><p>
A more recent dispatch from Washington (September 30, Associated Press ) says that "robot
warfare between continents is definitely possible." It states further that "the methods and
equipment needed to make missiles capable of carrying a five thousand-pound war head at six
hundred miles an hour for four thousand miles are already well known in this country."
</p><p>
On August 11, 1947, William P. Odom, twenty-seven-year-old airplane pilot, completed a
world record by flying around the globe in seventy-three hours, five minutes and eleven
seconds, at a speed of 310 miles an hour.
</p><p>
On August 26, 1947, a navy plane, piloted by Major Marion E. Carl, thirty-one years of age,
broke the air speed record by flying at the rate of 650 miles an hour.
</p><p>
What modern science is doing in other fields is even more astounding.
</p><p>
In a current magazine for this month, the thought is advanced as a possible accomplishment
that man may succeed in turning night into day, not by candles, lanterns, or electric lights, but
by "doing away with the earth's darkness entirely." One of the experiments now being carried
on has to do with forms of electrons that "rush through ninety million miles of space between
the sun and the earth and crash into the atmosphere."
</p><p>
When the electrons hit a molecule or atom of one of the atmospheric gases, the
molecule or atom is ionized, and the gas glows just as it does in a fluorescent light
bulb. There you have the germ of the idea that may prove to be one of the great
scientific developments of our time.
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY TO CONTROL DISCOVERIES
</p><p>
I refer to these marvels, which are merely illustrative of many others, to emphasize the fact&mdash;if
anything so obvious needs emphasis&mdash;that we are living in an age of scientific discovery and
invention unequaled by any previous period in the world's history&mdash;discoveries latent with
such potent powers either for the blessing or the destruction of human beings as to make
man's responsibility in controlling them the most gigantic ever placed in human hands.
</p><p>
This responsibility and its possible results prompted one man (Hayden) to write:
</p><p>
Today, as seldom if ever before, human society is threatened with disintegration,
if not complete chaos. All the ancient evils of human relationships, injustice,
selfishness, abuse of strength, become sinister and terrible when reinforced by the
vast increase of material power. The soul of man cowers, starved and fearful, in
the midst of a civilization grown too complex for any mind to visualize or to
control.
</p><p>
NEED FOR DIVINE GUIDANCE
</p><p>
Throughout the world generally today there is a spirit of unrest, a grasping for untried
ideologies, (and our community is not an exception), and, what is worst of all, a tendency
toward moral abandonment. It is all too apparent that "our spiritual culture lags far behind our
material culture in its development."
</p><p>
Now is a time when peoples in all the world should pause and in all earnestness repeat the
Pentecostal question propounded to Peter and other apostles:
</p><p>
Men and brethren, what shall we do?
</p><p>
Representatives of fifty nations are now assembled trying to find an answer. Communist
nations, however, are clashing with Christian groups, and it looks as though the proverbial
dove of peace if not killed might again be seriously crippled.
</p><p>
At the final plenary session of the United Nations Conference when the charter was about to
be signed, five great leaders invoked the Lord's aid to the end that the cause of peace would
not fail.
</p><p>
Said Mr. Edward Stettinius:
</p><p>
To the governments and peoples of the fifty nations here represented, this charter
is now committed, and may Almighty God from this day on and in the months
and years to come sustain us in the unalterable purpose that its promise may be
fulfilled.
</p><p>
The Earl of Halifax, chairman of the delegation of the United Kingdom, said:
</p><p>
Let us also, mindful alike of the world's need and of our own weakness, pray that,
under God's guidance, what we have done here in these last weeks will be found
worthy of the faith which gave it birth, and of the human suffering which has been
its price.
</p><p>
His Royal Highness, Amir Faisal Ibin Abdiel Aziz, chairman of the delegation of Saudi
Arabia, stated:
</p><p>
As long as we are united together in a spirit of cooperation, the hands of Almighty God will
lead us. We shall always have his aid so long as we help one another.
</p><p>
And Field Marshall Jan Christiaan Smuts of South Africa, said:
</p><p>
May heaven's blessings rest on it.
</p><p>
And the President of our own United States prayed that under God's guidance the cause
would succeed.
</p><p>
Unless such appeals were mere empty phrases, these leaders indicate the only safe and sure
way wars may be averted, and peace among nations established. Not through communistic
theories, not by the manifestations of mistrust, suspicion, and hatred will the turbulency of
national ills be quieted. Unless the spirit of Christianity permeate the deliberations of the
United Nations, dire tragedies await humanity.
</p><p>
OPPORTUNITY FOR SCIENTIFIC ADVANCEMENT
</p><p>
On the other hand never since the beginning of history has there been such an opportunity for
the nations to utilize inventions and scientific discoveries to the blessing and peace of human
beings.
</p><p>
Dr. Charles A. Elwood truly says:
</p><p>
Our material culture has advanced by leaps and bounds until we find almost
unlimited physical power in our hands; but our spiritual culture has lagged, and
we find many of the traditions of barbarism still strong among us, especially the
traditions of war and self-indulgence at the expense of others. These traditions,
along with the ignorance and paganism of the masses of mankind, make our
world, we must acknowledge, a veritable powder house at the present time.
Almost any powerful group foolish enough to do so could explode it. If western
civilization emerges from this situation safely, it will only be through a deeper
appreciation of the social ethics of Jesus than it has yet shown.
</p><p>
O, shall we never learn
The truth all time has taught&mdash;
That without God as architect
Our building comes to naught?
</p><p>
The following remarks made by United States congressmen in the House of
Representatives sound a true note of warning to the world:
</p><p>
The nations and peoples of the earth must go back to God the Father no matter
how hard, how long, or how bloody the road. The conflict in which we are now
and will be engaged during the coming years will determine the destiny and type
of government for mankind for the next thousand years. By our courageous faith,
by our patient sacrifice, and by our loyal obedience to God, we shall build a
permanent, new-world social order, founded upon the enduring and eternal
principles of Christian truth and justice. This will be the grand climax of
mankind's age-long endeavor and imminent struggle to conquer the chaos of evil
forces and achieve and establish the divine order of the ages&mdash;peace, plenty, and
prosperity for all nations and all mankind.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE NEEDED
</p><p>
Infidelity and sexual immorality are two principal evils that threaten to weaken and to wreck
present-day civilization. Unfortunately, the trends of modern life are tending to disintegrate
the very foundation of the Christian home. Sexual laxity among young people, birth control,
and intemperance are its insidious and vicious enemies. When family life disintegrates, the
foundation and bulwark of human society is undermined.
</p><p>
Men and brethren, what shall we do?
</p><p>
The answer today is the same as it was two thousand years ago, the same as it will ever be
throughout time.
</p><p>
All men must repent and believe on the name of Jesus Christ, and worship the
Father in his name and endure in faith on his name to the end or they cannot be
saved in the kingdom of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/29#29">D&amp;C 20:29</a>).
</p><p>
Said the Savior:
</p><p>
Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart; and ye shall
find rest unto your souls.
</p><p>
For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/29-30#29">Matt. 11:29-30</a>).
</p><p>
As the honest people of the world wonder in vain, and cry out in uncertainty, what shall we
do? Members of the Church of Christ who feel secure in the knowledge of the restored gospel
should say, "Men and brethren, what <i>can</i> we do?"
</p><p>
PLAN OF ACTION SUGGESTED
</p><p>
Some specific things which the priesthood and their families can and should do are these:
</p><p>
First&mdash;We can set an example of uprightness; be honest in all our dealings; avoid vulgarity and
profanity; demonstrate to our neighbors and to all whom we meet that we live clean,
honorable lives.
</p><p>
Let your light so shine among men that they may see your good works, and glorify your
Father which is in heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
Second&mdash;Let us strive for peace and harmony in the home. If we cannot keep quarreling,
bickering, and selfishness out of our home, how can we even hope to banish these evils from
society?
</p><p>
A true Mormon home is one in which if Christ should chance to enter, he would be pleased
to linger and to rest.
</p><p>
Third&mdash;Having at least striven for a good character, having a home environment that is
creditable, we may then consistently discharge our duty as authorized representatives of the
Lord Jesus Christ to declare to the world that the conditions that will bring peace and comfort
to the individual, to the family, and to the nation, are found in the restored gospel of Jesus
Christ. These can be named and understood and as easily practiced with resultant contentment
and peace as are the evils and vices that bring tribulation.
</p><p>
Summarized these fundamentals are: An acceptance of Christ as Savior and Redeemer; a
moving, soul-consciousness of the existence of God, and that he is our Father in Heaven; a
daily life consistent with such a knowledge; a love for one's fellow men.
</p><p>
In other words, as the Savior summarized the law and the prophets:
</p><p>
Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy
mind . . . and thy neighbor as thyself
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/12/31-32#31">Mark 12:31-32</a>).
</p><p>
WORLD NEEDS SPIRITUALITY
</p><p>
I realize, as I have said elsewhere, that skeptics, and pessimists say that these principles are
too idealistic, that mankind is too near the beasts of creation, struggling to eke out an
existence, even to attempt to apply them in daily life. In reply, I say men and women have
practiced them and have been happy, and have made the world better in so doing. Christ's
disciples did it in Jesus' day, (as impressively stated yesterday by Elder Albert E. Bowen),
and they have influenced millions of lives since. There have been thousands since their day,
some heralded on the pages of history, and others of whom the world has never heard who,
through love of God, truth, and of fellow men, have "never yielded to the pressure of
circumstances," and who, though they faced persecution and even death, could say in their
hearts as the Prophet Joseph Smith declared as he turned into the path that led to his
martyrdom: "If my life is of no value to my friends, it is of no value to me."
</p><p>
The world needs millions more whose influence will counteract the evil spread by the
multi-millions who grope in selfishness, sordidness, suspicion, hatred, and crimes of varying
degree.
</p><p>
After all, the spiritual life is the true life of man. It is what distinguishes him from the beasts
of the forests. It lifts him above the physical, yet he is still susceptible to all the natural
contributions that life can give him that are needful for his happiness or contributive to his
advancement. Though "<i>in</i> the world, he is not <i>of</i> the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/11,14#11">John 17:11,14</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus taught that men and women fail to live truly, unless they have spirituality. In the 
<i>Life and Teachings of Jesus</i>, we read that the spiritual force underlies everything, and without it
nothing worthwhile can be accomplished. "Spiritual needs can be met only by spiritual
means. All government, laws, methods, and organizations are of no value unless men and
women are filled with truth, righteousness, and mercy. Material things have no power to raise
the sunken spirit. Gravitation, electricity, and steam are great forces, but they are all
powerless to change the motives of men and women." Except a man be born again, he cannot
see the kingdom of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/3#3">John 3:3</a>).
</p><p>
GOSPEL OFFERS SOLUTION
</p><p>
Men of the priesthood, we must continue to declare that the gospel, the Glad Tidings of Great
Joy, is the true guide to mankind; and that men and women are happiest and most content
who live nearest to its teachings.
</p><p>
The voice of the Lord is unto all men, and there is none to escape; and there is
no eye that shall not see, neither ear that shall not hear, neither heart that shall not
be penetrated. . . .
</p><p>
And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I
have chosen in these last days
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/2,4#2">D&amp;C 1:2,4</a>).
</p><p>
What the sun in the heavenly blue is to the earth struggling to get free from winter's grip, so
the gospel is to sorrowing souls yearning for something higher and better than mankind has
yet found.
</p><p>
If men and nations will hold their belief in God, and accept the teachings of Jesus Christ,
pilotless planes and other argosies of the air encircling the globe in a nightless world will
carry not bombs of merciless destruction, but gifts and blessings to what is now a groping,
benighted world.
</p><p>
All the world is in the Valley of Decision<br />
And out of it there is but one sure road;<br />
Eyes unsealed can still foresee the mighty vision<br />
Of a world in travail turning unto God.
</p><p>
May heaven help all members of the Church of Christ to live and labor for the spreading
throughout the world of the gospel of light and truth and peace, I pray in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
