<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">What We Are Fighting For</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard R. Lyman</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard R. Lyman, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1943, pp. 82-86</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Long years ago Abraham Lincoln said that ". . . our fathers brought forth on this continent, a
new nation, conceived in liberty, and dedicated to the proposition that all men are created
equal. Now," said he, "we are engaged in a great Civil War, testing whether that nation or any
nation so conceived and so dedicated can long endure. . . ."
</p><p>
TO ENDURE FOREVER
</p><p>
Today we are engaged in a greater war, a war that covers the whole earth. We are fighting on
battlefields around the world for the sacred purpose of demonstrating that, God being our
helper, not only one nation, our nation, but that any and all nations ". . . conceived in liberty,
and dedicated to the proposition that all men are created equal . . ." shall not only endure
long, but shall endure forever. That is the great cause and blessing for which we are fighting
today. And using again the language of the immortal Lincoln, we have resolved that those
heroes of the other world war who gave their lives and those of this war who make the
supreme sacrifice ". . . shall not have died in vain. . . ." We have resolved that "under God"
the whole world ". . . shall have a new birth of freedom. and that government of the people,
by the people, for the people, shall not perish from the earth. . . ."
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; BETTER DEAD THAN A SLAVE
</p><p>
Henry Van Dyke says:
</p><p>
Oh, better to be dead<br />
With a face turned toward the sky,<br />
Than live beneath a slavish dread<br />
And serve a giant lie.
</p><p>
Stand up, stand up, my heart, and strive<br />
For the things most dear to thee!<br />
Why should we care to be alive<br />
Unless the world is free?
</p><p>
GIANT ROBBER'S WORLD-WIDE WAR
</p><p>
What he wrote then concerning the other world war and our flag applies to this world war
and to our flag with even greater accuracy and force:
</p><p>
O fiercer than all wars before<br />
That raged on land or sea,<br />
The Giant Robber's world-wide war<br />
For the things that shall not be!<br />
Thy sister banners hold the line;<br />
To thee, dear flag, they call;<br />
And thou hast joined them with the sign&mdash;<br />
The heavenly sign, the victor sign&mdash;<br />
Of the stars that never fall.<br /><br />
All hail to thee, New Glory!<br />
We follow thee unfurled<br />
To write the larger story<br />
Of the Freedom of the World.
</p><p>
THE WHOLE WORLD FREE
</p><p>
On the very day the other war was ended, November 11, 1918, he wrote:<br /><br />
Oh, welcome home in Heaven's peace, dear spirits of the dead!<br />
And welcome home ye living sons America hath bred!<br />
The lords of war are beaten down, your glorious task is done;<br />
You fought to make the whole world free, and the victory is won.
</p><p>
How unfortunate that that thrilling and glorious achievement, thus so dearly and so
dramatically stated, did not actually become a reality.
</p><p>
A TEMPLE AND THE CENTER OF PEACE
</p><p>
When President Grant was in Europe a few years ago, the mayor of Geneva, Switzerland,
took him and as many others of his party as the mayor's car would carry (seven as I
remember it) and showed the members of that party the flowers, the parks, the mountain
scenery, the loveliness of Lake Geneva, and many other of the attractions in and about that
famous city, that great center of peace. President Grant the next day expressed the thought
that somewhere among the hills surrounding that city, in that land of freedom and democracy,
it would be fitting indeed for the Church of Jesus Christ to build a temple.
</p><p>
OUR ALL UPON THE ALTAR
</p><p>
The mayor later also took the party through the historic municipal and national buildings of
Geneva and showed to us, the members of the party, the many and impressive historic
documents and other treasures which the people of Switzerland hold dear as we hold dear the
original copies of the Constitution of the United States and our Declaration of Independence.
Some twenty-one or twenty-two nations are held together in Switzerland by their love of
independence and liberty much as our forty-eight states are held together. The elimination of
war, that is, the preservation and maintenance of peace, is the principal aim of the officials
and people of that great city and that little but great republic, Switzerland. They are
endeavoring to secure for mankind in all the world that great blessing of peace and good will
which Christ came so long ago to bring, that blessing for which all good Christian people
around the whole world are so fervently praying during these terrible and trying times. It is
for this great cause that the United Nations including our own beloved country are now
unselfishly putting their all upon the altar of war. By force we have had thrust upon us this
great conflict and, spurred on by our love of liberty, we, the United Nations, are making
gigantic efforts to win. 
</p><p>
WILL WIN COURAGEOUSLY
</p><p>
The motto of our country is "In God we trust," and throughout our land we sing&mdash;
</p><p>
Long may our land be bright with freedom's holy light;
Protect us by Thy might, Great God, our King.
</p><p>
With faith in God the Eternal Father to whom nothing is impossible, we have carried into this
mighty and unparalleled struggle "the only flag in all the world that has never known defeat."
God helping us we shall not only win, but however great the cost in tears, in blood, in human
life, or in economic treasure, we shall win courageously.
</p><p>
And when peace finally comes and the war is ended, the following words of Van Dyke found
in his poem entitled "Golden Stars," will apply as appropriately no doubt as they did when
they were read for the first time at the Memorial Service held at Princeton University,
December 15, 1918, just four days after the Armistice was signed. He said:
</p><p>
But many a lad we hold<br />
Dear in our heart of hearts<br />
Is missing from the home-returning host.<br />
Ah, say not they are lost,<br />
For they have found and given their life<br />
In sacrificial strife:<br />
Their service stars have changed from blue to gold!
</p><p>
ONE TEAR, ONE WORD OF GRIEF
</p><p>
Listen to his expressions concerning the courage, the determination, and the daring of the
mothers of these whose stars have changed from blue to gold:<br /><br />
O happy warriors, forgive the tear<br />
Falling from eyes that miss you;<br />
Forgive the word of grief from mother-lips<br />
That ne'er on earth shall kiss you;<br />
Hear only what our hearts would have you hear&mdash;<br />
Glory and praise and gratitude and pride<br />
From the dear country in whose cause you died.<br />
Now you have run your race and won your prize,<br />
Old age shall never burden you, the fears<br />
And conflicts that beset our lingering years<br />
Shall never vex your souls in Paradise.<br />
Immortal, young, and crowned with victory,<br />
From life's long battle you have found release.<br />
And He who died for all on Calvary<br />
Has welcomed you, brave soldiers of the cross,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;       Into eternal peace.
</p><p>
Come, let us gird our loins and lift our load,<br />
Companions who are left on life's rough road,<br />
And bravely take the way that we must tread<br />
To keep true faith with our beloved dead.<br />
To conquer war they dared their lives to give,<br />
To safeguard peace our hearts must learn to live.<br />
Help us, dear God, our forward faith to hold!<br />
We want a better world than that of old.<br />
Lead us on paths of high endeavor,<br />
Toiling upward, climbing ever,<br />
Ready to suffer for the right,<br />
Until at last we gain a loftier height,<br />
More worthy to behold<br />
Our guiding stars, our hero-stars of gold.
</p><p>
TO THEE NOTHING IMPOSSIBLE
</p><p>
This struggle is like that great war of long ago which was fought in heaven. And the cause
for which we fight is the same, that is, liberty and freedom, the right of choice, for all the 
sons and all the daughters of God. However great the cost, this struggle must go on until we
are victorious. These are trying days, terrible times. The agony on the part of the mothers
and of the young wives of those soldiers who may be called upon to give their lives on the
field of honor is not unlike the agony of the Master Himself in the garden of Gethsemane. It
was under the trying conditions then surrounding Him that He exclaimed, ". . . Father, all
things are possible unto thee; take away this cup from me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/14/36#36">Mark 14:36</a>). Three times
He repeated this the most earnest, prayerful appeal that ever fell from His divine lips. The
situation was so serious that ". . . his sweat was as it were great drops of blood falling down
to the ground." The load He had to bear was so heavy that ". . . there appeared an angel unto
him from heaven, strengthening him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/43-44#43">Luke 22:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
PRAYER OF JESUS NOT ANSWERED
</p><p>
And was this His most earnest prayer answered? It was not. Then came the sublimest moment
of His most remarkable life when He added, ". . . nevertheless, not my will, but thine, be
done" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/42#42">Luke 22:42</a>).
Thus, by enduring that great agony, the Savior took upon Himself the
sins of all men that all men on condition of repentance might come unto Him.
</p><p>
FATHER, THY WILL BE DONE
</p><p>
And so with us. We, the United Nations, have put our hands to the plow
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/62#62">Luke 9:62</a>), and this contest, on
a world of battlefields, unparalleled as it is in magnitude and extent, we will win, however
great the cost. And being followers of Jesus, the Son of God, and members of His Church,
the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, let us do as He did at the time of His great
agony, that is, appeal to our Heavenly Father in great earnestness and humility for the lives of
our loved ones to be spared and for their bodies to be unharmed. But back of these earnest
and humble prayerful appeals, let us, as best we can, be courageous and Christ-like. Back of
all these appeals may we have, in some degree, that spirit Christ so gloriously exhibited
during that sublimest moment of His life when to His most earnest prayerful appeal He added,
". . . nevertheless, not my will, but thine, be done"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/42#42">Luke 22:42</a>). Thus courageously and
Christ-like, may we plunge with all our might into this greatest of all world wars, and by the
power of God may we deserve to win, and by that same power may victory be ours with the
least possible loss of blood, and the fewest possible number of tears, and of heartaches, I
humbly pray.
</p>
</div>
</div>
