<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Joseph Smith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1948, pp. 94-97</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Like all great movements in history, the rise of Mormonism has been interpreted in various
ways. When we think of its importance in the preparation of our modern habit of mind, we
must class it with the greatest epochs of advancement in human history. Great epochs have
always had a prime mover, a man with enlightened soul. So it is with Mormonism. Human
society contains in itself the causes of development in everything except the higher religious
and moral truths, and the real facts of our future life. To the divine help, the life of Joseph
Smith was confined; to the bringing of that higher truth and moral light which could not be
developed except by some divine message from heaven. He brought to light the nature of
God, man's immortality, and the highest elements of moral character. The things which he
taught are destined to be recognized as the most enlightened teachings for the world since
Jesus Christ gave his gospel to mankind. The power of his teachings is gradually rising to
shape the destiny of the human race. As a boy he bore witness to the nations of the earth of
the need of a light which is not of man.
</p><p>
DIVISIONS OF CHRISTIANITY
</p><p>
Itinerant preachers of the frontier came to the parental cabin with tracts on the subject of
religion. These preachers were the representatives of the denominations of America,
particularly the Protestant faiths. The divisions of Christendom were the most conspicuous
reproach and chief cause of the inefficiency of Christianity. "They presented a moral affront
to the enterprise inaugurated by Jesus Christ and constituted the outstanding limitation of its
progress in the world." Mr. Herbert L. Willett in a recent article in the magazine,
<i>Christendom</i>, says:
</p><p>
As truly as war is an anachronism and a scandal to civilization the divided state of the Church
is an affront to Christianity.
</p><p>
"Divide and conquer," was the counsel which Milton put into the mouth of Satan in the
assembly of the rebel angels.
</p><p>
DISPENSATIONS OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
In the history of mankind down to the time of Christ, there have been dispensations of the
gospel of Christ. Adam, the father of the human race, had the gospel. His descendants were
knowing men, men with a knowledge of God. Between God and the earth was man, created
in the image of God. The description is exalted. The greatness of man came by his knowledge
that he was closely related to his Creator, and he felt the divine creative presence. He knew
his Creator, he listened to him, he obeyed him, he loved him. In a phrase written long after
by the Psalmist, man was made "a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with
glory and honour" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/5#5">Ps. 8:5</a>).
From Adam's time to the present, we may know this truth:
"No religion made by man can do for men that which must be done."
</p><p>
One modern writer, Maurice Masterlinck, writes in his book, The Great Secret: "What we
read in the ancient archives of wisdom gives us only a faint idea of the sublime doctrines of
the ancient teachers, and even so these are not in their original form. The more ancient the
texts, the purer, the more awe-inspiring the doctrines which they reveal."
</p><p>
CONTRIBUTIONS OF JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
The facts of the Prophet's life are many. His teachings are reduced to writing in one of the
marvelous books of the age in which we live: The D&amp;C. We may contrast this fact with the
influence of other men upon the world, for there have been teachers whose influence never
will die. Socrates became a moral force for mankind throughout the ages. Plato, his disciple,
was second to none as a great teacher. He wrote copiously and elaborately. Possibly no one
has ever surpassed him in the art of writing and thinking. Then came Aristotle, who wrote on
science and philosophy. The force of the Greek mind of ages ago still lives. All of these
masters were morally and intellectually great. Joseph Smith stands out as the revealer of
God's eternal principles that show above all writers in this age the divinity of man; the
doctrine of eternal progression; the true meaning of salvation; the divine love which man must
have toward all other men; the purifying of the soul before God.
</p><p>
His teachings are not the result of mere intellectual attainments. It was not human genius that
made him what he was. I It is not enough for man to think wisely and well. The power of his
teachings has arisen from the words that God spoke to him. The secret of his power lay in the
truth that man is a divine creation and can understand the divine word if one's life is tuned to
the noblest feeling with his God. The men who accepted the revealed gospel, who were given
the priesthood, helped to inaugurate a new period in the history of the human race.
</p><p>
RELIGION REQUIRES REVELATION
</p><p>
The supreme test of religion is revelation. No religion can be persuasive and convincing that
does not rely upon and embody an authentic principle of revelation. Religion as a purely
human product, valuable as it might be to human progress, has not the inner vigor to maintain
a place of commanding power. <i>Religion requites revelation</i>. All truth is revealed not less so
because it is discovered.
</p><p>
The most complete carrier of revelation can be no other or less than a chosen personality.
This is the Christian doctrine and conception. Revelation requires development and the
concept of the divinity of the spirit and mind of man. Such was in brief the teaching of
Adam, of Abraham, of Moses, Isaiah, and all the prophets of the Old Testament. It constituted
the pure idealism and faith of Jesus Christ, for he gave to his Father in heaven the dominant
role in ordering the world for good. It gave in olden times, and must give now, the supreme
lesson that God lives, that the spirit and the body are the soul of man, and the resurrection
from the dead is the redemption of the soul. Therefore, it must needs be sanctified from all
unrighteousness, that it may be prepared for the celestial glory. It gives to man the supreme
principles of ethical and moral life. It becomes the supreme power whereby man knows life
and knows it more abundantly,
</p><p>
For intelligence cleaveth unto intelligence; wisdom receiveth wisdom; truth embraceth truth;
virtue loveth virtue; light cleaveth unto light; mercy hath compassion on mercy and claimeth
its own; justice continueth its course and claimeth its own; judgment goeth before the face of
him who sitteth upon the throne and governeth and executeth all things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/40#40">D&amp;C 88:40</a>).
</p><p>
"The glory of God is intelligence . . . light and truth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
</p><p>
"To his own master each man will
stand or fall; and he that judgeth us is the Lord." We will serve our church and country best as
we perform day by day and hour by hour those humble and simple acts of self-dedication
which make our lives a silent witness of him who brought light, and life and love into this
sorrowful world. 
</p><p>
THE FOUNDERS OF AMERICA
</p><p>
America must hold to the simple beginnings of our founders. They brought hither in their
little ships not money, not merchandise, no array of armed force, but they came with deep
religious feelings, learning, law, and the spirit of faith. When they stepped upon these shores
a wild, frowning wilderness received them. Strong in their faith in God, they began their
combat with danger and hardship. Sickness overcame them, but they fainted not. They feasted
on roots with patient spirits. The first thing they did was to kneel and give thanks to God for
his protective care. Then they built a meetinghouse where they might worship, then a house
for themselves. They established education and stern principles of morality. Their old town
government was the most democratic of all governments. They knew the meaning of the term
democratic, meaning a government of the people, but back of it is the feeling that every
person must have a due respect for the rights of all other people. Churches arose in the depths
of the forests, industry was fostered, no easy work in those days; colleges were established,
and their civic life soon grew into the majesty of states. Then came a mighty nation&mdash;a nation
of law, art, industry, education, and an expansion into new territory never before equaled in
the history of man. A government was brought into being with a background of civic and
political idealism which was the blessing of Almighty God, and for this they gave thanks in
solemn prayer.
</p><p>
CARRYING THE GOSPEL TO THE NATIONS
</p><p>
Today we are sending into all the world young men and women who are carrying the gospel
to the nations. It is a holy duty! We are turning our thoughts forward, as was done when the
Church was organized. The missionary idea cannot be lost and the expectations cherished by
our fathers cannot be forgotten. Men and women of many nations have found in the faith that
which they required. They have been the means of adding to the culture of our state. We must
not overlook the benefits which these men confer. They are by no means confined to things
unseen and eternal. They are students and teachers. Geography, ethnology, history, sociology,
philology, and every department of knowledge is indebted to them. They represent their
country, and with honor. What we term missionary work is not limited to personal effort.
Nations are missionaries. Our mission today is to act. We must advance the cause of the
restored gospel by our onward march to greater accomplishments. No one can measure the
years to come. To be alive and increasing, to be young and awake, this is the order of the
future. The heroes and divinities of the past have their own place. but we have our leaders
today. There is perspective in prophecy. A prophet of old declared: "Your young men shall
see visions. Your sons and daughters shall prophecy"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/joel/2/28#28">Joel 2:28</a>). Today it is superbly true. If there was
ever a time that the world needs vision, it is today.
</p><p>
DUTIES OF SEVENTIES
</p><p>
Our Seventies have a great duty, a divine call. They are workers in the vineyard of God
wherever they live. They must keep ever in mind that they have a fine ambition to teach and
to live. In their everyday walks of life, they are committed to nothing but the truth. They have
the ardor of youth with the discipline of study and prayer. The word Seventy signifies a
divine calling to teach God's word. The gospel must prevail in all the world. We need energy,
enterprise, to prove that the "now" is the most important time of all. It is an unmistakable idea
that a man who gives himself to Christ and his Spirit, will become what has been termed "a
new man." The gospel requires reverent and hopeful study. The gospel does more than teach
duty. It provides the motive and desire to do it, and it gives the moral strength. The divine
message is advancing, and the Spirit of the Lord moves before it, cloud by day and fire by
night. The truth of Christ is to find men and to save them.
</p><p>
My brother Seventies, what the world needs first and to the end is God. Not God in the
heavens and in the past alone. But God here, and known by "the man whom he hath
ordained" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/31#31">Acts 17:31</a>).
The renewed gospel is young, and the currents of its life are strong. It keeps pace
with knowledge, and intends to bring the world to the Lord. It is deep in the heart of man.
The peoples of the world have made some preparation in the past. They are making
preparation today. India will some day welcome missionaries. The walls of Egyptian
sanctuaries long since destroyed will be rebuilt for Christ. The land of the Nile sheltered
Christ when he was a child. It will shelter Christ again. All nations shall know his word.
</p>
</div>
</div>
