<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A True Servant of God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 19-20</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am grateful, my brothers and sisters, to meet with you in general conference again. I was
greatly impressed by that masterful sermon of our President as he opened the conference; and
with these other brethren. I surely sustain him as the prophet, seer, and revelator of the Lord.
</p><p>
I was more than happy to see Brother Thomas E. McKay here, and I am so glad that he bore
that wonderful testimony to you. I think I would like to tell you another testimony about
Brother Thomas E. McKay, and I believe I will make that my address to you here in this
conference.
</p><p>
INCIDENT OF HEALING
</p><p>
Not very long ago I was down in one of the California stakes attending a stake conference. At
the close of the morning meeting, one of the bishops brought his mother to the stand as she
wished to shake hands and send a message back home. When she reached the stand, she said,
Will you give a message from me to Brother Thomas E. McKay?
</p><p>
I said, "I shall be very glad to."
</p><p>
She said: "It has been a couple of years since he was here to stake conference, but I want you
to take a message to him."
</p><p>
At that time I was holding in my hands a Book of Mormon that I had used during the
conference. She took the Book of Mormon from my hands and opened it and read a
paragraph to me then she closed the book and gave it back.
</p><p>
She said, "Two years ago Elder Thomas E. McKay was down here to our stake conference. I
was blind. I knew that if he would lay his hands upon my head I would receive my sight
again. I sent over to the conference and had him come. He and the other brethren laid their
hands upon my head, and blessed me. Now you see that without even the use of glasses I
have been able to read a paragraph from your book. When you get back to Salt Lake City
will you tell him what I have done here today and express to him the gratitude I feel to the
Lord that one of his chosen servants came down here and was willing to lay his hands upon
my head? Whereas I was blind two years ago, now I can see and I can read without glasses"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/25#25">John 9:25</a>).
</p><p>
A TRUE SERVANT
</p><p>
I thought that was a beautiful testimony she bore to one of the servants of God. I have loved
Brother McKay ever since I first became acquainted with him some years ago. I can testify to
you along with this good sister from California that indeed Thomas E. McKay through his life
has been a true servant of God, and I am glad that he stood here today and bore that fervent
testimony that he knows that God lives; that he knows that Jesus is the Christ; that he knows
that Joseph Smith was a true prophet of God; and that all the men who have succeeded him in
the presidency of this Church likewise are prophets of the Lord.
</p><p>
I bear you this testimony also because I know that these things are true, and I give you this
testimony in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
