<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Something Missing"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 76-78</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
With you I rejoice in this forthright and impressive statement by President David O. McKay
of our interest and our position in a great national program. My earnest and humble prayer is
that we who have influence with the young may proceed from this conference throughout the
Church to give adequate emphasis to the great responsibility of developing fitness in our
young. I think, if we do we may expect three great results: that, first, much good will come to
the nation, and the nations of which we are citizens; second, that the missionary work of the
Church will receive great impetus through the marvelous example of the influence of the
program of the Church in the lives of its young; and third, that the Church itself and its
people may profit measurably by a renewed dedication to following the direction of the Lord
and the leadership of the brethren in providing opportunities for development in every aspect
of the personality in our young.
</p><p>
Early this week our seven-year-old daughter, leading our family in prayer, thanked God for
her and our eyes and our ears and our mouths, and asked the Lord to bless us that we could
say good things through our mouths, and because she knew her daddy had to talk that
morning to some people not of the Church, she prayed that he would be able to explain the
gospel understandably to them. I echo her great appreciation for God's gifts and her earnest
petitions also.
</p><p>
A time ago I had the privilege of going to a university campus to participate in what they
called "Religion in Life Week." Their theme, which I was to treat at the beginning of the
week was "Something Missing." I walked about the campus and into some of the buildings in
the period preceding the appointed hour, and in a certain building where there were
advertisements placed by students, I saw this written, line by line as I shall repeat the words: 
</p><p>
For Sale<br />
1929 Ford<br />
Good body and fenders<br />
New paint job<br />
No engine<br />
$20<br />
See ................
</p><p>
And I had the idea which permitted me to treat the theme, "Something Missing." The car
looked all right, I suppose. It may have seemed adequate from the exterior appearance to
fulfil its purposes, but in fact, it was not. Something was missing, and that something was the
chief element, the motivating power.
</p><p>
As President McKay spoke to the missionaries of the Church Friday night, I thanked God in
my heart that over a large part of my life I have been blessed to serve on that interesting
frontier where the Church meets the world&mdash;in the missionary cause. I rejoiced last evening
as he talked of the wonderfully fine, loyal, intelligent people of integrity in the world, because
though I seek premier position in few things in this world, I would not want to be second in
my appreciation of the wonderful people there are who are not of us and not like us, but who
are good and decent and honest and live to the light they have received. But I confess that
much as I have learned to love them, and as honest as is my respect for them and their
integrity, I have recognized . . . that in them there is something missing, and time and again I
have had the blessing, with many of you, of attempting to bear witness to them of what that
something is.
</p><p>
Why do they miss it? Why do they not enjoy it? Perhaps because they have not been taught.
Perhaps because they have a seemingly satisfactory circumstance in life. Perhaps because
though they may sense they miss something, the pressures and problems and influences of
their lives keep them from responding, from being willing to pay the price.
</p><p>
I read with some of you some time ago in an eastern newspaper a little article which had no
prominent place but which represented something meaningful. It was the story of a fire in one
of the clothing districts in New York City. It told of the death in this fire of
more than a dozen people&mdash;fifteen, as I recall, and one sentence from the latter part of the
short article was impressive and important to me. It said that these people had perished within
easy access of an escape door, but had not used it rather had huddled together and had died in
the middle of the floor because of "smoke and fear." I have wondered if some one of the
fifteen or so who died had been conscious enough of the door, if he had known of it and
realized its importance he might have led the others through it to life.
</p><p>
And I have thought a good deal more, as perhaps you will in contemplation, about what may
have happened in that clothing factory. Apparently they had been sitting within easy access of
that door, some of them, at least, for years, yet had paid no heed to it. It had not apparently
meant much to them, and in their hour of extremity they were not able to find it.
</p><p>
There are many wonderful people in the world for whom I have personal respect and love,
and whose intelligence and integrity I consider at least equal to our own, in terms of what
they are willing to do for what they believe. Yet I testify with all my heart that there is
something here for the finest of them, but it requires a consciousness that not all is well, that
there is something to be had in the world besides social competence or other of the earthly
pursuits which satisfy the ambitions of men.
</p><p>
"Smoke and fear" are everywhere about us. I read again this morning, at an early hour, out of
the eighth chapter of First Nephi, and then in the subsequent explanatory chapter, the vision
of Lehi. You remember the chief symbols&mdash;the tree representing the tree of life, or the love
of God; the path to it; the rod by which one holding fast could reach it, and the chasm; the
large and spacious building on the other side; the mists of darkness, of vapor, rising from the
river of filth to overcome those who would try to reach the tree. Do you remember these
words? An exceeding great mist of darkness came up and obscured the path, while across it
the great spacious building was filled with people, old and young, male and female, their
manner of dress exceeding fine, and who were in the attitude of mocking and pointing their
fingers toward those who had come and were partaking of the fruit. Some of those who had
tasted it were ashamed because of those who were scoffing at them, and they fell away into
forbidden paths and were lost. Note these words in the twelfth chapter of First Nephi: ". . .
the mists of darkness are the temptations of the devil, which blindeth the eyes, and hardeneth
the hearts of the children of men, and leadeth them away into broad roads, that they perish
and are lost.
</p><p>
"And the large and spacious building which thy father saw, [said the angel to Nephi], is vain
imaginations and the pride of the children of men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/12/17-18#17">1 Ne. 12:17-18</a>).
</p><p>
My testimony and witness and the assurances of my heart are that though there are
wonderfully fine people all about us, with whom I have the occasional privilege of
association, some of whom I have the blessing of attempting to teach, and to many of whom I
have the privilege of bearing witness, and while I have great respect for what they represent
and are, yet there is something missing in them if they have not found willingness to realize
that within easy access is a door leading to life and that the Savior stands there and knocks,
but they must open and walk through.
</p><p>
I have been deeply blessed by the great strong statements of the brethren this conference
reaffirming that there is something in the gospel and Church of Jesus Christ which will bless
the lives of the very finest of men who do not have it, and who therefore have something
missing.
</p><p>
To conclude, I mention that such a sermon as President Richards delivered this morning is
sometimes greeted by some of the people of whom I have spoken, with murmurings as to
arrogance and smugness, with some objection on the basis of lack of goodwill, even
sometimes, they say, lack of Christianity in such a statement. I say, and humbly, that though
the prophets were good and compassionate men who loved brotherhood and goodwill, yet in
every instance they testified that there is a way, that men must follow that way and obey the
commandments of God. We could proceed from the beginning to the end of
the sacred records, but I choose just one as the example, and this, section 52 of the Doctrine
and Covenants, where the Prophet, under the inspiration of God, encouraging and suggesting
compassion and love and brotherliness, and prayer and humility and every other virtue, also
had something else to say: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore he that prayeth, whose spirit is contrite, the same is accepted of me if he obey
mine ordinances.
</p><p>
"He that speaketh, whose spirit is contrite, whose language is meek and edifieth, the same is
of God if he obey mine ordinances" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/52/15-16#15">D&amp;C 52:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
I thank God for the blessing of the gospel, of some understanding of it, and of certain witness
that it is the very plan of God, and that they who speak for God are his servants in this day,
as anciently, which I say, and which witness I bear, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
