<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Hand of God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1950, pp. 106-112</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I feel humble, my brothers and sisters, as I stand here today. My heart is full of
gratitude to the Lord for my membership in this Church and for my fellowship with the Saints
and the brethren. To me, the conference started last Wednesday when we met with these
grand mission presidents for two sessions in the temple and heard them tell of the fine work
that is being accomplished in the mission fields and the wonderful spirit they have in their
work One who had just been released said, "I find it difficult to become interested in my
business." Another of the presidents said, "I prayed that the Lord would let me stay a few
months longer, and when my successor arrived and apologized for being late, I said 'You
don't need to apologize. You just answered my prayers.'" It is wonderful how these men can
make the sacrifices they make and then feel as they feel. I felt the same when I returned from
my first mission. I went into Oregon selling bonds for a company. Every home I entered, I
found it difficult to offer them bonds to purchase I wanted to offer them the gospel of the
Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
EARTH CRAMMED WITH HEAVEN
</p><p>
I couldn't help thinking as I sat through these meetings: Isn't it really a pity that it is so hard
for truth to get its boots on and to be able to reach the honest in heart of the earth? If they
just knew what we have&mdash;if their eyes were opened to see and understand! How wonderful it
would be for all of our Father's children who really want to do right, if they could know the
truth, instead of having to wait, many of them, to get it, possibly, in the eternal worlds.
</p><p>
I thought of the words of Elizabeth Barrett Browning, when she said,
</p><p>
Earth's crammed with heaven,<br />
And every common bush acre with God; <br />
And only he who sees takes off his shoes; <br />
The rest sit round it and pluck blackberries.
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;                 &mdash;from "Aurora Leigh"
</p><p>
And I thought, if the world could only know how the Lord has crammed the earth with
heaven, and how every common bush is afire with God, through the restoration of the gospel.
We have heard it referred to here today. "A marvelous work and a wonder"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/14#14">Isa. 29:14</a>), and it is all of
that, far beyond the ability of any man or any woman to comprehend. The greatest mission of
the Latter-day Saints is to be able to understand and appreciate what the Lord has done, and
then make their lives conform thereto. The Lord said, in a revelation to the Prophet Joseph
Smith, that "against none is his wrath kindled, save those who confess not his hand in all
things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/59/21#21">D&amp;C 59:21</a>).
I acknowledge the hand of God in all things. I believe that he rules
in the heavens above and that he rules upon this earth. We have heard the brethren today
speak of the fulfillment of prophecy, and Peter of Old said,
</p><p>
We have also a more sure word of prophecy; whereunto ye do well that ye take heed,
as unto a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day star arise
in your hearts: 
</p><p>
Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private interpretation.
</p><p>
For the prophecy came not in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God
spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/19-21#19">2 Pet. 1:19-21</a>).
</p><p>
KINGDOM OF GOD
</p><p>
You heard Brother Sonne this morning read from one of the tracts that Brother Penrose wrote
of how the kingdoms of this world would be destroyed. We read in Daniel's interpretation of
Nebuchadnezzar's dream, in which he states that the kingdoms of this world should become
as the chaff of the summer threshing floors; and the wind should carry them away. We have
seen them one by one being carried away. But that was not all Daniel saw.
In the more sure word or prophecy which holy men of old gave us under the inspiration and
power of the Holy Ghost, he saw that the God in heaven should set up a kingdom in the last
days which should never be destroyed, but like a little stone cut out of the mountains without
hands, should roll forth until it should become a great mountain and fill the whole earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/35-45#35">Dan. 2:35-45</a>).
</p><p>
One of our missionary boys preached on that theme down in Florida while I was president of
the Southern States Mission, and I think that boy is in this congregation today. At the close of
the meeting a minister who was present at that meeting met me at the door&mdash;I always went to
the door to meet those who had honored us with their presence&mdash;and he said, "Mr. Richards,
you don't mean to tell me that you think that kingdom is the Mormon Church, do you?"
</p><p>
I said, "Why not?"
</p><p>
He said, "It couldn't be."
</p><p>
"And why couldn't it?" I said.
</p><p>
He said, "You can't have a kingdom without a king, and we haven't any king, and so haven't
a kingdom."
</p><p>
"Oh," I said, "my friend, you did not read quite far enough. You just read the seventh chapter
of Daniel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/13-14#13">Dan. 7:13-14</a>),
and you will see that Daniel saw one like the Son of Man coming in the clouds of
heaven and unto him was given the kingdom, that all other kingdoms powers, and dominions
should serve and obey him. Now, how can the kingdom be given to him," I asked, "when he
comes in the clouds of heaven, if there is no kingdom here prepared for him? Maybe you
would like to know what is going to become of that kingdom. If you will just read it, you
will see that Daniel said,
</p><p>
And the kingdom and dominion, and the greatness of the kingdom under the whole
heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the most High, whose kingdom is
an everlasting kingdom, and all dominions shall Serve and obey him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/27#27">Dan. 7:27</a>).
</p><p>
The Saints of the most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, and as
if that were not quite long enough, Daniel adds, 'even for ever and ever'"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/18#18">Dan. 7:18</a>).
</p><p>
PART OF KINGDOM
</p><p>
Now, brothers and sisters, if you can see heaven in earth, if you have eyes that see, ears that
hear, hearts that understand, you know what you are a part of as members of this Church.
You are a part of that great kingdom that is being established in the earth.
</p><p>
President John Taylor once made this statement: 
</p><p>
We are gathered here for the express purpose of carrying out the purposes of God. The
world, however, do not understand it. But I will tell you what they will do, by and by.
You will see them flocking to Zion by thousands and tens of thousands, and they will
say, We don't know anything about your religion, we don't care much about religious
matters, but you are honest and you are honorable and you are upright and just and
you have a good, just, and secure government [speaking of the
Government of the Church], and we want to put ourselves under your protection for
we cannot feel safe anywhere else" (<i>Gospel Kingdom</i>, pp. 71-72).
</p><p>
IMPRESSIONS OF VISITORS
</p><p>
During the last six months I have had occasion to hear people express themselves as to how
they feel about this. We were in the Hotel Utah with one of the greatest economists in the
world, and after President Smith had spoken, this man stood up. He was overcome; he had to
shed a few tears; then he told us that never in his life had he been in such presence or in such
influence. Then he paid us some compliments about our people and said he had felt it on the
street and wherever he went.
</p><p>
We had another great national leader here not long ago who made a similar declaration. He
said, "I have to come out here in these valleys of the mountains to get inspiration," but he did
not want us to tell what he had said because he has to live with those people back in the
East, but he said it just the same.
</p><p>
A few weeks, ago a lady from Orlando, Florida, came into the office of the Presidency. The
receptionist called me and said that this lady would like to know something more about the
Church and would I have time to interview her. Well, I had preached in Orlando, Florida,
many times, and built a little chapel there, so anyone from Orlando looked good to me. I said,
"Send her up." She wanted to know all about the Church. She said, "Mr. Richards, I have
traveled all over the United States&mdash;I just came from California." (I would tell you what she
said about California, but I used to be president of a stake down there, and so my interests
there forbid.) But she said, "I don't know what it is, but I feel it everywhere I go. You are
different here; you have something different here than I have felt anywhere I have been."
</p><p>
"Well," I said "that is simple, we have the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ."
</p><p>
STORY OF MINISTER
</p><p>
If we just had eyes that could see, ears that could hear; if we could see heaven crammed into
this earth in this great work that God has set his hand to do, and every common bush afire
with God&mdash;we could understand the story one of the mission presidents told in the report
meeting at the temple, of the missionary who called at the home of a minister. This
missionary offered to leave a tract, and the minister would not accept it; so, as he left the
door he put the tract in the mailbox, and when he came back the next time the minister
invited him in. Now, to make the story short, what that man read impressed him, and finally
he paid for the publication of a thousand copies of the Book of Mormon. He gave nine
hundred of them to the missionaries and kept the other hundred for his family. When the
mission president invited him to speak at one of our conferences, he said
"Well, if you call me, I will preach what I have always preached."
</p><p>
The mission president said, "You preach anything you want to as long as you preach the
truth."
</p><p>
Then he said, "Hand me your Book of Mormon," He stood up, held up that Book of Mormon
before them and said, "Here is the greatest book I have ever read." Then he pledged his
loyalty to the Bible, but he said, "I've got something out of this book that I haven't got out of
any other book, including the Bible." That was a minister speaking.
</p><p>
If every minister in all the world professedly of the Christian Church could only humble
himself enough to put that book to the test, we might have a great army of men all over the
world bearing to their faithful people the witness of the great and mighty work the Lord has
set his hand to do in this day, the new witness for the Lord Jesus Christ in the earth.
</p><p>
MESSAGE FROM GOD
</p><p>
Speaking of these marvelous things, I heard Brother Ballard make this statement when he
visited our mission. He said that one of our greatest national commentators, and he told the
name but I will not give it here today as it will serve the purpose without, said he was asked
what message could be broadcast to the world that would be considered more valuable than
any other message that could possibly be broadcast. After giving the matter some thought and
consideration, he decided that to be able to say to the world over the radio that a man who
had lived upon the earth and had died had returned again with a message from God would be
the greatest message that could be broadcast to the world. Well, that being true, we have the
greatest message, for we announce to the world that not only one man, but many men,
prophets of the living God who have lived upon the earth have returned again with messages
from God; not only messages, but also keys and power in order that the kingdom of God
might again be established in the earth as promised by Peter when he said, that the heavens
must receive the Christ until the restitution of all things spoken by the mouth of all the holy
prophets since the world began (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21#21">Acts 3:21</a>).
Do you mean to tell me that if we believe in the words of the
holy prophets as I have referred to today, that we have any right to expect the Lord Jesus
Christ ever to come in fulfillment of this promise made except there first be a restitution of
all things? There isn't time for me to go into the restitution of all things here today. We have
built a monument in the state of New York to just such an individual to Moroni, who lived
upon this continent four hundred years following the crucifixion of the Savior and returned
again to deliver the plates from which the Book of Mormon was translated to the Prophet
Joseph Smith. There stands that majestic monument to his honor, the only one like it in all
the world.
</p><p>
Think also of what John the Baptist brought&mdash;the Aaronic Priesthood, Peter, James, and
John, the Melchizedek Priesthood; the prophets Moses, Elijah, and Elias came with the keys
of their dispensations.
</p><p>
HOLY PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
Then I am reminded of another story one of the mission presidents told in the temple last
Wednesday. He took out of his pocket a letter from a minister and read it to us, in which he
stated that he never believed that he did not have as much authority as any other man in the
world to administer the ordinances of the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ until he met the
Mormon missionaries and read the Book of Mormon. Now he admitted that he had to accept
baptism at the hands of the missionaries of this Church.
</p><p>
We have been told in this conference that we have to have the Priesthood, and I want to tell
you that if the world understood and knew the value of the sealing power and ordinances of
the Holy Priesthood that God has sent to us in this dispensation, it would revolutionize this
whole world.
</p><p>
TEMPLE WORK
</p><p>
I have one more thought I want to leave with you in the next few minutes, and that is about
this temple here, and the rest of our temples. When the corner stone of this temple was laid,
Brigham Young said something like this,
</p><p>
We are gathered here today upon one of the most momentous occasions that this world
has ever known since the foundations thereof were laid, an occasion that has caused
the tongues of prophets to speak and their pens to write.
</p><p>
You read the words of Isaiah, where he saw the mountain of the house of the God of Jacob
established in the tops of the mountains in these latter days, and he added,
</p><p>
All nations shall flow unto it. And many people shall go and say, Come ye, and let us
go up to the mountain of the Lord, to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach
us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/2-3#2">Isa. 2:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
I want to tell you, outside of these holy temples and the sealing ordinances therein, men
cannot learn fully of his ways, nor can they walk in his paths.
</p><p>
I have some wonderful testimonies in regard to this matter, but I will only take time to read
a few words from a sermon President Woodruff delivered from this pulpit in 1898, as
recorded in the conference pamphlet.
</p><p>
I am going to bear my testimony to this assembly, if I never do it again in my life,
that those men who laid the foundation of this American government, and signed the
Declaration of Independence, were the best spirits the God of heaven could find on the
face of the earth. They were choice spirits, not wicked men. General
Washington and all the men that labored for the purpose were inspired of the Lord.
</p><p>
Another thing I am going to say here, because I have a right to say it. Every one of
those men that signed the Declaration of Independence with General Washington,
called upon me as an Apostle of the Lord Jesus Christ, in the Temple at St. George,
two consecutive nights, and demanded at my hands that I should go forth and attend to
the ordinances of the House of God for them (<i>Conference Report</i>, 1898, pp. 89-90).
</p><p>
I wonder what the ministers of the world would say if they only knew that this were true, and
it is true. When these great men who framed the Constitution of our nation came back they
were not interested in the future destiny and the development of this great land of America.
They came back to request that the ordinances of the house of God be administered for them.
</p><p>
So I say,
</p><p>
Earth's crammed wit heaven<br />
And every common bush alive with God; <br />
And only he who sees takes off his shoes.<br />
The rest sit round it and pluck blackberries.
</p><p>
May God help us to see and understand his marvelous work I pray in the name of the Lord
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
