<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Innocent They Come</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 73-76</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The hallowed singing of these children's voices suggests the words of another song: 
</p><p>
"I think, when I read that sweet story of old,<br />
     When Jesus was here among men,<br />
     How he called little children like lambs to His fold,<br />
     I should like to have been with Him then.
</p><p>
"I wish that His hands had been placed on my head,<br />
     That his arms had been thrown around me,<br />
     That I might have seen His kind look when He said,<br />
     'Let the little ones come unto Me.'"<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &mdash;Jemima Luke
</p><p>
With our minds turned to our Savior, one of his most sobering sayings comes to mind: 
</p><p>
"And Jesus called a little child unto him, and set him in the midst of them,
</p><p>
"And said, Verily I say unto you, Except ye be converted, and become as little children, ye
shall not enter into the kingdom of heaven.
</p><p>
"Whosoever therefore shall humble himself as this little child the same is greatest in the
kingdom of heaven.
</p><p>
"But whoso shall offend one of these little ones which believe in me, it were better for him
that a millstone were hanged about his neck, and that he were drowned in the depth of the
sea.
</p><p>
"Woe unto the world because of offences! for it must needs be that offences come; but woe to
that man by whom the offence cometh!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/2-4,6-7#2">Matt. 18:2-4,6-7</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility for teaching children</b>
</p><p>
The innocence with which children come into the world is one of the awesome responsibilities
of all who, in any way, influence their lives. And to see such unstained innocence neglected
or abused, or exposed to evil or unwholesome influence, or warped by bad example, or by
false teaching&mdash;or by failure to teach&mdash;is a sobering concern.
</p><p>
There are many who have responsibility for teaching children: parents, teachers, friends,
anyone who in any way enters their lives, including the makers and promoters of products, of
policies; creators of entertainment, and the whole community, publicly and privately. And
children in their innocence have a right to be protected from exploitation and from evil
influence.
</p><p>
As to teachers, the following is cited from a significant source: "The personal influence of the
teacher, in molding the character of the pupils, is the most important element in their
education . . . In morals, a teacher cannot teach what he is not. If he <i>talks</i> what he is not, it
were better not said, for his life talks more forcibly and is sooner believed, both by children
and adults" (W. M. Welch, <i>How to Organize, Classify and Teach a Country School</i>).
</p><p>
Always we must remember that the teacher teaches himself. As Henry Adams said it: "A
teacher affects eternity; he can never tell where his influence stops"
(<i>The Education of Henry Adams</i>, ch. 20).
</p><p>
People who speak of their private lives as a thing apart from their professions would well
remember this sentence from Stanford University's Dr. David Starr Jordan: "There is no real
excellence in all this world," he said, "which can be separated from right living"
(<i>The University and the Common Man</i>).
</p><p>
<b>Patronizing the cheap or trashy side</b>
</p><p>
Now a comment on another question that concerns the whole community: It would be well if
young people, parents, and all others who are concerned with decency would not patronize
anything that tends to lower people's lives or lead their minds down to the cheap or trashy or
harmful or suggestive side.
</p><p>
Quite apart from the personal effect on the one who partakes of a
harmful product, or who witnesses an immoral or suggestive or obscene picture or play
(through whatever medium it may be presented), we well would remember that whenever we
patronize an immoral or unclean performance, or use a harmful or unwholesome product, we
are helping to make evil profitable. Whatever other motives there may be, immoral
entertainment or unwholesome products are produced to make money. And as a people, as
parents, as citizens of a great, beloved land, we ought to be committed to the principle of not
making evil profitable. The more profitable it is, the more evil will be offered.
</p><p>
One might well wonder about the term "adult entertainment." Could it be that something
unclean or immoral which is not fit for children is wholesome for adults? Is "adult evil"
acceptable? How consistent is it to have a double standard?
</p><p>
Or how would anyone be so shortsighted as to partake of that which would impair his
physical or mental or spiritual capacity, and say to himself, "It's not good for children, but
it's all right for me"?
</p><p>
If the content of a magazine encourages loose morals and low-mindedness and permissive,
degrading attitudes and practices, should we buy it? Should we read it? Should we have it
around the home?
</p><p>
If a book is filthy, should we buy it? Should we read it? ". . . books," said Thomas Carlyle,
"are like men's souls" (<i>Inaugural Address</i>, Edinburgh, 1866).
</p><p>
Should we keep a television or radio presentation exposed to viewing or listening if it is one
of crudeness or brutish violence or indecent suggestion&mdash;or even if it is simply trashy or
trivial?
</p><p>
"Unless virtue guide us," said William Penn, ". . . our choice must be wrong"
(<i>Some Fruits of Solitude: Temporal Happiness</i>).
</p><p>
The commandments of God have not been repealed. The laws of cause and consequence are
still in force.
</p><p>
<b>Honest and wise men needed</b>
</p><p>
The creators of community influence and environment and example&mdash;which is all of
us&mdash;would well remember the words of our Savior concerning whosoever "shall offend one of
these little ones" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/6#6">Matt. 18:6</a>)&mdash;or
older ones&mdash;or whosoever devotes his life to the production or
promotion or support of mind-corroding, soul-destroying evil in any of its forms.
</p><p>
"Liberty," said Horace Greeley, "cannot be established without morality, nor morality without
faith."
</p><p>
". . . honest men and wise men should be sought for diligently, and good men and wise men ye
should observe to uphold" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/10#10">D&amp;C 98:10</a>)&mdash;and
this would seem to suggest that qualified
and able and courageous people should prepare themselves and make themselves available for
public and civic service, and not be indifferent or complacent or resigned to sitting on the
sidelines.  Even at personal sacrifice there ought to be a sufficient number who will make
themselves available for public service.
</p><p>
<b>Obligations of parents</b>
</p><p>
Now what of our obligations as parents? We cannot safely leave the teaching and molding of
our children to chance. We cannot altogether count on others to teach our children. The first
responsibility is ours. We must build our own internal strength.
</p><p>
There is more and more evidence that the basic attitudes and capacity and character of
children are molded at a very early age. "No curious scientist," said an eminent authority,
"ever had as great curiosity as a youngster from eighteen months to three years of age," all of
which confirms the importance of implanting the truths of life early&mdash;and always.
</p><p>
"My life is my message," said Mahatma Gandhi. It is so with each of us. The impressions of
what we are and do and feel and believe and live and teach are carried over to our children. If
we depart from principles, may we reasonably expect our children not to depart?
</p><p>
Many a parent who has criticized sacred things or principles he should support wonders why
his children later depart further from principles.
</p><p>
Those who follow bad examples don't always know where to stop, and parents who indulge
themselves "in moderation" may have children who indulge themselves to excess.
</p><p>
There should be no double standard. Constantly others are learning from us, feeling from us,
reasoning their course of conduct from our course of conduct. And if we get a little over the
line, our children, our young people, may get a long way over the line.
</p><p>
Within the week I have read this comment from a neighboring country: "It is not the
policeman's responsibility . . . to substitute for the family. Respect for law . . . begins with respect
for parents . . . respect for the rights and privacy of brothers and sisters and of playmates."
(<i>The Royal Bank of Canada Monthly Letter</i>, January and March, 1969.)
</p><p>
<b>World no better than its homes</b>
</p><p>
"Law itself," said Samuel Smiles, "is but the reflex of homes."
</p><p>
This world will be no better than its homes. This country, this community, this Church, will
be no better than the strength and effectiveness of our homes and families.
</p><p>
Example and love and sheer goodness of life do more for children than can be calculated.
</p><p>
The integrity and effectiveness and affection of the home and family are first.
</p><p>
In a well-known work, Dostoyevsky had this to say: "The soul is healed by being with
children."
</p><p>
Healed, yes&mdash;and also searched. Perhaps we are never more open to penetrating scrutiny than
when the eyes of a child are upon us. And so often we underestimate their understanding. 
Children have a way of seeing inside. And our teaching must be more than talking. "[Boys]
know truth from counterfeit as quick as the chemist does," said Emerson. "They detect
weakness in your eye and behavior . . . before you open your mouth" (Emerson,
<i>Compensation</i>)
</p><p>
<b>Innocence of children</b>
</p><p>
Don't try to hide your heart from a child. They come here clean and sweet and teachable,
from the Father of us all. Innocent they come, and innocent they are, until environment or
example is otherwise.
</p><p>
One can scarcely conceive of corruption or cruelty to children.
</p><p>
"The child's grief throbs against its little heart as heavily as the man's sorrow," said Edwin
Chapin.
</p><p>
"I love these little people," said Charles Dickens, "and it is not a slight thing, when they, who
are so fresh from God, love us."
</p><p>
"Be ever gentle with the children God has given you," pleaded Elihu Burritt. "Watch over
them constantly; reprove them earnestly, but not in anger."
</p><p>
"The first duty to children is to make them happy.&mdash;If you have not made them so, you have
wronged them.&mdash;No other good they may get can make up for that." (Charles Buxton,
English author.)
</p><p>
To quote a sentence from Arnold Glasow: "The best thing to spend on children&mdash;is your
time."
</p><p>
We need more mothers at home&mdash;and fathers. We need more faithful observance of home
evenings&mdash;more unity and faithfulness in marriage, and devotion to duty, and happiness at
home.
</p><p>
We need to feed the minds of our children when they are most receptive.
</p><p>
We need to give them happy, wholesome memories.
</p><p>
Sometimes when you have said something to a child you didn't intend to say, or were more
severe than the situation called for, have you ever gone back and looked at that same
youngster when he was asleep, and felt terribly humble and terribly small? And, with a little
extra moisture in your eyes, have you ever uttered a fervent prayer that you would be the kind
of parent you ought to be?
</p><p>
O how sweetly, how often we have heard them sing: 
</p><p>
"I am a child of God,<br />
     And He has sent me here,<br />
     Has given me an earthly home<br />
     With parents kind and dear.
</p><p>
"Lead me, guide me, walk beside me,<br />
     Help me find the way.<br />
     Teach me all that I must do<br />
     To live with Him some-day."
</p><p>
&nbsp; &nbsp; &mdash;Naomi W. Randall
</p><p>
<b>Learn and live gospel</b>
</p><p>
Parents, learn the gospel; live it. Be a living sermon in the home. Take time for your children.
What better can you take time for?
</p><p>
". . . I have commanded you to bring up your children in light and truth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/40#40">D&amp;C 93:40</a>).
</p><p>
Let every parent, every teacher&mdash;and all of us&mdash;teach truly so that no one whom we should
have taught can ever, here or hereafter, accusingly say, "Why didn't you teach me? Why
didn't you tell me?"
</p><p>
"They are idols of hearts and of households; <br />
     They are angels of God in disguise; <br />
     The sunlight still sleeps in their tresses,<br />
     His glory still gleams in their eyes; <br />
     These truants from home and from Heaven,<br />
     They have made me more manly and mild; <br />
     And I know now how Jesus could liken<br />
     The kingdom of God to a child."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     &mdash;Charles M. Dickinson, <i>The Children</i>
</p><p>
May heaven help us to help all children, our own and others, worldwide, to be loved, to be
fed, to be taught, to be close to our hearts, and to be uncorrupted, unoffended, to have
happiness and faith and hope.
</p><p>
In the wonderful words of Alma: ". . . may the peace of God rest upon you, and upon your
houses and lands, and upon your flocks and herds, and all that you possess, your women and
your children, according to your faith and good works, from this time forth and forever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/7/27#27">Alma 7:27</a>).
</p><p>
I pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
