<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Seek Learning, Even by Study, and Also by Faith"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1968, pp. 128-132</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
For some reason I have had occasion to recall an experience I had in this Tabernacle several years ago when I presided over an afternoon session of the Pioneer Stake conference. Our visitor was President Brigham H. Roberts of the First Council of the Seventy. Brother Roberts had just come out of the hospital, where he had undergone a severe and painful operation that resulted in the amputation of part of his foot. When I asked him if he felt up to speaking in the Tabernacle, which is always an extra pressure, as 40 or more of us here today can testify, he said after some thought, "I understand there is an official Church stenographer to take down the sermons delivered there. I have a feeling that some of our members are following the philosophies of the world and are in danger of slipping from their moorings in the fundamental doctrines as taught by our early leaders. I have felt that there are a few things I would like to speak where they can be recorded, things which might be read after I am gone."
</p><p><b>
Address of Brigham H. Roberts
</b></p><p>
Now you can understand how I felt about that stake conference session, to listen to this message that he was addressing to me and to all of my generation to be read after he had gone. Somehow what he said on that occasion has come back to me again and again recently, and the Lord willing, I should like to introduce a part of what he said and then add to it some of my own reflections.
</p><p>
He began with a recital of the statements of scientists which indicated a marked trend of so-called knowledge away from a belief in God and to deny the continuance of the universe; and with that, of course, would fall all hope of immortality and eternal life, promised in the revelations of God.
</p><p>
He spoke for about half of the session, and his strength was waning. He turned to the Tabernacle Choir members who were there and asked if they would sing while he recovered some of his strength. After a few moments' rest he then addressed himself to the most glorious part of his whole sermon. He spoke of the restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ as not merely sweeping away the rubbish of past ages, such as disputations as to the mode of baptism, or how one's sins are remitted, or the various forms of church government. But he impressed the fact that a new dispensation of the gospel had been ushered in, built upon a strong "foundation of the apostles and prophets, Jesus Christ himself as the chief corner stone." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/2/20#20">Eph. 2:20</a>)
</p><p>
Those called to the ministry received two significant instructions by revelation as to how they should be prepared for the ministry to which they were called in this restored Church of Jesus Christ. The doctrines of the kingdom and the ordinances of the temple were instituted, the Lord said, that they might be "instructed more perfectly in theory, in principle, in doctrine, in the law of the gospel, in all things that pertain unto the kingdom of God, that are expedient for you." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/78#78">D&amp;C 88:78</a>)
</p><p>
Then President Roberts read that oft-repeated passage which has been mentioned two or three times in this conference, that teachers of the gospel were to interest themselves in secular learning in all fields (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/15#15">D&amp;C 90:15</a>). After he had said this, he then quoted another profound statement addressed to all others who "hath not faith." Possibly this meant, in its broadest sense, those who had not yet matured in their religious convictions. This is what the Lord said: "And as all have not faith, seek ye diligently and teach one another words of wisdom; yea, seek ye out of the best books words of wisdom; seek learning, even by study and also by faith." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>)
</p><p><b>
A call to higher wisdom
</b></p><p>
Now, with that as the introductory part of what I would wish to say, I would like to address myself to that last thought, "seek learning, even by study and also by faith." This was a call to higher wisdom that had been trumpeted through all the ages by the prophets. The apostle Paul asked this soul-searching question: "For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him?" and then he declared that most profound statement to all those who would drink more deeply of inspired wisdom than merely the teachings of men: "But God hath revealed them unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all things, yea, the deep things of God."
</p><p>
Said he, "Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him." (See <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/9-11#9">1 Cor. 2:9-11</a>)
</p><p>
It was a wise prophet who warned his brethren about being content with the teachings of vain men who hearken not unto the counsels of God. "O that cunning plan of the evil one! O the vainness, and the frailties, and the foolishness of men! When they are learned they think they are wise, and they hearken not unto the counsel of God, for they set it aside, supposing they know of themselves, wherefore, their wisdom is foolishness and it profiteth them not. And they shall perish."
</p><p>
Then this great prophet-teacher put the learning of men and the wisdom of God in their proper relationship when he declared, "But to be learned is good if they hearken unto the counsels of God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/28-29#28">2 Ne. 9:28-29</a>)
</p><p>
Fortunately there are great men schooled in worldly learning who attest to the need of a kind of learning that comes beyond secular knowledge. May I illustrate a few.
</p><p><b>
Faith of space scientist
</b></p><p>
A letter from Colonel Edward H. White, a national hero who eventually gave his life while engaging in an experiment designed for exploration of outer space, was printed in the local press a few years ago. In answer to an inquiry as to his beliefs in law and order in the universe, he answered in this rather unusual way: "I believe that law and order exist in God's creations, and that God has surely given life to others outside our earth. In our vast universe there are no fewer than billions and billions of solar systems comparable to our own&mdash;in dimension and magnitude far beyond the ability of the finite mind to comprehend. 'Out there' could be places where life, similar to our own, perhaps superior or perhaps inferior, may be a reality. We would be rather egotistical to believe that ours is the only life among all those possible sources."
</p><p>
How accurately this man's learning by faith has brought him into full accord with what the Lord declared in a great revelation to his prophet Moses: "And worlds without number have I created; and I also created them for mine own purpose; and by the Son I created them, which is mine Only Begotten.
</p><p>
"And the first man of all men have I called Adam, which is many." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33-34#33">Moses 1:33-34</a>)
</p><p>
Moses was not an astronomer. He tells us that he "beheld the earth, yea, even all of it; and there was not a particle of it which he did not behold, discerning it by the spirit of God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/27#27">Moses 1:27</a>)
</p><p>
Colonel White concluded with this declaration of his own, personal faith: "As to evidence of Gods presence during our journey in space and during the short period that 'I walked in space,' I did not feel any nearer to him there than here, but I do know that his sure hand guided us all the way during that four-day mission."
</p><p>
Presumably he is telling us that he was guided by faith in God, which transcended his scientific knowledge.
</p><p><b>
Supreme intelligence designed universe
</b></p><p>
One of our own great scientists, Dr. Henry Eyring, in the field of physical chemistry, a few years ago wrote an article for one of our Church periodicals under the heading "Myriads of Worlds."
</p><p>
He quotes from a professor-emeritus of astronomy at Harvard University [Harlow Shapley], in which the professor declares that out of the millions of suns, at least one sun in a thousand would have acquired planets, and that of those with planets at least one in a thousand has a planet the right distance for life. And then Dr. Eyring wrote: "Thus one concludes that there should be at the very minimum one hundred million planets in space which could support life, and the number is probably many times more. Thus, from the scientific point of view, it is hard to doubt that there are myriads of worlds suitable for human habitation.
</p><p>
"The mysteries of the universe lead most men to worship the Supreme Intelligence who designed it all."
</p><p>
Then mark you this next statement from Dr. Eyring: "However, the great blessing of the Gospel is the additional avenues it opens up for developing this faith into a perfect knowledge. Now, as always, sure knowledge of spiritual matters can only come by faith, by prayer, and by living in such a way as to have the companionship of the Holy Ghost as is promised to all the faithful." (<i>The Instructor</i>, November 1961, p. 373.)
</p><p><b>
The principle of revelation
</b></p><p>
The great volume of American history known as the Book of Mormon, we are told by the Lord, was translated by the Prophet "through the mercy of God, by the power of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/29#29">D&amp;C 1:29</a>), and "the interpretation thereof by the gift of God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>)
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith tells us something of the process by which knowledge by faith may come: "A person may profit by noticing the first intimation of the spirit of revelation; for instance, when you feel pure intelligence flowing into you, it may give you sudden strokes of ideas, so that by noticing it, you may find it fulfilled the same day or soon; (i.e.) those things that were presented unto your minds by the Spirit of God, will come to pass; and thus by learning the Spirit of God and understanding it, you may grow unto the principle of revelation, until you become perfect in Christ Jesus."  (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/col/1/28#28">Col. 1:28</a>) (Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 151.)
</p><p><b>
Scientific discoveries inspired
</b></p><p>
 A similar comment will illustrate the working of the Spirit of God or the light which lightens every person who comes into the world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/46#46">D&amp;C 84:46</a>), as a man of science not of the Church would define it. Some years ago in a class of seminary teachers at Brigham Young University, Dr. Edwin D. Starbuck, a University of Iowa professor, remarked that "every great scientific discovery came as an intuition to the mind of the discoverer." When he explained what he meant by intuition, his students said they called it inspiration.
</p><p>
The professor said that a careful search of the records and a contact with great living scientific discoverers made by him "explained that the scientist studies his problem, saturates his mind with it, puzzles over it, dreams about it, but seems to find progress impossible, blocked, as it were, by a black impenetrable wall. Then at last and suddenly as if 'out of the nowhere' comes a flash of light, the answer to his quest. His mind is now illumined by a great discovery." The professor was positive that no great discovery had been made by pure reasoning. Reason would lead to the borderland of the unknown, but it could not tell what was within.
</p><p><b>
No easy road to knowledge
</b></p><p>
Certainly learning by faith is not an easy road or a lazy means to knowledge. For instance, a prophet tells us there are times when no miracles can be found among the people: "And the reason why he ceaseth to do miracles among the children of men is because that they dwindle in unbelief, and depart from the right way, and know not the God in whom they should trust." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/20#20">Morm. 9:20</a>)
</p><p>
And then concerning directly the working of miracles, which of course is an evidence of the wisdom of God working through men, the prophet Nephi declared: "And now it came to pass that according to our record, and we know our record to be true, for behold, it was a just man who did keep the record&mdash;for he truly did many miracles in the name of Jesus; and there was not any man who could do a miracle in the name of Jesus save he were cleansed every whit from his iniquity." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/8/1#1">3 Ne. 8:1</a>)
</p><p><b>
Gifts of Spirit enjoyed by faithful
</b></p><p>
Thus, you see, such heavenly gifts of the Spirit are only to be enjoyed by those who have learned by faith and living worthily to receive the right to exercise these divine powers. To one who would be so taught, remember the Lord's command: "Search diligently, pray always, and be believing, and all things shall work together for your good, if ye walk uprightly and remember the covenant wherewith ye have covenanted one with another." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/24#24">D&amp;C 90:24</a>)
</p><p>
Our own Prophet who gave us the first revelations of this dispensation said, "We would say to the brethren, seek to know God in your closets, call upon him in the fields. Follow the directions of the Book of Mormon, and pray over, and for your families, your cattle, your flocks, your herds, your corn, and all things that you possess; ask the blessings of God upon all your labors, and everything that you engage in. Be virtuous and pure; be men of integrity and truth; keep the commandments of God; and then you will be able more perfectly to understand the difference between right and wrong&mdash;between the things of God and the things of men; and your path will be like that of the just, which shineth brighter and brighter unto the perfect day." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/4/18#18">Prov. 4:18</a>) (<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 247.)
</p><p><b>
God in the still small voice
</b></p><p>
Yes, as our great Tabernacle Choir has just sung, God isn't in the earthquake; he isn't in the whirlwind; he isn't in the fire; but he is in the still, small voice (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/12#12">1 Kgs. 19:12</a>). Always we won't have him in sight, but if we are living as we ought to live, we can always be sure he is there. Some of the most severe taskmasters that the world can know are sometimes beating us into a shape so we can pass such tests as necessary to gain that divine privilege.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony that the Master, as the apostle Paul spoke of him, "Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience by the things which he suffered; 
</p><p>
"And being made perfect, he became the author of eternal salvation unto all them that obey him." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/8-9#8">Heb. 5:8-9</a>)
</p><p>
I know this through the refining processes of some severity. May I not fail whatever test the Lord may have to qualify me for the place which I am now occupying. With all my soul and conviction, and knowing the seriousness and import of that testimony, I tell you that I know that he lives. I am conscious of his presence much of the time when I have needed him most; I have known it out of the whisperings of the night, the impressions of the daytime when there were things for which I was responsible and on which I could receive guidance. So I testify to you and tell you that he is closer to the leaders of this Church than you have any idea. Listen to the leaders of this Church and follow their footsteps in righteousness, if you would learn not only by study but also by faith (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>), which testimony I bear most humbly and sincerely in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</div>
</div>
