<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Strengthening the American Home</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 120-123</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Humbly and imploringly, my brethren and sisters and friends, I approach this very difficult,
but challenging task. I trust that I may have an interest in your faith and prayers and be
favored with the sweet influence of the Holy Spirit.
</p><p>
I rejoice in what we have just witnessed, in the call of these three noble men to fill vacancies
in the councils of the Church. This is but typical, my brothers and sisters, of what is going on
throughout the Church in the wards, stakes, and missions, weekly&mdash;the calling of men and
women to positions of responsibility. Always the response is the same. To me it is a modern
miracle not duplicated anywhere upon the earth. I am happy to welcome these brethren. I
know them all. I love them.
</p><p>
I have loved Brother Richard L. Evans since I first became acquainted with him years ago. He
is loved by the entire Church. He is loved by this nation, because for years he has had a
national audience. His influence has reached beyond the borders of America. And I would like
to say this to him: Brother Evans, you now enter upon the sweetest association known to men
in this world, the association which you will have with your brethren of the First Presidency
and the Council of the Twelve. There is nothing in this world in the associations of men so
sweet and so satisfying. I know that more deeply today than ever before, particularly since I
have been away since last December, and yet at times, though I have been miles away, I have
felt even nearer through their faith and prayers&mdash;the faith and prayers of my brethren.
</p><p>
I love Brother Brown. I have known him for many years. I was closely associated with him in
Europe right after the war, and he is loved by the people of the British Isles, the Saints of
Europe and the servicemen all over the Church, to whom he rendered such great service
during the last war. I had the privilege of serving as a counselor to his older brother, Scott B.
Brown, in the Boise Stake, who now serves as a patriarch there. Hugh B. Brown comes from
one of the great families of the Church.
</p><p>
I have not known Brother Marion Hanks intimately, but I have watched him with great
interest and considered him one of the most promising young men in the Church.
</p><p>
With all my heart I extend the hand of fellowship to these, my brethren and I am sure, as I do
so, I am but echoing the feeling of all the other brethren in the councils of the Church as well
as the entire Church membership.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, this has been a glorious conference. I have received a great spiritual
uplift. No, we have not heard anything particularly new. I recall some years ago a young
fellow, a Mormon boy, returned from sacrament meeting, and as he met his father, who had
been out on a high council assignment, his dad said to him, "Well, son, how did you enjoy the
sacrament meeting?" He replied, "Well, Dad, it was a good meeting. However, it was pretty
much the echoing of re-echoing echoes, but still it was a grand meeting."
</p><p>
We have heard discussed some of the old virtues. We have heard admonitions pertaining to
eternal principles. They have been presented in a little different setting, with different
emphasis, but in the main there has been very little new, but, oh, how we need the
admonitions which have been presented. I would to God that every man,
woman, and child in this nation and throughout the world might have been listening to the
counsel that has been given.
</p><p>
Now, as we leave the conference and go our various ways, how are we going to implement
the instructions that have been given, what are we going to do to see to it that this counsel
does not fall unheeded? As I think of the most effective way of implementing this counsel, I
turn, my brethren and sisters, naturally, to our most basic institution, the American home,
because, after all, it is still our greatest and most primary educational institution. It is, in very
deed, the center of our economic, social, and cultural interest. The home is the bulwark of the
nation and our most fundamental and basic institution.
</p><p>
Unless as parents, we can go back into the homes of the Church and carry these instructions
with a determination to put them into effect at our own firesides with our own children this
conference will not have been fully effective.
</p><p>
Marriage, the home, and family are sacred institutions. They are not manmade. Thank God for
that. They are divine. The first marriage performed was the marriage of two immortal beings.
Following the consummation of that marriage, the Lord gave important scriptures and
instruction to us regarding the home and the family.
</p><p>
The Lord made it clear it is not good for man to be alone
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>). Woman was created as a helpmeet
for man, and the two united in the sacred bonds of eternal marriage become one flesh.
</p><p>
"What therefore God hath joined together," said he, "let not man put asunder"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/9#9">Mark 10:9</a>).
Then later "Thou shalt love thy wife with all thy heart, and shalt cleave unto her and none
else" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/22#22">D&amp;C 42:22</a>).
How we need that counsel today in America! What heartaches could
be avoided if men would only heed that counsel wholeheartedly. How much less
unfaithfulness and infidelity there would be if we could live by that admonition.
</p><p>
Then as though to strengthen further the marriage bond in the home, the Lord gave
instructions to children through his prophets. The Apostle Paul, echoing the admonition of
Moses on Sinai, said,
</p><p>
Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right.
</p><p>
Honour thy father and mother; which is the first commandment with promise; 
</p><p>
That it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/1-3#1">Eph. 6:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
And then in modern revelation, the Lord has made it very clear that parents have great and
serious responsibilities. Listen to these words as the Lord speaks to the parents of the Church:
</p><p>
And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28#28">D&amp;C 68:28</a>).
</p><p>
And again, inasmuch as parents . . . teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance,
faith in Christ the Son of the living God, and of baptism and the gift of the Holy Ghost by
the laying on of the hands, when eight years old, the sin be upon the heads of the parents
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25#25">D&amp;C 68:25</a>).
</p><p>
That is a serious responsibility, and I believe, my brethren and sisters, the early history of this
Church clearly indicates that our grandparents, the pioneers of these valleys, in fact, the
Pilgrims, who came and settled this great American continent, honored these obligations and
were blessed in their homes for so doing.
</p><p>
I realize that many changes have come about in the last fifty to seventy-five years. Our
industrialization, specialization, concentration of populations in great cities, the great reduction
in the number of people living on farms, the change in our agriculture&mdash;all these have had
their effects. Greater emphasis upon material things and the seeking after money, after
pleasure, personal gratification, and the insidious inroads of liquor, tobacco, and
gambling&mdash;all these have had a pulling-away influence on this most sacred institution, the American home.
</p><p>
It is difficult to realize that fifty years ago there was only one divorce in
sixteen marriages here in America. By 1946 the ratio had increased to one in three, and it is
reported in some cities in America, there are actually more divorces each year than marriages.
Our best authorities indicate that most of the delinquency in America is the result of broken,
bad, and neglected homes. As J. Edgar Hoover, one of the best authorities, has indicated,
referring to delinquents, "The actions of the majority of them were, and are, directly related to
the conduct of their parents." Yes, crime begins at home.
</p><p>
Now, my brethren and sisters, as Latter-day Saints, what should be done? What can be done?
I am sure we all agree that no nation ever rises above its homes. This Church will never rise
above its homes. We are no better as a people than are our firesides, our homes. The school,
the church, and even the nation, I feel confident, stand helpless before weakened and
degraded homes. The good home is the rock foundation, the cornerstone of civilization. It
must be preserved. It must be strengthened.
</p><p>
There has never been and there never will be a satisfactory substitute for the home established
by the God of heaven. If this nation is to endure, then the home must be safeguarded,
strengthened, and restored to its rightful importance.
</p><p>
May I suggest, in the few moments remaining, five simple things that, I believe, we might
well give attention to, as some of the needs of our homes today: 
</p><p>
<i>First</i> of all, I am convinced, my brethren and sisters and this is no reflection on our devoted
mothers, who spend day after day, week after week, obediently serving their families&mdash;but I
feel sure that one of our greatest needs is more time of parents in the home. Youth of the
Church and of the nation need more than physical comforts. We will need to leave them more
than lands and stocks. They need more than a modern automobile and a lovely modern
building to live in. There is no satisfactory substitute for mother, and no one can take care of
her children as she can. No so-called social obligations, social enticements, or outside interests
should impel any mother to neglect the sacred charge which is hers of caring for her own
flesh and blood. Her first loyalty in the eyes of God is to her Church and her family. I feel
confident that while civic and social activities may return much good she will serve her
community and her nation best, if she first devotes herself to the needs of her own children.
</p><p>
<i>Second</i>, and this was emphasized this morning by Brother Cowley, we need daily devotion in
the home. We need to return to the practice of family prayer, secret prayer, the old-fashioned
practice of devotion in the home daily, night and morning, the singing of hymns, the reading
of the scriptures. How much more happiness there would be, how many fewer divorces there
would be, if these simple practices were followed as was the custom in the pioneer home, as
well as in the early days of this country, according to the diaries of our early founders.
</p><p>
<i>Third</i>, I think one of the great needs is more parental instruction in life's problems. I know
there is a tendency for parents to shrink from this responsibility, the instructing of their own
children in the problems of sex, the relationship with other young people, the problem of
dating, and all of the many temptations that confront a growing boy and girl. These
instructions should not be left to the school or to a class in sociology. The safest place the
best place, to give this vital counsel, these sacred instructions, in matters of moral purity
should be in the home on a basis of confidence between parent and child. As parents, we
should instruct our children. The sacred books of the ancient Persians say: "If you would be
holy, instruct your children, because all the good acts they perform will be imputed unto
you."
</p><p>
<i>Fourth</i>, I believe there is a great need, my brethren and sisters, for family recreation and
cultural activities together. We should do things together as a family. It may mean a reduction
in participation in women's clubs, in men's clubs, but if families could only
seek their recreation and cultural activities more as a family unit, I am sure that untold
benefits and blessings would accrue. A little boy was asked only this last summer, after he
said he was going to a summer camp, "What is a summer camp?" And he answered "Those
places where little boys go for mother's vacation." Let us take more of our vacations together
as families. Can we have a weekly evening at home, as has been admonished and counseled
for years by the First Presidency of the Church? More wholesome activities together is a great
need of the families of America.
</p><p>
<i>And fifth</i>, we need a closer parent-child relationship. This is closely related to the other four
matters. One of the greatest needs of our young people is a closer, more frequent
companionship with father and mother. There is no satisfactory substitute. I was thrilled some
time ago, as I picked up a paper in the East and read an account of a letter which a rich
industrialist had sent to his son, his sixteen-year-old boy, as a Christmas present. This man
could have given his son anything that money could buy&mdash;an automobile, a yacht, I guess, if
he wished. But when the boy came down from his room Christmas morning and went over to
the mantel where he usually found his present, there was an envelope, a plain envelope with
his name on it, and he opened it and read: 
</p><p>
"To my dear son: 
</p><p>
"I give to you one hour each weekday and two hours of my Sundays to be yours to be used
as you want it without interference of any kind whatsoever.
</p><p>
"Lovingly,
</p><p>
"Dad."
</p><p>
As I read that, I thought, what a wise father, and what a fortunate son! Yes that is what they
need.
</p><p>
God bless us, my brethren and sisters, that we may give personal attention now to these vital
matters: 
</p><p>
More time of parents in the home<br />
Daily family devotion in the home<br />
Parental instruction in life's problems<br />
Family recreation and cultural activities together<br />
A closer parent-child relationship
</p><p>
May we be faithful to this great obligation of parenthood, this sacred obligation, that we may
build our homes solidly upon eternal principles, that we may have no regrets. May we never
be recreant to the great trust which has been imposed in us. May we always keep in mind that
these spirits that have entered our homes are choice spirits. Many of them have been born
under the covenant. As we look into their faces and contemplate their needs we might well
consider that some of them were probably choicer spirits up there than we were. It is a grave
responsibility. May we not shirk it.
</p><p>
God bless us in our homes and in all our worthy endeavors. May we carry with us from this
conference the instructions given and put them into practice in our homes I humbly pray, in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
