<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Be Humble and Strong</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Franklin D. Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Franklin D. Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 69-72</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<b>The "weak" and "simple" to proclaim the restoration</b>
</p><p>
During the early history of the Church the Lord, in revelations to the Prophet Joseph Smith,
explained that the fullness of his gospel would be restored and that it would be proclaimed by
the weak and simple unto the ends of the world, and before kings and rulers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/23#23">D&amp;C 1:23</a>), that
he required their heart and a willing mind, and that they should not weary in well-doing
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/33-34#33">D&amp;C 64:33-34</a>).
</p><p>
And inasmuch as they are humble, they would be made strong, and blessed from on high, and
receive knowledge from time to time.
</p><p>
They would have power to lay the foundation of this Church and to bring it forth out of
obscurity and out of darkness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/28,30#28">D&amp;C 1:28,30</a>).
</p><p>
In these revelations the Lord explained his use of weak and simple instruments to proclaim
his gospel. However, he gave them commandments that they might possess understanding and
knowledge, receive power and become strong, thereby qualifying themselves to be effective
servants.
</p><p>
<b>The Prophet a witness</b>
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith is the chief example. He was weak insofar the learning of men is
concerned; but because he was humble, obedient, and possessed a willing mind, he became a
mighty and strong leader and witness of the divinity of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
In all ages this has been the pattern or those who would succeed in the work of the ministry:
humility, prayer, dedication, and a desire and willingness to learn the will of the Lord.
</p><p>
With the development and application of these qualities come knowledge, power, and strength.
</p><p>
<b>Members become witnesses</b>
</p><p>
Membership in The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints provides many opportunities
to participate in the building of the kingdom of God and what a great privilege this is. We
should, therefore, have an impelling desire to be humble and become strong, that we might be
worthy and able instruments&mdash;strong spiritually, morally, mentally, physically, financially,
and in every other way.
</p><p>
I would like to discuss the development of these qualities with you.
</p><p>
<b>Gospel changes lives of men</b>
</p><p>
President McKay has told us that the purpose of the gospel is to change men's lives, to make
bad men good and good men better, and to change human nature. The great joy received in
missionary work is to witness the change that comes into the lives of converts as they learn
these eternal truths and apply them in their lives.
</p><p>
Spiritual food is as essential as material food, and yet many are starving themselves
spiritually.
</p><p>
In this latter day the Lord has reconfirmed that his "Spirit is sent forth into the world to
enlighten the humble and contrite" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/33#33">D&amp;C 136:33</a>)
</p><p>
<b>How enlightenment comes</b>
</p><p>
How do we receive this enlightenment? We must of course, be humble, but we have also been
instructed to "seek . . . diligently and teach one another words of wisdom; yea, seek ye out of
the best books words of wisdom; seek learning, even by study and also by faith"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The scriptures a source</b>
</p><p>
Let us remember that the best books include the Bible, the Book of Mormon, the Doctrine
and Covenants, and the Pearl of Great Price, as they contain the words of the Lord to his
children.
</p><p>
In our studies we should also recognize the value of prayer and being submissive to
inspiration from the Holy Ghost. The Holy Ghost is a great teacher and revealer of truth and
will quicken our minds. Everyone who has received the Holy Ghost has the privilege of this
source of enlightenment, providing he is living in such a way as to be in tune with the Spirit.
</p><p>
The Savior explained to the Prophet Joseph that "the glory of God is intelligence, or in other
words, light and truth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>), that "it is impossible for a man to be saved in
ignorance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>); and that "whatever principle of intelligence we attain unto in this
life, it will rise with us in the resurrection" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/18#18">D&amp;C 130:18</a>).
</p><p>
The path is clearly defined&mdash;to seek diligently words of wisdom out of the best books by
study and faith. Let us resolve today to study regularly the four standard works of the Church
and other good books.
</p><p>
<b>Apply truth to living</b>
</p><p>
Then, as we are enlightened and learn the great eternal principles of truth, we have the
responsibility of applying them in our lives. Activity in the Church opens up many avenues of
service whereby we can apply these eternal principles. Through service we evidence our love
of God and of our fellowmen.
</p><p>
We are told that as we are humble and do this, we will be endowed with power and receive
growth and development, great joy and happiness.
</p><p>
This is the path to spiritual, moral, and mental power and strength.
</p><p>
<b>Health, an advantage</b>
</p><p>
Now let us consider the development of physical strength.
</p><p>
One of the outstanding blessings of this earth life is to obtain a body for our spirit to inhabit.
Lucifer's great punishment was that he should not possess a body.
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul in writing to the Corinthian Saints said, "Know ye not that ye are the temple
of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
</p><p>
"If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy for the temple of God is holy,
which temple ye are" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Inasmuch as our body is the abode of our spirit, the offspring of God, we should make certain
that we do not defile it. To this end the Lord has given us a specific Word of Wisdom by
revelation.
</p><p>
This principle was given with a "promise, adapted to the capacity of the weak and the weakest
of all saints, who are or can be called saints" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/3#3">D&amp;C 89:3</a>). It contains a promise that "all
saints who remember to keep and do these sayings . . . shall receive wealth in their navel and
marrow to their bones; 
</p><p>
<b>"Great treasures of knowledge"</b>
</p><p>
"And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures; 
</p><p>
"And shall run and not be weary, and shall walk and not faint" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-20#18">D&amp;C 89:18-20</a>).
</p><p>
We are counseled in this revelation to eat and drink those foods and drinks that are beneficial
to our bodies and to refrain from taking anything into our bodies that is injurious or harmful.
We can likewise protect our health by getting proper exercise and rest.
</p><p>
The Word of Wisdom is a basic law, and those who live the law will be strengthened in body
and in mind.
</p><p>
<b>Financial means. Avoid debt.</b>
</p><p>
Now with reference to the development of financial strength: God has given us our free
agency, but we are required to work for our sustenance, growth, and development.
</p><p>
We frequently refer to the gospel as "the gospel of work." This principle incorporates the
necessity of sustaining ourselves and our families. To properly fulfill this requirement in this
day, we must be financially responsible or strong. Being strong financially does not
necessarily mean being wealthy with earthly possessions; it means possessing sufficient to
meet our requirements and living within our income rather than overextending ourselves.
</p><p>
In modern revelation the Lord has given us these commandments: "Behold, it is said in my
laws, or forbidden, to get in debt to thine enemies" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/27#27">D&amp;C 64:27</a>). "And again, verily I say
unto you, concerning your debts&mdash;behold it is my will that you shall pay all your debts"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/78#78">D&amp;C 104:78</a>).
</p><p>
President Brigham Young repeatedly counseled the Saints to get out of debt and stay out of
debt. Other Latter-day Prophets have given similar counsel. President Joseph F. Smith told the
Saints, "Get out of debt and keep out of debt, and then you will be financially as well as
spiritually free."
</p><p>
President Heber J. Grant said in one of his sermons, "If there is any one thing that will bring
peace and contentment into the human heart, and into the family, it is to live within our
means; and if there is one thing that is grinding, and discouraging and disheartening, it is to
have debts and obligations that one cannot meet." (<i>Relief Society Magazine</i>, Vol. 19, page
302.)
</p><p>
One of the Relief Society lessons deals with this subject, and the appropriate title is "Don't
Let Your Yearnings Exceed Your Earnings." This lesson is certainly in line with the
injunctions of the Lord to his people. Today much unhappiness results from financial
problems; they are a major factor in unhappy marriages, many of which result in divorce.
</p><p>
Personal financial weaknesses come about primarily by unwise use of credit and obligating
ourselves for more than we receive. This frequently brings about bankruptcy, and
unfortunately, bankruptcies have greatly increased during the last few years.
</p><p>
Many business failures are likewise the result of overextension and inability to finance the
enterprise properly.
</p><p>
I counsel you to get out of debt and stay out of debt, and if it is necessary to use credit, use it
wisely and sparingly. Financial strength is realized by keeping God's commandments, one of
which is the payment of an honest tithe, and by developing habits of work, thrift, and living
within one's income.
</p><p>
<b>Be strong spiritually, morally, mentally, physically</b>
</p><p>
It is vital to our welfare and happiness that we be strong financially as well as spiritually,
morally, mentally, and physically. In all ages men and women who have had important
missions to perform possessed great strength. The trek to Utah of the Mormon pioneers, many
of whom were our ancestors, was made by those who were strong in purpose and in faith.
They left us a noble heritage.
</p><p>
Today's problems are, in many respects, different from those confronting our pioneer
forefathers. However, our problems are as real and important to us as their problems were to
them, and it requires great strength and faith on the part of men, women, and children to
successfully meet today's challenges.
</p><p>
We should consistently study the gospel, as it teaches us in simple terms how to develop this
strength. These gospel principles are eternal. As we apply them in our lives, we are able to
meet our challenges with purpose, faith, and vision, as did our forebears, and become strong
instruments in the hands of the Lord in building the kingdom. Yes, as we do our part, the
Lord will make us equal to the tasks that lie ahead.
</p><p>
I am grateful for my knowledge that God lives and that Jesus Christ is our Savior and
Redeemer, that the gospel in its fullness was restored to earth through the Prophet Joseph
Smith, and that we have a great Prophet at the head of the Church today, our beloved
President David O. McKay. May the Lord bless and sustain him as he continues to inspire us
and give us strength.
</p><p>
In October 1831 the Lord through revelation to the Prophet Joseph Smith said to William E.
McLellin, ". . . he that is faithful shall be made strong in every place; and I, the Lord, will go
with you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/66/8#8">D&amp;C 66:8</a>).
</p><p>
Each of us has this same assurance: As we are faithful we shall be made strong in every
place, and the Lord will go with us. May this be our great desire and blessing I pray in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
