<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">True Vision and Knowledge Required for Exaltation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 70-75</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I take my text from a conference statement by President Joseph Fielding Smith. He declared:
"The chief business of our lives is to build a house that will bear the weight of eternal life."
</p><p>
<b>To build a house for eternal life</b>
</p><p>
You will note that this statement is profound with its important content and challenge. It
suggests we are the architects and builders of our own fate. Our God-given free agency will
permit us to choose the pattern we wish to follow; hopefully the gospel will furnish the
blueprint for the eternal house we are now building.
</p><p>
Also involved in this statement is a challenge to obtain knowledge of God's plan for our
whole existence, both now and eternally. There are opposing evil forces who would tempt us
to forsake the teachings of our God and encourage adults, and youth particularly, that
everything can be explained on the basis of conditioned reflexes. They say that by removing
our inhibitions and reverting to an animal existence, everything will turn out all right, which
philosophy, of course, is false. Of such writers, Robert South observed: "He who has
published an injurious book sins in his very grave, corrupts others while he is rotting
himself."
</p><p>
We must be careful not to succumb to the insidious forces of evil, for they will divert us from
the path which leads to immortal glory.
</p><p>
Lehi said to his son Jacob: 
</p><p>
". . . it must needs be that there is an opposition in all things . . .
</p><p>
"Wherefore, men are free according to the flesh; and all things are given them which are
expedient unto man. And they are free to choose liberty and eternal life, through the great
mediation of all men, or to choose captivity and death, according to the captivity and power
of the devil; for he seeketh that all men might be miserable like unto
himself" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/11,27#11">2 Ne. 2:11,27</a>).
</p><p>
<b>What to avoid</b>
</p><p>
The Savior taught: "That which cometh out of the man, that defileth the man.
</p><p>
"For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornication,
murders,
</p><p>
"Thefts, covetousness, wickedness, deceit, lasciviousness, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride,
foolishness: 
</p><p>
"All these evil things come from within, and defile the man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/7/20-23#20">Mark 7:20-23</a>).
</p><p>
The apostle Paul, writing to the Romans about the sins of the flesh, admonished: 
</p><p>
"Let not sin therefore reign in your mortal body, that ye should obey it in the lusts thereof.
</p><p>
"Neither yield ye your members as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin: but yield yourself
unto God . . . and your members as instruments of righteousness unto God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/6/12-13#12">Rom. 6:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
<b>What to include</b>
</p><p>
By comprehending what to avoid, we will understand that which we must do. Our first step is
to make certain that our thoughts are clean and pure. Then we can give attention to our
bodies, since they house a spirit child of God both here in mortality and in eternity. The spirit
of man should have ascendancy and control over the physical body, for the spirit is the power
that quickens and animates the body and gives it life and intelligence.
</p><p>
We have the challenge; we ought now to concentrate on developing and improving our
present physical house, which tabernacles a spirit child of God, and prepare it for eternal
glory.
</p><p>
As his earthly mission neared its close, Jesus revealed this knowledge to his disciples: 
</p><p>
"In my Father's house are many mansions: if it were not so, I would have told you. I go to
prepare a place for you . . . that where I am, there ye may be also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/2-3#2">John 14:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
In his infinite wisdom and concern for all mankind, Jesus opened a vision wherein we get a
glimpse of the heavenly house and its mansions being prepared for us to inhabit. Each one of
us is inexorably building an eternal home, the mansion we will occupy in our future
everlasting life.
</p><p>
Brigham Young said: 
</p><p>
<b>Prepare to live</b>
</p><p>
"Prepare to die, is not the exhortation in this Church and Kingdom; but prepare to live is the
word with us, and improve all we can [for the] life hereafter, wherein we may enjoy a more
exalted condition of intelligence, wisdom, light, knowledge, power, glory, and exaltation.
Then let us seek to extend the present life to the uttermost, by observing every law of health,
and thus prepare for a better life." (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, p. 186.) Also, the words of
President Heber J. Grant: 
</p><p>
"Upon our lives here is predicated the degree of perfection in which we shall rise . . . A man
will not awake on resurrection morning to find that all that he neglected to do in mortal life
has been put to the credit side of his account and that the debit side of his ledger shows a
clean page. That is not the teaching of the gospel.
</p><p>
"'Whatsoever a man soweth, that shall he also reap. For he that soweth to his flesh shall of
the flesh reap corruption; but he that soweth to the spirit shall of the spirit reap life
everlasting (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/7-8#7">Gal. 6:7-8</a>).' He whose every act has fitted him for the enjoyment of eternity will be far in
advance of the man whose all has been centered on the things of this life." (<i>Millennial Star</i>,
Vol. 66, March 31, 1904, p. 201.)
</p><p>
It is worth all the effort we can muster to obtain the highest degree of glory&mdash;a promise
given only to the faithful. We are not without divine teachings as to how this glorified state
can be attained.
</p><p>
<b>Lay up treasures that endure</b>
</p><p>
The Savior gave this counsel: 
</p><p>
"Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and rust doth
corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal: 
</p><p>
"But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven . . .
</p><p>
"For where your treasure is, there will your heart be also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/19-21#19">Matt. 6:19-21</a>).
</p><p>
Treasures earned here are credited to our account in eternity and, if sufficient, will build for
us a house that will bear the weight of eternal life.
</p><p>
Alma informs us that this life becomes a probationary state, a time for men to prepare to meet
God (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/24#24">Alma 12:24</a>).
</p><p>
President David O. McKay has added this wise counsel: 
</p><p>
<b>God, the head of the house</b>
</p><p>
"Let us make God the center of our lives. That was one of the first admonitions given when
the gospel was first preached to man. To have communion with God, through his Holy Spirit,
is one of the noblest aspirations of life. It is when the peace and love of God have entered the
soul, when serving him becomes the motivating factor in one's life and existence . . .
</p><p>
"When God becomes the center of our being, we become conscious of a new aim in
life&mdash;spiritual attainment. Physical possessions are no longer the chief goal in life. To indulge,
nourish, and delight the body as any animal may do is no longer the chief end of mortal
existence." (<i>The Improvement Era</i>, June 1967, pp. 109-110.)
</p><p>
In these latter days we are surrounded by demons. We can identify some of these demons;
they are those who promulgate the uses of deleterious items that are not good for the
body&mdash;all the habit-forming drugs that are foisted upon us by seductive advertising and designing
persons who would lead us down the paths of sin to degradation and destruction, or, in the
vernacular, "on trips" through LSD, heroin, marijuana, morphine, and other habit-forming and
harmful drugs detrimental to the maintenance of a healthy body in which to house our eternal
spirit. We are thus encircled about by the angels of him who seeks to destroy our souls; but
thanks to the Lord, the days of probation are still with us. However, we cannot afford to
procrastinate the day of our salvation. We should be anxiously engaged in building a house
that will support and delight us in the eternal life to come.
</p><p>
<b>Nurture qualities of the spirit</b>
</p><p>
If we nurture the finer qualities of the Spirit that come from the presence of God, the Spirit
will gain ascendancy over the carnal body and subject the flesh to its will.
</p><p>
There is much conquering of self and overcoming of bad habits before the soul of man can be
sanctified by the Holy Spirit. We should determine now the kind of body or house we want
our resurrected being to occupy throughout the eternities of time. Shall it be clean and pure,
worthy to receive glory in the eternal mansions of our God, or shall it be one that cannot
abide that glory and thus will be assigned to a kingdom of lesser glory or to a place without
kingdom or glory?
</p><p>
The choice is ours to make. The Lord has said, "For the power is in them, wherein they are
agents unto themselves. And inasmuch as men do good they shall in no wise lose their
reward" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/28#28">D&amp;C 58:28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Vision of heavenly abodes</b>
</p><p>
Now I call your attention to one of the greatest visions ever granted to any prophet of God
respecting the future status of this earth's inhabitants. This revelation describes the three
degrees of glory and is without doubt one of the most profound revelations given in any
dispensation. It encompasses the knowledge, wisdom, and light that our Heavenly Father feels
is expedient for us to have in relation to the hereafter and the future destiny of his children.
</p><p>
Perhaps no other scripture furnishes us with such direct knowledge on this subject as does this
wonderful revealing vision. I direct your attention to the essentials in each of these degrees:
the celestial, the terrestrial, and the telestial. To further support this latter-day vision, I quote
the apostle Paul, who likened the highest degree of glory unto the sun, which
is the most radiant of all God's planets; the second is likened unto the moon, which is a much
lesser light than the sun; and the other is likened unto the stars; and as one star differs from
another star in glory so also is the resurrection of the dead (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/40-42#40">1 Cor. 15:40-42</a>).
</p><p>
An understanding of this revelation enables one living in mortality to examine himself and his
mode of life and to personally determine whether it fully satisfies his need. He can change his
life if additional time is spared him and set his sights on a higher goal. This knowledge
enables him to see more understandingly the purpose of life here and now, and makes
perfectly clear that the nature and quality of the life he pursues in this existence will
determine his destiny in the eternities to come.
</p><p>
From this vision of the three degrees of glory given to the Prophet Joseph Smith and Sidney
Rigdon, we learn the various punishments and rewards meted out to all persons according to
their worthiness.
</p><p>
<b>The celestial</b>
</p><p>
The conditions for entering the celestial glory for those who come forth in the resurrection of
the just are as follows: They are the ones who receive the testimony of Jesus and believe on
his name and are baptized in his name that they might be cleansed of their sins, that they
might receive the Holy Ghost by the laying on of hands of those possessing this authority.
They are they who have overcome by faith all things and are sealed by the Holy Spirit of
Promise, and into whose hands the father has given all things. They are priests and kings of
the most high and receive of the fullness of God's glory. They are they who will glory in
God and not in man. They shall dwell in the presence of God and Christ forever. They are
men, made perfect through the atonement of Christ, whose bodies are celestial and whose
glory is as that of the sun (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/50-70#50">D&amp;C 76:50-70</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The terrestrial</b>
</p><p>
The terrestrial glory differs from that of the celestial kingdom, as the moon differs in glory
from the sun. Those who achieve this glory are they who died without law. They are the
spirits of men kept in prison. They are the ones who did not receive the testimony of Christ in
the flesh, but who afterwards received it. They are the honorable men of the earth made blind
by men's craftiness. These will receive of Christ's glory but not of his fullness. They will
receive of the presence of the Son but not the fullness of the Father. Their bodies are
terrestrial (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/71-79#71">D&amp;C 76:71-79</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The telestial</b>
</p><p>
In the vision, they then beheld the glory of those in the telestial kingdom, which is the least
of the three degrees of glory. Its glory differs from that of the other two, as the glory of the
stars differs from those of the sun and the moon, and as the glory of one star differs from that
of another star in glory.
</p><p>
Those in this kingdom received not the gospel of Christ nor his testimony, yet did not deny
the Holy Spirit. They are thrust down to hell. They will not be redeemed from Satan until the
last resurrection, until the Lord, even Christ, the Lamb, shall have finished his work. Those of
the telestial glory will not receive the Lord's fullness of the eternal world, but of the Holy
Spirit through the ministration of the terrestrial, and the terrestrial through the ministration of
the celestial (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/81-87#81">D&amp;C 76:81-87</a>).
</p><p>
Such are the degrees of glory in Christ's many mansions. They provide the knowledge
necessary to understand the goals toward which we are to strive in order to enjoy the
blessings of our God in whatever kingdom we may merit, be it great or small. We cannot
inherit a higher glory than that which our bodies are prepared and conditioned to receive
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/28-32#28">D&amp;C 88:28-32</a>).
</p><p>
<b>A guide for mortality</b>
</p><p>
This enlightening revelation in the 76th section of the Doctrine and Covenants should be
prayerfully studied in its entirety and understood fully, for it is a safe guide to one's life here
in mortality. The goal for every person is to build a house by good works, to
attain the highest degree of the celestial kingdom of God. Anything short of this, with the
light and knowledge we possess, would be settling for a great deal less than our Lord offers
us.
</p><p>
By careful study of the revelation, each person can determine the degree of glory he will
inherit hereafter. Understanding this, he should project himself and his thinking into the
eternal world and picture himself there according to the pattern of life he is now living. If he
does so, I wonder if he would be happy with what he envisions his future inheritance to be?
</p><p>
<b>Saving power of knowledge</b>
</p><p>
Knowledge is necessary to salvation. The Prophet Joseph taught: "It is impossible for a man
to be saved in ignorance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>). Knowledge is power, the power to aid us to adjust to
the various conditions and circumstances of life in which we find ourselves at any moment of our lives.
</p><p>
Imagine a builder attempting to construct an edifice of any kind, without knowledge, plans,
and specifications to guide him. We all know it cannot be done successfully. Therefore, when
building mansions for our souls, the greater our knowledge concerning them, other things
being equal, the more glorious our mansions will be. It must, of course, be knowledge of the
right kind, divine knowledge, knowledge that comes through inspiration or revelation to us
from God or through his anointed servants. Knowledge, then, is the first requisite for building
a house that will bear the weight of eternal life.
</p><p>
Thus equipped, we are to observe the laws associated with the knowledge God has provided
us, and keep the commandments he has so abundantly given to help implement that knowledge.
</p><p>
<b>Vision</b>
</p><p>
To do all this we need vision and insight, for as is recorded in Proverbs, "Where there is no
vision, the people perish" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/29/18#18">Prov. 29:18</a>).
</p><p>
This means that without the type of vision given to our prophets, people in general will lack
the information necessary to discover divine truth. It also has a personal application, for any
man lacking vision or insight into truth is slow to progress in spiritual things.
</p><p>
One with active vision will seek understanding of God's commandments and will find ways to
obey and keep them. From such knowledge gained he will realize that his body is the
tabernacle of his immortal spirit, that the temple of the spirit should not, in any manner, be
defiled. It must be preserved in purity&mdash;physical, intellectual, moral, and spiritual purity. This is
why the Lord has given us the Ten Commandments, the Beatitudes, the Word of Wisdom, the
temple ordinances, and persuasive instruction from his prophets and servants. This is why he
requires that we resist and overcome all evil, all immorality, all baseness. This is why he
urges us to live righteously before him. Those who observe his physical or temporal laws
shall receive health in the navel and marrow to their bones, and shall find wisdom and great
treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-19#18">D&amp;C 89:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Physical health and spirituality</b>
</p><p>
There is a close relationship between physical health and spiritual development. All excesses
are wrong and ultimately lead to disaster. When one's physical health is impaired by
disobedience to God's eternal laws, spiritual development will also suffer.
</p><p>
The same is true of the intellectual phase of life. Intellectual dishonesty disquiets and curses
the lives of those guilty of such deceit. Can the spirit of the Lord activate one guilty of
intellectual dishonesty? How glorious our society would be if all those who make up that
society were intellectually honest.
</p><p>
<b>Sources of strength</b>
</p><p>
The quotable gem from Tennyson's beautiful character, Sir Galahad: "My strength is as the
strength of ten, because my heart is pure." What strength? Not only physical strength,
but moral strength, the strength that resides in purity of life, that faces
danger, disaster, abuse, false witness, and accusation undaunted; the strength that comes from
doing right and living righteously before the Lord, that knows no "new morality," but only the
one, the true, the eternal morality instituted by God and preserved in the Ten Commandments
and the Beatitudes.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, be not deceived and led astray by the wiles and seductive "charms" of
those advocating that which they call the "new morality." There is no such thing. It is a name
only, given to an old evil whose ultimate effect is to destroy man, the thing it has done under
other guises through the centuries. It will never permit you to build a house that will bear the
weight of eternal life.
</p><p>
The truly spiritual person is the one who finds joy and happiness and true purpose in the
things of God, such as prayer, humility, selfless service, kindness, virtue, chastity, obedience
to God's will and laws, love unfeigned, nobleness of soul, regard for that which is sacred and
holy&mdash;in short, all the attributes God would have us acquire and exercise here in mortality.
We may never know all of them in our brief mortal sojourn, but implementing those we know
will help us wisely build that structure which will bear the weight of eternal life.
</p><p>
Truly life on this earth is brief indeed, but the worth of it can be priceless. By vigorously
seeking God's help, by striving for true knowledge, the knowledge of God's eternal plan will
become ours to live by.
</p><p>
<b>Obedience and eternal life</b>
</p><p>
God has given this promise: ". . . if you keep my commandments and endure to the end, you
shall have eternal life, which gift is the greatest of all the gifts of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>).
</p><p>
The renewal and sanctification of our bodies by the power of the Holy Ghost is obtained by
living the gospel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33#33">D&amp;C 84:33</a>). Our treasures of good works that precede us are building our eternal
mansions. To project one's thinking into the eternities under the influence of the spirit will
stretch one's mind and give clear vision of God's plan, which will help chart a true course
back to his presence. Keep eternity always before you here in mortality and base your acts
and judgments and decisions upon God's eternal laws. We should educate ourselves not only
for time but also for eternity.
</p><p>
My brothers, sisters, and friends, I hope we will always remember and keep uppermost in our
minds and never forget that in all our doings, the chief business of our lives is to build a
house that will bear the weight of eternal life. I bear witness to the truthfulness of these
things. They are things we should know and never forsake. May God give us the courage to
walk humbly before him, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
