<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Salvation Dependent Upon Communication from God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 131-134</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, if varied experiences enrich the soul, then I would hope for every
one of you that you could be assigned to be one of the last speakers in a general conference
of the Church. It reminds me of a story that Brother Adam S. Bennion told once. He was a
great storyteller as you remember.
</p><p>
He said that there was a man who was disturbed by the howling dog of his neighbor. He
stood it as long as he could, and then at 3 am in the morning put on his bathrobe and slippers
and walked across the intervening lawn to his neighbor's home. He pounded on the door until
he finally roused the neighbor, who came to the door sleepy-eyed, and he said to him, "Say,
mister, your howling dog has kept me awake all night."
</p><p>
Strangely enough, the neighbor never said a word. He just closed the door and went back to
bed. But the next morning at precisely the same hour he went across the same lawn in the
other direction and pounded on his neighbor's door and finally got him up. And when he
came to the door, he said, "Say, mister, I haven't got a dog."
</p><p>
Well, that's the way I feel right now, brothers and sisters, I haven't got a subject. They have
all been spoken on.
</p><p>
But realistically, the breadth and the depth of the subjects of the gospel is so great that I
suppose every speaker, succeeding one after another, could well speak on the same subject.
</p><p>
In the days of ancient Israel, "the feast," which was similar to our present-day "conference,"
was a time of gathering, a time of harvest, a time of rejoicing, and, what is more particularly
significant, "the feast" was designated by the Lord as a time of remembrance. I cannot help
feeling that here should be the re-enactment of this ancient admonition of the Lord, that we
should remember the things that we have heard at this great conference of the Church.
</p><p>
That we have met under the peaceful influence of President McKay, who is nearby, at this
conference brings to all of us a comforting reassurance.
</p><p>
With due respect to Brother Petersen in the excellent treatment of the subject of revelation I
would like to offer one or two thoughts which go in a different direction, treating perhaps
another aspect of it.
</p><p>
<b>"All That God Has Revealed"</b>
</p><p>
Our Ninth Article of Faith states: "We believe all that God has revealed, all that He does now
reveal, and we believe that He will yet reveal many great and important
things pertaining to the Kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
From this we declare that the salvation of mankind is dependent upon communication from
God.
</p><p>
In this age of space exploration science is probing deeper and deeper into the universe. A
landing upon the moon is planned. Contact with Venus, Mars, and other planets is also under
consideration. That other beings will be found to exist "out there" in the depths of space is a
matter of scientific concern.
</p><p>
Suppose this proved to be true and contact with people of other planets were permitted by the
Lord; it would be ironic indeed if they were found to have the same lack of response or "no
concern" attitude as do the people of the planet Earth, generally, toward the visits and
contacts made by persons from outer space who have already come to the earth.
</p><p>
Since 1830 we have proclaimed to the world that visitors on divine missions have been sent
to this planet to reveal the purpose of this life and the needed preparation for life after mortal
death. Concerning other occupied planets, God made this known unto Moses, as revealed to
the Prophet Joseph Smith:
</p><p>
"And worlds without number have I created; and I also created them for mine own purpose;
and by the Son I created them, which is mine Only Begotten"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33#33">Moses 1:33</a>). As to his
purpose, he said to Moses: "For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the
immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Men dream of finding somewhere "out there" super beings whose intelligence is superior to
that found upon the earth. But this concept could have a two-way application in that visitors
from outer space with superior intelligence and understanding could come to the planet Earth
with vital truths of salvation.
</p><p>
<b>Redeemer of Mankind Revealed</b>
</p><p>
Speakers at this conference have testified of the appearance of God our Heavenly Father and
his Beloved Son, who is the Lord and Redeemer of mankind, unto the Prophet Joseph Smith.
Contacts have also been made by other messengers sent to the earth from the presence of
God. We are now firmly in possession of the knowledge of the way back from mortality into
immortality, there to dwell in the presence of our Heavenly Father, who in his holy purposes
desires his children back with him.
</p><p>
Revelation may be regarded as incredible to many. Its reality may also be taken for granted
by our own members, producing a danger of forsaking the very will of God.
</p><p>
I testify, as others have done here today, that God revealed his mind and will unto Joseph
Smith, the first prophet in our modern times, and that since his day there have been other
prophets who have presided over this work and who have been directed by the Lord. I testify
that President David O. McKay is the chosen leader of God's work here upon the earth today,
unto whom he has given revelation for the guidance and direction of the work which our
Heavenly Father desires carried out upon the earth to accomplish his purposes.
</p><p>
We are frequently asked the questions by those who are not of our faith, "When was the last
time that your prophet received a revelation?" and "How is it made known to your people?"
In answer to these questions may I cite two most recent evidences of divine instruction and
revelation from God which are for the guidance of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>The Love of Jesus Christ</b>
</p><p>
The first of these concerns the message of President McKay at the beginning of this
conference, the substance of which he also gave to the stake presidencies of the Oakland
Temple District not long ago. Upon both of these occasions he told of the great love of Jesus
Christ and charged the assembly to reflect this love in their acts and deeds toward their fellow
men. He also told of the increase of the powers of darkness in accordance with the spread of
the restored gospel.
</p><p>
He proclaimed a warning unto those of the Church who might compromise
their way of life and lose the power and understanding of the gospel that "Atheism is the
greatest weapon Satan has to use, and its evil influence is bringing degradation to millions
throughout the world." And then, what is singularly important as a divine inspiration from a
prophet of God, he said, "Only the declaration of the divinity of Jesus Christ to all the people
of the world can counteract this evil."
</p><p>
<b>Parents to Teach the Gospel</b>
</p><p>
The second concerns the remarks of Elder Harold B. Lee last night in the general priesthood
meeting unfolding the outline of the family home evening program, concerning which you
will hear a great deal in the weeks ahead. He premised his remarks by referring to the
statements made by the prophets of God in this dispensation, emphasizing the importance of
parents teaching their children the gospel. These statements made by the President of our
Church are actually revelations from God concerning the importance of the family unit in the
plan of the gospel.
</p><p>
Our high resolve should be to bring ourselves in harmony with this instruction, thereby
obeying the mind and will of God as it is revealed unto his servants. In contemplation of this
divine information and these instructions, I would say unto those who have asked the
question, "When was a revelation last given?" that they might profitably take note of the
nature of and the manner by which these revelations referred to have been given.
</p><p>
From the Doctrine and Covenants I quote the following: "Wherefore, I the Lord, knowing the
calamity which should come upon the inhabitants of the earth, called upon my servant Joseph
Smith, Jun., and spake unto him from heaven, and gave him commandments"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17#17">D&amp;C 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge Which Exalts Man</b>
</p><p>
The commandments given by revelations from God provide the laws and ordinances of the
gospel, and obedience thereto will exalt man in the presence of our Heavenly Father. They
contain "pure knowledge" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/42#42">D&amp;C 121:42</a>)
which man cannot find out in and of himself, thereby necessitating
their divine communication.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith once described the manner in which such direct inspiration comes,
for said he: "Yea, thus saith the still small voice, which whispereth through and pierceth all
things, and often times it maketh my bones to quake while it maketh manifest"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/85/6#6">D&amp;C 85:6</a>).
</p><p>
Speaking to those who would deny the revelations of God, I would conclude with the remarks
of the Prophet Moroni, the same who made contact with Joseph Smith as a visitor sent from
the presence of God, as recorded in the Book of Mormon:
</p><p>
"And again I speak unto you who deny the revelations of God, and say that they are done
away, that there are no revelations, nor prophecies, nor gifts, nor healing, nor speaking with
tongues, and the interpretation of tongues;
</p><p>
"Behold I say unto you, he that denieth these things knoweth not the gospel of Christ; yea, he
has not read the scriptures; if so, he does not understand them.
</p><p>
"For do we not read that God is the same yesterday, today, and forever, and in him there is
no variableness neither shadow of changing?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/7-9#7">Morm. 9:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
About six weeks before the death of the Prophet Joseph Smith, as he had been harassed by
many concerning the revelations which God had given unto him, he bore publicly, at that very
important meeting held in Nauvoo on May 12, 1844, perhaps one of his last testimonies
concerning the revelations of God, wherein he said:
</p><p>
<b>"Make Your Calling and Election Sure"</b>
</p><p>
"Oh! I beseech you go forward . . . and make your calling and your election sure
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/10#10">2 Pet. 1:10</a>).
</p><p>
"When did I ever teach anything wrong from this stand? When was I ever confounded? I want
to triumph in Israel before I depart hence and am no more seen. I never told you I was
perfect; <i>but there is no error in the revelations which I have taught</i>."
(Andrew Jenson, <i>The Historical Record</i>, Vol. 7, p. 548. Italics added.)
</p><p>
<b>The Revelations of God</b>
</p><p>
The challenge to the members of the Church in these closing minutes of this great conference
is to adhere to the revelations from God that we may make our election sure. The challenge to
those not of the Church who are watching and listening is to be concerned, to investigate, and
to find out for themselves the truth of revelations from God, as they have been given by
divine messengers who have visited the earth, that they may come to know the ways of the
Lord and then courageously accept and live by them.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony to be added to those already borne that this is the work of our
Heavenly Father. I am grateful, my brothers and sisters, to be associated with you and pray
that the work may go forward as the Lord has ordained that it should, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
