<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Growing Problem of Drug Abuse</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Loren C. Dunn</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Loren C. Dunn, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 21-23</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
By invitation I recently attended a conference on drug abuse that was called by a group of
concerned citizens.
</p><p>
Speaking at this gathering were experts in this field from throughout the United States. Their
messages were in accordance with that which has been echoed by almost every group
investigating this problem, and that is: Drug abuse is on the increase, especially among our
youth.
</p><p>
<b>Availability of drugs</b>
</p><p>
Despite the valiant efforts of law enforcement, the availability of drugs is increasing. In fact,
according to youthful offenders, drugs are readily available through what they term as "the
underground" in most of our high schools.
</p><p>
It is evident that this is a fast-growing problem within the United States and Canada, and it is
also having its effect on many countries throughout the world.
</p><p>
There is a great need for us as Church members to support efforts in our communities to
strengthen law enforcement and encourage other programs designed to deal with the drug
abuse problem.
</p><p>
In listening to a group of youthful former drug users, they stated that it frightens them to
think that possibly as many as 50 per cent of their fellow high school students might at least
try marijuana at some time with a smaller number continuing on to other drugs.
</p><p>
These are students who evidently come from all backgrounds and economic levels of life.
</p><p>
Should these young people be correct in their estimates, we would have to face the realization
that each of our children sometime is going to be faced with the temptation of drug use.
</p><p>
<b>Reason for drug use</b>
</p><p>
The reason most youthful offenders start on drugs gives us some idea as to what we might do
to prevent this disastrous situation. When one group was asked why they started, they said
without exception, "We were alienated from our parents."
</p><p>
Somehow, in the home the love, confidence, and self-assurance that should have been
conveyed from parents to children was not conveyed. Parents failed to understand the
children, and the children failed to understand the parents; and in frustration and alienation the
children sought escape by turning to drugs.
</p><p>
These youthful offenders had been given material gifts by their parents, but these gifts seemed
to be in place of love instead of an expression of love.
</p><p>
If there are love and unity at home, and if children feel comfort there, they will know what to
do when this problem presents itself. But if there are bitterness and disharmony and mistrust,
then it is possible that they will seek escape through any form of vice available.
</p><p>
<b>Importance of home example</b>
</p><p>
President McKay has the following to say about the importance of example in our homes: 
</p><p>
"I believe that parents generally are teaching their children the gospel, yet I am convinced that
there is still much opportunity for improvement in this regard. I am not thinking of the set
hours in which you sit down to teach these doctrines to your children, but of the example
fathers and mothers give to their children regarding the faith that is dear to your hearts. Your
example will teach these principles more effectively than what you say. Out of our homes
come the future leaders of the government. If our homes were all they should be, the nation
would be safe" (<i>Gospel Ideals</i>, p. 482).
</p><p>
I believe that the example of which President McKay speaks is most important.
</p><p>
<b>Faith in Heavenly Father</b>
</p><p>
It's a simple step for a young person to go from faith and love and confidence in an earthly
father to faith and love and confidence in our Heavenly Father, and what better heritage can
we give him than the ability to communicate with God.
</p><p>
From Alma we read: 
</p><p>
"Counsel with the Lord in all thy doings, and he will direct thee for good; yea, when thou
liest down at night lie down unto the Lord, that he may watch over you in your sleep; and
when thou risest in the morning let thy heart be full of thanks unto God; and if ye do these
things, ye shall be lifted up at the last day"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/37#37">Alma 37:37</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Intelligent obedience</b>
</p><p>
On another occasion President McKay said: "Children deserve to be taught intelligent
obedience. Unhappiness in the child's life, as in the adult life, springs largely from
nonconformity to natural and social laws. The home is the best place in which to develop
obedience, which nature and society will later demand . . . I do not mean getting control by
cruelty, nor by foolish threats, but merely by letting the child know that he is part of a
community in the home; and that the other children have their rights and each child must
respect those rights.
</p><p>
"There is the beginning of democracy, and it is in the home" (<i>Gospel Ideals</i>, p. 488).
</p><p>
And again the Prophet has said: 
</p><p>
"Homes are made permanent through love. Oh, then, let love abound. If you feel that you
have not the love of those little boys and girls, study to get it. Though you neglect some of
the cattle, though you fail to produce good crops, ever study to hold your children's love"
(<i>Gospel Ideals</i>, p. 484).
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of communication</b>
</p><p>
The responsibility of communication is not alone on the shoulders of parents. The youth also
have a responsibility to contribute love and strength to the family organization.
</p><p>
I recall a stage play that recently was made into a movie. It dealt win parents whose only
child, a son, returned from military service. The father and son had never been close. It was a
situation in which both father and son loved each other but were unable to find ways to
express themselves, and therefore hostilities arose because each thought the other did not like
him. It was a breakdown of communication. But now the son was home from the army, and
things were different. The father and son began to establish a whole new relationship. The
high point of the play came when the boy said to his father something like this: 
</p><p>
"Dad, I always resented you when I was younger because you never told me that you loved
me, but then I realized that I had never told you that I loved you either. Well, Dad, I'm
telling you now: I love you."
</p><p>
For one electrifying moment the father and son embraced each other as the pent-up love and
appreciation of years came flooding out. This probably would never have happened had the
son not realized that he was as guilty of lack of expression as his parents.
</p><p>
<b>Love in the home</b>
</p><p>
So young people can make a difference. They can contribute to the love in their own home by
expressing their love for parents and in supporting the family. May the Lord bless us to know
that it is not our material heritage that can meet and defeat this problem of drug abuse, but
our spiritual heritage as expressed in the sanctity of the home and the strength of the family.
May our homes be havens of spiritual strength and may we constantly bear witness to our
children in word and deed of those truths that make a difference.
</p><p>
In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
