<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Children Are an Heritage of the Lord"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Boyd K. Packer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Boyd K. Packer, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 131-133</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters: We are greatly pleased to be in the mission field. In trying to
convey to you that feeling, the best I can do is to tell you that when it comes to missionary
work we feel just the way Elder LeGrand Richards sounds. We appreciate deeply the
opportunity to serve in the New England Mission. We are amazed at the great power and
strength of the missionaries. We stand in awe of the Latter-day Saint missionary.
</p><p>
A few days ago the general authorities assembled in the upper room of the temple to prepare
for general conference.
</p><p>
President McKay admonished us to feel free, perfectly free, uninhibited. From this invitation I
approach with reverence a subject I had theretofore not intended to pursue.
</p><p>
<b>"I'm a person"</b>
</p><p>
Some years ago two of our little boys were wrestling on the rug before the fireplace. They
had reached the pitch&mdash;you know the one&mdash;where laughter turns to tears and play becomes a
struggle. I worked a foot gently between them and lifted the older boy (then just four years of
age? to a sitting position on the rug, saying, "Hey there, you monkey, you had better settle
down." He folded his little arms and looked at me with surprising seriousness. His little boy
feelings had been hurt, and he protested, "I not a monkey, Daddy&mdash;I a person.
</p><p>
I thought how deeply I loved him, how much I wanted him to be "a person"&mdash;one of eternal
worth. For "children are an heritage of the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/127/3#3">Ps. 127:3</a>).
</p><p>
That lesson has lingered with me. Among the many things we have learned from our children,
this, perhaps, has been the most tempering.
</p><p>
Much of what I know&mdash;of what it matters that one knows&mdash;I have learned from my children.
</p><p>
Parenthood is the greatest of educational experiences. Bishop Brown made reference to a
lesson taught to his 12 year-old son. Were you conscious of the lesson learned by a much
older Bishop Brown?
</p><p>
Our children and the children and youth in the Church are great teachers. Let me relate two
lessons.
</p><p>
In the days of the pioneer settlements, it was not uncommon to have a ward marshal whose
assignment it was, under the direction of the bishop, to maintain orderly conduct among the
teenagers.
</p><p>
On a Sunday evening after sacrament meeting, the ward marshal at the little settlement of
Corinne came upon a buggy with some teenagers. Since it was his responsibility to check on
the young people, he stealthily crept near the buggy to see just what was going on. He
managed to reach a rather insufficient tree very close to the buggy just as the moon came out.
He had to stand more or less at attention to keep from being seen, but he could easily hear all
that was transpiring in the buggy.
</p><p>
Later, in reporting it to the bishop, he told of what had gone on. There had been some jokes
told, much laughter, and the usual teenage chatter. He said they sang several songs. The
bishop interrupted his report with the question, "Well, was there anything out of order in that
situation?" His answer, "Yes! me behind that blamed tree."
</p><p>
Always our youth are teaching those of us who are older, and they teach serious, sacred
lessons, too.
</p><p>
<b>"When do I die?"</b>
</p><p>
President Joseph T. Bentley presided over the Mexican Mission. I recall hearing him tell an
incident that happened, I think, somewhere in Mexico. An 11-year-old boy had been seriously
injured in an automobile accident. By the time they got him to the doctor, he was dying from
loss of blood. In looking for a donor for an emergency transfusion, the doctor decided on the
boy's seven-year-old sister. He explained to the little girl that her brother was dying and
asked whether she would be willing to donate her blood in order to save his life. The little
girl turned pale with fright, but  a moment she consented to do it.
</p><p>
The transfusion was made, and the doctor came to the little girl. "The color is coming back
into his face," he said. "It looks as though he is going to be all right." She was happy her
brother would be all right, but said, "But doctor, when am I going to die?" She had thought
all the time that she was not just giving her blood but literally her life to save an older
brother. We learn great lessons from our youth.
</p><p>
With parenthood such a glorious experience, how important it is that we have reverence for it.
</p><p>
Frequently I receive letters and not infrequently young couples come, particularly of college
age, struggling to achieve advanced degrees, and they ask for counsel on the coming of
children in their lives.
</p><p>
<b>Planned parenthood</b>
</p><p>
<i>Never</i> has a generation been so surrounded with those who speak irreverently of life. <i>Never</i>
has there been such persuasion to avoid responsibilities of parenthood. <i>Never</i> has it been so
convenient to block that frail footpath of life across which new spirits enter mortality.
</p><p>
Several years ago, while representing the Church at the University of Montana, I found
myself on a panel with representatives from several churches. The moderator asked each of us
to respond to the question, "Do you believe in planned parenthood?" My answer was a
resounding "yes!" with this explanation: We <i>plan</i> to have families.
</p><p>
Often when young couples come, they ask the specific question, "How many children should
we plan to have?" This I cannot answer, for it is not within my province to know. With some
persons there are no restrictions of health and perhaps a number of children will be born into
the family. Some good parents who would have large families are blessed with but one or two
children. And, occasionally, couples who make wonderful parents are not able to have natural
offspring and enjoy the marvelous experience of fostering children born to others. Planned
parenthood involves a good deal more than just the begetting of children. Nothing in our lives
deserves more planning than our responsibilities in parenthood.
</p><p>
I am concerned because our young couples are often in a quandary, particularly when the
arbitrary limiting of families is represented as an act of social good.
</p><p>
In this generation we find the indiscriminate marketing of products. Medical advancements
with the potential to sustain life and to extend it for the infirm are advertised&mdash;even among
our unmarried youth&mdash;as agents to prevent life and to extinguish it.
</p><p>
Young couples are continually told that parenthood means forfeiture of advanced degrees and
limiting of occupational progress, a representation they will live to know is false.
</p><p>
<b>Approach parenthood with reverence</b>
</p><p>
Whether you will be blessed with many children or but a few, or perhaps experience
parenthood through the raising of little ones left homeless, is a matter that will be made
known as your life unfolds. But I urge you, I warn you to approach parenthood with
reverence. When you covenant in marriage and are free to act in the creation of life, when
you stand at the threshold of parenthood, know that you stand on holy ground. Recognize also
that in those areas of greatest opportunity lie the snares of persistent temptation.
</p><p>
We are grateful for our family, grateful for all of our children. We have learned so much
from them, some of the things we weren't conscious that we wanted to know. Each of them is
needed and wanted in our family; and I say again, much of what I know, of that which
matters that one knows, I have learned from our children.
</p><p>
Young couples, draw reverently close to your Father in heaven in these monumental decisions
of life. Seek inspiration from the teachings of the gospel of Jesus Christ. Grow close to him.
Perhaps you, as he, will come to "suffer the little children to come unto [you], and forbid
them not: for of such is the kingdom of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/14#14">Mark 10:14</a>). In the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
