<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Excess Baggage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1960, pp. 118-120</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I have come to know how it feels to be the last leaf on the tree.
</p><p>
I am grateful for my membership in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, and with
these other Brethren, I bear my witness that I know that the gospel is true, and that this
Church is led by divine and inspired leadership.
</p><p>
I rejoice in the growth of the Church. As Brother Lee reported on the organization of a stake
in England, and we heard from Brother Stapley and Brother Romney of the organization of a
stake in Australia, I was reminded of some prophetic words by President McKay. Sometime
ago, as President and Sister McKay returned from New Zealand after the dedication of the
temple there, many of us met them at the International Airport in Los Angeles. President John
M. Russon of Los Angeles Stake and I were walking with President McKay from the plane
toward the terminal, when he stopped us and said, "Brethren, next Thursday when the First
Presidency and Council of the Twelve meet, I am going to recommend that a
stake be organized in New Zealand." He continued, "You know, we live in a jet-age, and with
these fast planes it will be possible for the General Authorities to travel swiftly to any part of
the world, to visit stakes as they are organized."
</p><p>
Now we have seen those words fulfilled not only in New Zealand but also within the last
week in England and Australia.
</p><p>
Rather recently I enjoyed my first experience of traveling on a jet-propelled plane. It was
amazing the speed at which we traveled. Less than two hours after leaving Denver, we were
in Chicago. Prior to departure we were required to place our luggage on a pair of scales. If
the weight was under forty pounds the amount allowed each passenger, a green light flashed.
But if the weight exceeded forty pounds, a red light flashed, and a bell rang. The weight
exceeding the allowance is considered excess baggage and a penalty or additional charge is
levied. When the red light flashes, one begins to consider the unnecessary articles he could
have left behind, such as an extra pair of shoes, for example.
</p><p>
The thought occurred to me that this earth life is also a rapid flight or journey. We are
traveling toward a desirable destination, that of eternal life and exaltation. Now the Lord has
said, "For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and
eternal life of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Our goal should be to become perfect, even as our Father in heaven is perfect
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>). It would be
well in early life to select and make secure the characteristics and traits needed for this
journey of life, discarding the ones which are harmful and which might be classed as excess
baggage. We can then be sure as we continue our journey, that the green light and not the red
one will be flashing.
</p><p>
What are some of the traits which might be regarded as excess baggage on our journey
toward perfection? To mention but a few: hate and anger and the holding of grudges, a hot
temper and a quick tongue, envy, jealousy, and greed, a critical attitude resulting in
faultfinding, backbiting, and judging harshly. All these are excess baggage and we shall have
to pay dearly for them.
</p><p>
In contrast there are certain basic, essential characteristics or traits which are very desirable.
They constitute legitimate or necessary baggage on our life's journey. One is love, love for
our Father in heaven love for fellow men and neighbors
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/37,39#37">Matt. 22:37,39</a>).
The Savior taught, "But I say unto
you, Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you, and pray
for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
</p><p>
Someone has said, "Be kind to your enemies, for you are the one who made them."
</p><p>
One of the most beautiful stories of love, loyalty, and devotion, related in the scriptures is that
of Ruth. It seems that there was a famine in the land of Bethlehem. A certain man took his
wife, Naomi and their two sons and journeyed to the land of Moab. The husband became ill
and passed away, leaving his widow and the two boys. Subsequently the two sons married
Moab girls, but within ten years' time, both of the sons also died. Naomi felt impressed that
she should return to her homeland in Bethlehem. Her two daughters-in-law expressed a desire
to accompany her. But Naomi encouraged them to return to their former homes, friends, and
loved ones. One left, but the other, whose name was Ruth, overcame Naomi's objections,
when she uttered these tender and memorable words: "Intreat me not to leave thee, or to
return from following after thee: for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I
will lodge: thy people shall be my people, and thy God my God: 
</p><p>
"Where thou diest, will I die, and there will I be buried: the Lord do so to me and more also,
if ought but death part thee and me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ruth/1/16-17#16">Ruth 1:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Self-control is a very valuable asset to possess on life's journey. The ability to control one's
temper, one's tongue, one's thoughts is highly commendable. As pointed out in Proverbs: 
</p><p>
"He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty; and he that ruleth his spirit than he that
taketh a city" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/16/32#32">Prov. 16:32</a>).
</p><p>
Another excellent quality is a forgiving nature and disposition. The Lord has admonished us
to be ever ready and willing to forgive our fellow man. In these latter days he has counseled: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, I say unto you, that ye ought to forgive one another; for he that forgiveth not his
brother his trespasses standeth condemned before the Lord; for there remaineth in him the
greater sin.
</p><p>
"I, the Lord, will forgive whom I will forgive, but of you it is required to forgive all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/9-10#9">D&amp;C 64:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
One of the virtues possessed by the Savior so perfectly that we should strive to perfect in
ourselves, is that of tolerance, that is, a willingness to be long-suffering, patient, to appreciate
another's point of view. Let us be strict and critical with ourselves, but lenient and tolerant
with others.
</p><p>
With the passing of each day we travel along our journey, some improvement should be
found in our lives. As a woman testified in a prayer meeting, "I ain't what I ought to be; and
I ain't what I'm gonna be; but anyway, I ain't what I was."
</p><p>
The Savior set us the example. We should earnestly strive to pattern our lives after his. If we
do this, we will discard those qualities that constitute excess baggage. We will carry with us
only those characteristics that are essential and that will permit us to continue our journey
unencumbered.
</p><p>
The poet Henry Van Dyke has given us these words of counsel regarding our way of living: 
</p><p>
"To be glad of life because it gives you the chance to love and to work and to play, and look
up at the stars; to be satisfied with your possessions, but not contented with yourself until you
have made the best of them; to despise nothing in the world except falsehood and meanness
and to fear nothing except cowardice; to be governed by your admirations rather than by your
disgusts; to covet nothing that is your neighbor's except his kindness of heart and gentleness
of manners; to think seldom of your enemies, often of your friends, and every day of Christ;
and spend as much time as you can with body and with spirit in God's out-of-doors. These
are little guide posts on the footpath of peace."
</p><p>
May we all live so that our life's journey may be pleasant and we can obtain the peace of
God which passeth all understanding (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/4/7#7">Philip. 4:7</a>),
I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ, our Savior. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
