<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Blessings of Eternal Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1947, pp. 95-100</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is an awe-inspiring sight to stand here and look into the faces of this vast audience. It is in
humility that I occupy this position today. I pray to our Father in heaven that his Spirit will
attend me.
</p><p>
I desire to direct my remarks this afternoon to the youth of the Church. I, like the brethren
who have spoken previously, have a strong faith and admiration and love for the youth of the
Church. I know that they have a testimony of the gospel of Jesus Christ and that they will
carry on faithfully.
</p><p>
BLESSINGS PROVIDED FOR YOUTH
</p><p>
Youth of the Church, young men and young women, you are the richest people in the world.
Some of you may say in your minds that you have no money. I care not whether you have
ten cents or a million dollars. Money perishes; but the wealth that you have surpasses
anything that you can gain here in this world which is of the world. You are members of the
true Church of Jesus Christ and are recipients of the restored gospel of our Lord and Savior.
You have the Holy Priesthood after the order of the Son of God. You have at your command
all the blessings which come to those who love God and keep his commandments, even the
promise of the blessing of eternal life which he says is the greatest gift that he has for man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>)
if you will but serve the Lord your God with all your heart, might, mind,
and strength
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/2#2">D&amp;C 4:2</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/5#5">D&amp;C 50:5</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/19#19">D&amp;C 51:19</a>).
</p><p>
More than a hundred years ago God the Eternal Father and his Only Begotten Son appeared
to the Prophet Joseph Smith and opened up the last dispensation of the gospel. Following this
great vision a number of heavenly beings appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith and bestowed
upon him all the gifts, blessings, powers, ordinances, and priesthood necessary for the
salvation of the human family. It is this priesthood and these gifts and blessings which the
youth of the Church today possess.
</p><p>
GOSPEL BRINGS JOY
</p><p>
The gospel of Jesus Christ was given to us in order that we might have joy. In fact,
</p><p>
Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
It is God's purpose and will that we might be happy today, tomorrow, next week, a hundred
years from now&mdash;yes, a million years from now. You may say in your mind, "But we won't
live that long." We will live that long. Life is eternal, and the thing that is important to
remember is that the way we live today, and the way we live throughout mortality, will
determine our happiness throughout eternity, will determine our status forever.
</p><p>
In order to illustrate what I have in mind, I would like to tell an old story. There was once an
old dog that went to the meat market and secured a piece of meat. On the road home he had
to cross over a bridge that spanned a stream of water. As he reached the middle of that
bridge, he looked down into the sparkling water and saw another dog with a piece of meat in
his mouth. He became covetous and decided that he would have the meat the other dog
possessed. Thereupon he opened his mouth and grabbed after that meat, and as he did so, his
meat dropped into the water and floated away. To his sorrow, the old dog found that he was
grabbing after a shadow.
</p><p>
SHADOWS OF TRUE HAPPINESS
</p><p>
Youth of the Church, there are many shadows of true happiness that you will be tempted to
grab after, and I promise you that if you grab after them, you will be like that old dog. You
will find that you have lost the good things that you now possess&mdash;happiness, the gospel, and
probably eternal life&mdash;and you will receive in return only a shadow of true happiness. The
things that I have in mind we call sins, all of the sins that we may commit. Remember that
Alma, the ancient Nephite prophet, warned us that "wickedness never was happiness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/41/10#10">Alma 41:10</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/13/38#38">Hel. 13:38</a>).
</p><p>
TOBACCO HABIT
</p><p>
There are three or four shadows of true happiness that I would like to point out briefly today.
The first one of them is the use of tobacco. Every young man in the Church, and I am sorry
to say that today every young woman in the Church also, is tempted and will continue to be
tempted to take up the habit of tobacco. In fact your friends may already have taken up this
habit. They may say to you: "Come on, take a smoke. It's smart to smoke, It's being a good
sport to smoke. All important people smoke. Have a good time while you are young, and you
can repent when you get old." In fact they not only make these remarks but also put forth all
sorts of other arguments to induce you to use tobacco.
</p><p>
Young people, youth of the Church, it is the devil that is talking through your friends to try
to induce you to adopt that evil habit. He wants you to be unhappy. He desires to tear down
your spiritual, physical, and mental life and to destroy your chances for a fulness of joy. For
these reasons he is putting forth his strongest efforts to try to induce you to take up the
tobacco habit.
</p><p>
NICOTINE A DEADLY POISON
</p><p>
Tobacco, as we all know, is very poisonous. It kills the body. In order to illustrate how
deadly the poison is in tobacco, I would like to tell a story that took place in my own family
when I was just leaving my teens. I had a sister who was at that time thirty-seven years old.
She was the mother of seven children. On this occasion her children had the
whooping cough. She went one day with her husband down to the farm, about six or seven
miles below town. Upon arriving there her husband found that he had to drive a cow home;
and so he brought my sister up to a little store about four miles below town, left her there,
and went back on his horse to the farm. When my sister went into the store, the lady back of
the counter asked her how her children were getting along with the whooping cough. She
replied, "Not very well." Then the lady picked up from the counter a bottle which was about
half full of a black substance. The label on the bottle read, "Whooping Cough Medicine." The
clerk said to my sister, "This is the best whooping cough medicine that I have ever seen. I
don't have any in the store right now, but I can order some for you if you wish me to." Then
she laid the bottle down and went to the telephone to call my sister's son for the purpose of
having him come down to her store to drive the car and take his mother home.
</p><p>
My sister picked up the bottle, pulled out the cork, smelled the contents of the bottle and then
took a taste. She said, "My, this is nasty." Then she instantly fell over dead. The doctor was
rushed to the scene. Upon examining the contents of the bottle, he declared it to be straight
nicotine. He said that nicotine was one of the most deadly poisons that people could take and
that the one swallow that my sister had taken had gone directly to her brain and had suddenly
killed her.
</p><p>
Young people, that is the deadly poison that we take into our bodies when we smoke or chew
tobacco.
</p><p>
Tobacco not only kills the body, but it kills the spirit&mdash;it kills spirituality. It is incompatible
for a man holding the Holy Priesthood of God to use tobacco and to study the Bible or to use
tobacco and to keep up his Church activities. Usually when he picks up the habit of tobacco
he lays down the Holy Scriptures, he decreases his Church activities, and he becomes to a
certain extent spiritually dead, which is the worst death that we can die.
</p><p>
God has given us the commandment that we should not kill. Youth of the Church, when we
take poisons into our bodies knowingly we are to a certain extent breaking this great law.
</p><p>
THE DRINKING HABIT
</p><p>
Another shadow of true happiness which I would like to mention today is more damaging in
its effects than is the habit of tobacco. It is the habit of drinking liquor. Elder Joseph F.
Merrill has already graphically described the bad effects of alcohol and so I will be very brief
on this subject.
</p><p>
It is my honest opinion that the devil has never discovered or invented a tool outside of liquor
which is more destructive to the human soul. He has no other tool which can bring human
beings down into misery, poverty, and degradation, which can cause corruption, and which
can cause people to commit all other kinds of sins more than by having them
use liquor. People when they get drunk are not in their right minds. In other words, they are
crazy. While under the influence of liquor, the moral controls of men and women are relaxed,
and they commit many sins that they would not otherwise do, such as adultery and murder. I
know, youth of the Church, that the devil puts it into the hearts of wicked men to give our
lovely girls liquor and get them drunk in order that they might rob them of their virtue.
</p><p>
In referring to alcohol, Robert G. Ingersoll said:
</p><p>
It murders the soul; it is the sum of all villainy, the father of all crime, the mother
of all abominations, the devil's best friend, and God's worst enemy. (Editorial,
Church Section, <i>Deseret News</i>, September 27, 1947.)
</p><p>
Today I call upon all the youth of the Church to make a resolution that you will never take a
smoke. If you already have taken one, that you will never take another one. That you will
never take a drop of liquor in any form. If you have already done so, that you will repent and
resolve today that as long as you live you will never take another drop of liquor. I promise
you that if you will make this resolution and never break it that you will be happy throughout
this life and throughout eternity, because you have kept your bodies clean.
</p><p>
SEX IMMORALITY
</p><p>
A third shadow of true happiness I would like to point out is even worse than the other two.
It is sex immorality. I firmly believe that there is no sin that human beings commit that
causes a loss of happiness, that causes the people to be degraded more completely, that breaks
up homes more thoroughly, that ruins love more permanently, that drives out the Spirit of
God and causes apostasy from the true Church more definitely than does the sin of sex
immorality.
</p><p>
All the way through history the prophets of God have taught the value of virtue. In fact, you
and I can still hear the voice of God crying down from Mr. Sinai to Moses,
</p><p>
Thou shalt not commit adultery
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/14#14">Ex. 20:14</a>).
</p><p>
Alma, the great Nephite prophet, told his son, Corianton, who had had an illicit association
with the harlot Isabel, the following:
</p><p>
Know ye not, my son, that these things are an abomination in the sight of the Lord; yea, most
abominable above all sins save it be the shedding of innocent blood or denying the Holy
Ghost? (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/39/5#5">Alma 39:5</a>).
</p><p>
The prophets in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, the Presidents of the Church
from the beginning down to the present time, have declared that our virtue is as valuable to us
as is our life, and we should guard our virtue with our life.
</p><p>
More than a hundred years ago the Lord revealed the following to the Prophet Joseph Smith:
</p><p>
And verily I say unto you, as I have said before, he that looketh on a woman to lust after her,
or if any shall commit adultery in their hearts, they shall not have the Spirit, but shall deny
the faith and shall fear.
</p><p>
Wherefore, I, the Lord, have said that the fearful, and the unbelieving, and all liars, and
whosoever loveth and maketh a lie, and the whore-monger, and the sorcerer, shall have their
part in that lake which burneth with fire and brimstone, which is the second death.
</p><p>
Verily I say, that they shall not have part in the first resurrection. . . .
</p><p>
But unto him that keepeth my commandments I will give the mysteries of my kingdom, and
the same shall be in him a well of living water, springing up unto everlasting life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/16-18,23#16">D&amp;C 63:16-18,23</a>).
</p><p>
BODIES ARE TEMPLES OF GOD
</p><p>
Youth of the Church, again I call upon you to make a resolution that you will keep your
bodies clean and pure in every respect. Obey all the words that proceedeth forth from the
mouth of God, living all the principles of the gospel to the best of your ability in order that
you might be happy. Do these things in order that you might have that joy which God wishes
you to have. Remember at all times that your bodies are temples of God, as Paul, the ancient
apostle, has said:
</p><p>
Know ye not that ye are the temple of God, and that the Spirit of God dwelleth in you?
</p><p>
If any man defile the temple of God, him shall God destroy; for the temple of God is holy,
which temple ye are (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16-17#16">1 Cor. 3:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
If we will do all these things as members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints,
most of the youth of the Church in due time will have the privilege of going into the house of
the Lord with the one of his or her choice and there be married not only for life but also for
all eternity, and the children which are born under that covenant shall be theirs forever. These
blessings, however, are predicated on a continuance of righteous living.
</p><p>
BLESSINGS PROMISED TO RIGHTEOUS
</p><p>
When the great judgment day comes, and when all men and women who have been true and
faithful in all things stand before the judgment seat of God the Eternal Father and Jesus the
Christ to give an account of their actions, words, and thoughts, while in mortality, it shall be
said unto them.
</p><p>
Well done my beloved servants, enter ye into your exaltation. Receive your life eternal.
</p><p>
And at that day this great scripture which was given to the Prophet Joseph Smith shall be
fulfilled:
</p><p>
. . . and they shall pass by the angels, and the gods, which are set there, to their
exaltation and glory in all things, as hath been sealed upon their heads, which
glory shall be a fulness and a continuation of the seeds forever and ever. [And the
Prophet Joseph Smith said that promise meant to have the power to beget spirit
children.]
</p><p>
Then shall they be gods, because they have no end; therefore shall they be from
everlasting to everlasting, because they continue; then shall they be above all,
because all things are subject unto them. Then shall they be gods, because they
have all power, and the angels are subject unto them.
</p><p>
Verily, verily, I say unto you, except ye abide my law ye cannot attain to this glory.
</p><p>
For strait is the gate, and narrow the way that leadeth unto the exaltation and
continuation of the lives, and few there be that find it, because ye receive me not
in the world neither do ye know me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/19-22#19">D&amp;C 132:19-22</a>).
</p><p>
This is life eternal, my brothers and sisters. This is the exaltation which the gospel of Jesus
Christ promises those who love God and keep his commandments.
</p><p>
I humbly pray to our Father in heaven that he will bless the youth of the Church that they
might live clean and pure in every way, walking righteously and undefiled before God, that
they might receive this great exaltation of life eternal, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
