<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Revelation: The Challenging Message of Mormonism</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 93-97</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am sure we all respond from the depths of our being to that glorious rendition, "Crown Him
Lord of All," rendered as only the Tabernacle Choir, I think, could sing it.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, and in that salutation I should like to include all who are listening
regardless of their church affiliation, because we are convinced that we are brothers and
sisters. We believe in the universal brotherhood of man under the Fatherhood of God.
</p><p>
As this is the first conference since my change of status in the Church, I should like to take
this opportunity to express publicly to President McKay and his associates my sincere
appreciation for the confidence which prompted them to submit my name for your approval,
and I wish to thank you members of the Church for your confidence in their judgment. I
pledge only that I shall do my level best to make that judgment good and to that end humbly
invoke divine guidance and your indulgence. I shall need your prayers of faith.
</p><p>
But we are speaking this morning not alone to Church members. We are advised that perhaps
more than fifty percent of those attending in person or through the use of modern media are
friends of the Church who are visiting us. We appreciate your interest&mdash;we extend to you a
hearty welcome. Your attendance seems to indicate that you have heard something about the
Mormons and perhaps would like to know more. We should like to respond briefly to your
implied inquiry about the Church. We shall avoid dogmatism, for that ordinarily brings
antagonism. We simply invite you, our friends, this morning to, as Isaiah said, "Come, and let
us reason together" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/1/18#18">Isa. 1:18</a>).
</p><p>
We respect all men in their religious beliefs, but the divergent beliefs and multiplicity of
creeds have, through the centuries, been the cause of much confusion and concern. The
condition of the world religiously is stated in the <i>Catholic Encyclopedia</i>, from which I quote
the following: 
</p><p>
"A Babel of religious organizations all proclaim themselves to be the Church of Christ. Their
doctrines are contradictory and precisely in so far as one of them regards the doctrine which it
teaches as vital, it declares those of rival bodies to be misleading and pernicious."
</p><p>
Now, while we do not agree that the beliefs of others are necessarily pernicious, we do think
it regrettable that the original Church of Jesus Christ, as outlined in the New Testament, has
been broken up into so many creeds. We believe the Lord's house should be a house of order
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/8#8">D&amp;C 132:8</a>),
not divided against itself (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/25#25">Matt. 12:25</a>).
</p><p>
The question is often asked, what are some of the distinguishing characteristics of the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints? What, if anything, has this Church to offer which is new?
Would it be worthwhile to take a closer look at Mormonism?
</p><p>
Though there are many fundamental differences between this Church and others, we must
today be content to mention&mdash;and that only briefly&mdash;just one of them. We refer to our faith
in continued revelation from God to men. It seems somewhat paradoxical that this
fundamental doctrine of the Church should make it unique or distinguish it from others,
inasmuch as in all dispensations of the gospel current revelation has been the sustaining
power, the vivifying spirit of the divine Church.
</p><p>
In a concrete statement of beliefs known as the Articles of Faith, we declare our faith in all
that God has revealed, all that he does now reveal, and we believe that he will yet reveal
many great and important things (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/9#9">A of F 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
History proves that when the spirit or gift of revelation is withdrawn from the Church there is
nothing but a dead form left and men are prone to worship God with their lips and honor him
with their mouths, but, because there is no communication and therefore no understanding,
their hearts are far from him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/13#13">Isa. 29:13</a>).
</p><p>
The things of God can only be understood by the Spirit of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11#11">1 Cor. 2:11</a>) and the
Spirit of God is a revealing spirit. The Master promised before he left the earth to send
another Comforter (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/16-17#16">John 14:16-17</a>)
which would lead men into all truth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/3#3">John 16:3</a>).
Divine revelation has always been a
characteristic of the living Church&mdash;it is absolutely essential to its continued existence in an
organized state on the earth.
</p><p>
You remember the Prophet Amos said, "Surely the Lord God will do nothing but he revealeth
his secret unto his servants the prophets"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/3/7#7">Amos 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
And in Proverbs we read, "Where there is no vision, the people perish"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/29/18#18">Prov. 29:18</a>).
</p><p>
We have ample scriptural authority for our declaration that a man must be called of God by
prophecy and by the laying on of hands by men of authority to preach the gospel and
administer its ordinances (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/5#5">A of F 1:5</a>).
The Apostle Paul said, "And no man taketh this honour unto
himself, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/4#4">Heb. 5:4</a>). And Aaron was called by
direct revelation through Moses. When revelation ceases, people dwindle in unbelief, and not
only the people but also the Church apostatizes in the absence of inspired leadership.
</p><p>
That is exactly what happened in the primitive church, and that situation was a harbinger of a
universal apostasy, of which the Church of England speaks in its "Homily against Peril of
Idolatry," as follows: "So that laity and clergy, learned and unlearned, all ages, sects, and
degrees of men, women, and children of whole Christendom&mdash;an horrible and most dreadful
thing to think&mdash;have been at once drowned in abominable idolatry; of all other vices most
detested of God and most damnable to man; and that by the space of eight hundred years and
more."
</p><p>
Without continued revelation there can be no authorized ministry on the earth, and without
authorized officers there can be no Church of Christ. If some say there is no revelation and
will not be further revelation from God, we ask, "Why not? Has God lost the power to reveal
his mind and will to men?" Of course, to so state is tantamount to blasphemy. Do we not
need revelation or word from God? I ask you to consider the condition of the world and note
the dire need of the world for some divine guidance and direction.
</p><p>
Well, then, if God could reveal, and we need revelation, is the fault with man? Have we lost
the gift or the faith or the understanding that will enable us to receive revelation? Certainly it
would be more modest of us to admit the fault in ourselves than to blame God for not
speaking, if he does not speak. Or perhaps there may be some jamming of the messages by
the enemy as a result of which some have been tried to believe that there is power that can
transmit. We ask, in radio or television language, "Has the broadcasting station gone out of
business or broken down, or are there no receiving sets?"
</p><p>
So long as men believe there can be no revelation, they will make no at tempt to tune in.
They will lose their faith and will no longer look up and listen. Some even deny there is need
for revelation, but the daily press challenges that statement. In this imperiled, divided, and
chaotic world the need for God's help was never more apparent and urgent.
</p><p>
An English divine recently said. "Oh, that some man would arise who could authoritatively say
to the world, 'Thus saith the Lord!'"
</p><p>
Is it possible, our friends, that religion is the one department of human interest, investigation,
and research where progress is impossible? Would any professor say to his class in chemistry,
astronomy, physics, or geology, that no further discovery or revelation of scientific truth is
possible? Is religion the only human interest which is static and quiescent? Did Christ leave his
Church leaderless and intend it to continue so to be?
</p><p>
For ourselves, because of our faith in the universal and unchangeable love and justice of God,
we cannot believe that his Church in one dispensation would be blessed and led by what in
television parlance might be termed "live" revelation and in another dispensation leave a
distraught and imperiled world with only the recorded messages of ancient prophets, some of
which messages were for specific purposes and under special circumstances. We believe that
revelation both "live" and recorded is now and will continue to be available
to men Whenever the Lord has recognized his Church, he has given through his prophets
messages of warning, instruction, and hope.
</p><p>
When we say that we believe all that God has revealed, we declare our faith in the scriptures.
We believe the Bible to be a repository of divine truth and that it is authoritative, though not
beyond the need for interpretation and proper translation and, therefore, we say, when we
declare our faith in the Bible, "as far as it is translated correctly"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/8#8">A of F 1:8</a>). When we declare that we
believe that God does now reveal, that he still speaks through his prophets, and that his word
is scripture whenever and wherever given, when we make this statement we are simply
teaching the gospel of Jesus Christ and declaring as true the Judeo-Christian religion.
</p><p>
We sometimes meet with skepticism when we say that he still reveals, but let us paraphrase
the words of Paul for a moment. Why should it be thought a thing incredible
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/8#8">Acts 26:8</a>) that God will do
what he has promised to do? If time would permit we could take you through the scriptures
from Genesis to Revelation and show the promises of God with respect to the latter days.
Why should it be thought incredible not only that he would keep his promise but that he
would continue to do what he has done through all the dispensations of the gospel from the
beginning?
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ was established and is now directed by revelation, and that fact is
largely responsible for the appeal which this new Church makes, and when I say "new," I
wish to emphasize that to us it is not new but a restoration of that which was. The true
Church of Christ is not a blind alley, it is an open thoroughfare, where men may confidently
pursue truth in the light of revelation. That the Church is progressive and responsive to
revealed truth is evidenced by our further declaration that we believe that God will yet reveal
many great and important things.
</p><p>
This Church, our friends is not committed to any formal or inflexible creed, but its members
are taught to believe in and live by the revelations of the past and present and thus prepare
themselves for the revelations yet to come. Our concepts and even our faith must be held
subject to new light. The present and urgent need for continued revelation in this age of
communism, atheism, godlessness, the spirit of the anti-Christ becomes more apparent when
we realize that revelation gives us our most conclusive proof that there is a Divine
Being&mdash;and how the world needs to know of him!
</p><p>
In an age when hundreds of millions of people are being systematically indoctrinated with the
abominable doctrines of communism which are that there is no God, religion is an opiate,
Christ is a myth; surely in the midst of such determined, persistent, and relentless attacks from
the enemy, we may expect from God our Father some direction, and for that direction we
constantly pray.
</p><p>
But our message is this, our friends, God has spoken from the heavens; communication
between heaven and earth is still possible; the lines are open! That is the challenging message
of Mormonism, it is an ensign to the nations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/5/26#26">Isa. 5:26</a>), a message of hope to an imperiled world. If we
are to exercise saving faith and accompany it with works and, of course, "faith without works
is dead" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/26#26">James 2:26</a>),
we must know something of him, of his existence, his personality, his laws, his
purposes with respect to man, and realize that we are, in fact, his children, related to him. He
said, "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jesus Christ,
whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
We do not say that God is immaterial and incomprehensible and without a body. Rather we
say he is approachable as our Father. Now, revelation may come through dreams or visions,
the visitation of angels, or, on occasion such as with Moses, by face-to-face communication
with the Lord (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/33/11#11">Ex. 33:11</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/34/10#10">Deut. 34:10</a>).
You remember the Lord spoke to Adam, not only while he was in the Garden
of Eden (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/14#14">Moses 4:14</a>),
but after he was cast out (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/4#4">Moses 5:4</a>).
He spoke to other patriarchs and prophets through the
ages. He spoke to Enoch, who was called "The Seventh from Adam"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jude/1/14#14">Jude 1:14</a>), and it is said that he
was translated because he was especially favored with the presence of the
Lord. The record reads, "And Enoch walked with God: and he was not; for God took him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/5/24#24">Gen. 5:24</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord by revelation warned Noah of the coming flood. He talked with Abraham and told
him to leave his country and go into a new land and gave him some promises with respect to
his posterity. By revelation he commissioned Moses to go into Egypt, and under God's
personal direction he released the children of Israel from the bondage of the Egyptians.
</p><p>
So we may trace the line of revelators, men who have stood, each in his time, as the medium
through whom God speaks to his people, from Moses to Joshua, through the Judges, on to
David and Solomon and down to Zachariah and Malachi. Christ, himself, came to this world
to reveal God to men, and he himself was led and directed by revelation from his Father
while he dwelt on this earth.
</p><p>
The Lord, as you know, revealed to Zacharias, the father of John the Baptist, what was to
happen, and you remember what happened to Zacharias because of his lack of belief
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/20#20">Luke 1:20</a>). The
Lord revealed to Mary that she was blessed among women, that she should bring forth a son
and call his name Jesus (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/28,31#28">Luke 1:28,31</a>).
Christ himself said: "For I have not spoken of
myself; but the Father which sent me, he gave me a commandment, what I should say, and
what I should speak.
</p><p>
"And I know that his commandment is life everlasting: whatsoever I speak therefore, even as
the Father said unto me, so I speak"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/49-50#49">John 12:49-50</a>).
</p><p>
The apostles in the Meridian of Time were in touch with the heavens by revelation. Note
what Paul says: 
</p><p>
"But God hath revealed them [divine truths] unto us by his Spirit: for the Spirit searcheth all
things, yea, the deep things of God.
</p><p>
"For what man knoweth the things of a man, save the spirit of man which is in him? even so
the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/10-11#10">1 Cor. 2:10-11</a>).
</p><p>
You remember John, on the Isle of Patmos, wrote the book of Revelation, and, incidentally,
this is sometimes called the Apocalypse, and that means in Greek "revelation." This is what
he wrote in the first chapter of his book&mdash;it was not written of his own wisdom: 
</p><p>
"The Revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto him [speaking of himself], to shew
unto his servants things which must shortly come to pass; and he sent and signified it by his
angel unto his servant John" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/1#1">Rev. 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
The scriptures, then, are not only replete with evidence, but conclusive in proving that God
does and always has whenever there has been a dispensation of the gospel upon the earth,
been in touch with his people. Remember Paul said this, and he is speaking now of our time: 
</p><p>
"That in the dispensation of the fulness of times he might gather together in one all things in
Christ, both which are in heaven, and which are on the earth; even in him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10#10">Eph. 1:10</a>).
</p><p>
From the scriptures cited and many others, it seems evident that revelation from God to man
has been a vital characteristic, and standard procedure in all dispensations of the gospel. All
the prophets and leaders of ancient times were led, directed, chosen, inspired by God himself
through revelation.
</p><p>
Eusebius records what happened after the apostles had been slain and when no authoritative
answers could be given. He writes, "When the sacred choir of apostles became extinct and the
generation of those that had been privileged to hear their inspired wisdom had passed away,
then also the combinations of impious error arose by the fraud and delusions of false teachers.
These, as there were none of the apostles left, henceforth attempted without shame to preach
their doctrine against the Gospel of truth."
</p><p>
And Mosheim reminds us that both Jews and heathens were accustomed to a vast variety of
pompous and magnificent ceremonies in their religious service. All the records of the second
century mention the multiplication of rites and ceremonies in the Christian Church. "But," you
ask, "were these the times that have been?" Some of you may say, "We can
believe in revelation in Adam's day and in the days of Moses, in the days of Christ, in the
days of the apostles, but not now."
</p><p>
Is there any indication that we might, with reason, expect some word from God? Hear John's
testimony as he spoke of things that were to come in the latter days. He said: 
</p><p>
"And I saw another angel fly in the midst of heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach
unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people,
</p><p>
"Saying with a loud voice, Fear God, and give glory to him: for the hour of his judgment is
come" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6-7#6">Rev. 14:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
That, my dear friends, is a prophetic promise of revelation in our time. The Church today is
founded on the rock of revelation as securely as it was in the days of Peter when Christ said
to him, after Peter had spoken of his knowledge of him,
</p><p>
". . . upon this rock I will build my church; and the gates of hell shall not prevail against it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/18#18">Matt. 16:18</a>).
</p><p>
We think we are justified in anticipating future revelation, and we believe that it will be
surpassing in importance and glorious fulness anything that has yet been revealed. We believe
that he will continue to reveal himself as long as man continues his probation here on earth.
</p><p>
Now, you friends of ours probably ask, "What particular revelation is the one on which you
found your Church?" Time will not permit, of course, a complete answer to that, but humbly,
and from the very center of my heart, I say to you, our friends, and to you members of the
Church, God has restored the gospel of Jesus Christ and there was a great revelation, one of
the greatest of all time, when the Father and the Son, anticipating our very day and the events
of these times, appeared to a man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
They were personal Beings; they were separate and
distinct; they were in form like man, thus proving the first scripture in Genesis, "So God
created man in his own image"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>).
They spoke to him. Other revelations
followed. The whole message of Mormonism centers around the life and mission of Jesus the
Christ, and we proclaim to the world in contradiction to the hellish doctrine of communism,
God does live. He still speaks to men. There are prophets on the earth.
</p><p>
If that statement is true, it is the greatest message that has come to this earth since Christ
ascended into heaven because it is a message of his coming, and if it is true, all of you should
know it. That it is true we humbly testify.
</p><p>
We ask you to listen, to read, to pray&mdash;ask God for guidance&mdash;and we promise you,
paraphrasing the Prophet Moroni, that if you will ask of God in faith in the name of Jesus
Christ, whether what we declare is true, he will reveal the truth of it unto you by the power
of the Holy Ghost (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/4#4">Moro. 10:4</a>).
</p><p>
We believe this is the message for which the world has been waiting. We declare it is the
very truth of God, and for my own self I bear witness to that effect and say to you in
humility, but without any equivocation, by the same power and authority with which Peter
spoke, I say, with him, "Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/16#16">Matt. 16:16</a>). I
know this to be true, and I plead with men everywhere to hearken; for it is a message from
the heavens, to which I testify in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
