<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">In His Steps</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra T. Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 128-132</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Humbly I approach this sacred assignment on this glorious Easter Sunday.
</p><p>
Today as a great Christian nation&mdash;a nation with a spiritual foundation&mdash;we join the
Christian world in commemoration of that all-important and glorious event&mdash;the resurrection
of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
<b>Testimony of Jesus Christ</b>
</p><p>
I bear witness that Jesus is the Christ, the Savior and Redeemer of the world, the very Son of
God.
</p><p>
He was born the Babe of Bethlehem.
</p><p>
He lived and ministered among men.
</p><p>
He was crucified on Calvary.
</p><p>
He is risen&mdash;really resurrected.
</p><p>
He has appeared to men as a glorified Eternal King&mdash;in Palestine and also in America.
</p><p>
I bear this witness to all, but direct my remarks today especially to our youth of the free
world for whom I have great hope and a fervent prayer.
</p><p>
My text, from Luke in the New Testament, stands out boldly in its impressive beauty. It
covers a period of 18 years following the return of Jesus from Jerusalem to Nazareth. Except
for this one rich sentence of greatest import, the scriptures for this 18-year period are silent: 
</p><p>
"And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/52#52">Luke 2:52</a>).
</p><p>
Here then in one sentence&mdash;14 words&mdash;is the impressive, meaningful, and comprehensive
account of 18 years of preparation of the Son of God the Savior and Redeemer of the world.
</p><p>
From these impressively simple words of Luke we can well take inspiration for this hour: 
</p><p>
"And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/52#52">Luke 2:52</a>).
</p><p>
Here in broad outline, in one succinct sentence&mdash;four points&mdash;are given the major fields of
man's activity and striving&mdash;mental, physical, spiritual, and social.
</p><p>
<b>People; all-important</b>
</p><p>
Young men and women, remember, it is people&mdash;not things&mdash;that are all-important.
Character is the one thing we make in this world and take with us into the next. God's
purpose is to build people of character, not physical monuments to their material
accumulations.
</p><p>
<i>Point 1:</i> "And Jesus increased in wisdom . . ."
</p><p>
In the 14th chapter of John, Jesus is tenderly saying his farewell to his disciples after the last
supper. He tells them that he goes to prepare a place for them in his Father's house; that
where he is, they also may be (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/2-3#2">John 14:2-3</a>).
And Thomas says to him: 
</p><p>
"Lord, we know not whither thou goest; and how can we know the way?
</p><p>
"Jesus saith unto him, I am the way, the truth, and the life: no man cometh unto the Father,
but by me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/5-6#5">John 14:5-6</a>).
The road lies before us. It is clearly marked.
</p><p>
<b>Wisdom and understanding</b>
</p><p>
In Proverbs we read: "Happy is the man that findeth wisdom, and the man that getteth
understanding" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/3/13#13">Prov. 3:13</a>).
</p><p>
This same Jesus who increased in wisdom declared to a modern prophet: "Seek not for riches
but for wisdom, and behold, the mysteries of God shall be unfolded unto you, and then shall
you be rich" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>).
</p><p>
It was once thought, and still is in some places, that when a young man sets out upon a quest
for academic knowledge, his faith in God would soon be destroyed. Our youth generally are
living proof to the contrary. It is not the search for knowledge&mdash;nor knowledge itself&mdash;that
costs a man his faith. It is rather the conceit of small minds proving anew that a little
knowledge can be a dangerous thing It is intellectual pride that leads one to think he is
self-sufficient in matters of mind and of spirit. Let us ever realize the vast difference that
exists between discovery of the truth and the custodian of all truth. The one is human; the
other is divine.
</p><p>
<b>Truth through religion and science</b>
</p><p>
Religion and science have sometimes been in apparent conflict. Yet the conflict should only
be apparent, not real, for science should seek truth, and true religion is truth. There can never
be conflict between revealed religion and scientific fact. That they have often occupied
different fields of truth is a mere detail. The gospel accepts and embraces all truth; science is
slowly expanding her arms and reaching into the invisible domain in search of truth. The two
are meeting daily&mdash;science as a child, revealed religion as the mother. Truth is truth, whether
labeled science or religion. There can be no conflict. Time is on the side of truth&mdash;for truth
is eternal.
</p><p>
Yes, truth is always consistent, whether it is revealed direct from God to man through his
inspired prophets or comes from the laboratory through the diligent searching of his children
and the influence of the spirit of the Lord upon them.
</p><p>
Youth of the free nations, you face a changing world beset with many perplexities. But while
change is and will continue to be all about us in the physical world, we must recognize that
there are certain heaven-sent verities, principles, and values that are eternal. These never
change.
</p><p>
As you travel life's highway, you will encounter theories, proposals, and programs that have
wide appeal. You will be required to pass your judgment on them. Be not misled. Remember
that ideas and theories are either sound or unsound; soundness does not depend upon which
men hold them.
</p><p>
Our inability to explain a thing in terms of our materialism does not disprove its reality.
</p><p>
"Opinions at variance with time-honored beliefs, although receiving considerable current
acceptance, may not always rest on truth." It is the truth that endures. It is the truth that
makes men courageous enough to become Christlike. It is the truth that makes men and
nations free. Yes, be intelligent. Intelligence is the wise and judicious use of knowledge.
</p><p>
Continue to grow mentally&mdash;to grow in wisdom&mdash;to grow in truth. Desire it! Pray for it!
Study it! Practice it!
</p><p>
Do all this and you will find truth; it cannot be denied you. Having found it, never forget its
source, remembering always that "the glory of God is in truth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>).
</p><p>
"And Jesus increased in wisdom . . ." Like the master, in whose footsteps you should follow,
may you constantly increase in wisdom.
</p><p>
<b>Gain stature</b>
</p><p>
<i>Point 2:</i> "And Jesus increased in . . . stature . . ."
</p><p>
You, the youth of the free world, are the trustees of posterity. The future of your country will,
sooner than you think, rest in your hands and those of your contemporaries.
</p><p>
Be worthy trustees. Continue to grow in stature.
</p><p>
Be cheerful in all that you do. Live joyfully. Live happily. Live enthusiastically, knowing that
God does not dwell in gloom and melancholy, but in light and love.
</p><p>
A clean mind in a healthy body will enable you to render far more effective service to others.
It will help you to provide more vigorous leadership. It will give your every experience in life
more zest and meaning. Robust health is a noble and worthwhile attainment.
</p><p>
Possibly the best measure of the stature of men or women is in their own homes, at their own
firesides. Some of you have already established homes. Practically all of you will do so. As
you look hopefully forward, what conclusions have you reached about marriage, the home,
and family?
</p><p>
Are you planning for honorable parenthood even at the sacrifice perhaps of parties, clubs, and
other social enticements? Parenthood carries with it peculiar responsibilities. Are you planning
to accept these without quibbling? Are you willing to accept and enthrone motherhood as the
highest calling of woman?
</p><p>
No nation rises above its homes. In building character the church, the school, and even the
nation stand helpless when confronted with a weakened and degraded home. The good home
is the rock foundation&mdash;the cornerstone of civilization. There can be no genuine happiness
separate and apart from a good home, with the old-fashioned virtues at its base. If your nation
is to endure, the home must be safeguarded, strengthened, and restored to its rightful
importance.
</p><p>
Remember that moral purity is an eternal principle. Its violation destroys the noblest qualities
and aspirations of man. Purity is life-giving; unchastity is deadly.
</p><p>
Moral purity is one of the greatest bulwarks of successful homemaking. Happy and successful
homes&mdash;let alone individual lives&mdash;cannot be built on immorality.
</p><p>
Youthful sweethearts, be true to God's holy laws. Remember they cannot be broken with
impunity. If you would be happy and successful in your early association, courtship, and
homebuilding, conform your lives to the eternal laws of heaven. There is no other way.
</p><p>
And in so doing you shall increase "in stature."
</p><p>
<b>Favor with God and man</b>
</p><p>
<i>Point 3:</i> "And Jesus increased . . . in favour with . . . man."
</p><p>
The formula for successful relationships with others boils down to that divine code known as
the Golden Rule: 
</p><p>
"Therefore all things whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do ye even so to them . . ."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/12#12">Matt. 7:12</a>).
</p><p>
It was the Master who said: 
</p><p>
". . . whosoever will be chief among you, let him be your servant"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/20/27#27">Matt. 20:27</a>).
</p><p>
Unselfish, willing service to others was the keynote of his relationship with men.
</p><p>
"For even the Son of man came not to be ministered unto, but to minister, and to give his life
a ransom for many" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/45#45">Mark 10:45</a>).
</p><p>
Love one another. Serve your fellowmen. The example has been given you. The road lies
clearly before you.
</p><p>
If we would serve God through service to our brethren, we shall have need of a love for
work.
</p><p>
Energetic, purposeful work leads to vigorous health, praiseworthy achievement a clear
conscience, and refreshing sleep. It has always been a boon to man. Have a wholesome
respect for labor, whether with head, heart, or hand. Accept the challenge given by one of
America's eminent journalists, Edward W. Bok: 
</p><p>
<b>Vigorous participation</b>
</p><p>
"When you are called to get into the game, get into it good and strong. There's no fun in
going through life spoon-fed; in finding the soft seat. That makes a man soft, and a soft man
is an abomination before God and man. And put everything you've got into it Take hold and
carry the biggest load your shoulders can carry, and then carry it right. Set the pace for
others, don't let them set it for you."
</p><p>
<b>Honest toil</b>
</p><p>
May you ever enjoy the satisfaction of honest toil. The decree that by the sweat of his brow
man should eat bread is still basic. You will never wish or dream yourself into heaven. You
must pay the price in toil, in sacrifice, and in righteous living.
</p><p>
It is a truism that "security is achieved not bestowed." It cannot be gained by self-pity or
compromising principles. The world owes no man a living.
</p><p>
Youth of the world, as you strive to increase in favor with man, be ever on your guard that
you do not unwittingly, in the name of tolerance, broadmindedness, and so-called liberalism,
encourage foreign "isms" and unsound theories that strike at the very root of all we hold dear,
including our faith in God. Proposals will be offered and programs will be sponsored that
have wide, so-called "humanitarian" appeal. Attractive labels are usually attached to the most
dangerous programs, often in the name of public welfare and personal security.
</p><p>
<b>Apply standard of truth</b>
</p><p>
Have the courage to apply this standard of truth. Determine what the effect of the various
issues at stake is upon the character, the integrity, and freedom of man. Which increase his
freedom? Which abrogate or destroy? Which recognize and respect the individual dignity of
man?
</p><p>
We have the greatest material wealth ever known because we are free, and our people have
been encouraged to produce it&mdash;out of themselves.
</p><p>
It is foolish to place our material wealth first and decide that it, rather than the freedom and
energy that produced it, is our real wealth.
</p><p>
Freedom, a willingness to work, and the desire to serve your God through service to your
fellowmen&mdash;these are the sources of true wealth. Cling fast to these truths, and you must
inevitably increase in favor with man. "And Jesus increased . . . in favour . . . with man."
</p><p>
<i>Point 4:</i> "And Jesus increased . . . in favour with God . . ."
</p><p>
<b>Seek first the Kingdom of God</b>
</p><p>
This is the most important of all man's strivings&mdash;without it, nothing is of the slightest
account.
</p><p>
"For what shall it profit a man, if he shall gain the whole world, and lose his own soul?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/8/36#36">Mark 8:36</a>).
</p><p>
Growing in favor with God is the most important because it is the veritable foundation upon
which all other worthwhile blessings rest. Concerning this fact the Savior admonished his
disciples: 
</p><p>
". . . seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness; and all these things shall be
added unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
</p><p>
Spiritual strength promotes positive thinking, positive ideals, positive habits, positive attitudes,
and positive efforts. These are the qualities that promote wisdom, physical and mental
well-being, and enthusiastic acceptance and response by others. "Favour with God" gives
necessary incentive and perspective to life. It gives man real purpose for living and achieving.
</p><p>
As always, we have the example of the Master to guide us. "My meat," he said, "is to do the
will of him that sent me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/34#34">John 4:34</a>).
</p><p>
And again: "Father . . . I have glorified thee on the earth: I have finished the work which
thou gavest me to do" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/1,4#1">John 17:1,4</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Faithful in duty</b>
</p><p>
We increase in favor with God as we do the will of God. Let us be faithful in the work he
gives us, whatever it may be and whatever our station in life. Let our desires be in harmony
with God's will as it is revealed to us&mdash;keeping his word in our hearts&mdash;conquering selfish
desires that would lead us astray.
</p><p>
If we would advance in holiness&mdash;increase in favor with God&mdash;nothing can take the place of
prayer. And so I adjure you to give prayer&mdash;daily prayer&mdash;secret prayer&mdash;a foremost place
in your lives. Let no day pass without it. Communion with the Almighty has been a source of
strength, inspiration, and enlightenment to men and women through the world's history who
have shaped the destinies of individuals and nations for good.
</p><p>
Will you value and take advantage of the opportunity to tap these unseen but very real
spiritual powers? Will you, with Lincoln before Gettysburg and Washington at Valley Forge,
humble yourselves before Almighty God in fervent prayer?
</p><p>
Prayer will help you understand the apparent conflicts in life&mdash;to know that God lives, that
life is eternal.
</p><p>
Be not ashamed to believe and proclaim that God lives, that he is the Father of our spirits;
that Jesus is the Christ, the Redeemer of the world; that the resurrection is a reality; that we
lived as spirits before mortal birth and will live again as immortal beings through the
eternities to come. Blessed are you if you have a testimony of these things. These great
spiritual truths have seen systems come and go, and so it will be in the future. These truths
will, if you are wise, take precedence in your lives over all contrary theories, dogmas, or
hypotheses from whatever source or by whomsoever advocated.
</p><p>
Therefore go forward intelligently and yield simple and loyal obedience to all the laws of the
universe and the truths of eternity.
</p><p>
Yours is a great responsibility in this day when the need for courageous leadership is so
urgent: 
</p><p>
<i>You</i> can become those leaders!
</p><p>
Young men and women of the Free World, yours is a great challenge. You can be choice
spirits in your land. Forget not that each of you has been endowed with the priceless gift of
free agency. Each of you is, in very deed, the master of your fate, and Christ should be the
captain of your soul. You need not be the victims of circumstance, for unto you it is given to
achieve and become "perfect, even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>).
</p><p>
Jesus lives today. He is risen. This I know.
</p><p>
"And Jesus increased in wisdom and stature, and in favour with God and man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/52#52">Luke 2:52</a>).
</p><p>
May you, by following this same path, merit the same commendation. For if you follow this
divine pattern established by the resurrected Christ, you cannot fail, for you will have fulfilled
the measure of your creation.
</p><p>
Yes, Jesus Christ is divine. He lives today. He was resurrected. He is the Son of God, the
Redeemer of the world.
</p><p>
I bear this witness and pray that the young men and women of all the world may be blessed
with a testimony of this all-important truth, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
