<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Carnal Mind is Enmity Against God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 107-110</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am grateful, my brothers and sisters, for the presence of President McKay. It is always an
honor to be in his presence.
</p><p>
The degree of a man's faith in God, his religious concepts, and his feeling of eternal destiny
are characteristics that make him different. Man is a spirit child of God the Eternal Father, and
his birth into mortality is a crowning achievement; whether to be rich or poor, ignorant or
educated, white, brown, or black, as to color, sinful or righteous by nature.
</p><p>
<b>God is mindful of man</b>
</p><p>
God is mindful of man and, such as he is, has given him dominion over all things upon the
earth. He is the appointed master over all creatures of a lower kingdom of creation, and over
inanimate objects upon the land, in the sea, and in the air. ". . . thou hast made him," declared
the Psalmist, "a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and honour"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/5#5">Ps. 8:5</a>).
</p><p>
Mortal existence is such that man must give concern to material progress, but since he has
been given, by divine right, dominion over all things upon the earth, all material things can be
made to serve him. But, as to carnal things, God has given man a special warning, with the
commandment to cultivate the attributes of spirituality and intelligence, the opposites of
carnalism.
</p><p>
Unto the early day Roman Saints, Paul the Apostle wrote: ". . . to be carnally minded is
death, but to be spiritually minded is life and peace." He then explained what was meant by
the carnal mind, when he said the carnal mind "is enmity against God: for it is not subject to
the law of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/8/6-7#6">Rom. 8:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
Unto the Latter-day Saints, the Prophet Joseph Smith speaks of intelligence, with an
explanation of its meaning; said he: "The glory of God is intelligence, or, in other words,
light and truth."
</p><p>
"Light and truth forsake that evil one" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36-37#36">D&amp;C 93:36-37</a>).
</p><p>
He said also that a man with a carnal mind cannot abide the presence of God (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/67/12#12">D&amp;C 67:12</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Material progress</b>
</p><p>
Almost everyone today who has given the matter any concern and study is convinced that
material gain progressively achieved during the past century and a half has reached great
heights. The oft-referred-to phrase, "this age of enlightenment," refers to the progress that man
has made in the fields of science and industry. These advances, generally, are proving to be of
great benefit to man's natural existence, and there is no foreseeable end to this type of
progress. But the terrific impact of transpiring material progress is making inroads upon man's
spiritual and moral behavior.
</p><p>
These inroads, I believe, are not made because of that which has been achieved materially, for
surely the true spiritual concept does not stand in the way of material progress; but rather
inroads are being made because of the contemporary surrender and mutation of spiritual
values and the fundamental truths of righteous existence needed to meet the challenge of
material progress.
</p><p>
Man's spiritual decay in the face of material advancement, the evidence of which surrounds
us, must then be attributed to intensive drifts to carnalism.
</p><p>
As the apex of time draws closer, which will culminate the earth-life existence of man, the
basic issues of the spiritual mind and the carnal mind, of right and wrong, and of good and
evil will become more pronounced. For example, we see at work in the world today powerful
forces of carnalism that are opposed to God and the influences of a spiritual nature that can
persuade and direct man to the righteous life. These advocates of carnalism would substitute
God for an invisible earthly comrade and are prepared to lead the masses into a global
conquest, on the carnal premise that, collaterally, concepts of God as a
creator and the divine mission of the Son of God, the Redeemer of mankind, who is the
advocate of a system of proven and eternal laws of progress, are to be systematically
"nominalized," and finally eliminated.
</p><p>
But man need not be deceived by such principles of unrighteous dominion that are centered in
"carnalism," for the opposite&mdash;those principles of spirituality, faith in God, and exposure to
the eternal laws of righteousness&mdash;have been made fresh and new by divine restoration from
God, through his chosen prophets, in our own day and time. But as this and other issues of
right or wrong, good or evil, grow even sharper, we shall witness separations among men.
Out of the masses will come those who are of the "carnal mind" and those who are of the
"spiritual mind." It is in the latter realm that, by persistent conformity to spiritual or eternal
laws, man can reach perfection. In this we see the work and glory of God.
</p><p>
It is the right of each individual to work out his salvation. Given enough of such individuals
who adhere to this right, there exists a kingdom of righteousness, or a kingdom of God. Paul,
the apostle, evidenced his clear understanding of this when he said: "But the natural man
receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God: for they are foolishness unto him: neither can he
know them because they are spiritually discerned." He declared: "For what man knoweth the
things of a man save the spirit of man which is in him? even so the things of God knoweth
no man, but the Spirit of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/14,11#14">1 Cor. 2:14,11</a>).
</p><p>
In my own life I have received complete confirmation of righteous principles taught in my
early years by parents who cared, and by others, pertaining to a spiritual life. In my weak way
I am working with these traits, hoping to gain the complete supremacy that they offer. To the
Prophet Joseph Smith were revealed many divinely inspired truths that can lift man into the
light. In the following, the effect of spiritual mindedness in one's life is given: 
</p><p>
". . . your whole bodies shall be filled with light, and there shall be no darkness in you; and
that body which is filled with light comprehendeth all things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/67#67">D&amp;C 88:67</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Cultivating "spiritual mindedness"</b>
</p><p>
Here are a number of practical and effective ways of cultivating "spiritual mindedness": 
</p><p>
1. <i>Hold fast to the standards of right and truth</i>. When we "water down" or compromise
standards, we weaken our personal selves, and our chances of true happiness grow less and
less as each sliding step is taken downward.
</p><p>
Certain biblical and other contemporary writings confirm the fact that, in the days of Israelite
bondage in Egypt, not all of the Israelites were slaves; some gained release and favored
positions by "going over" to the gods of Egypt. On the garden walls of their palatial mansions
they painted pictures of the idols of the land, demonstrating their defection and surrender of
principle, as well as infidelity to their own people. This incident portrays a universal lesson
that has many parallels today in faith, in family, and in government.
</p><p>
2. <i>Rise above adversity</i>. David Starr Jordan once said: "Only that becomes real or helpful to
any man which has cost the sweat of his brow, the effort of his brain, or the anguish of his
soul. He who would be wise must daily earn his wisdom." Continuing, he said: "No one is
ever miserable who would truly pay the price of happiness. No one is miserable who has not
tried to cheapen life." (<i>The Strength of Being Clean</i>, pp. 6-7.)
</p><p>
I recall a fable of the Norsemen that when a man won a victory over another, the strength of
the conquered went over into his veins, suggesting that a victory over the carnal natures of
adversity and weakness brings strength.
</p><p>
The life of the apostle Paul, after his conversion to the gospel of Jesus Christ, gives evidence
of faithful endurance in rising above adversity.
</p><p>
If in any man a sense of disappointment, a conviction that life is too hard for us and that we
cannot shake off the crushing weight of its destinies, could have ever been
excusable, it would have been so in the life of Paul. What visible success had he
achieved?&mdash;the founding of a few churches, of which the majority were already cold to him.
</p><p>
He saw his efforts at Corinth, Ephesus, Thessalonica, and Galatia slowly undermined by
heretical teachers, a movement that eventually spread throughout all of early Christendom,
leading to complete apostasy.
</p><p>
But what had Paul personally gained? Wealth? He was absolutely dependent upon the chance
gifts of others. Personal power? At his time of greatest need there had not been one friend to
stand by his side. Love? He had learned by bitter experience how few there were who were
not ashamed, even to own him in his misery.
</p><p>
Now, after all that he had suffered, after all that he had done, what was his condition? He was
a lonely prisoner awaiting a malefactor's death. What was the sum total of earthly goods that
the long labor of his life had brought to him? An old cloak and some books.
</p><p>
And yet in what spirit did he write Timothy, his young convert, who was faltering in the
faith? Does he complain of his hardships? Does he regret his life? Does he dampen the
courage of his younger friend by telling him that almost every earthly hope is doomed to
failure, and that to struggle against human wickedness is a fruitless fight?
</p><p>
Not so! His last letter to Timothy is one of hope rather than despair. For himself the battle is
over; the race is run. The days' work in the Master's vineyard is well nigh over. When it is
quite finished and when he has entered the Master's presence, then and there&mdash;nowhere and
now&mdash;shall he receive the crown of righteousness and unspeakable reward
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/6-8#6">2 Tim. 4:6-8</a>). It is Timothy, not
Paul, who is in danger of yielding to languor and timidity, and forgetting that the Spirit of
God is not of fear but of power and of love and of a sound mind (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/6/20#20">1 Tim. 6:20</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/1/6-7#6">2 Tim. 1:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
3. <i>Overcome weaknesses</i>. One of the great principles of the gospel is found in the fact that
man by divine right is an agent unto himself and therefore dues only that which he wills (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/28#28">D&amp;C 58:28</a>).
</p><p>
Someone offered this suggestion: 
</p><p>
"Life by the yard is hard, but<br />
         By the inch, it's a cinch!"
</p><p>
The overcoming of the tobacco habit is much the same as overcoming any weakness that is
detrimental to health, happiness, and being of a spiritual mind.
</p><p>
Take, for instance, the case of a man I knew who had the habit of smoking to the extent that
he would set the alarm clock for definite intervals during the night and then sit in reverie on
the edge of his bed. Or take another man I knew who did the same thing without the aid of
an alarm clock, simply in response to the habitual urge to smoke. With such men the desire to
answer the challenge to quit requires something more than just the statement, "I have smoked
my last cigarette."
</p><p>
As one of them said to me: "If I could just quit for one hour, it would be an achievement.
Then I would say, 'now I'll go another hour.'" He learned a great lesson: anything you can
do for one hour, you can do for two, and as each hour passes, new strength comes&mdash;yes,
even new strength to meet the times of extreme pressure when things seem to go all to pieces.
</p><p>
From the apostle James we have this for those who overcome a weakness: "Blessed is the
man that endureth temptation; for when he is tried, he shall receive the crown of life, which
the Lord hath promised to them that love him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/12#12">James 1:12</a>).
</p><p>
5. <i>Love the truth</i>. In my own acquaintance, the most happy persons are those who love the
gospel and its truths of righteousness and who are making a real effort to live by the
standards of life it teaches.
</p><p>
To be truly happy, our thoughts and deeds must be on the side of good, not evil. When men
love darkness rather than light, their deeds are evil (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/19#19">John 3:19</a>).
</p><p>
I love the restored Church of Jesus Christ, because I know it helps me to be a better person. I
cannot say how good I am, but I know that without the gospel I would be
less good. Like all men, I have inherent weaknesses, and if yielded to, they could take me
down to sin and carnal-mindedness; but this will never happen so long as I magnify the
priesthood that I bear and stay close to the Church and its gospel influences. And so it is with
all men. To know and love the truth is to be free.
</p><p>
6. <i>Be humble</i>. One of the crowning goals of being spiritually minded is the human quality of
humility, especially if it is self-imposed. As Alma, a prophet of ancient America, once said, ".
. . blessed are they who humble themselves without being compelled to be humble . . ."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/32/16#16">Alma 32:16</a>).
Actually such humility is of the nature of meekness, concerning which the Master
said: "Blessed are the meek: for they shall inherit the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/5#5">Matt. 5:5</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith possessed this quality of humility, as evidenced from this account:
During the translation of the Book of Mormon, food was brought to Joseph Smith and Oliver
Cowdery by Joseph Knight, a farmer friend. They had no money, not even for paper needed
in the translation. The Prophet asked Joseph Knight if he would bring them some paper that
the translation could continue, which he did. His great interest in what was happening led him
to ask the Prophet to inquire of the Lord what he might do to further the work.
</p><p>
In response to this the Lord gave to the Prophet a revelation for Joseph Knight, which teaches
the great principle of humility: 
</p><p>
"Behold, I speak unto you, and also to all those who have desires to bring forth and establish
this work; 
</p><p>
"And no one can assist in this work except he shall be humble and full of love, having faith,
hope and charity, being temperate in all things whatsoever shall be entrusted to his care"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/12/7-8#7">D&amp;C 12:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
This account indicates the circumstances of humility under which the Book of Mormon was
brought forth. The Prophet and these men had nothing of the world's goods, yet they were
pursuing a cause that was to bring to the world a record of the ancient inhabitants of North
and South America, which without doubt is <i>a new witness of Christ</i>, and of the divine work
of God our Eternal and Heavenly Father in bringing to pass the immortality and eternal life of
man.
</p><p>
I bear testimony that the truth has been restored, that man may seek for and find in the
restoration the power that can lift him into the light of spiritual understanding and conviction.
This I do in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
