<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John H. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 83-86</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have a thought, brethren and sisters, that I would like to bring to you this afternoon. It came
to me when I was coming into the tabernacle grounds.
</p><p>
A HOUSE BUILT UPON A ROCK
</p><p>
There was a little lady rushing out through the gates going to her work. On her way she had
come into the temple grounds because to her it was home&mdash;home, because this is where she
found God, where she found a testimony of the gospel of Jesus Christ, where she was
baptized, where she went to the house of the Lord and obtained blessings in his holy house.
As I saw her going out, I said to myself, "This place is truly a home, because, like a home, it
brings us blessings and safety, strength, courage, and faith that endures."
</p><p>
You remember the parable of the house that was built upon the sand and the house that was
built upon the rock (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/24-27#24">Matt. 7:24-27</a>).
A house that is built upon the sand is always in peril. When the rains of
regret and disappointment fall upon the house, and the winds of discord and suspicion beat
upon it, the house falls, and great is the ruin thereof. Truly it is the ruin of happiness for the
father and mother and the children. Fortunately, in order that theirs will not be a total loss,
the house that is built upon the sand and is washed away, may be rebuilt again by the family.
This time, if they are wise, they will build upon the rock of faith and confidence and
cooperation, and the house will always be safe from the storm. When a house is built upon
the rock of love, of good will, of sacrifice, and of tolerance, and the rains of temptation and
misunderstanding fall upon it, and the winds of derision and mockery blow against it, it will
still stand because it is built upon a rock.
</p><p>
HIS FATHER'S LOVE FOR HIS HOME
</p><p>
I used to wonder why my father did not want to move away from his home. It was a large
house and most of the family had married and gone away. I wondered why he did not also go
away and find a smaller place. I found out later when I understood what life was about. A
long time before, he brought his wife to this house. In it his children had been born and some
of them had died. From it sons were sent out into the field to preach the gospel. One of them
was brought home by his mother and laid away on the hillside. He had planted the trees; he
had remodeled the house. Truly it was built with his love and with his confidence. It
represented a lot of sacrifice and doing without many comforts. That is why he wanted to stay
in the house that was built upon the rock of his life. And so it became a rock, to us who were
born in the house. We knew about the things that happened. We were grateful for the
blessings of a father and mother who taught us the gospel of Jesus Christ, who helped us to
travel along the right road and find success. That was our home; that is why we loved it; that
is where stability and goodness came to us.
</p><p>
PLACES OF WORSHIP BECOME HOMES
</p><p>
Nearby was another home which we loved and which was the meeting house, the old
Fourteenth Ward. I went there during all of my youth. There I found a testimony; there I
came to know something about the gospel of Jesus Christ; there I found the priesthood of
God. There I went to my first dance, and my mother was my partner: a mother so kind, a
mother so beautiful, that all the many years that came to her, her large family, all the
struggles, the trials and sorrows, yes, even the tears, could not wash away, nor wear away her
beauty. She had not only the physical characteristics of beauty, but was beautiful in all the
things that God gives to mothers to make them beautiful.
</p><p>
In this block is the tabernacle, another house that is built upon a rock, and one that I love,
because of what it did for me. As a little boy, mother brought me to hear the sermons, and
we sat here on the side and listened to the servants of God. When I became tired, I cuddled
up to her, and she put her arms around me and I went to sleep. This is a home. When I was
eight years of age I went over to the Endowment House to be baptized. Then I knew what it
was to receive baptism and forgiveness, and as I went out of the door and walked up by the
side of this building, I said to myself, "Well, John, you've been baptized and the Lord has
forgiven you your sins." I tried to think of all the sins I had committed, and there seemed to
be a lot and even then I couldn't find, it seemed to me, enough, and so I magnified what I
had that I might leave them with the Lord.
</p><p>
This is the place where I came to see a girl that I wanted to marry. She came here each
Sunday afternoon to meeting. When I went on my mission, and came back, she was still
sitting in the same place on the Sabbath day. A little later we went into the House of the Lord
and received his blessings. Truly the houses of life are a part of us, and to bring us happiness
or joy they have to be built upon a rock, otherwise the storms of life will wash away the sand
from beneath the house, and it will go down to ruin and destruction.
</p><p>
One day I went out into the great home called missionary life, and there I found a greater
testimony. The sweetness of living for others and doing for others increased my testimony so
that it became stronger and better than it had been before.
</p><p>
A MISSIONARY INCIDENT
</p><p>
One day I had been out in the country and as I was walking home, I came to a house where
some Saints lived. It seemed too late, but I saw a light and therefore decided that they must
be up. They were a poor family and had been out of work. When I opened the door and went
in, to my surprise I found that they were just eating their supper. The lady of the house said:
"Brother Taylor, have you had your supper?" and I said hesitatingly, "No, not tonight." She
said: "Come and sup with us." She drew up another stool to the table, and I sat down with the
husband and three or four little children. She got a plate and a spoon and I thought she was
going over to the stove to get a portion for me, but she went to her own plate and took a few
spoonfuls and put it onto my plate. Then she went to the father and to all the children doing
the same thing, and then brought it to me, a servant of the Lord.
</p><p>
I prayed in my heart that to this home should come the kindly spirit of the Christ, that he
would bless the food as he had the loaves and the fishes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/19#19">Matt. 14:19</a>), and that the little children should not
go from the table hungry. That house, so humble, was built upon the rock of kindness and
love of God. When the meal was over, we knelt down around the same little table in family
prayer, and as a servant of the Lord, I left my blessing and went away humbly with the desire
in my heart that God would surely bless that home.
</p><p>
THE MANSIONS ABOVE
</p><p>
Someday, brethren and sisters, we will all have another home to go to. We are building it as
we live our lives on the earth. I trust that we won't be disappointed in the place that we have
chosen for it. If it is to bring us the maximum of happiness and security, and be numbered
among the mansions of the Lord, we must build it on a foundation of faith, good works, and
obedience to the commandments of the Lord. May we be like unto the wise man who built
his house on the rock, and when the rains came and the winds blew, it fell not, because it was
founded upon a rock.
</p><p>
May our Heavenly Father bless us in our homes, whether they have to do with where we live,
or where we meet to worship him, or where we go to get his special blessings; and when we
go back to him, these final homes be pleasant places where God dwells and his spirit is
always with us, I humbly pray, in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
