<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"They Call for New Light"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 80-84</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Humbly I seek divine guidance.
</p><p>
The Savior said: "And this is life eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and
Jesus Christ whom thou hast sent" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3#3">John 17:3</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Revival of Religion</b>
</p><p>
The remarks of yesterday of President Mark E. Petersen and today of President Tanner and
others, calling our attention to conditions as they exist in the world, were very challenging.
</p><p>
Leaders in both scientific and religious fields are calling for new light. From a sermon which
was recently preached in England by an eminent professor of theology and published to the
world by Dean Inge, we read:
</p><p>
"How great is the need in Britain today for a man to arise among us to lead a mighty crusade
for the revival of our religion. For years all Christendom has prayed that that revival might be
near, and according as the need is great, so great is the opportunity. From end to end of the
land, north and south and west and east, the feeling is arising that something more is required
today than the advice, however good, of our statesmen, and the ability, however great, of our
businessmen, that there are problems to be solved more urgent and more fundamental than
those of economics and elections."
</p><p>
And then he adds: "<i>The organized churches offer no solution to these problems</i> . . . Men and
women look for an <i>interpreter of their emotions</i>, for someone who will give expression to
their spiritual convictions and beliefs, submerged too long in a materialistic age. The seed has
been sown. It has sprung up under showers and sunshine. The grain is swollen inside the
husk. Now the field lies golden and ready for the harvest. Where is the man who will go in
and reap?"
</p><p>
In the midst of national and international unrest, confusion, and stress, the questions of
theology have acquired a new importance and urgency. Throughout the Judaeo-Christian
world, in fact the entire world, there is a soul-stirring search for new meanings in religion
upon which men may ground their lives and establish their personal and
social values.
</p><p>
In recent months an intense theological debate has been waged around a
volume entitled <i>Honest to God</i>, in which Dr. Robinson, the Bishop of Woolwich of the
Anglican Church, asks the question whether it is possible for modern men to accept traditional
Christian faith, to believe in the established conception of God, and to accept Christ as their
Savior. He questions whether Christianity carries with it the trappings of an ancient world and
culture, and whether it can be made relevant to the thought and character of modern scientific
man, living in a rapidly shrinking technological world.
</p><p>
The bishop says, "Our image of God must go," and the <i>Church Times</i> comments: "It is not
every day that a bishop goes on public record as apparently denying almost every Christian
doctrine of the Church in which he holds office" (<i>The Honest to God Debate</i>, Philadelphia:
Westminster Press, 1963, p. 7).
</p><p>
Dr. Alasdair MacIntyre of the University College of Oxford says, "Dr. Robinson's book needs
not only to be understood as a symptom of our condition, but to be sympathized with as a
desperate attempt that cannot succeed," (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 227) and he adds, somewhat cynically, "The
creed of the English is there is no God and it is wise to pray to him from time to time."
(<i>Ibid.</i>, 228.) This book of which I speak is not just the voice of an individual, but it "testifies
to the existence of a whole group of theologies which have retained a theistic vocabulary but
acquired an atheistic substance" (<i>Ibid.</i>, 227) and one wonders whether they can continue to
co-exist.
</p><p>
The Archbishop of Canterbury says, ". . . if Dr. Robinson's argument is right the traditional
views of God are not outmoded, they are simply false" (<i>Ibid.</i>, 217).
</p><p>
<b>A New Birth in Our Time</b>
</p><p>
The argument that has ensued around these and other questions has engaged the leading minds
in both Europe and America recently, and they indicate a sense of loss, frustration, and failure
that are so much a part of modern life. The hope is expressed that there will be a new birth in
our time that will restore something of the meaning and value of human existence.
</p><p>
We have all felt the impact of war and economic depression, the dehumanizing influence of
industrialization, the overcrowding of our cities, the ever-present and ominous threat of
nuclear war with its total destruction, and the myriad social forces that complicate our lives
and affect our values. We share the conscience of a world in which mass murder has been
real and in which millions go to bed hungry every night in the presence of abundance.
</p><p>
<b>Absolute Confidence in the Gospel</b>
</p><p>
While we look forward hopefully to the help we may get from science and technology in our
attempts to solve our problems, we rely with absolute confidence upon the theology and
religion of the Church of Jesus Christ for the inspiration and faith to sustain us in this
endeavor, and to this end our spiritual strength is grounded firmly on the foundation of
revealed religion and the biblical conviction of the reality of the Living God.
</p><p>
Unlike those whose religious faith is uneasy and precarious in the modern world of expanding
scientific knowledge, we are at home with the most advanced truths discovered by scientists
and with all competent philosophic thought&mdash;with truth wherever found&mdash;because our
religion enjoins in us a love of knowledge and education, encourages us to seek understanding
through the broadening of our vision and the deepening of our insight. This is an eternal
quest.
</p><p>
<b>Newly Revealed Truth Accepted</b>
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints accepts newly revealed truth, whether
it comes through direct revelation or from study and research. We deny the common
conception of reality that distinguishes radically between the natural and the supernatural,
between the temporal and the eternal, between the sacred and the secular. For us, there is no
order of reality that is utterly different in character from the world of which
we are a part, that is separated from us by an impassable gulf. We do not separate our daily
mundane tasks and interests from the meaning and substance of religion. We recognize the
spiritual in all phases and aspects of living and realize that this life is an important part of
eternal life. We aspire to the best of which we are intrinsically capable and will think our
thoughts, fashion our ideals, and pursue every task firm in the faith that in a very real sense
we are living in the presence of God here and now.
</p><p>
We accept the testimony of the
sacred scriptures that the purposes of God are enacted in human history, that he is primarily
interested in man's condition and welfare though he will never trammel our free agency. His
work and his glory is, as the prophets have said, to bring to pass the immortality and eternal
life of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Positive Doctrine of Man</b>
</p><p>
Our doctrine of man is positive and life affirming. We declare unequivocally that by his very
nature every man has the freedom to do good as well as evil, that God has endowed him with
a free moral will and given him the power to discern good from evil, right from wrong, and to
choose the good and the right. We refuse to believe, with some churches of Christendom, that
the biblical account of the fall of man records the corruption of human nature or to accept the
doctrine of original sin. We do not believe that man is incapable of doing the will of God or
is unable to merit the rewards of Divine approval; that he is therefore totally estranged from
God and that whatever salvation comes to him must come as a free and undeserved gift. We
never tire of proclaiming the inspiring truth of the gospel that man is that he might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
For us the so-called fall of man placed the human spirit in a world of experience and
adventure where evils are real but can be overcome, where free moral decision is a constant
requirement, and where choices, freely made, determine the quality of life and the eventual
condition of the soul.
</p><p>
This does not mean that we are oblivious to the evils of the world, the sins of men, and the
immeasurable suffering that is daily endured by millions. Ours is not a superficial faith that
sees only the bright side of life and denies the fact of human tragedy. Our conscience is
wounded by the massive evils that men have perpetrated in our own time, by sins that are
unspeakable in the depth of their horror. But we have the positive faith that places the
responsibility of these sins squarely upon the individuals and societies who commit them.
</p><p>
<b>Man, A Child of God, Not Alone</b>
</p><p>
In our theology, God did not bring the world into being from nothing. He organized it from
existing materials. We accept the scriptural statement that God created man in his own image.
". . . in the image of God created he him; male and female created he them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>). He
is engaged in a constant struggle with the evils of the world, to overcome whatever brings
pain and suffering, frustration and failure, and he asks that we cooperate with him by
keeping his commandments, by obeying the laws upon which all blessings are predicated.
This is the meaning of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ, that man as a child of God is not
alone in the world, for God shares our suffering and delights in our joys. In this community
with him we can overcome the world, achieving the abundant life here, and immortality and
eternal life hereafter.
</p><p>
We shall overcome any seeming contradictions between science and religion if and as we
learn to adhere to the teachings of the restored Church which have always been dedicated to
the search for knowledge and intelligence, which is the glory of God.
</p><p>
<b>Christianity Relevant to the Modern World</b>
</p><p>
To the question raised by the Bishop of Woolwich, "Is Christianity relevant to the
modern world?" we find positive and affirmative answers in the unequivocal declarations of
the gospel of Jesus Christ. The gospel does not belong to an antiquated world that has passed
away but is a real and powerful force in our world here and now. It invests
our individual lives with meaning and purpose and will yet transform the course of human
history.
</p><p>
When we speak of the unity of the Godhead, we refer to the attributes, powers,
and purposes of its members. Jesus testified to the unity existing between himself and his
Father on many occasions as is recorded in the Holy Bible and other revealed documents. He
referred to this unity in his memorable prayer recorded in the seventeenth chapter of John,
where he prayed that he and his followers might be one even as he and his Father are one
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/11#11">John 17:11</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Evidence of Intelligence</b>
</p><p>
It will become clear to any unbiased reader of the scriptures that the Father is a personal
being, possessing a definite form with bodily parts and spiritual passions. The Son, who was
in the express image of the Father (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/1/3#3">Heb. 1:3</a>),
is a separate identity by whom the worlds were made and
without whom was not anything made that was made (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/3#3">John 1:3</a>). He was, in fact, a
revelation of God.
</p><p>
We see everywhere in nature evidence of cause and effect, of means adapted to an end, which
indicate a given purpose. This is evidence of intelligence, and intelligence is an attribute of
mind. We must therefore conclude that it was an intelligent mind that built the stupendous
universe of God.
</p><p>
<b>Convincing Knowledge of God</b>
</p><p>
Human reason may not of itself lead its possessor to convincing knowledge of God, yet if
properly exercised will confirm his inherited instinct toward his maker. Truly "the fool hath
said in his heart, There is no God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/14/1#1">Ps. 14:1</a>).
</p><p>
We know him to be a living being with every essential property and attribute of
personality&mdash;that he thinks wills, feels that he is a moral being who demands righteousness
and justice&mdash;but that in his love he is compassionate, merciful, and longsuffering.
</p><p>
For us God is not an abstraction, he is not just an idea, a metaphysical principle, an
impersonal force or power. He is not identical with the totality of the world, with the sum of
all reality. He is not an "absolute" that in some way embraces the whole of reality in his
being. Like us, he exists in a world of space and time. Like us, he has ends to be achieved,
and he fashions a cosmic plan for realizing them. He is a concrete, living person, and though
in our finite state we cannot fully comprehend him, we know that we are akin to him, for he
is revealed to us in the divine personality of his Son Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
There has been a marked change in the teachings of many of the churches concerning God,
and many thinking men and scholars now believe him to be a personal being and not an
abstract essence. This is shown in the book <i>A Century's Change in Religion</i>, wherein the
author, after telling the beliefs of the churches in America at the beginning of the nineteenth
century, says, "It is within the last fifty years that this mighty change or extension of belief
has come about. The new thought is the kingdom of God on earth in the Christian society.
The church is now dominated by this idea. The gospel of the kingdom on earth is the latest,
the newest, the oldest, and the truest gospel."
</p><p>
He further adds, "There has been a change in our thought of God from the conception of
sovereignty to this conception of Fatherhood. The center of doctrine has shifted from
sovereignty to Fatherhood.
</p><p>
"God is a person; He is intelligence, and that is purpose, plan, He is will, and that is realizing
purpose; He is love, that is, He is person related to person. Whatever more than personality,
as we know it, He may be, He is that in perfect degree which our best is in imperfect degree."
(Harris, George, <i>A Century's Change in Religion</i>, Boston, Houghton-Mifflin, 1914, p. 251.)
</p><p>
<b>He Is Real and Personal</b>
</p><p>
For ourselves, we reaffirm our conviction that God is real and personal, that Jesus the Christ
is his Only Begotten Son. We rejoice to proclaim to the world that he is omnipotent,
omniscient, and omnipresent. Our answer, then, to the Bishop of Woolwich is that God is real
and personal, and we are not concerned as he seems to be as to whether he
is "up there" or "out there" or whether this is a three-storied universe. We know that he lives,
that he can and does appear to men. In fact, the whole structure of Mormonism is based on
revelation. The Father and the Son were revealed to a young man in the state of New York in
1820, and since that time many glorious revelations have come to reassure us in our faith that
he lives. He declared it to be his work and his glory to bring to pass the immortality and
eternal life of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
This is our answer, then, to the question whether it is possible for modern
men to accept the true Christian faith. It was established by Jesus Christ in the Meridian of
Time and restored by him in the Fullness of Times. Hence, we do not share the fear,
uncertainty, and confusion mentioned by Dean Inge or the Bishop of Woolwich. We call
attention to the biblical image of God in which he is identified as personal, eternal,
unchangeable, and everlasting, to which we humbly bear witness in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
