<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1943, p. 125</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I think it was Carlyle who said:
</p><p>
In this world there is one Godlike thing, the essence of all that ever was or ever will be of
Godlike in this world&mdash;the veneration done to human worth by the hearts of men.
</p><p>
TRIBUTES TO RUDGER CLAWSON AND SYLVESTER Q. CANNON
</p><p>
That came to my mind this noon when our beloved President suggested that something should
be said in this conference by way of appreciation and tribute to two members of the General
Authorities who, since our last Conference, have passed to the other side&mdash;President Rudger
Clawson and Elder Sylvester Q. Cannon.
</p><p>
President Grant is one of the most thoughtful men in the world, one of the most kind-hearted.
Many people do not know that. This request is typical of him; his mind was on an
appreciation of services rendered by these two men who associated with him so many years,
particularly Brother Clawson, who came into the Council somewhere near the time or soon
after President Grant was called.
</p><p>
President Clawson was a heroic defender of truth. He faced death, as you know, on one
occasion, folded his arms and said, "Shoot." His life, however, was preserved. His companion
sacrificed his life, was martyred for the truth. President Clawson's heroism on other occasions
is a good example for us, when we face temptation. Rather than yield the truth or honor, let
us sacrifice any convenience, and if necessary life itself.
</p><p>
President Clawson's life was integrated with the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
He has passed to a great reward.
</p><p>
Elder Sylvester Q. Cannon was Presiding Bishop of this Church for many years. Hours
counted nothing; it was just service, early morning until late at night. The gospel was all in
all to him. In fact, he, I believe, shortened his life through over-exertion. We pay tribute to
his memory, and pray God to bless his loved ones, and give them the assurance that Brother
Cannon, too, received the welcome plaudit: "Well done, thou good and faithful servant, enter
into the joy of thy Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/21#21">Matt. 25:21</a>).
</p>
</div>
</div>
