<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Measure of What Is Good</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1964, pp. 126-129</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay and my beloved brethren and sisters:
</p><p>
From the time of President McKay's opening address until this moment, we have been
strengthened and refreshed in spirit. We have heard our President's appeal against pernicious,
enslaving habits and for preserving the integrity of the home and maintaining moral standards.
Last night late, I reread the President's opening address, which I feel was one of his finest.
These sentences I have taken from his text:
</p><p>
". . . that our homes are kept unpolluted and unbroken by infidelity; that children therein will
be trained to keep the commandments of the Lord, to be honest, true, chaste, benevolent, and
virtuous, and to do good to all men."
</p><p>
". . . the Word of Wisdom . . . goes deeper than the ill effects upon the body and strikes at
the very root of character . . ."
</p><p>
"No other success can compensate for failure in the home."
</p><p>
"The most vicious enemy to home life is immorality.
</p><p>
"The word of the Lord to his Church is: 'Keep yourself unspotted from the sins of the world!'"
(<a href="http://scriptures.byu.edu/getscrip.php?ID=26176#27">James 1:27 (JST)</a>).
</p><p>
We have heard Brother Lee's appeal not to be "almost" only but altogether
what we ought to be.
</p><p>
And we have heard Brother Hunter's most interesting analysis of the obligation and privilege
of tithing. I recall in this connection a quotation from President Moyle, given in the Manti
Temple not many months before he left us, in which he was quoting as I recall partly himself
and partly President McKay. He said, "Tithing is as much a law as is baptism itself. We are
no more compelled to keep the one than the other." And then quoting President McKay: "We
have been praying for this day for a hundred years, and if we have the faith to meet the needs
of the growth of the Church, the Lord will provide a way for us to do so. The Lord sets the
times and seasons of this great growth."
</p><p>
Each of the brethren who has spoken, in his own way and in his own time, has added to our
reminder of the fundamental position of the Church and its mission among men and has
reminded us of our obligations and opportunities.
</p><p>
We have been reminded of the principles that will solve mankind's problems and that will
lead us to everlasting life.
</p><p>
<b>Repentance&mdash;the Principle of Progress</b>
</p><p>
Now, why all this effort and exhortation? Because time moves swiftly and is short, and
because people are of everlasting importance, and because there never comes a time when we
do not need to be taught! There never comes a time when we do not need to know that
repentance is the great principle of progress and that there is room for all of us to improve.
</p><p>
And since these things are so, what a person believes becomes exceedingly important, because
what he believes determines how he lives. A person will prepare much differently for a short
journey than he will for a long one, and he will prepare much differently for an everlasting
journey than he will for one that ends after a short season.
</p><p>
Now since eternity is forever, and since life is going to be lived one way or another
everlastingly, and since what we do here has its effect on our eternal opportunities, we ought
frequently to do some self-searching&mdash;auld that is what we have been doing these past three
days.
</p><p>
One of life's greatest lessons is to learn that there are causes and consequences. God has
given us our free agency and will not violate it, but everything we do has its effect on our
everlasting life. As Samuel Johnson said it: "The future is bought with the present."
</p><p>
President McKay and several others have mentioned the surgeon general's report on tobacco
and its adverse effects on human health and length of life. We may now expect to see much
maneuvering to set aside the effects of these findings.
</p><p>
When the evil of an unrestrained indulgence is under attack, there will be a plea for
moderation, for half steps, as if to say that a little of something that isn't right is all right. It
comes down in another sense to this "almost" that Brother Lee spoke of. To quote some
words from Nephi: "And there shall also be many which shall say: . . . there is no harm in
this" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/8#8">2 Ne. 28:8</a>).
This is in error. If it isn't good&mdash;let it alone. If it isn't right&mdash;avoid
it, not "almost," but altogether.
</p><p>
It has been over 130 years since the answer was given on this subject and on many other
subjects. Why do we so long wander in the wilderness?
</p><p>
Now there are those who would ask what all this has to do with religion. In the Church and
kingdom of God, the practical and the physical are intermingled with the spiritual. We <i>are</i> a
practical Church. Life is a practical matter. So is eternal life. There are laws and
commandments and physical facts that pertain to peace and progress and health and happiness,
and I cannot conceive of a Loving Father's not being interested in everything that pertains to
his children&mdash;what they do, what they eat, what they think, what they learn, how they live,
their health, their happiness, their character, their conduct. Conscientious fathers are interested
in all these things, or should be, and so is our Father in heaven. This is part of the gospel. It
is part of life. It is part of religion&mdash;to give us peace and health and
happiness and to qualify us for the highest opportunities of everlasting life.
</p><p>
<b>To Enlarge Life</b>
</p><p>
In all of life, as Phillips Brooks put it, there are the "fulfillers" and the "destroyers"&mdash;those
who build up and those who pull down, and the measure of what is good for man is what it
does for him. What isn't good isn't good. What is good is good. And why should we vacillate
between the two?
</p><p>
I heard President Brown ask this question not long ago. I can't recall the occasion, but I
remember the words. I hope he will pardon me for using them from him. "Do you want to
repent or rationalize? Repenting means pulling yourself up to a set of standards, and
rationalizing means letting your conduct down to your appetites and to a less worthy
inclination."
</p><p>
We ought to turn our attention to those things that enlarge and fulfil life and not those things
which enslave and destroy.
</p><p>
"Man's success or failure, happiness or misery," President McKay has said, "depend upon what
he seeks and what he chooses."
</p><p>
Last June in St. Louis at a Rotary International Convention, Willy Brandt, Mayor of Berlin,
came to speak there at our invitation, and in a significant and challenging talk made this
among other observations: "Nobody, no system, no ideology can prevail over the future unless
the central interest is humanity. The world is not to be won by disregarding people."
</p><p>
What he was saying, in his own way, was, in speaking of communism as he was, that unless
it changes to serve the highest possibilities of mankind, it cannot survive, and if it changes to
do this, it would not be communism.
</p><p>
What this says to me is that, here and hereafter, what is good for man is the measure of what
is good and the ultimate in our Father's plans and purposes, and we must have the wisdom,
the strength, the discernment to shape our lives toward this end and to choose between what is
and isn't good.
</p><p>
<b>"Another angel . . ."</b>
</p><p>
At our World&rsquo;s Fair site in New York a few days ago, with Brothers Lee and Stapley and
Brockbank and others, we saw raised atop the center tower of the temple a beautiful
gold-leafed replica of the Angel Moroni. Earnestly we asked for a variance of the World&rsquo;s
Fair building code so that our temple spires could reach to a height that would be symbolic
and significant and would appear in proportion&mdash;and as we saw the angel put in place and
contemplated our exhibit with all its planning (the product of many minds and many men, to
whom should be paid personal tribute, and they will receive their everlasting credit where it
counts, even if they worked somewhat behind the scenes), we could not help recall these
words from the book of Revelation, already more than once quoted at this conference:
</p><p>
"And I saw another angel fly in the midst of heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach
unto them that dwell on the earth, and to every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people,
</p><p>
"Saving with a loud voice, Fear God, and give glory to him; for the hour of his judgment is
come: and worship him that made heaven, and earth, and the sea, and the fountains of
waters" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6-7#6">Rev. 14:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
To the literal fulfillment of this event, we bear witness, and we have an obligation to live
according to the witness that we bear.
</p><p>
<b>Joseph Smith Told the Truth</b>
</p><p>
Some days ago I was searching in an autobiography of Dr. John A. Widtsoe, one of my
beloved mission presidents many years ago&mdash;scientist, scholar, educator, and Apostle. And in
this book called <i>In a Sunlit Land</i>, published shortly before his death, he reviews his
beginnings in a far country, on a rocky island off the North Sea coast of Norway; his birth
into another church; the coming of the missionaries; the conversion of his mother and later his
own conversion; his going to Harvard as an immigrant lad; his going later to Germany to
acquire his doctor's degree in chemistry; his study of the sciences and of the religions and
philosophies of men; his serving as president of two universities. And then
on about the last page of that book he says:
</p><p>
"During this long life, I have had occasion to test, time and time again, the verity of the
foundations of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The answer has always been
the same: Joseph Smith told the truth." (Salt Lake City: Deseret News Press, 1952, pp.
243-244.)
</p><p>
Joseph Smith did tell the truth. This is the witness that I would leave with you, my beloved
brothers and sisters, my beloved family and friends, along with the witness that Jesus is the
Christ and that God our Father did make us in his own image and that it is his purpose to
bring to pass our immortality and eternal life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>), and this I do in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
