<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Law of the Fast</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Robert L. Simpson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Robert L. Simpson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 16-19</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my dear brethren and sisters of this great Church: May I spend a moment
and discuss with you one of the most neglected of all our Heavenly Father's laws and
commandments to his children.
</p><p>
May I begin this important assignment by bearing my testimony that all of Heavenly Father's
commandments are perfect; each law when lived brings happiness to the individual.
</p><p>
<b>The law of the fast</b>
</p><p>
One of the most neglected and yet most needed laws for this troubled
generation in a modern world of acceleration and distraction is the law of the fast. Fasting and
praying have been referred to almost as a singular function from the earliest times. Adam's
generation fasted and prayed, as did Moses on Sinai (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/9/9-11#9">Deut. 9:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Elijah
traveled to Mt. Horeb under the influence of fasting and prayer. There he received the word
of the Lord. His preparation had not been in vain (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/19/8#8">1 Kgs. 19:8</a>).
</p><p>
Mordecai's advice from
Esther as he faced an emergency at Shushan pointed out that he and his people should
"neither eat nor drink three days, night or day" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/esth/4/16#16">Esth. 4:16</a>). This was the true fast,
abstinence from both food and drink. This is still the manner of the true fast in our day.
</p><p>
There were significant changes made at the time of Christ's mission in mortality. The law of
sacrifice, for example, was replaced by a higher law. We are told that following the Master's
visit to this, the western hemisphere, the people were told to continue in "fasting and prayer
[there was no change in this law] and in meeting together oft both to pray and to hear the
word of the Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/12#12">4 Ne. 1:12</a>). So complete and sincere were the people in obeying his
commandments "that there was no contention among all the people, in all the land; but there
were mighty miracles wrought among the disciples of Jesus" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/13#13">4 Ne. 1:13</a>). Wouldn't it be
thrilling to enjoy such a condition today!
</p><p>
<b>Prayer and fasting today</b>
</p><p>
His law has been reconfirmed in our day, for through a modern prophet in the year 1839, he
said: ". . . I give unto you a commandment that ye shall continue in prayer and fasting from
this time forth." Then in the very next verse he mentions gospel teaching almost as a prime
product of the prayer and fasting process. In the words of the Lord: "And I give unto you a
commandment that you shall teach one another the doctrine of the kingdom.
</p><p>
"Teach ye diligently and my grace shall attend you, that you may be instructed more perfectly
in theory, in principle, in doctrine, in the law of the gospel, in all things that pertain unto the
kingdom of God, that are expedient for you to understand" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/76-78#76">D&amp;C 88:76-78</a>).
</p><p>
No man or woman can hope to teach of things spiritual unless he is directed by that spirit, for
"the Spirit shall be given unto you by the prayer of faith; and if ye receive not the Spirit ye
shall not teach.
</p><p>
"And all this ye shall observe to do as I have commanded concerning your teaching, until the
fulness of my scriptures is given.
</p><p>
"And as ye shall lift up your voices by the Comforter, ye shall speak and prophesy as seemeth
me good; 
</p><p>
"For, behold, the Comforter knoweth all things, and beareth record of the Father and of the
Son" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/14-17#14">D&amp;C 42:14-17</a>).
</p><p>
<b>A promise for every teacher</b>
</p><p>
Oh, that every teacher might catch the spirit of this promise and claim this offered
partnership, available to all who are engaged in the teaching of truth.
</p><p>
There are no better examples of teaching by the Spirit than the Sons of Mosiah. The Book of
Mormon tells us how they became "strong in the knowledge of the truth; for they were men
of a sound understanding and they had searched the scriptures diligently, that they might
know the word of God.
</p><p>
"But this is not all; they had given themselves to much prayer, and fasting; therefore they had
the spirit of prophecy, and the spirit of revelation, and when they taught, they taught with
power and authority of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/17/2-3#2">Alma 17:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
Is there a priesthood or auxiliary leader any place in this Church who wouldn't give all to
possess such power, such assurance? Remember this, above all else, that, according to Alma,
they gave themselves to much fasting and prayer. You see, there are certain blessings that can
only be fulfilled as we conform to a particular law. The Lord made this very clear through the
Prophet Joseph Smith when he declared: "For all who will have a blessing at
my hands shall abide the law which was appointed for that blessing, and the conditions
thereof, as were instituted from before the foundation of the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/5#5">D&amp;C 132:5</a>).
</p><p>
Now, the Lord could not have stated the position more clearly, and, in my opinion, too many
Latter-day Saint parents today are depriving themselves and their children of one of the
sweetest spiritual experiences that the Father has made available to them.
</p><p>
<b>The monthly Fast Day</b>
</p><p>
In addition to the occasional fasting experience for a special purpose, each member of the
Church is expected to miss two meals on the fast and testimony Sunday. To skip two
consecutive meals and partake of the third normally constitutes approximately a 24-hour
period. Such is the counsel.
</p><p>
Competent medical authorities tell us that our bodies benefit by an occasional fasting period.
That is blessing number one and perhaps the least important. Second, we contribute the
money saved from missing the meals as a fast offering to the bishop for the poor and the
needy. And third, we reap a particular spiritual benefit that can come to us in no other way. It
is a sanctification of the soul for us today just as it was for some choice people who lived
2,000 years ago. I quote briefly from the Book of Mormon: "Nevertheless they did fast and
pray oft, and did wax stronger and stronger in their humility, and firmer and firmer in the
faith of Christ, unto the filling their souls with joy and consolation, yea, even to the purifying
and the sanctification of their hearts, which sanctification cometh because of their yielding
their hearts unto God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/35#35">Hel. 3:35</a>). Wouldn't you like this to happen to you?  It can, you know!
</p><p>
Did you notice it said that those who do this have their souls filled with "joy and
consolation"?  You see, the world in general thinks that fasting is a time for "sackcloth and
ashes," a time to carry a look of sorrow, as one to be pitied. On the contrary, the Lord
admonishes: "Moreover when ye fast, be not, as the hypocrites, of a sad countenance: for they
disfigure their faces, that they may appear unto men to fast. Verily I say unto you, They have
their reward.
</p><p>
"But thou, when thou fastest, anoint thine head, and wash thy face; 
</p><p>
"That thou appear not unto men to fast, but unto thy Father which is in secret: and thy Father,
which seeth in secret, shall reward thee openly" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/16-18#16">Matt. 6:16-18</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Blessings of fasting</b>
</p><p>
Now, may we turn to the most important part of this great law. So far we have only discussed
those areas that bless us. The real joy comes with the blessing of the poor and the needy. For
it is in the fulfillment of this wonderful Christlike act that we practice "pure religion and
undefiled" spoken of by James (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>). Can you think of a better or more perfect Christian function
than "pure religion and undefiled"? I can't.
</p><p>
The Lord speaking through Moses observed: "If there be among you a poor man of one of thy
brethren within any of thy gates in thy land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, thou shalt
not harden thine heart, nor shut thine hand from thy poor brother: But thou shalt open thine
hand wide unto him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/15/7-8#7">Deut. 15:7-8</a>). Then he goes on to promise him who gives: ". . .
the Lord thy God shall bless thee in all thy works, and in all that thou puttest thine hand
unto" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/15/10#10">Deut. 15:10</a>). He concludes: "therefore I command thee, saying, Thou shalt open thine
hand wide unto thy brother, to thy poor, and to thy needy, in thy land" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/15/11#11">Deut. 15:11</a>).
</p><p>
Amulek had something to say on this subject. Alter instructing the people for some time on
various vital matters, he turned his thoughts to the poor and the needy, advising the
congregation that even if they are diligent in all of these other things, and "turn away the
needy, and the naked, and visit not the sick and afflicted, and impart of your
substance . . . to those who stand in need&mdash;I say unto you, if ye do not any of these things,
behold, your prayer is vain, and availeth you nothing, and ye are as hypocrites who do deny
the faith" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/28#28">Alma 34:28</a>).
</p><p>
<b>A perfecting law</b>
</p><p>
Yes, the law of the fast is a perfect law, and we cannot begin to approach perfection until we
decide to make it a part of our lives. When you start and stop the fast is up to you, but
wouldn't it be nice to culminate it and be at your spiritual peak for the fast and testimony
meeting?
</p><p>
How much you give the bishop as a donation is also up to you, but isn't it thrilling to know
that your accounting with the Lord has been paid willingly and with accuracy?
</p><p>
<b>Satisfaction comes with obedience</b>
</p><p>
Why you fast is also up to you. But suppose the main reason was simply that you wanted to
help someone in need and to be a part of "pure religion undefiled" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>). Wouldn't your faith be
lifted and sanctified?  Of course it would. And incidentally, have you ever noticed how
satisfying it is way deep inside each time you are obedient to Heavenly Father's desires? 
There can be no equal to the peace of mind that always comes as the reward for obedience to
truth.
</p><p>
The world needs self-discipline. You can find it in fasting and prayer. Our generation is sick
for lack of self-control. Fasting and prayer help to instill this virtue.
</p><p>
The world's future depends upon an urgent return to family unity. Fasting and prayer will
help to guarantee it. Each person has greater need for divine guidance. There is no better way.
We all have need to overcome the powers of the adversary. His influence is incompatible with
fasting and prayer.
</p><p>
<b>Joy in helping others</b>
</p><p>
There can be no greater joy than in helping others, for "inasmuch as ye have done it unto one
of the least of these my, brethren, ye have done it unto me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/40#40">Matt. 25:40</a>).
</p><p>
And now, my dear brothers and sisters, although not as worthy perhaps, but equally
enthusiastic in the cause we represent, I join my testimony with Alma of old when he
declared: Behold, I testify unto you that I do know that these things whereof I have spoken
are true. And how do ye suppose that I know of their surety?
</p><p>
"Behold, I say unto you they are made known unto me by the Holy Spirit of God. Behold, I
have fasted and prayed many days that I might know these things of myself. And now I do
know of myself that they are true; for the Lord God hath made them manifest unto me by his
Holy Spirit" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/45-46#45">Alma 5:45-46</a>). In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
