<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Greatest Weight</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop John H. Vandenberg</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Vandenberg, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 63-65</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters: I feel a great honor and responsibility was given me a year ago
when I was called to be the Presiding Bishop. I pray humbly that my inadequacies will not be
a hindrance to the fulfillment of this calling. I muster some courage as I think of the words of
Francis Bacon when he said, "God hangs the greatest weights upon the smallest wires."
</p><p>
I realize that many others have had greater weights placed upon them. In particular, I am
thinking of Joseph Smith who, as a boy, ventured into the unknown, searching for an answer
to a query that came to him pertaining to some religious matters. In his innocence, he could
not have known what lay before him as he sought his answer. He said, "While I was laboring
under the extreme difficulties caused by the contests of these parties of religionists, I was one
day reading the Epistle of James, first chapter and fifth verse, which reads: <i>If any of you lack</i>
<i>wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not, and it shall</i>
<i>be given him</i>" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/11#11">JS&mdash;H 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
"So, in accordance with this, my determination to ask of God, I retired to the woods to make
the attempt . . . It was the first time in my life that I had made such an attempt, for amidst all
my anxieties I had never as yet made the attempt to pray vocally.
</p><p>
". . . having looked around me, and finding myself alone, I kneeled down and began to offer
up the desire of my heart to God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/14-15#14">JS&mdash;H 1:14-15</a>).
</p><p>
This simple action of the faith of a youth unfolded great truths to young Joseph. It was a
reality that Satan stood by as a power of darkness and tried to overpower and destroy Joseph
Smith, and he might have succeeded had it not been that God heard Joseph's supplication and
appeared in the power of his light to dispel the evil.
</p><p>
Joseph said, ". . . I saw a pillar of light exactly over my head, above the brightness of the
sun, . . .
</p><p>
"It no sooner appeared than I found myself delivered from the enemy . . . When the light
rested upon me I saw two Personages, whose brightness and glory defy all description,
standing above me in the air. One of them spake unto me, calling me by name and said,
pointing to the other&mdash;<i>This is My Beloved Son. Hear Him!</i>"
</p><p>
And in answer to the question, "Which should I join?" came the reply, ". . . join none of
them, for they were all wrong . . . 'they draw near to me with their lips, but their hearts are
far from me, they teach for doctrines the commandments of men, having a form of godliness,
but they deny the power thereof'"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/16-17,19#16">JS&mdash;H 1:16-17,19</a>).
And Jesus instructed Joseph that further direction would come to him.
</p><p>
This is the testimony of a young lad on whom God placed the "very great weight" of the
restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ. To the noble way in which he carried it throughout
his life, we give him thanks honor, praise, and admiration. Though he was subjected to
ridicule and punishment, his testimony remained steadfast with the
statement, ". . . For I had seen a vision; I knew it, and I knew that God knew it, and I could not
deny it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/25#25">JS&mdash;H 1:25</a>).
</p><p>
Arthur E. Jensen makes this significant statement, "The only way an institution . . . can grow
old is to stay young forever . . . Its officers must have ears trained to catch the signals."
</p><p>
That The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is growing old, while staying young,
cannot be denied. Its officers and leaders "have ears trained to catch the signals" of inspiration
as God reveals them.
</p><p>
George W. Cornell writes "Such were the humble, ridiculed beginnings, 135 years ago, of a
movement that today has become one of the most prosperous, diversified and fast expanding
religious forces in the world . . . that it should have reached its present stature from its most
unpromising origin is a modern paradox."
</p><p>
Some may wonder why?
</p><p>
The answer comes that this is not a work of man&mdash;it is the eternal work of God,
re-established in proper order and authority in this last Dispensation of the Fulness of Times.
</p><p>
In the Book of Mormon, the ancient religious record of the inhabitants of North and South
America, translated by the gift and power of God through Joseph Smith, is an explanation to
the key of the vigor of this Church: 
</p><p>
"For behold, God knowing all things, being from everlasting to everlasting . . . sent angels to
minister unto the children of men . . .
</p><p>
"And God also declared unto prophets, by his own mouth . . .
</p><p>
"And behold, there were divers ways that he did manifest things unto the children of men,
which were good; and all things which are good cometh of Christ; otherwise men were fallen,
and there could no good thing come unto them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/22-24#22">Moro. 7:22-24</a>).
</p><p>
It further states: ". . . neither have angels ceased to minister unto the children of men . . .
</p><p>
"And the office of their ministry is to call men unto repentance, and to fulfil and to do the
work of the covenants of the Father, which he hath made unto the children of men . . . by
declaring the word of Christ unto the chosen vessels of the Lord . . .
</p><p>
"And by so doing . . . prepareth the way that the residue of men may have faith in Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/29,31-32#29">Moro. 7:29,31-32</a>).
</p><p>
Hereby God keeps his Church eternally young with vigor and power. He sends his ministering
angels; he reveals his will to his prophets; and by divers means manifests truths to the
children of men.
</p><p>
In the summer of 1828, the Lord revealed to the Prophet, ". . . Satan doth stir up the hearts of
the people to contention concerning the points of my doctrine; and in these things they do err,
for they do wrest the scriptures and do not understand them.
</p><p>
"Therefore, I will unfold unto them this great mystery
</p><p>
"For, behold, I will gather them as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, if they will
not harden their hearts
</p><p>
"Yea, if they will come, they may, and partake of the waters of life freely.
</p><p>
"Behold, this is my doctrine&mdash;whosoever repenteth and cometh unto me, the same is my
church" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/63-67#63">D&amp;C 10:63-67</a>).
</p><p>
John the Baptist commissioned by the Savior, as a resurrected being and an angel of God, in
May of 1829, ministered unto two of God's chosen vessels, Joseph Smith and Oliver
Cowdery, and conferred upon them, ". . . the Priesthood of Aaron, which holds the keys of
the ministering of angels, and of the gospel of repentance, and of baptism by immersion for
the remission of sins" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/13/1#1">D&amp;C 13:1</a>).
</p><p>
Here was the restoration of the authority to put into effect again the redeeming principles of
the gospel.
</p><p>
He again confirmed the validity of the forgiveness of wrongdoing. ". . . go, and sin no more,"
was his decree (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/11#11">John 8:11</a>).
This we must understand.
</p><p>
John Locke, the English philosopher, expresses it this way, "Repentance is a hearty sorrow for
our past misdeeds, and a sincere resolution and endeavor, to the utmost of our power, to
conform all our actions to the law of God. It does not consist in one single act of sorrow, but
in doing works meet for repentance in a sincere obedience to the law of Christ for the
remainder of our lives."
</p><p>
The ability to receive the blessings of repentance lies within our individual
power. It is a never-ending endeavor. There is no restriction to those who may achieve: All
may partake of this gift from God.
</p><p>
The promise of Ezekiel is again made alive, "But if the wicked will turn from all his sins that
he hath committed, and keep all my statutes, and do that which is lawful and right, he shall
surely live, he shall not die" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/18/21#21">Ezek. 18:21</a>).
</p><p>
The avenue of repentance is a thoroughfare which all may tread. It is the path to peace.
</p><p>
William Jennings Bryan gave us these words, "I am glad that our Heavenly Father did not
make the peace of the human heart to depend upon our ability to buy it with money, secure it
in society or win it at the polls, for in either case but few could have obtained it, but when
He made peace the reward of a conscience void of offense toward God and man, He put it
within the reach of all. The poor can secure it as easily as the rich, the social outcasts as
freely as the leaders of society, and the humblest citizen equally with those who wield
political power" (From <i>The Prince of Peace</i>).
</p><p>
May we give thanks to God for the great gift of the gospel of repentance, for its author, his
Son Jesus Christ, for the boy Prophet who had the courage to carry the great weight placed
upon him. For all those who succeeded him and to those who are laboring in building the
kingdom of God on earth, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
