<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1950, pp. 162-168</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
When we realize that the twelve thousand or more members of the priesthood quorums
assembled here tonight can say, each one in his own heart, "I know that my Redeemer lives,"
we can sense at least dimly the strength of this Church, for upon the priesthood rests the
structure, the entire structure of the Church of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
EVIDENCES OF PROGRESS
</p><p>
We have cause to be thankful that we have many evidences today of the marvelous growth of
this work. In the mission fields we have more missionaries than we have ever had before,
nearly six thousand, not counting the missionaries in the stakes of Zion; tithing is greater than
ever and increasing; baptisms in the field are greater; only within the last two weeks we had
reports of a hundred and fifty baptisms in one mission in August; another, in the same month,
two hundred and sixty-three, and these are converts, not children. The stakes and wards are
increasing. More Church edifices are now under construction than we have ever had before in
the history of the Church. All these are sure evidences of progress; and this attendance tonight
is another&mdash;one of the most encouraging. As President Smith has said, you are not here out of
curiosity. You are not here because of any special attraction. You are here because you
respect your calling. You honor your priesthood because of the sense of the responsibility that
you carry. Each of you who holds the priesthood carries a certain amount of responsibility for
the success of God's work. That realization that willingness to respond to duty, has brought
together tonight on this September 30, 1950, the largest assembly of priesthood, I believe,
ever held in the Church at a priesthood meeting.
</p><p>
The assembly of itself is an inspiration, especially when you contemplate its significance, and
realize that in the brotherhood of Christ we are all one, supporting one another. It is sublime.
</p><p>
I pray for your sympathy, for your faith and prayers, and above all, for the inspiration of the
Lord, that what I may say may be of worth, of interest, and contributive to the advancement
of God's work.
</p><p>
NEED OF REVERENCE
</p><p>
I have, really, on my mind but one message. I am going to say one appeal for this vast
audience of leaders. I believe there is one great need in the Church which you presidencies of
stakes, bishoprics of wards, presidencies of quorums, and officers in auxiliaries, can supply. I
have in mind the need of more reverence in our houses of worship, better order and discipline
in our classrooms, in quorum meetings and in auxiliary groups.
</p><p>
The more we try to cultivate the attributes of the Savior, the stronger we become in character
and in spirituality, and those are the two great purposes of life, so to live that we may be
susceptible to the inspiration of the Holy Ghost and to his guidance.
</p><p>
OVERCOME EVIL TENDENCIES
</p><p>
I do not know who it was who wrote many years ago that the whole purpose of life might be
summed up in these words: "To subdue matter that we might realize the ideal."
</p><p>
When I first read that I thought I could paraphrase it and say, "The whole purpose of life is to
bring under subjection the animal passions, proclivities and tendencies, that we might realize
the companionship, always, of God's Holy Spirit." I think that is the ideal. One chief purpose
of life is to overcome evil tendencies, to govern our appetites, to control our passions&mdash;anger,
hatred, jealousy, immorality. We have to overcome them: we have to subject them, conquer
them, because God has said: "My spirit will not dwell in unclean tabernacles, nor will it
always strive with man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/6/3#3">Gen. 6:3</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/37#37">Mosiah 2:37</a>).
</p><p>
A DIVINE ATTRIBUTE
</p><p>
The principle of self-control lies at the basis of reverence and good order in classrooms. I do
not know how to define reverence but I do know how to classify or to place it as one of the
objectives of nobility, indeed, one of the attributes of deity.
</p><p>
Love is the divinest attribute of the human soul. I am not so sure but sympathy is next to
it&mdash;sympathy for the afflicted, for suffering animals, for our brethren and sisters. That is a
God-like virtue.
</p><p>
Kindness is also a sublime virtue. The first sentence in what is now known as the Psalm of
Love is this: "Love suffereth long and is kind"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/4#4">1 Cor. 13:4</a>).
</p><p>
However, in my thought tonight, I am prompted to place reverence next to Love. Jesus
mentioned it first in the Lord's prayer: "Our Father which art in heaven, hallowed be thy
name . . ." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/9#9">Matt. 6:9</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/11/2#2">Luke 11:2</a>). Hallow&mdash;to make holy&mdash;to hold in reverence.
</p><p>
When Jesus cleansed the temple, he was filled with reverent indignation because men were
desecrating his Father's house, selling doves and lambs to be offered as sacrifice
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/21/12#12">Matt. 21:12</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/2/13-17#13">John 2:13-17</a>). Money
changers were there for the convenience of those who came from other countries, so they
could give in local currency their temple contributions. Seemingly, in their own eyes, they
were justified, but they were doing these things in the House of God. We are told that he
overturned the money changers' tables, and said to the sellers of doves, "Take these things
hence. Make not my Father's house a house of merchandise"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/2/16#16">John 2:16</a>).
</p><p>
REVERENCE DEFINED
</p><p>
"Reverence," wrote Ruskin, "is the noblest state in which a man can live in
the world. Reverence is one of the signs of strength; irreverence one of the surest indications
of weakness. No man will rise high who jeers at sacred things. The fine loyalties of life must
be reverenced or they will be foresworn in the day of trial."
</p><p>
Charles Jefferson, the author of "The Character of Jesus" writes: "Men in many circles are
clever, interesting, brilliant, but they lack one of the three dimensions of life. They have no
reach upward. Their conversation sparkles, but it is frivolous and often flippant. Their talk is
witty, but the wit is often at the expense of high and sacred things."
</p><p>
You can tell a true soul of wit by the things of which he makes light. The best humorous
writers avoid making light of religion, or of sacred things.
</p><p>
Jefferson continues: "One finds this lack of reverence even in the church. In every community
there are those who treat the House of God as they treat a streetcar, entering it and leaving it
when they please. Even habitual church attendants often surprise and shock one by their
irreverent behavior in the House of Prayer. Those persons are not ignoramuses or barbarians;
they are simply undeveloped in the virtue of reverence.
</p><p>
ORDER IN CLASSROOMS
</p><p>
Our classrooms are sometimes places of boisterousness. Here is where we need good teachers.
A teacher who can present a lesson interestingly will have good order, and when he or she
finds students who are rebellious, flipping papers, paying no attention, stumbling, kicking one
another, he or she may know that the lesson is not being properly presented. Perhaps it was
not even properly prepared.
</p><p>
One of our mothers recently went to a Sunday School class to try to find out why her son
was losing interest. There was so much boisterousness, so much confusion, so much noise,
that she felt heartsick; and as she arose to leave she said to the teacher: "I thought this was a
Sunday School class, not bedlam!"
</p><p>
SELF-CONTROL EXEMPLIFIED
</p><p>
I have said something about self-control, self-mastery, as being one of the fundamental
purposes of life. You see it exemplified in the life of the Savior, on the Mount of Temptation,
when he resisted the tempter, who said: "If thou be the Son of God, command that these
stones be made bread,"&mdash;an appeal to his appetite. "Man shall not live by bread alone, but by
every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/3-4#3">Matt. 4:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
"If thou be the Son of God," again strong in his taunting, "Cast thyself down; for it is
written"&mdash;he quotes scripture&mdash;"He shall give his angels charge concerning thee, and in their
hands they shall bear thee up, lest at any time thou dash thy foot against a stone"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/6#6">Matt. 4:6</a>).
</p><p>
"It is written," said the Savior, "Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/7#7">Matt. 4:7</a>).
</p><p>
In the next temptation Satan is not taunting, but pleading. "All these things will I give thee,"
showing him the kingdoms of the world, "if thou wilt fall down and worship me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/9#9">Matt. 4:9</a>).
</p><p>
That is a lesson of life. The tempter was foiled, taunting at first, strong in his assurance that
he could tempt, but at last pleading, and finally banished. "Get thee hence, Satan, for it is
written, thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/10#10">Matt. 4:10</a>). And angels
came and administered to him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/11#11">Matt. 4:11</a>).
</p><p>
Now then, there is a lesson of life to us all. Satan tauntingly tempts us, and unless we resist
and have in mind a higher goal than the mere indulgence or gratification of the physical, we
are going to weaken, and the tempter will gain in strength.
</p><p>
TO BEGIN IN CHILDHOOD
</p><p>
The lesson of self-control should begin in childhood, in the home. Little children should have
a sense of freedom to do as they wish up to a certain point. Beyond that point they cannot go,
and that is when that freedom interferes with the rights, comfort or convenience of another
member of the family.
</p><p>
I have told before about an incident that occurred in a zoo. It is simple, and some probably
may think we should not go to the monkeys for lessons. I think they can teach us some. Sister
McKay and I stood one day, I believe it was at San Diego, watching a mother monkey with a
new born babe. She was guarding it, her quick eye watching the other monkeys in the cage;
but the little babe was free to do just as it pleased, hopping around, weak in its infancy,
getting hold of the bars, starting to climb. When it would reach a certain place, the mother
would reach up and bring it back. When it got into a danger point, that mother instinctively
guarded it and said, "Back this way." And then the babe was free again, but only within
certain limits.
</p><p>
I said to Sister McKay, "There is a lesson of life in guiding children."
</p><p>
RIGHTS OF OTHERS
</p><p>
In the classrooms children should be taught, should be free to discuss, free to speak, free to
participate in class work, but no member of the class has the right to distract another student
by jostling or making light and frivolous remarks. And I think in this Church, in the
priesthood quorums and classes and in auxiliaries, teachers and superintendents ought not to
permit it. Disorder injures the child who makes it. He should learn that when he is in society
there are certain things which he cannot do with impunity. He cannot trespass upon the rights
of his associates.
</p><p>
Let children learn this lesson in youth because when they get out in society
and try to trespass against the law they will feel the restraining hand and probably suffer
punishment.
</p><p>
Good order in the classroom is essential to instill into the hearts and lives of young men and
young women the principle of self-control. They want to talk and they want to whisper, but
they cannot do it because it will disturb somebody else. Learn the power and lesson of
self-mastery.
</p><p>
Reverence should be particularly manifest in sacrament meeting in quorum meetings, in
Sunday School, in M.I.A., in Primary, yes and in Relief Society. This is a missionary Church.
People come here for light and knowledge, for instruction, and they have a right to find it
when they come.
</p><p>
EXTRACT FROM LETTER
</p><p>
The following extract from a letter that came to the First Presidency last week will illustrate
my point: 
</p><p>
"About one month ago two of your missionaries came to my door with a Book of Mormon.
Since I am a Catholic, and a Catholic writer for our press, and since I am fully acquainted
with Catholic doctrine and our Holy Bible, I at first refused the offer of the Book of Mormon.
They, however, persisted, and as I have permission to read other books, it being given me by
my pastor since I am a writer I finally took the book. Of course you might well guess what
happened. Having been trained during my sixteen years as a Catholic to recognize the truth
when I see, hear or read it, I could not very well fail to recognize also that the Book of
Mormon is true. This was even more the case when they later brought what might be termed
its companion book, The Doctrine and Covenants.
</p><p>
"Surely this is not the kindly, gentle Jesus, as most Catholics are taught to know him, but just
as surely in the Doctrine and Covenants this is the voice of Jesus as he spoke to the Apostles,
the Pharisees and scribes, and all the people during his three years of public ministry on earth.
Consequently, I began taking instructions, and your missionaries came twice a week to hold
cottage meetings.
</p><p>
"Then I was taken to some Church meetings over in Rodeo three miles from here, and I must
admit that each time I have returned home broken-hearted and mourning to myself, 'Oh, poor
Jesus, surely you have made the most miserable failure in your life in trying to establish your
Church anew with these people.'
</p><p>
"During the distribution of the bread and water I can discern no spirit of prayer or prayerful
reception among the congregation. They are just as liable to be smiling and whispering
together as not, scarcely discerning the body of the Lord."
</p><p>
       "Your own defects to know,<br />
       Make use of every friend and every foe."
</p><p>
IRREVERENCE IN SERVICES
</p><p>
On September 13 there came to my desk this letter from one of our stake workers: 
</p><p>
"I refer to pronounced irreverence in our church services, with the noise, laughter and
confusion that often accompanies such a condition. This is responsible for considerable
criticism and dissatisfaction and results in absenting many members from the meetings. Our
home, stake missionaries, are seriously handicapped in their work as many fear to bring
investigators to our meetings while this condition of irreverence prevails.
</p><p>
"The trouble is often intensified by reason of frivolous remarks by speakers on the stand, and
outbursts of laughter from the audience in which the children feel free to participate. This is a
sad admission in connection with the true Church of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
"Irreverence in God's house is not conducive to the best interests of the sacrament
administration and God must be displeased with the insincerity of his children who partake of
the sacred emblems carelessly, devoid of reverence that should characterize true worship."
</p><p>
IMPROVEMENT NOTED
</p><p>
I should like to say here that my observation leads me to believe that we have made a
wonderful step in that. I have not been in a house of worship, either in Sunday School or in
sacrament meeting, where the order during the administering of the sacrament has not been
just as perfect as it is at this moment in this building. A baby's voice, perhaps, somewhere,
but God is not displeased with a baby's voice, when the parents and others are reverently
thinking of the covenants they are making. However, the writer of this letter seems to have
had a different experience.
</p><p>
I plead with you to develop this Christ-like attribute of reverence in our houses of worship
and better discipline in our classrooms. And I believe that you brethren can lead in it.
</p><p>
ELDERS EXAMPLE FOLLOWED
</p><p>
I remember in 1923, attending a conference at Burnley, Liverpool Conference. Brothers and
sisters came from various parts of the district, and happy to see one another as you
missionaries know they are, shaking hands, members of the Church happy to see the elders,
shaking hands with them, and the elders joining in social greetings.
</p><p>
The meeting was held on the third floor of a public hall. In the adjoining room the sisters
were preparing the lunch. We could hear the rattle of tin pans and of other receptacles. Ten
o'clock came and there was still noise. It was fully five minutes before there was order.
</p><p>
Six months from that time when we held a meeting with the elders in that district, prior to the
opening of the conference, we said: "Brethren, the Lord is not displeased with our greetings,
expressions of love and brotherhood, but he is displeased with the irreverent
attitude, and we have some choice people, strangers who are not used to this free intercourse
of greetings so characteristic of Latter-day Saint meetings. So tomorrow morning, after you
have greeted your friends from various places, without any announcement, at seven minutes to
ten o'clock, you quietly take your seats. Do not say a word. You just go to your assigned
places."
</p><p>
They did so and at four minutes to ten o'clock every member of that district in attendance at
the conference, following the example of the missionaries, was in his or her seat, and there
was order even before the hour of opening arrived.
</p><p>
REVERENCE ENJOINED
</p><p>
It is said that "Where two or three are gathered in my name there will I be to bless them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/20#20">Matt. 18:20</a>),
and I tell you when he is present we should be reverent.
</p><p>
Someone said if Shakespeare were to enter this hall tonight, we should all stand up to greet
him, but if Christ entered, we should fall on our knees and worship him.
</p><p>
God bless you, brethren, as leaders in Israel, as guides to youth to increase your influence
with those among whom you labor. The Lord help us to sanctify our houses of worship, that
our chapels may be indeed sacred places in which we meet to worship God, I pray, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
