<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"He Went About Doing Good"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Oscar A. Kirkham</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Oscar A. Kirkham, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 69-70</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I humbly pray that the Lord will bless me this Easter morning. This is truly a great day
when we contemplate what is happening across the earth. In ten thousand churches, on a
thousand hilltops, everywhere, men and women are declaring their faith in the divine mission
of Jesus Christ. We of the Latter-day Saint Church join our voices happily with the multitudes
that declare their faith in God.
</p><p>
One of the most striking expressions of the Savior is, "He went about doing good"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/38#38">Acts 10:38</a>). With my
life's work with youth I have constantly been reminded that I must be practical. Youth lives
in action, in doing. "He went about doing good."
</p><p>
I read also these words from Psalm 27:11: "Teach me thy way, O Lord and lead me in a plain
path" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/27/11#11">Ps. 27:11</a>).
Recently in a small village in Nevada, I was called to dedicate a small, lovely chapel.
The story was told by the bishop of how they had a great struggle to raise the money and do
their part. He said "The time came when we had to get the last five thousand dollars to do our
part." He went before the people and literally not figuratively, but literally took off his coat,
and said, "I will not put on my coat again, with the Lord's help, until we have raised our
part." And he went forward, and his family was with him. And then I saw the joy of the
accomplishment. My heart was thrilled. People came from distant states. They rode down the
valley from everywhere to be with their friends and neighbors, and when it was all over, a
delightful thing happened. Although an appointment called me to hurry away to a neighboring
city, as we looked back from the car window, we saw the crowd was still there, shaking
hands with neighbors and friends, enjoying the loveliness of the occasion and the spirit of
their accomplishment.
</p><p>
May we also "take off our coats," to do our part in this hour of challenge and opportunity.
May I suggest one or two simple things, plain things, as David said in the Psalms, which are
also the teachings of the Latter-day Saint Church?
</p><p>
<i>Help someone in need:</i> Rushing from one city to another to escape bombing not long ago,
people by the thousands were trying to find a way to safety, in one of the cities of China. All
at once in the rush the crowd crossing the bridge stopped, for someone was holding up the
traffic. It was a boy. He could not cross the bridge. He heard the cry of a child that had
fallen. Quickly he went to help&mdash;to help someone in need. When the child was made safe, he
again hurried on his way.
</p><p>
Did you read the other day that on Baldy Hill fifteen American soldiers were
commissioned to go and bring out a number of boys that had been left, unfortunately not able
to get away under the fire? They worked and worked; they heard of another buried
somewhere out in the debris. They went again very early in the morning before it was light.
As they came to a nob of the hill, they heard a voice crying, "Water, water." They quickly
dug. They rescued a young man from death and by the grace of God carried him safely down
the hill where he received further help. There are many everywhere calling, "Water, water."
</p><p>
<i>Stand for the truth and the right with all good men:</i> In this very tabernacle I heard one
evening an appeal made by the queen of Holland. She told of the sorrow of her people, many
of them giving their lives, but she ended that beautiful appeal of deep sincerity with these
words, "Let us all do our best, and leave the rest to God."
</p><p>
President David O. McKay, addressing the graduating class at the University of Utah, said: 
</p><p>
Young men and young women: The future awaits you! It's yours! If you would end war and
give peace to the world, you have campaigns to organize and conquests to achieve. These will
be campaigns planned for the establishment of justice. These are the conquests of the soul:
whether it is better to walk along the easy road to selfishness and indulgence than to strive
through self-mastery and service in the realm of spirituality, you must decide.
</p><p>
<i>Have courage for prayer.</i> That must be part of the high resolve of this conference. Courage
for the right! So much is happening in public places, so many are brought into contact where
public opinion is a power. I am proud and you are proud, when you heard the President of the
United States before he gave his inaugural address say, "I want to say a little prayer."
</p><p>
I went one day down to the station with a group of missionaries to say goodbye. A father, my
neighbor, was with me. There was a group about us. The stationmaster came out and said, "It
will be about twenty minutes before the train leaves. Don't go far away." Then I saw my
neighbor walk through the crowd quickly, his son on his arm through the station, and they
were gone for a time. Then I saw him return just before the train pulled out. He kissed the
boy good-bye, and the boy was off. I walked over to my friend and said: "I want to ask you a
personal question. I have a thought that I want to ask you about your boy." I said, "Where did
you go when you took your boy? Now, pardon me, if this is too private, you do not need to
answer, but I have an idea." He said "Oh, I think you have the right idea. I took my boy
home. We went to the bedroom alone. I said, 'Son, I am so proud today,' and I finally
mustered up courage to do what I should have done probably many times before. 'Sit on the
edge of the bed, I want to bless you. I am proud of you. Mother is proud of you. This is a
great day.' And I blessed my son."
</p><p>
One other closing story: I heard it in the temple from one of the mission presidents. The
children of neighbors and friends often come with their playmates to the auxiliary
organizations of the Latter-day Saint Church. One little girl had caught the message on several
occasions about family prayer. When she came home one day, she said to her parents, "Have I
got any rights in this family?" The father answered, "Why, certainly you have, dear." "Well, I
want family prayer." "Well, my dear, you shall have family prayer." But it went on, and when
the occasion came again, the child said "Have I got any rights in this family?" There was a
longer pause, more reflection, then, "Yes, dear." And family prayer was said.
</p><p>
May God bless us. May we help someone in need. May we stand for the truth and right. May
we have courage for prayer. "Teach me in thy way, O Lord, and lead me in a plain path"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/27/11#11">Ps. 27:11</a>).
May we as he did ever go about doing good, I pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
