<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Courage to Face the Inevitable through Faith in a Divine Redeemer</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 133-137</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"Now upon the first day of the week, early in the morning, the women came unto the
sepulchre . . .  They found the stone rolled away from the sepulchre.  And they entered in,
and found not the body of the Lord Jesus.  And it came to pass that as they were much
perplexed thereabout, behold two men stood by them in shining garments! And as they were
afraid, and bowed down their faces to the earth, the angel said unto them, Why seek ye the
living among the dead?  Fear not ye, be not affrighted; for I know that ye seek Jesus of
Nazareth, which was crucified.
</p><p>
He is not here, for He is risen, as He said.  Come, see the place where the Lord lay&mdash;where
they laid him.
</p><p>
And go quickly and tell his disciples and Peter that He is risen from the dead&mdash;that He goeth
before you into Galilee; there ye shall see Him. Remember how He spoke unto you while He
was yet in Galilee saying: The Son of Man must be delivered into the hands of sinful men
and be crucified and the third day rise again.  Lo, I have told you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/5-7#5">Matt. 28:5-7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/5-7#5">Mark 16:5-7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/1-8#1">Luke 24:1-8</a>).
</p><p>
Thus do the writers of the gospels of Matthew, Mark, and Luke, record the greatest event in
the history of the world, the literal resurrection of the Lord Jesus Christ, the Savior of
mankind.  Dramatically had been demonstrated the greatest of all the divine powers of an
incarnated Son of God. He had declared to the sorrowing Martha, at the time of the death of
her brother Lazarus: "I am the resurrection and the life: he that
believeth in me, though he were dead, yet shall he live!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/25#25">John 11:25</a>).
</p><p>
To the Jews with murderous intent, His pronouncement of His divine power was even more
explicit and meaningful.
</p><p>
"Verily, verily, I say unto you, The hour is coming, and now is,
when the dead shall hear the voice of the Son of God: and they that hear shall live.<br />
"For as the Father hath life in himself, so hath He given to the Son to have life in Himself:<br />
"And to execute judgment also, because He is the Son of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/25-26#25">John 5:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
Following swiftly His own resurrection, there came an evidence of a second transcendent
power to raise from the grave, not only Himself, but others "who though dead, had believed
in Him." Matthew makes this simple, forthright record of the miraculous resurrection of the
faithful, from mortal death, "And the graves were opened; and many bodies of the Saints
which slept arose, And came out of the graves, after His resurrection, and walked into the
holy city and appeared unto many"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/27/52-53#52">Matt. 27:52-53</a>).
</p><p>
Nor was this to be the end of the redemptive powers of this illustrious Son of God.  Down
through the ages, in every dispensation, has come the cheering promise: "For as in Adam all
die even so in Christ shall all be made alive"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/22#22">1 Cor. 15:22</a>), ". . . they that have done good
unto the resurrection of life, and they that have done evil, unto the resurrection of damnation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/29#29">John 5:29</a>).
Time is rapidly moving on to a complete consummation of His divine mission.
</p><p>
If the full significance of these thrilling events were understood in this day when, as the
prophets foretold: The wicked are preparing to slay the wicked; and "fear shall come upon
every man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/33#33">D&amp;C 63:33</a>),
this understanding would put to flight many of the fears and
anxieties which beset men and nations.  Indeed if we "fear God and honor the king"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/17#17">1 Pet. 2:17</a>)
we can then lay claim to the glorious promise of the Master: "If you strip yourselves
from jealousies and from fear, you shall see me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/67/10#10">D&amp;C 67:10</a>).
</p><p>
In the brief time allotted for this Easter message, I should like to cite a few of the
"inevitables" which all may one day face, and draw some parallels from sacred writings in the
hope of vitalizing the mission of the Redeemer to all who listen and hopefully to those who
may read.  This evidence will demonstrate, to some extent, how an unshakable faith in the
reality of the resurrected Lord and in the certainty of the resurrection of all mankind would
provide the essential courage to accept "insecurity with equanimity" in a material world. Thus
may all successfully combat the apprehensions and tensions which are so destructive among
us today.
</p><p>
Consider as one of life's inevitables, if you will, the condition of one suffering from an
incurable malady, or faced with the heart-breaking prospect of impending death to a loved
one. Have you ever felt yourself spiritually devastated by an inconsolable grief?
</p><p>
May I take you to a sacred scene portraying one whose all seemed slipping from her grasp
and let you feel her strength in a fateful hour!  Huddled at the foot of the cross was the silent
figure of a beautiful middle-aged mother with shawl drawn tightly about her head and
shoulders.  Cruelly tormented on the cross above her was her first-born son.  One can but
feebly understand the intensity of the suffering of Mary's mother-heart.  She now faced in
reality the import of old Simeon's doleful prediction as he had blessed this son as a tiny
infant child, "He shall be as a sign for to be spoken against; Yea, a sword shall pierce thine
own heart also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/34-35#34">Luke 2:34-35</a>).
</p><p>
What was it that sustained her during her tragic ordeal?  She knew the reality of an existence
beyond this mortal life.  Had she not conversed with an angel, a messenger of God?  She
undoubtedly had heard of her son's last recorded prayer before His betrayal as it has been
written by John: "And now, O Father," he had prayed, "Glorify thou me with thine own self
with the glory which I had with thee before the world was"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/5#5">John 17:5</a>). This sainted mother
with bowed head heard His last prayer murmured from the cross through tortured lips:
"Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/46#46">Luke 23:46</a>) thus inspiring
her with resignation and a testimony of reassurance of a reunion shortly with Him and with
God her Heavenly Father. Heaven is not far removed from him who, in deep sorrow, looks
confidently forward to a glorious day of resurrection. It was a wise man who said: "We
cannot banish dangers but we can banish fears.  We must not demean life by standing in awe
of death." (Sarnoff)
</p><p>
Now to mention another of the "inevitables": As the press, the radio and television brings to
you daily the frightening prospect of devastating war with atomic or hydrogen bombs and
guided missiles, are you filled with forebodings of impending doom? What is there to set your
soul free from such terrifying anxieties?
</p><p>
May I take you to the example of Peter whose loyalty to the Master seemed to have exceeded
his courage, when in the face of physical hazard, he denied the Master thrice on the night of
the betrayal (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/69-75#69">Matt. 26:69-75</a>).
Compare this fear-torn Peter with the boldness in him manifested shortly
thereafter before those same religious bigots who had so recently demanded the death of
Jesus (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/12-26#12">Acts 3:12-26</a>).
He denounced them as murderers and called them to repentance&mdash;suffered
imprisonment, and later went fearlessly to his own martyrdom.
</p><p>
What was it that had changed him? He had been a personal witness to the change which came
to the broken, pain-racked, body taken from the cross, to a glorified resurrected body which
could pass thereafter unhindered through walls of mortar and stone, which could eat broiled
fish and honey comb; which could appear and disappear suddenly from the sight of mortals. 
The plain and simple answer is, that Peter was a changed man because he knew the power of
the risen Lord.  No more would he be alone on the shores of Galilee, or in prison, or in
death.  His Lord would be near him.
</p><p>
And now still another of the all-too-often "inevitables" among us: 
</p><p>
In the writings of Luke, just an inference is made as to what may have been thought to be the
reason for mental and spiritual turmoil and which may have been as much in evidence then as
it is among us today in those who have advanced degrees in their higher learning in secular
fields but have neglected spiritual nourishment.  Such a one, no doubt, was Saul of Tarsus,
the Apostle Paul to the Gentiles.  During his interview and defense before King Agrippa,
Festus who was present "said with a loud voice, Paul thou art beside thyself; much learning
hath made thee mad" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/24#24">Acts 26:24</a>).
Indeed it may have seemed so to those who had known of
his zealous persecution of the followers of the Master, in contrast to his now declared
allegiance, to that Jesus he had before so loudly denounced.
</p><p>
The insinuation of Festus suggests what higher education could do to a frustrated man, with
but a smattering of unrelated bits of information with no unifying philosophy.  Psychologists
today tell us that one such, without a belief in either God or the Devil, "like a blocked body
of water turns back upon itself, collecting scum, refuse, and silt, so the soul turns back upon
itself and collects instinctive, dark forebodings," (Peace of Soul) which makes of his days and
nights torture-chambers of discontent.
</p><p>
Years later, Paul explained to his beloved Timothy the simple formula which makes for a
contented soul: "Godliness with contentment is great gain"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/6/6#6">1 Tim. 6:6</a>), and then explains the
source from which that essential "godliness" comes; "But godliness" he said, "is profitable
unto all things, having promise of the life that now is, and of that which is to come"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/4/8#8">1 Tim. 4:8</a>).
</p><p>
That promise of eternal life had given meaning and purpose to the life of Paul as it does to all
of us who so believe.  He had heard the Master's voice at the time of his conversion,
declaring the reality of the Resurrected Lord, and whose teachings by his authorized servants,
Paul now knew were the "power of God unto salvation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
As the challenge of dictator nations is before us with their advances in destructive military
science, it is a challenge, of course, for us to be strong in military science. 
We must beware, however, lest our much learning in these worldly matters likewise makes us
mad.  It is also a challenge for us to be holy through faith in that Divine Redeemer by whom
all who obediently serve Him might be saved. Atomic power and guided missiles, are dangers
only when they are in the hands of evil men.
</p><p>
And now, finally, may I make one further reference to another "inevitable" with which many
are confronted: 
</p><p>
Have you never stood seemingly defeated after years of grueling struggle and faced with the
prospect of programs, or principles, or policies, dear to your heart, ruthlessly condemned to
failure?  Why do some men commit suicide when their bank fails or their earthly possessions
are swept away? Why do some rise above the heartbreak of disaster and calamity while others
go down to inglorious and pitiful despondency of bitterness as though the struggle of life had
all been wasted? These and others are sobering questions.
</p><p>
I am indebted to one of the leading educators in our own state university to impress this
problem.  After noting the great interest in industrial, governmental, and university circles in
clinical psychology or in what he called behavioral science, he summarizes the thinking of
eminent authorities with this significant statement: "This interest derives not only from the
trend cited above, but because of the tremendous social conflicts, such as war, which
demonstrate behavioral breakdown." (Dr. G. Homer Durham)
</p><p>
This final illustration may suggest a solution to such as these and other similar frustrating
problems.
</p><p>
The prophet Joseph Smith in this modern day was facing martyrdom at the hands of enemies
for saying that he had seen visions in which God the Father and His Son
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-19#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-19</a>) and others who had
lived upon the earth had appeared to him as living, resurrected, glorified beings.  Like the
Apostle Paul; he dared not deny having had these heavenly manifestations lest by so doing he
would offend God and come under condemnation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/24-25#24">JS&mdash;H 1:24-25</a>).
</p><p>
In the midst of bitter persecution with his coming doom already foreshadowed, the word of
the Lord came to him: "if the very jaws of hell shall gape open the mouth wide after thee,
know thou, my son, that all these things shall give thee experience and shall be for thy good.
The Son of Man hath descended below them all.  Art thou greater than He?  Therefore hold
thy way . . . for the bounds (of your enemies) are set, they cannot pass . . . Fear not what men can
do, for God shall be with you forever and forever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/122/7-9#7">D&amp;C 122:7-9</a>).
</p><p>
"Let virtue garnish thy thoughts unceasingly; then shall thy confidence wax strong in the
presence of God . . . and thy dominion shall be an everlasting dominion"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/45-46#45">D&amp;C 121:45-46</a>).
</p><p>
There you have your answer, you strong, noble statesmen in worldly councils of men
involving human welfare. Better, as Paul said it, "godliness with contentment"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/6/6#6">1 Tim. 6:6</a>), than an empty
compromise for the sake of expediency or the plaudits of men.  You, too, can know that your
Redeemer lives (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/19/25#25">Job 19:25</a>),
as did Job in the midst of his temptation to "curse God and die"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/2/9#9">Job 2:9</a>), and know
also that you, too, can open the door and invite Him in "to sup with you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/3/20#20">Rev. 3:20</a>). See also yourselves
one day as resurrected beings claiming kinship to Him who gave His life that the rewards to
mortal men for earthly struggle and experience will be the fruits of eternal life even though as
measured by human standards ones life's labors seemed to have been defeated.  This is what
the voice of wisdom has said, "The best thoughts, affections, and aspirations of a great soul
are fixed on the infinitude of eternity. Destined as such a soul is for immortality, it finds all
that is not eternal too short, all that is not infinite too small." (Stanford Memorial Chapel.)
</p><p>
Today in commemoration of the world's greatest victory I invite the honest in heart
everywhere in deep humility to rise above their human fears and frustrations and rejoice as
did the apostle to the Gentiles "Thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our
Lord Jesus Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/57#57">1 Cor. 15:57</a>).
</p><p>
All of which I pray for us and for all men everywhere who seek to serve
Him and keep His commandments.
</p>
</div>
</div>
