<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Temple Work</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 21-24</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I need the help of the Spirit of the Lord. Elder Christiansen
reported his visit to the various branches of the Church in Europe. I made a promise to the
good members of the Church in the far Pacific that when I returned I would remember them
to you and express to you their love and fellowship. It is a glorious thing to go into a country,
one so far away, and find members of the Church who think and act just as we
do here, with the same testimony of the truth of the gospel of Jesus Christ. I
am fulfilling my promise in expressing to you their goodwill and fellowship.
</p><p>
For the few minutes that I have I would like to take a text from the words of our Savior,
". . . except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
I am firmly convinced that nowhere else in the world, outside of the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints, is there anyone who has the authority to perform the ordinances that
would bring the birth of the water and of the Spirit to mankind. That would have to be from
someone who has the authority of the priesthood of God, and that authority was revealed in
these latter-days, the Aaronic Priesthood first by John the Baptist to the Prophet Joseph Smith
and Oliver Cowdery, and then the Melchizedek Priesthood under the hands of Peter, James,
and John, also to the Prophet Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery.
</p><p>
And from that source we have obtained the priesthood of God by which we act and by which
we go forth into the world to preach the gospel to those who sit in darkness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/28#28">D&amp;C 45:28</a>). I know this
statement is not pleasing to the great majority of people upon the face of the earth, but
nevertheless it is true. And I realize that it is impossible for us&mdash;all things are possible, of
course, to the Lord&mdash;but it is impossible for us with all the means that we have at our
command and the means at our command have increased wonderfully in the last few 
years&mdash;but we cannot reach every soul living upon the face of the earth. They are dying off every
day. They are being born every day into the world.
</p><p>
However, the Word of the Lord being true, the time must come when the message of
salvation will reach every soul. How is that to be done? We do the best we can with all the
facilities at our command, through the preaching of the gospel, disseminating the truth by
word of mouth, by the many facilities that are at our command, through the magazines that
are published through the press and every other means. But it is impossible for us with the
facilities such as they are, to reach every soul.
</p><p>
Furthermore, there have been millions upon millions of people who have lived in this world
who never had the opportunity to hear of Christ, never heard his name; they lived at a time
and in a place where his name was not known, where the gospel did not reach them not
because of any fault on the part of our Father in heaven nor of his servants to reach the
peoples of the earth, but because from the beginning of time men have loved Satan more than
they loved God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/13#13">Moses 5:13</a>),
and they have turned away and refused to receive the truth, have raised their
children in darkness, and they have died in darkness, so far as the gospel of Jesus Christ is
concerned.
</p><p>
Nevertheless, the promises of the Lord must and will be fulfilled. From the very beginning of
this dispensation, just a few months after the organization of the Church, the Lord gave a
revelation in which he foreshadowed the salvation of the human family, all of those who
would repent and believe. I shall read to you this part of the Lord's Preface to the book of his
commandments; the words of Jesus Christ, himself.
</p><p>
"Hearken, O ye people of my church, saith the voice of him who dwells on high, and whose
eyes are upon all men; yea, verily I say: Hearken ye people from afar; and ye that are upon
the islands of the sea, listen together"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1#1">D&amp;C 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
Now, that is to all those who are living. But the Lord goes on to enlarge this thought. And he
says: 
</p><p>
"For verily the voice of the Lord is unto all men, and there is none to escape, and there is no
eye that shall not see, neither ear that shall not hear, neither heart that shall not be
penetrated" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/2#2">D&amp;C 1:2</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord has not limited that to any dispensation or any age upon the face of the earth. He
has made that just as broad as the history of mankind and he adds: 
</p><p>
"And the rebellious shall be pierced with much sorrow; for their iniquities shall be spoken
upon the housetops, and their secret acts shall be revealed"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/3#3">D&amp;C 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
It seems so strange to me that the peoples of this world since the days of the great apostasy,
when the apostles of old were removed and those who held the priesthood were destroyed,
that the world could fall into the awful condition which today prevails,
which denies salvation to every soul born into this world who never heard the name of Jesus
Christ or never had an opportunity to repent and be baptized or receive the gift of the Holy
Ghost. They have held out no hope for all of these people of the nations, pagan or otherwise,
who have dwelt upon the face of the earth without the knowledge of the gospel of Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
The Lord is just, and he has made it clear that the time will come when every soul shall have
an opportunity to hear the truth. That does not mean that every soul has the opportunity or
will have that opportunity in this mortal world. Millions have died without that opportunity. It
has been no fault of theirs, but the fault lies with their fathers before them, who turned away
from the truth which truth was given in the beginning to Adam who was commanded to teach
these things to his children. The scriptures say that Adam did teach these things to his
children but that they loved Satan more than they loved God, and Satan came among them
and said, "I, too, am a son of God, believe it not, and they believed it not and from that time
forth men became carnal, sensual and devilish" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/13#13">Moses 5:13</a>), and so darkness spread over
the face of the earth.
</p><p>
In his justice, the Lord has revealed to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, just as
he revealed it in the days of the apostles, that there is a salvation even for the dead and the
time must come when every soul must have an opportunity to hear it. Those who did not get
the opportunity to hear it in this world will have that opportunity in the world of spirits, and
Peter made that very clear in his Epistles
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/18-19#18">1 Pet. 3:18-19</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/4/6#6">1 Pet. 4:6</a>),
and it is only fair that those who died without a
knowledge of the gospel should have the opportunity to hear it, and the Lord revealed that
great truth to the Prophet Joseph Smith
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/19#19">D&amp;C 128:19</a>),
that the time would come when the gospel of the
kingdom would be declared to the dead and they who never had the opportunity of hearing it
should have that opportunity given to them, and if they would repent in that spirit world then
we could go into the temples of the Lord and perform the ordinances for them vicariously,
being saviors upon Mount Zion (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/obad/1/21#21">Obad. 1:21</a>),
and thus give unto the dead the opportunity to hear the truth,
to repent of their sins, and if they will repent and turn away from evil and accept the truth,
we can go into the temples of the Lord and perform the ordinances for them which will be
valid unto them just the same as if they were living upon the face of the earth.
</p><p>
The gospel of Jesus Christ is a vicarious work. Christ came into this world and died for
mankind. He did not die just for those who repented of their sins and received his gospel. His
death upon the cross brought salvation to every living soul, so far as the resurrection from the
dead is concerned, and every soul born into this world shall receive the resurrection from the
dead because he was not guilty of bringing death into the world, and man is not penalized
because death came into the world, but naturally he has to die&mdash;that is part of the mortal
life&mdash;but he will be raised again in the resurrection no matter who he is, no matter when he
lived, no matter what he believed or what he failed to believe. That is a universal gift from
Jesus Christ to every soul.
</p><p>
It is a different matter, however, so far as the kingdom of God is concerned, and no soul is
going to enter into that kingdom until he has received either in this life in person or by proxy
because he was not here to do it for himself, baptism for the remission of his sins and the
laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost. What a wonderful gift it is the Lord has
placed into our hands, to bring salvation to the dead, to those who are willing to repent and
receive the truth.
</p><p>
I have no idea in my mind that every soul that has lived upon the face of the earth, who has
died and gone to the spirit world, is going to repent and receive the gospel. There will be
many that will not do that. Our scriptures point to that fact. They are not going to receive the
gospel in the spirit world, when their souls are full of bitterness and hate towards the truth,
but they have a right to have it taught to them.
</p><p>
The Lord went into the spirit world, himself, turned the key for the salvation of the dead and
our elders when they pass to the next world, go into that world to continue
their labors of preaching the gospel, bringing to repentance all who are willing to repent and
receive the truth, that they might come into the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/30-35#30">D&amp;C 138:30-35</a>), or as Paul calls it, "the
family of God in heaven and on earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/3/15#15">Eph. 3:15</a>).
For it is the family of God. The kingdom of God will
be one great family. We call ourselves brothers and sisters. In very deed we become joint
heirs with Jesus Christ through the gospel of Jesus Christ, sons and daughters of God, and
entitled to the fullness of the blessings of his kingdom if we will repent and keep these
commandments.
</p><p>
In conclusion I want to read to you one or two statements dealing with our responsibilities
towards the dead. First from the Prophet Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
"The greatest responsibility in this world that God has laid upon us, is to seek after our dead"
(<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 356).
</p><p>
"This doctrine was the burden of the scriptures. Those Saints who neglect it, in behalf of their
deceased relatives, do it at the peril of their own salvation" (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 193).
</p><p>
"It is one of the greatest and most important subjects that God has revealed. He should send
Elijah to seal the children to the fathers, and the fathers to the children . . . without us, they
could not be made perfect, nor we without them; the fathers without the children, nor the
children without the fathers . . . I wish you to understand this subject, for it is important"
(<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 337).
</p><p>
"We have a work to do just as important in its sphere as the Savior's work was in its sphere.
Our fathers cannot be made perfect without us; we cannot be made perfect without them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/15#15">D&amp;C 128:15</a>).
They have done their work and now sleep. We are now called upon to do ours; which is to be
the greatest work man ever performed on the earth." (Brigham Young, <i>Discourses</i>, p. 406).
</p><p>
"The ordinance of sealing must be performed here man to man, and woman to man, and
children to parents, etc. until the chain of generation is made perfect in the sealing ordinances
back to Father Adam" (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 407).
</p><p>
"Brethren and sisters, lay these things to heart. Let us go on with our records . . . I pray God
that as a people our eyes may be opened to see, our ears to hear, and our hearts to understand
the great and mighty work that rests upon our shoulders, and that the God of heaven requires
at our hand" (President Wilford Woodruff, <i>The Utah Genealogical and Historical Magazine</i>,
Vol. 13, p. 152).
</p><p>
"This is the day in which the Lord expects his Church at least to inaugurate the great work of
turning 'the heart of the fathers to the children, and the heart of the children to their fathers'"
(President David O. McKay, <i>The Utah Genealogical and Historical Magazine</i>, Vol. 25, p. 59,
or <i>Gospel Ideals</i>, p. 19).
</p><p>
"What about your great great ancestors who never heard the name of Jesus Christ? . . . You
may have the opportunity of gathering the names of your ancestors and, by being baptized for
by proxy, they may become members of the kingdom of God in the other world as we are
members here" (President David O. McKay, see <i>Instructor</i>, November 1958, p. 322).
</p><p>
Now, brethren, these are our responsibilities, and the Lord requires this work at our hands.
The Church has gone to great expense endeavoring to gather the records of the dead, and I
want to say to you, has been very, very successful in that labor to gather in the records of
your ancestors so that we could go into the temples of the Lord and perform these labors for
them so that all who are willing to repent and receive the gospel of Jesus Christ may be
brought into his kingdom and into that great family of God, which is both in heaven and on
earth.
</p><p>
And I humbly pray that this spirit will take hold of the members of the Church, in the name
of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
