<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Can You Bear Testimony?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph L. Wirthlin, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 65-68</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, it has been a great source of inspiration to have the privilege of
attending this wonderful conference. As I listened yesterday to our prophet, I felt that we
were receiving the same direction, the same inspiration, the same guidance, as did the
members of the Church two thousand years ago when Peter and the apostles stood before
them periodically and taught them the gospel. Yesterday we had that Spirit here. We have had
it today. It is the Spirit of the Lord. Each and every one of us can feel it as we listen to what
is said by our Brethren.
</p><p>
It is a marvelous thing to belong to the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints and know
that there stands at the head, a prophet who receives from on high the guidance and the
direction that is necessary for the sons and daughters of our Heavenly Father, not only those
here, but those all over the world. Our President in the years gone by has traveled to many
lands for the purpose of preaching to the people that they can understand the gospel of the
Lord Jesus Christ and have the privilege of living it and enjoying all the blessings therein.
</p><p>
I often think that I happen to be a member of the Church, not because I accepted it, but
because I was born in the Church, and I assume most of you who are present this afternoon
have membership in the Church because you were born in it. On the other hand, we have
quite a number of our brethren and sisters who are converts, those who had the privilege of
receiving the gospel from the missionaries in various parts of the country. You and I who
were born in the Church have received it, brethren and sisters, without any great demands on
our part, except that we live the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ and set the proper example to
those not of our faith.
</p><p>
I often think of my two grandfathers&mdash;one was born in England and the other was born in
Switzerland. The one in England at the age of twenty-one was very anxious to find the
Church of the Lord Jesus Christ. Yes, he belonged to another church, a great church, but he
was not satisfied. He could not understand the matter of baptism. He could not understand the
matter of authority. He could not find it.
</p><p>
One Saturday evening on retiring to his bed, he made it a matter of prayer. He asked the Lord
if the Church of Jesus Christ was upon the earth could he be directed to it. That night he had
a dream, and in the dream he saw not too far from where he lived a road, and at the end of it
was a little chapel. When he arose Sunday morning, he was so impressed with the dream he
immediately dressed and went down the road, and there was the little chapel. In it two men
were preaching the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, and who were they&mdash;two Mormon
missionaries! My grandfather immediately joined the Church. There was no question about it
in his mind.
</p><p>
I am positively sure that over the world where individuals have a desire to find the true
Church, they can find it. They may find it in the way of a dream, or they may find it by the
missionaries who may come to their homes and teach them the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ.
</p><p>
My grandfather finally made the long trip to America and came into this area with his family
of ten children of which my mother was the youngest. It was a difficult thing to find the right
kind of work. He worked in a coal mine, an experience he had never had. He labored there
for some six months, then came to Salt Lake City to get his pay. He was paid for three
months. He quit his job and finally settled on a little farm near Tooele, Utah, but there was
no water and that created a problem. As I have read his history he had written day by day,
there was difficulty on every hand, but not once did I ever find my grandfather finding fault
or condemning the Church. When general conference was held comparable to this one, he
used to hitch up his old team, and it was an old team, and drive into Salt Lake City, and here
he remained for four days and attended all of the meetings. It is marvelous to read of the
great inspiration he received hearing the Prophet Brigham Young at that time.
When he attended conference, they were the best four days of the whole year, hearing the
gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ taught by the prophet. Brigham Young was a prophet to him,
and is it not a wonderful thing to know, brethren and sisters, that from the days of the
Prophet Joseph Smith until the present time, we have a prophet, seer, and revelator, so that
through the direction of our Heavenly Father we will be guided and directed wherein we will
receive the blessings that we need.
</p><p>
President Clark told of conditions that might exist in the world because there is a great nation
and a government which does not teach or permit its people to believe that Jesus Christ
actually lives and is the Son of God. As President Clark said, some day that may create
difficulties for us. Nevertheless, I hope and pray that each and every one of us will so live the
gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ that when that day of difficulty comes, we through prayer,
faith, and divine direction from our Heavenly Father will be able to meet our problems and
solve them.
</p><p>
We have a great responsibility of living the gospel because the world expects us to be a
different people, which brings to mind the statement of an individual who had the privilege of
visiting the Los Angeles Temple before it was dedicated. This individual said, "The temple is
beautiful. It is a marvelous building, but the Mormons have something that is different." I do
not know exactly what that individual had in mind, whether she thought the temple in and of
itself was beautiful or something that was different, whether she thought we have the
priesthood of the Lord Jesus Christ, or whether or not she was giving consideration to the fact
that we are doing work for the dead. Nevertheless, an impression was made upon that
individual. So, in all of our lives, wherever we go, we are going to make an impression on
those with whom we come in contact. As a people, we are indeed a "different" people.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing to know that in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints,
brethren and sisters, the choice young men at the age of twelve may receive the Aaronic
Priesthood&mdash;the Aaronic Priesthood, a divine gift which was bestowed upon the Prophet
Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery by John the Baptist himself. I humbly pray that in your
homes where your sons hold the office of deacon, teacher, or priest, there is going to be
positive assurance that these young men realize that they have the most divine gift of God to
his sons.
</p><p>
If we have any difficulty at all in connection with the Aaronic Priesthood, where some of
them may become inactive and not as interested as they should be, I think it comes about
many times because fathers and mothers are not giving consideration to the fact that their sons
hold the Aaronic Priesthood, the priesthood that was held by John the Baptist.
</p><p>
It is a wonderful thing to sit down with your son&mdash;he may be a deacon, a teacher, or a 
priest&mdash;and say to him, "You hold the Aaronic Priesthood. John the Baptist held the Aaronic
Priesthood. He was a priest. He baptized Jesus Christ."
</p><p>
Is it not wonderful to know that your son at the age of sixteen may have the same privilege
of baptizing as did John the Baptist about two thousand years ago. It is so impressive,
brothers and sisters, that these young men will come to the conclusion that holding the
Aaronic Priesthood is the most important gift that God can bestow upon them at their
particular age. So teach them, inspire them, and direct them in connection with their
assignments in the Aaronic Priesthood work, that when the day comes for them to receive the
Melchizedek Priesthood, they are going to feel in their own souls, "Now I hold the priesthood
of the Lord Jesus Christ," for the Christ himself is the Great High Priest, and everyone of
these young men, if worthy, sooner or later is going to have the privilege of holding the
office of an elder or a seventy or a high priest.
</p><p>
It is most inspiring and encouraging to me as I have the privilege of coming in contact with
these young men who have a desire to go out and preach the gospel, as they may have been
called by the President of the Church in connection with the bishop of the ward. In
interviewing them, I always ask them the question, "Can you bear testimony that Joseph
Smith actually saw the Father and the Son? That is the statement you will have to make
because we stand on that wonderful event as a Church, that Joseph Smith at
the age of fourteen actually saw the Father and the Son."
</p><p>
It is most thrilling and inspiring to know that these young men at the age of twenty can say,
"Yes, I can bear testimony that Joseph Smith actually saw the Father and the Son." They
should be able to do that, brothers and sisters, because they have held the Aaronic Priesthood
from the age of twelve until the age of twenty when they receive the Melchizedek Priesthood.
They should have been taught and should have the knowledge that they can bear these
wonderful testimonies which are so important.
</p><p>
In the final analysis, this Church is the Church of the Lord Jesus Christ. That is the testimony,
brothers and sisters, that we ought to bear to our sons our daughters, and our grandchildren.
This is the Church which is preparing the way for the second coming of Christ. That is our
responsibility. It is one of the most important responsibilities that any group of people can
have.
</p><p>
Now with reference to these other nations that do not have the privilege of hearing or
understanding the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, it is my feeling that some day they will
have that opportunity. They are going to have that privilege. Was it not said to whom the
gospel was to be preached&mdash;to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people. Whether or not we
will be able to send missionaries into Russia to preach the gospel, I do not know, but I do
remember President Clark said something about two years ago, and I have never forgotten it.
He said that perhaps we will be able to preach the gospel to the people of Russia out of Salt
Lake City over television or radio or something else. That day will come when the Russian
people will hear and understand the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, not only the people of
Russia, but also the millions in China and the millions in India. They are all the sons and
daughters of our Heavenly Father, and I am satisfied that Jesus Christ is just as anxious that
they hear the gospel and enjoy all the same privileges that we have. In some way and at some
future time, these great events are going to take place.
</p><p>
We have a great responsibility, and I think of the words of Peter when he said, speaking to
the people: 
</p><p>
"But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye
should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvelous
light" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
If we live the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ, we are "a chosen generation." We are a chosen
generation because through the wonderful revelations that were given to the Prophet Joseph,
we have the commandments, we have the direction, we have the guidance that is necessary to
so live the gospel that we indeed are going to be a chosen generation.
</p><p>
And "a royal priesthood"&mdash;the Aaronic and the Melchizedek&mdash;the Aaronic Priesthood coming,
as I have already indicated, when John the Baptist appeared and bestowed it upon Joseph
Smith and Oliver Cowdery. Then, Peter, James, and John, the apostles of old and the
Presidency of the Church some eighteen hundred years before, appeared and bestowed upon
Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery the Melchizedek Priesthood. Indeed, might we say, it is a
royal priesthood.
</p><p>
"An holy nation," of course, an holy nation, as I understand it, is the Church of the Lord
Jesus Christ. This is an holy nation, and all of those who have membership in the Church of
the Lord Jesus Christ are in that holy nation as long as they live the gospel.
</p><p>
"A peculiar people"&mdash;a peculiar people because we accept without question Jesus Christ as the
Son of God! A peculiar people because we declare to the world that God the Father and his
Son Jesus Christ appeared to that fourteen-year-old young man and gave him the direction and
inspiration whereby the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints could again be established
upon the earth for the benefit, the direction, and the inspiration of all the sons and daughters
of our Heavenly Father, and ". . . that ye should shew forth the praises of him who hath
called you out of darkness into his marvelous light"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
My testimony to you is this: if my grandfather in Switzerland, if my grandfather in England
had not had the privilege of hearing and understanding the gospel, we as a
family, without a doubt, would still be in the darkness of the world, but because they accepted
the gospel, it is possible now for all of us to go into the marvelous light of the Church, the
marvelous light of Jesus Christ himself.
</p><p>
We have a great responsibility of so living the gospel that it will be a great source of
inspiration and divine guidance to all of those with whom we come in contact.
</p><p>
In the final analysis, as we live the gospel, it is a wonderful thing to think of the words of
Jesus Christ, "And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>).
That is the promise and the blessing that each and every one of us may live and 
understand&mdash;that we shall know the truth and the truth shall make us free.
</p><p>
May the Lord continue to inspire us in all of our endeavors, I humbly ask in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
