<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">This We Believe...</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Richard L. Evans</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Richard L. Evans, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1962, pp. 96-98</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
There is a salutation customary among us which includes all within sight and sound&mdash;"My
brethren and sisters"&mdash;and I see no reason to modify it. I am grateful for the relation that all of
us bear to all of us in the Fatherhood of God and the relationship we have to him
</p><p>
Because of an unusual series of assignments, we have circled the world twice this past
year&mdash;once flying east, and once moving westward. We have been in many countries, among many
peoples, in many places. We have encompassed areas where hundreds of different dialects and
languages were spoken. We have been in the midst of a diversity of men, and in the midst of
many differing religions and philosophies of life.
</p><p>
We count among our friends, men of many races, many faiths, many backgrounds, and
beliefs, and these are not superficial friendships. They are part of our lives. We respect them
and what they are and have an affection for them. We respect them and their beliefs, and we
believe they respect us and ours.
</p><p>
As a consequence of this long journeying and these many friendships, we have been earnestly
reading and seeking to understand the basic beliefs, the many philosophies of India and of
Asia, and in doing so have consulted as closely as possible the people themselves and their
authentic sources; and this we would ask our friends to do for us, as we would do it unto
them also. When they want to know what we believe, we ask them to ask us, or consult our
authentic sources instead of sources of intentional or unintentional distortion. No matter how
many times an error is repeated, it is still an error. We believe that we ourselves are the best
source of what we believe, as are other men of what they believe, and to those interested we
should like to give the simple facts.
</p><p>
We have discovered, we think also, that mankind generally is sincerely searching, searching
for the reasons, for the purpose of being, searching for the ultimate answers. "Man's success
or failure, happiness or misery," President McKay has said, "depend upon what he seeks and
chooses." What people believe is exceedingly important because what they believe will
determine how they live. A person prepares differently for a short journey than he does for a
long one, and a person who believes that life here is the end of all would prepare much
differently and live much differently from him who believes that life is everlasting.
</p><p>
Thomas á Kempis said, "Where my thoughts are, there am I," and might
have added, Where my beliefs are, where my convictions are, there am I&mdash;or at least in that
direction I am headed.
</p><p>
For these reasons and because we love our friends, and because many of them have asked us,
and because even if they hadn't we would want to do it anyway, we would like to say some
few things today basic to our beliefs: 
</p><p>
First of all, in common with many millions of men, we are devoutly Christian. This is the
Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Jesus the Christ, with the doctrines, the
commandments, the revelation, the inspiration, the authority that come of him and through
him, is the foundation of this Church. He is the chief cornerstone, and not any man.
</p><p>
We believe what Jesus taught, and in this we rely on scripture, including the Bible, which we
believe as it came from the mouths of the prophets. We believe also other works, given to
other peoples anciently and modernly, in addition to that word given to ancient Israel&mdash;works
which are consistent with and complementary to the Bible. In addition, we believe in the
words of the living prophets. We believe in continuous revelation, for we feel that a Loving
Father still gives divine guidance, and would not leave his sincerely seeking children alone
without counsel or direction&mdash;and him whose countenance you have seen this morning in
conducting this conference&mdash;President David O. McKay&mdash;we accept and sustain as a prophet
of God, as we accept Moses and Abraham, and Peter and Paul, and Isaiah and Elijah or any
such others.
</p><p>
It does not seem a strange thing that God would speak to his children in the present as well as
he would speak to them in the past. Certainly we do not need his guidance less today. What
loving father would hold himself altogether aloof from his sincerely seeking children?
</p><p>
We believe in the literal language of scripture concerning the Fatherhood of God. We believe
the language of Genesis which says that God made man in his own image
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/27#27">Gen. 1:27</a>). We
believe that God is an infinite intelligence with an infinite love for us, not indefinable, but a
Father with a father's interest in us. This gives us a peace and purpose in life, a sense of
belonging and of not being left alone.
</p><p>
We believe that the glory of God is intelligence
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/36#36">D&amp;C 93:36</a>);
that no man can be saved in ignorance
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/6#6">D&amp;C 131:6</a>); that
the search for truth is an obligation, as is education also; and that there must be freedom for
the search.
</p><p>
We believe in the commandments of God; in causes and consequences; in the necessity for
living within the law; and that there is real reason for every commandment and requirement.
</p><p>
We believe that the human body should be preserved in health; that it is unwise and
ungrateful and unjustifiably foolish to partake of things that impair the fullest well being of
the body and effective physical functioning. What is not good for us simply should be left
alone.
</p><p>
We believe literally in everlasting life, in the eternal perpetuation of personality; that
whatever knowledge a man attains to in this life will rise with him in the resurrection
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/18#18">D&amp;C 130:18</a>); and we
believe in a literal resurrection, remembering the words of Pascal, who asked, "Which is more
difficult? To be born, or to rise again?"
</p><p>
Birth is a great miracle. Life is a great miracle, and he who gave us life here will give us life
everlasting. This we believe.
</p><p>
We believe that all men will be resurrected; that all men in this sense will receive salvation,
but that in the hereafter there are different degrees of glory
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/22-23,40-42#22">1 Cor. 15:22-23,40-42</a>),
entitlement to which will depend upon the life we have lived, and by the living of the law and
the keeping of the commandments we shall be entitled to return to live with our Father and
go back to him where once we were, to a place of peace and progress, where there will be
everlasting life, with family and friends, in a relationship that is everlasting.
</p><p>
Thus we believe in marriage, not only for time but also for eternity, and that we have an
inescapable obligation for the children God has given us to teach, to train, and to set before
them a righteous example of the living of life.
</p><p>
We believe in the divinity of Jesus the Christ. We believe in the scripture
which says that he was in the express image of his Father
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/1/3#3">Heb. 1:3</a>). We believe that he
was born of a virgin, as the scripture says
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/7/14#14">Isa. 7:14</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/13#13">1 Ne. 11:13</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/7/10#10">Alma 7:10</a>);
that he lived, that he preached, that he ministered
among men, that he was put to death, that he rose on the third day, that he ascended to his
Father, that he will come again on earth to rule and reign.
</p><p>
This is a simple belief. It is a profound one also. It gives peace in life. It gives a sense of
everlasting purpose. It gives the assurance that we are helping to shape our own future with
our faith, with our works, with our learning, with our lives. It gives us the assurance that life
is purposeful, meaningful, limitless, everlasting; that the gospel was given as a guide to help
us realize our highest happiness; that all its ordinances are essential; that authority to
administer them is also; and that this authority was again restored in the nineteenth century
through Joseph Smith the Prophet, as the heavens were opened and the personality of God
again revealed as the Father, pointing to his Beloved Son our Savior, said,
"This is My Beloved Son. Hear him!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
In this brief time there is much omitted, but this in essence is the faith that gives us peace and
purpose in life and freedom from many of its fears. We believe there are clear-cut answers to
life's questions; that much of the groping of life can be eliminated.
</p><p>
In Calcutta, in India, we read in the notebook of a wonderful grandmother an inscription
which, among others, she had cherished since she was a young girl&mdash;an inscription which
India's great poet, Rabindranath Tagore, had written in there for her in his own handwriting:
"Surrender your pride to truth."
</p><p>
These lines Tagore also wrote on freedom&mdash;freedom for the search and on the importance of
such searching&mdash;(and we have altered a word or two by inserting "me" instead of "my
country" in the last line): 
</p><p>
"Where the mind is without fear and the head is held high; <br />
 Where knowledge is free; <br />
 Where the world has not been broken up into fragments by narrow domestic walls; <br />
 Where words come out from the depth of truth; <br />
 Where tireless striving stretches its arms towards perfection<br />
 Where the clear stream of reason has not lost its way into the dreary desert sand of dead habit; <br />
 Where the mind is led forward by thee into ever-widening thought and action&mdash;<br />
 Into that heaven of freedom, my Father, let . . . [me] awake."
</p><p>
An eminent analyst has said: "I have learned in forecasting economic futures that what is
going to happen is already happening." It is so in our lives. It is so everlastingly, and all of us
ought to determine our ultimate objectives as early as possible and then faithfully pursue
them. Life is not limitless here. Time soon passes. Every man takes himself and what he is
with him wherever he goes, and he takes himself also into eternity.
</p><p>
What do we have to lose by indifference, by neglect? In words already cited this morning at
an earlier hour, "we have nothing to lose except everything," and, conversely, we have
nothing to gain&mdash;except everything.
</p><p>
In the words of Archibald Rutledge: "I am absolutely unshaken in my faith that God created
us, loves us, and wants us not only to be good, but to be happy." No man can be indifferent
to the issues of life and death. These are uppermost at one time or another in the minds of all
of us.
</p><p>
With some awareness of the responsibility of doing so, with myself, my family, and to all
men, I would bear witness of the truth of these things, of the everlasting importance of them,
of the obligation that all of us have to seek and to search, of the interest that our Loving
Father who made us in his image has in us, and of the incalculable importance of the gospel
he has given us. I leave with you my witness, in the name of our Lord and Savior, who died
that we might live, even Jesus the Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
