<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"What Is Man, That Thou Art Mindful of Him?"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Robert L. Simpson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Robert L. Simpson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 87-89</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters: I am grateful to my Heavenly Father for this opportunity. I want
each of you to know the strength that we feel in your presence. I am sure you come to conference
to receive, but I want to promise you that you also give as you come to general conference,
because we are the recipients of that giving. As we look at you and as we feel your unity and
your strength and your combined faith, we feel built up, and we are better able to carry out our
assignments. Without that feeling, we couldn't do it, I promise you.
</p><p>
<b>Fatherhood of God</b>
</p><p>
May I bear you my witness that I know that God lives. I know it just as surely as I stand here, and
I know that Jesus is the Christ, and that Joseph Fielding Smith is a prophet of God. And because
he is a prophet, those things that he says are true. Just yesterday he gave two great discourses,
and one of the things that he said I shall ever remember, for it was something that was taught me
even as a child at the knee of my mother. He said, "God is our Father, and we are his children."
O that the world, three billion people, could listen to a prophet of God and have this firm
thought, this basic and fundamental concept, as an anchor to their lives.
</p><p>
Not too long ago a schoolteacher, anxious to extract some participation from her class of third
graders on the subject of modern-day progress, asked her little ones a simple question: 
</p><p>
"Can anyone here name one important thing in this world that was not here ten years ago?" After
a few moments of thinking, an eager and confident eight-year-old boy near the back raised his
hand. His answer: "Yes&mdash;me." As humorous as this incident might sound on the surface, I am
certain that Heavenly Father smiled approvingly at the boy's response, a response that was made
in all seriousness.
</p><p>
<b>Father-to-son relationship</b>
</p><p>
This lad, in my mind, is a modern-day David, for it was he who declared centuries ago: 
</p><p>
"When I consider thy heavens, the work of thy fingers, the moon and the stars, which thou hast
ordained; 
</p><p>
"What is man, that thou art mindful of him? and the son of man, that thou visitest him?
</p><p>
"For thou has made him a little lower than the angels, and hast crowned him with glory and
honour.
</p><p>
"Thou madest him to have dominion over the works of thy hands; thou hast put all things under
his feet." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/3-6#3">Ps. 8:3-6</a>)
</p><p>
If the world could but learn and have feelings about this one basic concept of God to man, of
father-to-son relationship, many of our mortal frustrations and contentions could be greatly
diminished.
</p><p>
Just a couple of days ago in Primary conference, we were reminded once again by the little
children: "I am a child of God, and he has sent me here." This is a basic doctrine, and all
mankind needs to believe it.
</p><p>
<b>Basic family relationships</b>
</p><p>
We seem so inclined to forget that there are certain basic and fundamental relationships within
the human family that do not alter as the scene changes from one side of the veil to the other.
One of those concepts, in my opinion, is the right that every child hat to communicate with and
obtain assistance from his father, mortal and heavenly. Each of us has two fathers&mdash;a spiritual
father and an earthly father. Not only that, but I have also been taught that every parent has the
right and the capacity to know and be concerned about the welfare of his children. It is an eternal
commission and right shared by the father of your physical body and the father of your spirit.
</p><p>
<b>God knows his offspring</b>
</p><p>
Why must we continually limit God, our Eternal Father, and his abilities by our own mortal
incapabilities, immaturities, and our earthbound, physical restrictions? Should he who has the
ability to create worlds and father billions of children be denied the right to know his offspring?
Of course not. Every father has that privilege. To think otherwise is inconsistent with all that we
hold as basic and fundamental in life&mdash;life here, life before, and life hereafter.
</p><p>
May I be bold enough to suggest that your Heavenly Father knows you personally and can call
you by name&mdash;yes, you plus three billion other children who share this world with you. And you
can add to that family circle the billions upon billions who have lived and died since Father
Adam. This thought itself is admittedly almost beyond the comprehension of mortal
understanding, but please, let us not limit the Creator of heaven and earth in any way, for his
powers are limitless, and the basic concept must hold that a father knows his children.
</p><p>
<b>Prayer is heard</b>
</p><p>
As a child of God kneels to pray, that individual must believe implicitly that his prayer is being
heard by him to whom the prayer is addressed. The thought that our Heavenly Father is too busy
or that our message is being recorded by celestial computers for possible future consideration is
unthinkable and inconsistent with all we have been taught by his holy prophets.
</p><p>
It was thrilling to listen to a father relate this story about his three-year-old youngster recently, as
they knelt by the crib in the usual manner for the little fellow to say his simple bedtime prayer.
Eyes closed&mdash;heads bowed&mdash;seconds passed, and there were no words spoken by the child. Just
about the time Dad was going to open his eyes to check the lengthy delay, little Tommy was on
his feet and climbing into bed. "How about your prayers?" asked Dad. "I said my prayers," came
the reply. "But son, Daddy didn't hear you." Then followed the child's classic statement: "But
Daddy, I wasn't talking to you."
</p><p>
<b>Communication not in vain</b>
</p><p>
Even three-year-olds have personal, private matters to discuss with Heavenly Father from time to
time. But most important of all is the implicit faith that the communication is not in vain. Each
word is finding its way to a Father who is not too busy, a Father who has the ability to hear, to
judge, and to act for our benefit. This must be the personal faith of us all regardless of our age,
regardless of our station in life, regardless of how long it has been, regardless of how grievous
the confidence might be.
</p><p>
". . . this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>) His total purpose and plan is involved in our success. It's natural for a father to
want success for his offspring. A son or daughter should want to please his parents and to help
guarantee an eternal relationship with them.
</p><p>
<b>The vine and the branches</b>
</p><p>
"What is man, that thou art mindful of him?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/8/4#4">Ps. 8:4</a>) A loving Father in heaven, concerned for the
welfare of his child, might well answer: "Why, you are my son, you are my daughter. I love you
very much. I listen carefully each day, hoping to hear from you. I want so to one day have you
back where you belong. Please share with me your innermost thoughts, your hopes, yes, and
particularly your problems. I know I can help, but listen carefully, child&mdash;don't close the door
when I give you the answer. I need you very much, just as you need me." And I suppose that a
fitting climax to such comments that a loving Heavenly Father might conceivably utter to any
one of his children could well be couched in the same language that the Savior used as he spoke
tenderly through John: 
</p><p>
"I am the vine, ye are the branches: He that abideth in me, and I in him, the same bringeth forth
much fruit: for without me ye can do nothing.
</p><p>
"If ye abide in me, and my words abide in you, ye shall ask what ye will, and it shall be done
unto you." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/5,7#5">John 15:5,7</a>) What a promise]
</p><p>
We are children of God. He is our Father in very deed. May we revere that relationship. Without
this lofty concept as the foundation of our lives, our chances for temporal happiness and true
success are extremely limited; our possibility for eternal joy and exaltation is nonexistent. But
with it in sharp focus and meaningful on a daily basis, we will best be able to comprehend and
realize the great statement that "men are, that they might have joy." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>) I pray in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
