<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Show Your Faith by Your Works</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 122-125</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The singing, as you know, for this afternoon and this morning has been furnished by the
members of the Tabernacle Choir. We have been inspired with their singing. I think it would
be fitting at this moment to represent you as well as the General Authorities in saying just a
word, at least, of appreciation of the services rendered by many during this three-day
conference in making this inspirational gathering so meaningful: 
</p><p>
First, to the General Authorities, we express deep appreciation for the inspirational messages
they have given to us. Second, to the public press, the reporters, for their fair and accurate
reports throughout the sessions of the conference. Third, to the city officials the city traffic
officers in handling increased traffic. etc; members of the fire department, some of whom you
met after one or two of these sessions; and to the Red Cross representatives who have been on
hand to render any assistance and service that might be needed. To the Tabernacle ushers who
have rendered service in seating the great  audiences of these conference sessions. Quietly and
unobtrusively they have looked after your convenience and welfare.
</p><p>
We have already expressed, and we do so again, appreciation to the radio and television
stations throughout our own city and the nation who all through the three days have carried
the proceedings of these inspirational sessions. These stations have been the means of
permitting untold thousands of persons to hear the proceedings of the one hundred thirty-first
semiannual conference.
</p><p>
We appreciate especially those who have furnished the singing throughout this conference. Let
me remind you again, as you enjoy the service they have rendered: <i>first</i>, the
Relief Society Singing Mothers from the Central Utah and Mt. Timpanogos regions, who
rendered service faithfully for two days with the Relief Society sisters before they joined us
Friday morning. Sister Florence Jepperson Madsen conducted. <i>Next</i>, the University of Utah
Mixed Chorus for the Saturday morning session, with Ardean W. Watts conducting. The
University of Utah Institute of Religion, University Stake Chorus, and the Bonneville Strings,
furnished the music for the Saturday afternoon session, with Elder David Austin Shand
conducting.
</p><p>
<i>Third</i>, the Tabernacle Choir Men's Chorus last night. How inspiring that group was! <i>Fourth</i>,
last, but certainly not least, the Tabernacle Choir, who furnished the music this morning and
this afternoon, with Elder Richard P. Condie and Elder Jay E. Welch conducting, and how
they have thrilled not only this nation, but also people in other countries, wherever they have
been. Our best wishes and prayers go with them in their prospective tour, for they will receive
a welcome wherever they go. God bless them, and all officials connected with that great
organization.
</p><p>
We mention again these beautiful antheriums from Oahu Stake.
</p><p>
Indeed, we thank all those who have contributed in any way to the success and inspiration of
this great conference.
</p><p>
Carlyle said: "There is one godlike virtue, the essence of all that ever was or ever will be of
godlike in this world&mdash;the veneration done to human worth by the hearts of men." During
the last few days especially, and frequently in the position which General Authorities occupy,
we have occasion to ask men and women to accept certain positions and to devote their time
and their means to the work of the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Recently I have seen men's hearts touched, tears roll down their cheeks, as they were
surprised to hear a request of the General Authorities to accept some responsibility or be
called in some other position. Without exception, no matter what sacrifice they had to make
financially no matter how unable they feel themselves to fill the position, each one has said,
"Yes, if that is what the Church wants, I will do it."
</p><p>
Frequently we hear reports from wards and branches of efforts the people put forth to
contribute, perhaps to the erection of a building, perhaps to renovate, or to build an addition
to a present building. They see that two, three, four, sometimes six or seven groups&mdash;wards
or branches&mdash;have to meet in one building, and they feel the necessity of contributing of
their means. And what those members of the Church, unknown beyond the borders of their
branch or ward, do to make more effective conditions to preach the gospel of Jesus Christ!
</p><p>
I wish all the world could glimpse the willingness of those people, the sacrifices they have to
make. I think it would preach the gospel more effectively than any one other thing we could
do. I recall just a few years ago of visiting a stake and dedicating their meetinghouse. I
learned of the struggles they had in order to finish paying for that building. None of our
chapels are dedicated until they are free from debt. That means that millions of dollars have
been spent in the erection of stake houses and ward buildings throughout the 336 stakes and
sixty-seven missions.
</p><p>
That meetinghouse had just been paid for about a week before the dedicatory services were
held. The bishop had to call for an extra contribution, and a young boy who earned his money
by washing cars, polishing shoes, and doing little odd jobs, had quite a little sum of money,
for a boy, in the bank. I received this information from the banker himself who was an officer
in the stake. I do not know whether the father had contributed much to the chapel. I had my
own thoughts, but when the bishop made an extra call for money this boy went to the bank
and asked the banker, "How much have I in the bank?" He told him, and I think it was
something near one hundred dollars. Sister McKay, who knew about the circumstances, says it
was near a hundred. The boy said, "Well, I shall take ten dollars, and you give the rest to the
bishop to finish paying on this meetinghouse."
</p><p>
"Oh, but you can't afford that," said the banker.
</p><p>
"Yes, I can," and he took ten dollars for himself and gave the balance to the bishop.
</p><p>
What a lesson! I think I told that afterwards when I went back to the stake, and the young
boy was then on a mission. I cite this incident merely as an illustration of the loyalty and
faith of the membership of the Church. I appreciate these acts, and because of them, in our
hearts there will be a love for one another, which is the Spirit of the Christ, the spirit of
brotherhood, the spirit of love.
</p><p>
I am a great believer in the doctrine of James. He was a practical man in the early Church.
Paul preached faith; James preached works, and it was James who said, ". . . shew me thy
faith without thy works, and I will shew thee my faith by my works"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/18#18">James 2:18</a>).
</p><p>
"What doth it profit, my brethren, though a man say he hath faith, and have not works? can
faith save him?
</p><p>
"If a brother or sister be naked, and destitute of daily food,
</p><p>
"And one of you say unto them, Depart in peace, be ye warmed and filled notwithstanding ye
give them not those things which are needful to the body; what doth it profit?
</p><p>
"Even so faith, if it hath not works, is dead, being alone.
</p><p>
"Yea, a man may say, Thou hast faith, and I have works: shew me thy faith without thy
works, and I will shew thee my faith by my works"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/14-18#14">James 2:14-18</a>).
</p><p>
Throughout this conference emphasis has frequently been made by the speakers to the great
responsibility resting upon the membership of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
to declare to the world that God lives; that Jesus Christ, his Son, is our Savior; that his is the
only name ". . . under heaven given among men, whereby we must be saved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>). It
was said at the opening of this conference that there are men and women who are now forty
to fifty years old who have heard all their lives that God does not exist, that Jesus Christ is a
myth. You have heard the testimony from men with tears in their eyes, if you were close
enough to see, their lips quivering with emotion, testify that they know that God lives, that
Jesus is the Christ, and that they appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith and gave instructions
about organizing his Church, and that Peter, James, and John, who held the authority from the
Christ himself, gave that authority in this dispensation; that the Melchizedek Priesthood was
bestowed upon the Prophet and Oliver Cowdery; that John the Baptist who baptized Jesus
Christ bestowed the Aaronic Priesthood, a direct successor of the authority from heaven.
</p><p>
Now you know that. You know these men. I give you my testimony that God lives; that he is
close to us; that his spirit is real, that his voice is real; that Jesus Christ, his Son, stands at the
head of this great work; and no matter how much the atheistic philosophy takes hold of
blinded boys and girls and men who hear Satan's voice, the truth stands as declared by the
Father and the Son to that boy Prophet. You and I and all the members of the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints have the responsibility to declare that truth to the world, and
the world is full of honest men and women waiting to hear that truth. Let us not condemn
them. Condemn the evil men who would blind them with their sophistry and with false
reasoning. Some of our young boys are so blinded, but it is our duty as officers of the Church
to lead them from that blindness to the truth. I think I can repeat here, as I did last night, for
those misguided boys: 
</p><p>
"Dim as the borrow'd beams of moon and stars<br />
     To lonely, weary, wandering travelers,<br />
     Is reason to the soul; and as on high<br />
     Those rolling fires discover but the sky,<br />
     Not light us here, so Reason's glimmering ray<br />
     Was lent, not to assure our doubtful way<br />
     But lead us upward to a better day."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                         &mdash;Dryden
</p><p>
That brighter day is the light of the Holy Spirit emanating from God the Father, and his Son,
Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
God bless you, my dear fellow workers, bless you in your homes. Make your faith shown by
your works in your home; husbands true to your wives, not only in act, but
in thought; wives true to your husbands, not only in act, but in thought; children true to your
parents. Do not arrogate to yourselves that they are old-fashioned in their beliefs and that you
know more.
</p><p>
Girls, follow that sweet mother and her teachings. Boys, be true to your fathers who try to
live the gospel; then strangers, seeing such homes, will say, "Well, if that is the result of
Mormonism, I think it is good." You will show your faith by your works in everyday life
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/18#18">James 2:18</a>).
</p><p>
God bless you that we may have power so to do, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
