<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Be Thou an Example of the Believers</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Antoine R. Ivins</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Antoine R. Ivins, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 37-38</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, if I say anything that will be helpful to you this afternoon,
it will be because you join your faith and prayers with mine that the Lord may bless me.
</p><p>
The other night Sister Ivins and I attended a meeting in the Assembly Hall in which the
theme of the Mutual Improvement Associations was treated: 
</p><p>
. . . be thou an example of the believers in word, in conversation, in charity, in spirit, in faith,
in purity (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/4/12#12">1 Tim. 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
I would like to tell you the thoughts that that has brought to me.
</p><p>
Be thou an example of the believers&mdash;
</p><p>
I would like to add there the faithful Christian believer&mdash;"in word." What is the word of the
faithful Christian? In those days the most electrifying thing that the world had experienced in
years was so close to them that they no doubt were still startled by it&mdash;the resurrection the
actual, glorified resurrection of Jesus Christ our Lord. We are going to celebrate it now, but it
was a new thought in that day, that it could be possible. It became a reality, and it was the
thing that was passing from believer to believer, publicly and in private conversation. The
resurrection of Jesus Christ verified the statement that he was and is the Son of God, and that
must have been the theme of every devout Christian of that day, just as it must be today. Of
course, they would amplify it, after bearing testimony that Christ had risen, that he was the
Son of God, that he was born of Mary by miraculous means, then they would pass on to his
teachings as to how men and women should live to gain an exaltation in the kingdom of God.
That, it seems to me, would have been and should have been and must have been the "word"
of every faithful Christian in that day. Likewise it should be your "word" and my "word"
today. We, however, have something to add to that because we must tell the world not only
these things but also that not too far back Christ the Lord and his Father appeared to the boy
Prophet Joseph Smith and brought back to man the testimony that Jesus Christ is the Son of
God. Then we must teach also that Peter, James, and John, John the Baptist, the Angel
Moroni, and the men who had held the keys of the various past dispensations, came back to
the Prophet Joseph Smith restoring unto him the keys, all of the keys that had ever been given
to man through the various dispensations of time. We are under that obligation, too, and we
must do it, not only publicly, but we must do it in our conversations. This
should be the theme of every religious conversation of a good member of the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints. And it should go out as a living testimony that it is true. Of
course when we bear that testimony to others who have not received it, we should do it in all
charity, but we should do it with spirit, fearlessly, courageously, and never doubting. If we
can develop the faith that will enable us to do that, a faith that God is the Father of our
spirits, that he is the Father of Jesus Christ, that Jesus Christ is the Redeemer of the world,
and that if we will repent and purify our lives, he will carry the burden of the sins of the
world, (and it is only upon that condition, brethren and sisters, that he says he will do it), if
we can develop that faith in our hearts, then we should be able to carry on. We must not only
develop that faith, but also the faith of a good Latter-day Saint, the faith of a good Christian
must be in himself, in his neighbors, and especially in his leaders, that the Church shall go
forward vigorously, courageously to a wonderful realization of its purposes.
</p><p>
Now I say, it must be done very largely in conversation, and in that each one of us becomes a
missionary for the Church. He who is warned must warn his neighbor, and if we have that
testimony given to us by the Spirit of God, it remains for us to pass it on by word of mouth
to those who have not received it. It does not require a call from President McKay to enable
us to bear our testimonies to our neighbors. We have been warned. God himself has given us
the charge to do it. Then it is not only by word of mouth that we bear testimony, but it is also
by purity of life. Through the power we hold in the priesthood of God, we must be able to
demonstrate by our lives its value. We can if we will. Our problem is to will to do it, and we
must do it in good spirit. I wonder if many of us are sorry that we have so many things that
we are told we ought not to do, whether or not they become burdensome to us. I frequently
tell the missionaries when I talk to them that they must consider the rules that are set up in
the mission field for their protection, and so it is with these things which we ought not to do
as members of the Church. They are for our protection; they are the reflection of purity of
life.
</p><p>
Brethren and sisters, if we will be an example of the faithful believer, all these things we will
do, and in this time of decreasing missionary help, those of us who can should make available
our services and go forth to bear this testimony. There is no compromise with the testimony
that Jesus Christ was born of Mary by miraculous means, that he is the Son of God, that he
was the firstfruits of the resurrection
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/20#20">1 Cor. 15:20</a>),
that through that resurrection he made possible to you
and me a return to the presence of God our Heavenly Father, contingent only, that is, an
exaltation in his presence is contingent only upon faithful service unto him and our fellows.
Let us let that service be in good spirit. Let us be glad to give up the things we are asked to
give up. Let us be glad to devote ourselves to His service. Let us do it without fear, without
compromise, with great courage, and with all the energy which we may possess. If we will do
this, my brethren and sisters, we will always enjoy the Spirit of God, that testimony will
always remain with us, and the devil will never prevail against us. God grant it, I pray, in the
name of Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
