<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1949, pp. 185-191</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am sure that everyone present feels to say sincerely in his own heart, thank the Lord for the
spirit of the brotherhood of Christ. I am overwhelmed at this vast audience. I believe it is the
largest Priesthood meeting held in the history of the Church. We sense even though dimly that
the strength of Zion is to "put on the authority of the priesthood."
</p><p>
I pray for the inspiration of the Lord, and for your sympathy while I attempt to say something
which will be of interest and value to you leaders of Zion.
</p><p>
"EVILS AND DESIGNS"
</p><p>
One of the most significant statements in the Doctrine and Covenants, one which carries with
it evidence of the inspiration of the Prophet Joseph Smith, is found in the 89th Section of the
Doctrine and Covenants:
</p><p>
In consequence of evils and designs which do and will exist in the hearts of
conspiring men in the last days, I have warned you, and forewarn you, by giving
unto you this word of wisdom by revelation . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>).
</p><p>
METHODS OF TOBACCO INTERESTS
</p><p>
"Evils and designs which do and will exist in the hearts of conspiring men..." The purport of
that impressed me in the twenties,  and the thirties of this century. I
just ask you men tonight to recall the methods employed by certain tobacco interests to induce
women to smoke cigarettes.
</p><p>
You remember how insidiously they launched their plan. First, by saying that it would reduce
weight. They had a slogan: "Take a cigarette instead of a sweet."
</p><p>
Later, some of us who like the theatre, noticed that they would have a young lady light the
gentleman's cigarette. Following this a woman's hand would be shown on billboards lighting
or taking a cigarette. A year or two passed and soon they were brazen enough to show the
lady on the screen or on the billboard smoking the cigarette.
</p><p>
I find here a clipping which I set aside in the early thirties, which corroborates this idea. This
is 1931:
</p><p>
It is well known that the cigarette manufacturers are after the young women and
girls, now. They say there are twenty-five million of these in the United States,
and if they can popularize smoking among them, they will be able to increase their
sales from three billions, six hundred million dollars annually to six billion dollars.
This is their claim and their aim.
</p><p>
CIGARETTE ADVERTISING
</p><p>
Now, it is common to see beautiful young women depicted on billboards, and in the popular
journals advertising certain brands of cigarettes. "Last year three of the large cigarette
manufacturers, we are informed, spent fifty-four million dollars in advertising their wares.
This is probably a greater outlay than has ever before been spent to popularize any kind of
merchandise.
</p><p>
"There is hardly a dead wall in the country or a railroad right of way that escapes the
cigarette posters. The revenue from one Broadway, New York, billboard covering the front of
a building, it is said, exceeds the rent for the building itself.
</p><p>
"The radio has become one of the most successful means of advertising cigarettes. Attractive
programs are presented, not for the purpose of entertaining the youth, but for the purpose of
enticing and encouraging them to reach for a cigarette.
</p><p>
"Parents meekly submit to this and later deplore the fact when their children are
hopeless cigarette addicts."
</p><p>
I may be wrong, but I thought I saw an indication recently that <i>conspiring</i> men now have evil
designs upon our youth. Keep your eyes and ears open, to observe if they are not taking the
same steps now to get our young men as they did to entice women to use that vile weed. You
know that:
</p><p>
Sin is a monster of such hideous mien,<br />
As to be hated needs but to be seen,<br />
But seen too oft, familiar with its face,<br />
We first endure, then pity, then embrace.
</p><p>
CONFIDENCE IN YOUTH
</p><p>
Lest you might think from what I am going to say in giving some statistics, that I am losing
confidence in the youth, I want to say here that my confidence in them is unshaken. Every
week I sit with my brethren and hear recommends from you bishops, of young men and
young women to go on missions. While there are some whom we think you should not have
recommended, the great majority of these young men and young women are the noblest in the
land. They are not addicts; they are not seeking evil ways; they have high ideals.
</p><p>
The young men, even the boys in Sunday School, particularly those in the Deacons Quorums,
Teachers and Priests, and girls of corresponding age, are a credit to the parents, a credit to the
Church. As an illustration, out in Uintah recently, I had the privilege of dedicating three
church edifices. I learned from the president of the stake that many people had "given their
all."
</p><p>
EXAMPLES OF DEVOTION
</p><p>
I have heard that expression in other places, and took it at first that it was just an exaggerated
expression of devotion. But when I learned on this occasion of a widow who had given all
she could possibly give&mdash;others, each of whom had sold their last cow, and others who had
taken the tax money that had been saved, then I began to realize that there was something in
that phrase. And the whole thing was climaxed by the following incident.
</p><p>
The ward was putting forth every effort to finish the meetinghouse, but it was unpaid for.
They needed more money. I am not sure that young boy's father is in the Church. I think he
is, but he would not contribute, and I have to imagine the devotion of his mother. But this
young boy, about fourteen, had saved money by shining shoes, washing automobiles, doing
odd chores, and had saved a hundred and fifty-nine dollars.
</p><p>
He had heard of a recent call for more contributions and said to the president of the stake
who was cashier of the bank: "I need the nine dollars, but I wish you would take the hundred
and fifty and give to the bishop to help pay the cost of that meetinghouse."
</p><p>
"But," said the president, "you cannot afford it." "Yes, I can."
</p><p>
He gave his hundred and fifty dollars as a contribution. Several months passed and the ward
needed more money, and that young boy out of his meager savings gave a total of two
hundred and twenty-five dollars.
</p><p>
An entire group of the lesser priesthood taking turns in shifts carried every brick from
one old meetinghouse over to the new.
</p><p>
Well, I could multiply incidents of the devotion of the youth, so I have not lost confidence in
them, but, we must not close our eyes to the approaching wolves who would ravish the flock.
We must not close our eyes to the fact that there are conspiring men who would pollute
young boys, and girls of corresponding age for sake of increasing profits. I have these things
in mind as I read you the following statistics:
</p><p>
A VICE TO BE SHUNNED
</p><p>
I think tobacco is a vice which should be shunned as the bite of a rattlesnake. When I say
that, I am not unaware of the fact that though seemingly there are some young men who can
use tobacco without serious injury, there are many others who are poisoned, their character
weakened, and their health undermined by the ingredients of the cigarette. The Lord has said
that tobacco is not good for man. That should be sufficient for Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
Too many of our boys are tampering with cigarettes. I do not like to hear tobacco programs
on the radio. Young people say: "Well, they are the best we have." Of course they are,
because tobacco interests can pay the highest salaries and get the best actors, and singers to
further their evil "designs."
</p><p>
REPORT ON DELINQUENCY
</p><p>
I have been favored recently, as I have told you once before, in receiving a monthly report of
the young people who are arrested in Salt Lake County. Note from the following how many
delinquents are users of tobacco:
</p><p>
In <i>January</i> there were 94 fingerprinted. Eighty of these were tobacco users, and sixty-eight
used liquor. Twenty-two of them belonged to our Church; thirty to the Catholics,
twenty-seven to the Protestants, and fifteen no religion at all. There were five deacons, three
priests and five elders among them.
</p><p>
<i>February</i> there were seventy-one fingerprinted. Fifty-six used tobacco and fifty-one drank
liquor.
</p><p>
<i>March</i>, eighty-eight. Seventy-eight tobacco users, and seventy-four drinkers.
</p><p>
<i>April</i>, there were a hundred and four. Eighty-seven used tobacco, eighty-six used liquor.
</p><p>
<i>May</i>, ninety-three. Seventy-five tobacco, sixty-seven liquor. June, ninety-four. Ninety-two
tobacco users, eighty-six whiskey.
</p><p>
<i>June</i>, ninety-four. Ninety-two tobacco users, eighty-six whiskey.
</p><p>
<i>July</i>, one hundred and six. Ninety-four tobacco users, eighty-eight liquor.
</p><p>
Out of the six hundred and fifty, five hundred and sixty-two used tobacco, five
hundred and twenty drank liquor.
</p><p>
TOBACCO AND LUNG CANCER
</p><p>
Recently there came to this city a gentleman who has been specializing on cancer, Dr. E. L.
Winder, Department of Surgery, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis,
Missouri. He is attached to the National Cancer Foundation and is one of the most eminent
men in cancer treatment in the country. He spent a few days here in Salt Lake City the week
of August 29th.
</p><p>
He came to the laboratory in which Dr. George R. Hill, Jr., works, because the company who
employs him had published a paper on arsenic content of tobacco smoke. This gentleman
stated that he had come to Utah to make a study of lung cancer since he had heard that
cigarette smoking is appreciably lower in Utah than in any other state, "because Mormons do
not smoke." He reports that lung cancer, virtually unknown a hundred years ago, and
occurring only rarely in 1912, is today taking the lives of more men than any other type of
cancer. More than twenty percent of the cancers attributed to men are lung cancers. They have
been endeavoring to find out why this increase in lung cancer, and have found the
answer&mdash;cigarette smoking, definitely and unmistakably so.
</p><p>
He has personally investigated over five hundred cases of lung cancer and says that in every
case but four, these men have been smoking cigarettes, from one pack to two packs a day, for
some twenty to thirty years. And then he adds: "That percentage is far too great to be
meaningless."
</p><p>
He says that the average patient of lung cancer dies at fifty-two years of age, and that the
average lung cancer lasts only thirteen months before proving fatal.
</p><p>
He interviewed eleven or twelve Mormons who call themselves "Jack-Mormons," having lung
cancer, and found them in every case but one, a man seventy-four years of age, to be heavy
smokers.
</p><p>
Dr. Hill asked him if he had found similar cases among women. The doctor answered, "No,
but I look for a very great increase in lung cancers among women in the next ten or fifteen
years."
</p><p>
DRINKING ON INCREASE
</p><p>
Liquor drinking is increasing. In Salt Lake County we have reports from seven of these liquor
stores. From June 1st to 5th of 1948, one store that week&mdash;note only about four days&mdash;sold
$62,381 worth. The corresponding week this year $72,000. June 14th to 19th, $65,900,
practically $66,000. And this year, corresponding week $78,900, or
$79,000. The increase in the first week was $9,700, the second $13,000, the fourth, $4,000,
the fifth, $3,000, the sixth, $12,000, seventh, $19,000, eighth, $13,000, and in August
$10,000.
</p><p>
"In consequence of evils and designs which do and will exist in the hearts of conspiring men,
I have warned you, and forewarn you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>).
</p><p>
Now, we do not want to condemn the unfortunates, but we do want to warn our boys and
girls against these evils. We must not shut our eyes to the fact that all this smoking and all
this drinking is not done by those who are non-members of the Church. Even if we have only
a small percentage, it is worth our while to be on our guard and try to save our boys and our
girls from these evils.
</p><p>
RESULTS OF ALCOHOLISM
</p><p>
A young man who, addicted to drink, became an alcoholic, and finally took his own life in a
New York hotel, left his last will and testament as follows:
</p><p>
I leave to society a ruined character. I leave to my parents as much misery as they
can bear. I leave to my brothers and sisters the memory of a misspent life. I leave
to my wife a broken heart. I leave to my children the memory of a drunkard's
name.
</p><p>
James L. Gordon, by whom this is quoted, says this ought to be written on the memory of
every youth who is prone to say to himself, "I can drink and I can let it alone."
</p><p>
OBLIGATIONS TO YOUTH
</p><p>
Some of our foolish girls, here in the city particularly, are becoming addicts to nicotine. We
should warn them, labor with them, not drive them from us, bring them into our Mutuals, our
Sunday Schools, and into our socials where they may mingle with those who cherish higher
ideals. I want to tell you, brethren, that we cannot with impunity sit by and be satisfied with
having the best of our boys and girls come to auxiliary and priesthood meetings and let the
others go unvisited.
</p><p>
If parents are failing in guiding the youth then it is the duty of ward teachers and priesthood
quorums and auxiliary teachers to supplant in the lives of these children the love which they
are losing perhaps because of broken homes.
</p><p>
PREVALENCE OF DIVORCE
</p><p>
If I had time to give you the number of these young people who have been fingerprinted who
come from broken homes, you would see where one source of this evil lies. Divorces are
altogether too common in our Church. I hope the time will come
soon when there will be no divorce granted, no sealing cancelled, unless that couple first
come to a member of the priesthood, stake or ward, and try their best to avoid a separation.
</p><p>
STANDARDS OF SERVICEMEN
</p><p>
Now I conclude with a reference to the standards of our boys during the war. Many of them,
under difficult conditions, proved themselves strong enough to resist the temptations. Only
today a returned soldier came and put this into my hands with the remark: "I collected this
while overseas during the war years."
</p><p>
No matter what else you are doing,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        From cradle days through to the end;<br />
You are writing your life's secret story,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Each night sees another page penned.<br />
Each month ends a thirty page chapter,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Each year the end of a part;<br />
And never an act is misstated,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Nor even a wish of the heart.<br />
Each morn when you wake the book opens,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Revealing a page clean and white;<br />
What thoughts and what words and what doings,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Will cover its surface by night!<br />
God leaves that to you, you are the writer,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        And never one word will grow dim;<br />
Until someday you write the word "finish"<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        And give back your life's book to Him.
</p><p>
God help us as men of the priesthood to keep the lives of our boys and girls pure and white,
that they may return, with us, back to the presence of our Father in heaven, worthy of the
welcome, "Well done, thou good and faithful servants"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/21#21">Matt. 25:21</a>),
I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
