<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 170-173</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren and co-workers, some of you who have had to occupy this pulpit can appreciate the
deep sense of responsibility which I now have. No man can face an audience of the
Priesthood of God without a sense of humility and a prayer in his heart for guidance from our
Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
THE TRAGEDIES OF WAR
</p><p>
When President Evans referred to the casualties of war, my mind went out to the parents
whose boys did not come back from the battlefield. I had two sons and a son-in-law in World
War II and they all three came back unmaimed. So the tragedy of losing a son did not come
directly home to Sister McKay and me. I have a very dear friend however&mdash;who lost his only
son, an ideal son full of promise, and a worthy member of the Church. My heart has bled,
with my friend, in that loss. But he went from the world gloriously, and I use that word
advisedly, for I am sure that no young man living complied more aptly with the old saying,
"Be fit to live, be ready to die," than that young man. These thoughts came to me just with
the mentioning of that tragedy of war.
</p><p>
They were followed by other tragedies here at home, deeper, more poignant, more tragic than
the death of the boys on the battlefield: That is the degradation of our girls. And there came
to my mind the picture of one home out of which came three young girls. They came to Salt
Lake City to get work, prompted, undoubtedly, by a desire to help in the war. Perhaps they
did help win the war, but they lost their souls. A policeman gave me his confidence and told
me their story. It is tragic. Unfortunately, it has been repeated here in this city and I suppose
in Ogden, and other large cities. I mention this in connection with the tragedy of divorce. I
commend with all my heart the suggestions made by President Evans.
</p><p>
What I am leading up to is this: The brethren realize that the dangers to our young girls who
leave home and go out to work or for other purposes, are still among us. There are daily
tragedies now in this city. If possible, we should like to prevent them, or at least reduce them
to a minimum.
</p><p>
COMMITTEE TO ASSIST L.D.S. GIRLS
</p><p>
Many of you, perhaps, do not know that during the war Elder Charles A. Callis and President
Alma Sonne were appointed a committee to see what could be done to protect the girls who
left their homes and came to the centers. You, perhaps, do not know that there has been
appointed a young woman a mother to assist this committee in finding these girls and keeping
them from arrest and degradation. Brother Callis has gone; Brother Sonne is in Europe. Two
other brethren have been appointed, Elder Spencer Kimball and Elder Mark Petersen of the
Council of the Twelve. The reports of the activities of this young woman and those who have
assisted her are in their hands. It is pleasing to note that a number of girls have been saved;
but some have been lost.
</p><p>
Recently, you received a letter, Bishops, asking that you notify these brethren of any young
girls who leave your Wards for whatever purpose and go to another town. It will be necessary
for the Ward Teachers and those who are in charge of the young girls&mdash;the teenage girls to
assist you in this duty. Here is an opportunity to apply the injunction of our Father in Heaven
to the teachers, "Watch over the Church, always. Be with and strengthen them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>). No other
organization in the world, I think, is so adequately equipped as is the Church to guard our
young men and young women and to keep them from the tragedies of sin. Will you please
cooperate with these brethren, for your own sake, for the sake of the fathers and mothers who,
perhaps, have lost control of their children. The reports indicate that most of these
unfortunates come from broken homes. They are tragedies.
</p><p>
LOST SHEEP
</p><p>
Another thing, once a month, through the courtesy of two County Officers, there come to my
desk reports of the young men and older men who have been caught in the meshes of the law.
In these reports, those who hold the priesthood are designated. Do you teachers know about
them? So many Deacons, so many Priests, so many Teachers, so many Elders, Seventies and
High Priests. These too may be tragedies! Remember that the injunction, "Watch over the
Church, always," does not mean just once a month.
</p><p>
In the parable of the lost sheep, ninety-nine were safe in the fold, but one had strayed; and
the Good Shepherd did not rest until the lost one was found
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/3-7#3">Luke 15:3-7</a>).
</p><p>
I have in mind another theme, tonight, which I should like to preface with these statements:
(1) That truth never grows old; and (2) that responsibility is never disassociated from the
Priesthood.
</p><p>
THE IMPORTANCE OF EXAMPLE
</p><p>
To the Priesthood here assembled tonight I quote the truth and the admonition given by the
chief Apostle to the members of the Priesthood over nineteen hundred years ago&mdash;that chief
Apostle, my favorite, wrote this letter,
</p><p>
To the Elders which are among you.
</p><p>
I who am also an Elder, and a witness of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory that shall be
revealed. Feed the flock of God, which is among you, taking the oversight thereof not by
overruling, but willingly, not by constraint, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind. Neither
as being lords over God's heritage, but being examples, examples to the flock. And when the
Chief Shepherd shall appear, ye shall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away. Likewise,
ye younger submit yourselves unto the Elders; yea, all of you be subject one to another and
be clothed with humility, for God resisteth the proud, or rather seeth the proud and giveth
grace to the humble. Humble yourselves, therefore, unto the mighty hand of God, that He
may exalt you in due time, casting all your care upon Him, for He careth for you. Be sober,
vigilant, because your adversary, the devil, as a roaring lion walketh about seeking whom he
may devour. Whom resist, steadfast in the faith, knowing that the same afflictions are
accomplished to your brother in the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/5/1-9#1">1 Pet. 5:1-9</a>).
</p><p>
Just one element I wish to emphasize. The instructions I give are nineteen hundred years old,
yet new today and applicable as then to elders, from the chief elder. But he said, "Be an
example to the flock" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/5/3#3">1 Pet. 5:3</a>).
Ever keep in mind, fellow workers that <i>example should start at home.</i>
That is the best place to exercise the lofty ideals of the Priesthood.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR PARENTS
</p><p>
The older I grow the more grateful I am for my parents, for what they did for us children in
that old country home. They lived the gospel. Father used to preach it, particularly to visitors
who came, more than to us boys and girls; but both Father and Mother lived the gospel. And
I have realized throughout this conference, more than ever before, that my testimony of the
reality of the existence of God dates back to my childhood, that my parents' teachings and
their examples led me to the absolute knowledge that God is my Father; that I received then
the knowledge of the reality of the spiritual world, and I testify to you tonight that that is a
reality.
</p><p>
It is just as easy for me to accept as a divine truth the fact that Christ preached to the spirits
in prison while His body lay in the tomb
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/18-19#18">1 Pet. 3:18-19</a>),
as it is for me to look at you from this pulpit. It is
true. And it is just as easy for me to realize that one may so live that he may receive
impressions and direct messages through the Holy Ghost. The veil is thin between those who
hold the Priesthood and divine messengers on the other side of the veil.
</p><p>
That testimony was born in that home, because of the example of a man who lived the
Priesthood and a wife who sustained him and lived it in daily life. I do not know that Peter
had that in mind, particularly, when he mentioned, "Be an example to the flock"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/5/3#3">1 Pet. 5:3</a>), but I know
that each home is a part of that flock. The influence you spread in your home will go
throughout the town, will go throughout the county, the Wards and the Stakes.
</p><p>
TRUTH NEVER GROWS OLD
</p><p>
The most precious thing in the world is a testimony of the truth. I repeat, truth never grows
old, and the truth is that God is the source of your Priesthood and mine; that He lives, that
Jesus Christ, the great High Priest
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/4/14#14">Heb. 4:14</a>), stands at the head
of this Church, and that every man who
holds the Priesthood, if he lives properly, soberly, industriously, humbly and prayerfully, is
entitled to the inspiration and guidance of the Holy Spirit. I know that is true.
</p><p>
STRENGTH TO RESIST EVIL
</p><p>
Peter admonished the young men to be careful about the sins of the world. Evil things tempt
them. Now is the time when our young men are tempted. They always have been. Some have
resisted and some have not, but those who have resisted have succeeded and are happy. It is
the happiest life. The boys of our Church who uphold the standards are the ones who are
respected and who receive honor from the men of the world as well as from those of the
Church.
</p><p>
For the benefit of those young men who have inspired us tonight and come here in such a
large body to sing the songs of the Lesser Priesthood, I am going to conclude with a story of
a boy who was not in the Church&mdash;as far as I know&mdash;but he grew in his teens and using and
using the inheritance of his father, he started in business. His father had set him a proper
example. Then he found himself in financial difficulties; and in distress he went to a friend of
his fathers, a Mr. Chaplin. "Mr. Chaplin," said the young man, "I am in distress, and I need
ten thousand dollars. Those upon whom I have depended have not paid me. Perhaps they will,
but they have not to date, and I need money. I have come to you because you knew my
father." "Come in," said Mr. Chaplin, "Have a glass of wine." "No, thank you," said the
young man, "I do not drink." "Well, come in anyhow, and have a cigar." "No, thank you, I do
not smoke." "Well, I am sorry, but I do not think I can lend you the money." "Very well,"
said the young man, "I am sorry." And he started to go out. "Wait a minute," said Mr.
Chaplin, who had just been testing him, "Come here. Your father asked me those same
questions years ago. He trusted me for five thousand dollars, and I am going to trust you for
ten or five times that amount if you want it. No, do not thank me, I owe it to your father. He
trusted me as I am trusting you, and I am just trying to pay him back."
</p><p>
Think of that, young men! Try to picture what would have happened had the boy taken his
wine and taken his tobacco, just to show off in the presence of another. An example!
</p><p>
The responsibility of keeping these young men and aiding them is started in our homes and is
never disassociated with the Priesthood.
</p><p>
God help us to be true to the testimony which is ours; give us power to discharge the
responsibility placed upon us when the Priesthood of the Almighty was placed upon our
shoulders and given to us as an eternal endowment, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
