<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">By the Word of Their Testimony</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Nathan Eldon Tanner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">N. Eldon Tanner, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 103-107</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Moyle, President Brown, President Smith, and my brethren and
sisters, I thank my Heavenly Father from the bottom of my heart for my membership in his
Church and kingdom here upon the earth, for the priesthood which I hold, and for the honor
and call that has come to me, which makes it possible for me to spend my time in the service
of the Lord, and to associate with our beloved President, a prophet of God, David O. McKay,
and these other inspired leaders who have been chosen by him to direct the activities of the
Church and to lead us in the paths of truth and righteousness.
</p><p>
I am truly grateful for the opportunity I have of attending this outstanding
conference with you, and partaking of the spirit that is here, and to be instructed and
encouraged by the wonderful messages that we have heard. As I stand before you, I feel more
keenly than I have words to express my inadequacy and humility and a need of, and I humbly
pray for, an interest in your faith and prayers as I speak to you today.
</p><p>
As approximately one seventh of all the full-time missionaries in the world are laboring in the
West European Mission, over which I have the honor to preside, and which includes the
missions of the British Isles, France, and the Netherlands, and because we have in these
missions young men and young women representing families, wards, and stakes from all parts
of Canada and the United States, I feel that I should make a brief report of their activities, the
work that is being done, and the progress that is being made in those areas.
</p><p>
First, I should like to congratulate those devoted stake and ward officers and the people in the
five stakes in England and Holland on the fine work that they are doing and the progress that
is being made. I wish to acknowledge the presence of, and welcome here today,
representatives of the stake presidencies, of the bishoprics, and stake Relief Society Presidents,
who are here from those stakes, also President and Sister Boyer of the London Temple. I am
sure that they, as the rest of us, will enjoy the spirit of this great conference and return to
their wards and stakes with a keener desire and determination and ability to carry on with the
heavy responsibilities placed upon them.
</p><p>
Also, I wish to express my deep appreciation to those unselfish, dedicated mission presidents
and their wives who are devoting every minute of their time and energy in directing the
missionary work in their several missions. To see the love and devotion which they have for
your sons and daughters who are placed under their care and direction is most encouraging
indeed. They could not show a keener interest in their own children. The help and leadership
which they give them will influence their lives for years and years to come.
</p><p>
Brother Roy M. Darley, with his organ recitals in the Hyde Park Chapel in London, is making
a great contribution to missionary work.
</p><p>
Now, regarding that wonderful corps of missionaries who are serving in these different
missions, I am happy indeed to be able to report that they are really doing a marvelous work
and a wonder in the mission field. It is most encouraging and inspiring to go from one
mission to another and hear those devoted missionaries bear their testimonies to one another
and give their reports and experiences which they have had in teaching the gospel to the
world. They are certainly to be congratulated on their enthusiasm, dedication, and their
success as they go forward in their proselyting efforts.
</p><p>
To see how humble they are, and yet how fearless and determined, reminds one of Paul as he
stood in chains before King Agrippa. Defending himself, he replied to the accusations of
Festus, "I am not mad, most noble Festus, but speak forth the words of truth and soberness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/25#25">Acts 26:25</a>),
always with the hope that those who hear might accept their message. The
results of their efforts are evident throughout the mission. In April I reported that in the
previous eighteen months the LDS membership in the British Isles had increased from
approximately 10,000 to 20,000, or nearly double. Today, I am happy to report that in these
islands we had 1,197 baptisms in July; 1,274 in August; and in September, at the present rate,
we will have over 1,400. This means that we are baptizing in the British Isles alone enough
people for four or five stakes each year.
</p><p>
But more significant than this is the fact that the church population there is being increased at
the rate of over 5 percent each month, or over 60 percent each year throughout the whole of
the British Isles, while in some local areas the increase is as high as 200 to 300 percent in one
year.
</p><p>
In France and the Netherlands the number of baptisms are also greatly increased. It is not
difficult to see that a tremendous fellowshipping program is necessary, and I am happy to
report that in these wards and branches, though many of them are new members and
though the building facilities are most inadequate, the people are accepting
the responsibility of trying to make the new converts feel at home and a part of the church
organization.
</p><p>
The building program necessary to provide the facilities for this great influx of members
presents a real problem.
</p><p>
I personally wish to congratulate the building committee and those fine men who are directing
the work on the ground, on the very efficient way in which they have organized their work
and their staffs to go forward with the program of starting a new building every week.
</p><p>
I also wish to congratulate the members in the stakes and missions on the very wonderful way
in which they have responded to this building program and in making labor missionaries
available to assist wherever new buildings are being constructed.
</p><p>
President McKay, I am happy to tell you that the people there are responding beautifully to
your call and slogan, "Every Member A Missionary," first, by striving to live lives worthy of
example, and second, by opening their homes for group teaching and inviting their friends and
neighbors and associates in to hear the gospel.
</p><p>
I should like to tell you of some of the experiences and observations that Sister Tanner and I
had in September as we met with the Saints in the stake and district conferences in the
capitals and some of the larger cities in England, France, Germany, the Netherlands, and
Belgium which I feel are significant and which helped to strengthen our testimonies and
helped us to appreciate probably more than ever before our free agency and our membership
in this great Church.
</p><p>
First, we found that wherever we went, regardless of country or city or language, there was
the same sweet spirit of devotion and willingness to accept office and give service in the
Church. As we interviewed the men in these cities for office, we told them they would be
required to live up to the standards of the Church, that it would require much of their time,
and that the responsibilities were heavy and would require sacrifice on their part.
</p><p>
All of them, though they knew that there was no remuneration but a great deal of hard work,
had only one response: "I am willing to do my best, but am I worthy?" Where in all the
world, outside of this Church, can you find this kind of dedication? It is evident that the
members of the Church are being prepared to accept and follow the admonition of James
wherein he said, ". . . be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only, deceiving your own
selves" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/22#22">James 1:22</a>).
</p><p>
Secondly, we observed that the members, when speaking to one another and when addressing
the people in meetings, referred to them, as they do all over the Church, as brothers and
sisters. This too was very significant. What a grand and glorious feeling it is to know that you
are really brothers and sisters, spirit children of God, who are interested in one another and
enjoy the fine feeling of love and brotherhood and oneness in the Church wherever you are,
regardless of whether you have known one another before or not. As the Lord has said, "I say
unto you, be one; and if ye are not one ye are not mine"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/27#27">D&amp;C 38:27</a>).
</p><p>
The third observation we made, and which is also significant and important to the members of
the Church, is that all speakers concluded their reports and talks by bearing their testimonies,
all of which were essentially the same. As Sister Tanner and I are unable to understand or
speak the language of any of the countries on the European Continent, we have to arrange for
someone not only to translate what we say to the congregation, but also to sit behind us and
give us a running commentary of what is being said by the local people.
</p><p>
While in Brussels we had an interesting experience when the district and branch presidents
were giving their reports. After two or three had spoken, and another was concluding, the
man who was sitting there translating for us said, "He is now bearing his testimony." And he
said no more. For the speakers who followed he did the same thing. This made me very
conscious of the fact that the testimonies borne by members anywhere in the Church,
regardless of who they are, or where they come from, state or imply certain
fundamental and significant truths, and that testimony bearing itself is peculiar to the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
I should like to deal briefly with three or four of the fundamentals in the testimony of a
Latter-day Saint. These testimonies include essential points of the message now being taken
by the missionaries to the world. First, that the Godhead is composed of God the Eternal
Father and his Son Jesus Christ and the Holy Ghost, and it is their testimony that God the
Eternal Father and his Son Jesus Christ are Living Beings of flesh and bones and spirit, in
whose image we are made, and that ". . . God so loved the world, that he gave his only
begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish, but have everlasting life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>),
that Jesus Christ is the Savior of the world who gave his life that all mankind
may be saved and by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the gospel work out their own
salvation and exaltation; that God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ both appeared in person
and spoke to and instructed Joseph Smith; that Joseph Smith was chosen as a Prophet of God
and that the priesthood was restored by John the Baptist and by Peter, James, and John upon
the heads of Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery; that this priesthood is the power of God
delegated to man to act in his name, and that it is now in the Church and is the authority by
which all ordinances are performed in the name of Jesus Christ; that the gospel has been
restored, and that the true Church of Jesus Christ is established; that this Church is an
organization similar in all essentials to the primitive Church set up by Christ among the Jews
with apostles and prophets, pastors and teachers, evangelists, etc.; and that we have a prophet
at the head of our Church today through whom the Lord speaks and directs his people.
</p><p>
This is the testimony of these individual members of the Church throughout the world. It is
their testimony also that the Book of Mormon, which was translated by the power of God, is
a divinely inspired record of God's dealings with the early inhabitants of the people on the
American Continent, and that it is the word of God, and as recorded on the flyleaf of the
Book of Mormon, it is "Written by way of commandment, and also by the spirit of prophecy
and of revelation&mdash;. . . to the convincing of the Jew and Gentile that Jesus is the <i>Christ</i>, the
<i>Eternal God</i>, manifesting himself unto all nations"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg">BM Title Page</a>).
</p><p>
This message is a message of peace, the plan of life and salvation, which is the message to all
the world, to accept Christ as the Savior of the world and him crucified and to follow the
admonition of Peter: "Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ
for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38#38">Acts 2:38</a>).
</p><p>
This is the reason there are 9,000 young missionaries, ranging in ages mostly from nineteen to
twenty-two years out in the world, receiving no remuneration, paying their own expenses at a
cost of more than $800,000 each month, or approximately ten million dollars each year, or
twenty million for the two to two and a half years they are in the mission field. While in the
field they will have contributed over 18,000 missionary years. They will have sacrificed
18,000 man years of schooling or otherwise productive life to teach the restored gospel, which
is the plan of life and salvation, and to bring souls unto Christ.
</p><p>
This is a service of love, with no thought of financial gain, but with an unselfish desire on the
part of these devoted young missionaries and their parents who sacrifice so much to serve
God and their fellow men.
</p><p>
The struggle in the world today and the threat of nuclear war would be averted tomorrow and
peace would reign upon the earth if the people in the world would accept this message. The
conflict in the world which threatens the free agency and life of every individual is a
continuation of the war in heaven, where Satan was determined to take away our free agency,
God's greatest gift to man.
</p><p>
As we read in the scriptures: ". . . because that Satan rebelled against me, and sought to
destroy the agency of man, which I, the Lord God, had given him, and also,
that I should give unto him mine own power; by the power of mine Only Begotten, I caused
that he should be cast down; 
</p><p>
"And he became Satan, yea, even the devil, the father of all lies, to deceive and to blind men,
and to lead them captive at his will, even as many as would not hearken unto my voice"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/3-4#3">Moses 4:3-4</a>).
</p><p>
"Wherefore, he maketh war with the saints of God, and encompasseth them round about"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/29#29">D&amp;C 76:29</a>).
</p><p>
This was so evident to me as we were in Berlin to organize a stake there. I took the
opportunity of going into East Berlin, as a tourist may if he has his proper papers. Here we
have an outstanding example of the contrast of conditions and the way of life in a divided city
where the East is under the domination of a dictator where man has been robbed of his
freedom and is now a slave of the state, and the other part of the city where he still enjoys
much of his freedom. In the West, the stores, the streets with their bright lights, the cars, the
hotels, and beautiful parks are all bustling with people who can go and come as they wish and
who are joyously and actively engaged in building and other industrial development. While in
the East under the domination of man, you see very few people on the streets, a very limited
number of cars, a drab-looking city with ruins on all sides, and the people with an attitude of
despondence, despair, and defeatism, knowing that they are at the beck and call of a foreign
anti-Christ dictator with policemen and soldiers on every side to see that they do as they are
told and that they cannot escape. Why? Is it because they are so happy and prosperous and
contented with conditions there?
</p><p>
Satan is at work, my brethren and sisters. Our freedom is at stake. It is the responsibility of
everyone who calls himself a Christian, and particularly for every member of the Church of
Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, and more particularly for every holder of the priesthood of
God, to take a firm stand and a determined stand against evil. It is my testimony to you, my
brothers and sisters, wherever you may be, that God has given us the solution to our
problems, the plan by which we can enjoy peace in the world and peace in our lives.
</p><p>
I plead with you, everyone, wherever you may be, to accept Christ as the Savior of the world
and to go forward as champions of our Heavenly Father and his cause and keep his
commandments that we may enjoy his Spirit to be with us at all times, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
