<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Engines and People</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Paul H. Dunn</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Paul H. Dunn, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 123-126</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brothers and sisters, both seen and unseen: I too am very
grateful this morning for the many blessings that are mine.  I have thrilled with this delightful
conference and the divine messages that have been delivered. Now I too seek an interest in
your prayers and your faith, that I might relate some of the things that are in my heart at this
hour.
</p><p>
<b>Stopped by a speck</b>
</p><p>
This summer I made a trip through Arizona and California. While driving with my family
across the desert and enjoying every minute of the trip, even though it was quite warm, I
suddenly became conscious of the fact that my car had lost all of its power. For a few
moments it coasted, and then at a very slight rise in the road it stopped dead still.  I looked at
the gas gauge and discovered that I had plenty of fuel; the radiator temperature was normal;
the oil level was all right; and the fan belt was still in place. So I knew that the trouble was
not in an over-heated engine.  And knowing my mechanical aptitude, I knew I was in for a
short hike.  A friendly traveler took me to a phone a couple of miles up the grade; I called a
mechanic and then had to walk back two miles to the car.  The mechanic arrived and almost
immediately sensed the difficulty; he stuck the end of a very tiny pin through a hole in one of
the parts in the engine, and the car was ready to go again. A tiny speck of dirt, so small that
it could hardly be seen by the naked eye, yet sufficient to stop the progress of five people for
two hours, cause one of us to walk two miles, and change the plans of the entire party for
that night and for the rest of the trip.
</p><p>
<b>Stopped by a false idea</b>
</p><p>
I've been thinking, since that experience, that it's not only cars and carefree travelers, but also
the work of whole institutions and the plans of communities and nations that are sometimes
held up by tiny specks of dirt&mdash;for our purposes, false philosophies or untruths that
thoughtless and sometimes scheming people place in our way.  For some reason or another
there are those who seem to feel that the highest mission they have is to undermine and
weaken the faith and belief of our youth in the reality of God, of Christ, and of his mission.
These are they whom I would call modern anti-Christs.  They are found in many walks of
life.  Some are religionists; some are teachers; others are influential community leaders.  Their
cry is like the cry of old.
</p><p>
Many years ago on this continent one of the great prophets of the Book of
Mormon, Alma, called our attention to such an anti-Christ in the form of a teacher, a
philosopher, a lecturer, a man by the name of Korihor.  Let me just give a brief quote from
that great Book of Mormon section, which sounds almost modern: "O ye that are bound down
under a foolish and a vain hope, why do ye yoke yourselves with such foolish things? Why
do ye look for a Christ? For no man can know of anything which is to come.
</p><p>
"Behold, these things which ye call prophecies, which ye say are handed down by holy
prophets, behold, they are foolish traditions of your fathers.
</p><p>
"How do ye know of their surety? Behold, ye cannot know of things which ye do not see;
therefore ye cannot know that there shall be a Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/30/13-15#13">Alma 30:13-15</a>).
</p><p>
No age in history has been exempt from such teaching or thinking.
</p><p>
<b>Faith frustrated by fear and fraud</b>
</p><p>
Gilbert Murray, in his famous description of the mood of the Roman world in the first
century of our era, used the phrase, "the failure of nerve." This failure of nerve exhibited
among other things "a rise of asceticism, of mysticism, in a sense, of pessimism; a loss of
self-confidence, of hope in this life and faith in normal human effort; and a despair of patient
inquiry." (<i>Five Stages of Greek Religion</i>, p. 119.)
</p><p>
A cursory survey of the cultural trends of our times reveals many signs of a modern failure of
nerve in western civilization and of the anti-Christs among us.  Our day is also characterized
in many quarters by pessimism, a loss of self-confidence and hope in this life, a disregard for
traditional values, and a large-scale skepticism of a belief in God and in his Son Jesus Christ
and his divine mission. Perhaps it is more accurate to say that men today are losing faith in
themselves because they have lost faith in God. Having lost faith in both God and themselves,
many of our contemporaries have no place to turn.  Much of the literature of today describes
this situation.  Such titles as <i>The Decline of Western Culture, The Predicament of Man,</i>
<i>The Annihilation of Man</i>, "The Twisted Age," "The Troubled Campus," and, if you or any sincere
thinking person can imagine, a most recent edition, <i>A Cat Called Jesus</i>, suggest something of
the posture of present-day western man.
</p><p>
Perhaps the most familiar example of the temperament of our times comes from our
university and college campuses.  Nearly every newspaper or magazine one reads today has
an article or report about the ferment within a sizable segment of our college students.  The
general reaction is to blame the colleges; and while the philosophies that are causing this
ferment are often found at their greatest height in the university environment, and while some
of the great teachers must take part of the blame, the one thing we sometimes fail to realize is
that if the proper direction were being given by the homes, communities, and, in general, the
society that produces these young people, students would not be as susceptible to these false
teachings.
</p><p>
As Milton Barron has accurately stated, the problem isn't one of juvenile delinquency, but of
the juvenile in a delinquent society.
</p><p>
<b>Youth rebellion</b>
</p><p>
Children who have grown up in a society of broken marriages and homes, of slums, of false
and misleading advertising of war, and of a general disregard for spiritual values are now
rebelling as young adults.  The sad and most distinguishing features of their resistance are
their disillusionment with their own rebellion and the absence of any redeeming ideals. Theirs
is a rebellion, not without a cause, but without a purpose.
</p><p>
It is not an unusual thing for young people to rebel.  Every new generation has its rebels. 
But a rebellion of sad young people with little confidence in their own rebellion is something
quite unique.  One needs only to have a brief exposure to a university environment to witness
the demonstrations of rejection against proven values. Beards, long hair, grubby clothes,
sit-ins, and the lack of restraint in matters of alcohol, chastity, and drugs are
merely the symptoms of the problem that is, at its deepest level, a spiritual problem.
</p><p>
It seems to me that the pessimism and frustration of our time, particularly among our
students, are not due to any lack of commitment, but rather to the absence of a faith in
anything worthy of one's commitment. And this in turn is due to the lack of faith in God,
which alone gives any ultimate meaning, value, or lasting purpose to man's existence or
actions.
</p><p>
It is when this lack of purpose is found that the anti-Christ makes his appeal.  Here is a
typical statement: "I'm less and less inclined to believe that religion is a necessary thing."
This is a quote from a minister of one of our prominent faiths, made to a large college
audience in which I was recently in attendance.  Within the last few months this statement
came from a college professor and appeared in a widely circulated campus newspaper:
"Nobody believes in God.  God is dead.  The God of the long beard and the arm six cubits
long has been dead for a long time. He's stinking up the whole western world in refusing to
get buried."
</p><p>
<b>Compounded by confusion</b>
</p><p>
Is it any wonder that many young people are confused?  Thirteen years' experience in
working directly on university and college campuses has proven to me that these statements
are not isolated but are quite common in the experience of college youth.  However, students
for the most part don't learn their atheism and doctrines of uncertainty from the philosophies
they study in school.  These philosophies only make articulate a latent and unexpressed way
of life that they have learned all too well in the home and from the society that nurtured
them.
</p><p>
One professor, in describing the condition of some of his students, said, "Lacking an
embracing cause and a fervent ideology, the students' search for a durable purpose is likely to
become aggressive, extremist, at times despairing. It can easily turn into preoccupation with
subjective feelings and plain egoism. Paradoxical as it sounds, the real problem of our college
youth is to discover some authority, both private and public that will make possible authentic
individuality." (J. Glenn Gray, <i>Harpers</i>, May 1965, p. 54.)
</p><p>
The professor further states, "But before we succeed in building the great society, we shall
need to resolve the doubt and bafflement about its validity and worth in the minds of those
now in college who should serve as its leaders.  Many of the harassed young men and women
I teach, at any rate, have not decided what sense, if any, their existence has." (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 59.)
</p><p>
<b>Confused youth needs identity with divine power</b>
</p><p>
What alienated youth of today need most is a self-definition, a feeling of identity, and a sense
of belonging&mdash;indeed, a sense of belonging to a universe which, at its core, is not hostile or
indifferent to man's highest values, hopes, and longings.  What youth need today is a faith
and a confidence that the things that matter most are not at the mercy of the things that matter
least; that man is not simply an "accidental arrangement of atoms," but a child of the living
God who gives meaning and purpose to existence, not only in ultimate terms but also in terms
of the problems of the here and now.
</p><p>
The principles of the restored gospel are the surest, safest guide to mortal man.  Christ is the
light to humanity. In that light man sees his way clearly; when it is rejected, the soul of man
stumbles in darkness.  No person, no group, no nation can achieve true success without
following him who said, ". . . I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk
in darkness, but shall have the light of life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Human life is full of purpose and meaning</b>
</p><p>
As members of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, we bear witness to the
troubled youth of today that God is real and that he lives, that he has
concern for you and for me and for the world, that the world is a moral order, and that man's
life is purposeful and meaningful.
</p><p>
We reject the inherent pessimism of humanism and fundamentalism alike; we reject the
negativism of existentialism as the logical extension of a thorough-going atheism. We
proclaim that "man is that he might have joy" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>); we therefore look upon the despair and melancholia of our day as abnormal and unnatural.
</p><p>
We believe that the only real cure for this spiritual sickness, which I have described as a
"failure of nerve," is to be found in a faith that looks upon God and man as real partners in
the task of creating a better world.  And we believe that man's contributions to that
partnership make a real difference to the final outcome.
</p><p>
<b>Alliance with Jesus Christ</b>
</p><p>
We believe that the peace and happiness of mankind lie in the acceptance of Jesus Christ as
Redeemer and Savior, and that there is "none other name under heaven given among men,
whereby we [may] be saved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>).
</p><p>
We believe that to declare this faith is our greatest responsibility, and for the moment it is
man's greatest need. And we bear added testimony, my brothers and sisters, wherever you are,
that in the life, death, and resurrection of Jesus Christ, God our Father, in whom our faith
resides, was revealed to the world. We believe that it is only with this kind of meaning that
man can give himself wholeheartedly and courageously to the solution of our current
problems.  "And now, after the many testimonies which have been given of him, this is the
testimony, last of all, which we give of him: That he lives!" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/22#22">D&amp;C 76:22</a>). And I know this
from the inner whisperings of the Spirit from on high, and I hear this testimony humbly and
gratefully in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
