<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Participation: The Way to Salvation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 89-92</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren and fellow workers: 
</p><p>
Of the many groups we are asked to address from time to time, there is none more inspiring,
but more humbling, than this body of priesthood, thousands of whom we can see and
probably tens of thousands whom we cannot see. One approaches the responsibility of a few
moments talk with deep humility and a prayer for divine guidance. I shall speak for a few
minutes only, as we are all anxious to hear from President McKay.
</p><p>
I certainly congratulate Brother Lee on his excellent presentation of a difficult program, which
has taken the committee several years to work out. He has been trying to get us to see it in
just a few minutes and has done a very good job of compressing into those few minutes what
could well occupy several hours.
</p><p>
Among other things I have been impressed by the fact that it is not easy to be a Latter-day
Saint. I notice these charts call for work, work, work on the part of all concerned. In some
churches, one man, as has already been indicated, does most of the work. In this Church all of
us are expected to participate.
</p><p>
Another thing that impressed me as I listened to Brother Lee's explanation of this program
that will be carried forward under the direction of the President of the Church is that it
provides opportunity for everyone who is willing to make some contribution to the cause. We
recognize in the Church a cause which is greater and more important than we are as
individuals, and in it we enjoy the fellowship of our brethren who hold the priesthood. Unless
we with them can cooperate in advancing that cause we shall not make a success of this
program. We should all give to this committee not only a vote of thanks by expressing it in
words but a vote of appreciation by putting into operation the work as here outlined and as it
will be more fully explained as we go forward. Let no one of us feel or say or think that the
brethren are just trying to find something more for us to do&mdash;don't think that because they
are&mdash;they are trying to find something for us to do because they know there is only one way
to salvation, that is by active participation.
</p><p>
In all teaching&mdash;and one of the functions of the priesthood is teaching&mdash;what the teacher is
counts for more than what he says. What we are as members of the priesthood and as
missionaries in the field, at home or abroad, means more to those to whom we go than what
we teach. So my first thought is, let us be what we teach. The teacher and the truth taught
should be of the same pattern. Let each one be an example to all whose lives we touch; let us
recognize in all of our fellow workers some value, some worth, and never forget that each
one of them has a heart, has feelings, has ambition, has a certain amount of pride; therefore,
let us never by virtue of the priesthood or the positions we hold trample on the rights or the
feelings of our fellow men; let us never be sharp in what we say to them by way of criticism,
but let us be kindly, considerate, and have in our hearts a love for our fellow
men, for in each one of them there is value.
</p><p>
I read something this morning I'd like to leave with you. Every human life has in it more or
less gold which is usually not readily apparent to the casual observer. Kindness is a part of
that gold, the gold of the spirit, that part which is known to others because it has lessened
their burdens and made their pathways lovelier. The man who has gold in his life has
something that is bigger than anything that can happen to him. He doesn't worry about
defeats or obstacles or sorrows, for he knows these are but froth on the river of life to last but
a brief time and then be blown away. What matters is not the froth, but the strong, pulsating,
ongoing current in the river, which is never disturbed by the leaves floating up at the quiet
eddies of the surface. One day you may find that your house of life has collapsed, but in the
wreckage you may find the gold which cannot be destroyed. not by the worst disaster, for the
gold of life is imperishable and immortal. Search for it in the wreckage, for out of it you can
mint new coins. Out of defeat arises the gold of life.
</p><p>
Priesthood involves presidency, authority, and power; it involves the right and duty under
certain circumstances to reprove others. You remember what the Prophet said, "Reproving
betimes with sharpness . . . and then showing forth . . . increase of love"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/43#43">D&amp;C 121:43</a>). Let
us be very careful about this matter of reproving, and yet part of our duty is to see that there
is no iniquity in the Church (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/54#54">D&amp;C 20:54</a>).
Again I say, let us be careful how we trample on the feelings of
our brothers and sisters. Let us lift them and bless them and benefit them as we go forward
and never be guilty of humiliating them or causing them to think that we do not appreciate
their work.
</p><p>
The next thought I'd like to leave with you is that we must not be deceived by the boom in
numbers and dollars and buildings going on in the Church. We thank the Lord for them, but
they are not the main part of our work. All we need to say on that is that the body without
the spirit is dead (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/26#26">James 2:26</a>).
</p><p>
As we go forward in the special work of the priesthood, which is missionary work both for
the living and the dead, and as we carry the gospel to our friends who are not members of the
Church, let us try to keep things in proper balance. The revealed order is faith and then
repentance and then baptism. A Baptist minister was heard to say about some of his own
people recently that the church had recruited some people who had been starched and ironed
before they were washed. I think we might take a lesson from that thought and convert the
people before we baptize them.
</p><p>
Let us read from the Doctrine and Covenants with respect to priesthood. This is a section with
which you are more or less familiar, but I never hesitate to refer again to that which has been
referred to so often any more than I would hesitate to invite a friend to come to my table
when I had only the things that we usually serve at the table. We do not complain much
because we do not have something different at every meal. We enjoy that which is set before
us if we have an appetite for it. The Lord said: 
</p><p>
". . . whoso is faithful unto the obtaining these two priesthoods of which I have spoken, and
the magnifying their calling, are sanctified by the Spirit unto the renewing of their bodies"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/33#33">D&amp;C 84:33</a>).
</p><p>
Brethren, I bear testimony to the fact that that promise has been realized in the lives of many
of us. I know that it has been realized in the life of President David  O. McKay, that he has
been sanctified by the Spirit unto the renewing of his body, and some of the rest of us are
better off today than we were many years ago so far as physical health is concerned&mdash;and we
attribute that fact to his blessing.
</p><p>
"They become the sons of Moses and of Aaron and the seed of Abraham, and the church and
kingdom, and the elect of God.
</p><p>
". . . also all they who receive this priesthood receive me, saith the Lord; 
</p><p>
"For he that receiveth my servants receiveth me; 
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth me receiveth my Father; 
</p><p>
"And he that receiveth my Father receiveth my Father's kingdom; therefore all that my Father
hath shall be given unto him.
</p><p>
"And this is according to the oath and covenant which belongeth to the priesthood.
</p><p>
"Therefore, all those who receive the priesthood, receive this oath and covenant of my Father,
which he cannot break, neither can it be moved"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/34-40#34">D&amp;C 84:34-40</a>).
</p><p>
It is important that we consider occasionally the oath and the covenant which each of us has
taken. All who have been baptized and all who hold the priesthood are under covenant to do
and refrain from doing certain things. We must remember and keep our covenants, one of
which is that we be willing to give of ourselves, our means and all that we have to the
upbuilding of the Church and kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Young fellow workers, deacons and teachers and priests, we who are growing older have
great confidence in you, based upon what we believe to be a fact, that you would not now be
holding the priesthood unless God had thought you worthy of it and unless he had something
for you to do. Each one of you young men who is listening tonight has a future. What that
future is to be will depend upon your attitude toward your calling, your faith in yourselves,
your belief that there is some gold in you. It is important that you young men and all of us
try to refine that gold by active participation and not wait until the house is burned down, and
we have passed through the fire. It is very important that every young man make up his mind
that he is going to respond to the voice of conscience, that he is going to be true to himself
and not yield to the down-drag of any environment in which he may find himself.
</p><p>
May I tell a story to illustrate the point that a man must respond to his better self if he is
going to be a worthy holder of the priesthood. The story is told that the Arabians, when they
are training their horses, put them to a final test of character and stamina. It is said that the
finest of the Arabian horses which are kept for breeding stock are trained from the time they
are colts to respond to a bell which rings intermittently at the tent of the master. Wherever
they are and whatever they are doing, they must run to the tent of the master when the bell
rings. Their mothers were taught it before them, and they respond, and the colt, running
beside the mother, habitually as time goes on responds to the bell and knows that it is the call
of duty. When the colts are three years old, they are placed in a corral, a pole corral that they
can see through. They are left there three days and nights without food or water. At the end
of the third day hay and grain and water are placed just outside the corral. You can imagine
the eagerness of the young colts as they look through the bars at the food and water. When
the gate is opened the young colts rush out, and just as they are about to reach the food and
water, the bell rings. Only those of them that have stamina enough to respond to the bell and
resist the urge of appetite are kept for the breeding stock of the future.
</p><p>
Brethren, as we go forward, we become increasingly aware of the fact that there is a bell
which rings very frequently throughout life. Sometimes men become unresponsive or hard of
hearing and disregard the bell to their own sorrow. You young men are going to hear it many
times between now and the time you are our age. We plead with you to resist the call of
appetite and passion and hearken to the bell which is your conscience. If you are tempted to
do wrong, there will always be something within you saying, "Don't do it." Hearken and
respond to that bell, and you will be worthy of the confidence that the President of the
Church has in you, worthy to take over the responsibilities now held by your fathers, your
brothers, your leaders.
</p><p>
God bless you and all of us that we may co-operate with the General Authorities, with the
stake and ward and mission authorities, and be responsive to their
admonitions. The Church&mdash;your Church and my Church is growing in numbers and influence
with an accelerating speed beyond anything that we who are older could have imagined in our
youth. I am grateful for and testify to the truth of the restored gospel in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
