<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">As We Labor We Are Blessed</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Oscar A. Kirkham</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Oscar A. Kirkham, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 45-47</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I humbly pray that the Lord will bless me.  I take the privilege of letting my first words be those
of appreciation.  I bear my testimony to the truthfulness of the gospel of Jesus Christ.  I pray
daily to a personal God.  I bear testimony to the divine mission of Jesus Christ, of Joseph
Smith, and of President David O. McKay.  I never utter these words and bear this testimony
but something fine, something worthy within me swells my bosom and makes me proud, and
yet extremely humble.
</p><p>
I am grateful for this song, "Come, come, ye Saints" that has just been sung.  It truly is a
classic among the Latter-day Saint people.  And if President Clark will permit, I would love
to read part of his eloquent tribute to this glorious, west land of pioneers.  After expressing himself in his
book, <i>To Them of the Last Wagon</i>, he finishes with these words: 
</p><p>
Log cabins grew into adobe houses and these into buildings of brick and stone.  A mighty
Temple, dedicated to the work of the lord, rose in their midst, carved from the granite of
canyon walls, the first of eight that this people were to build to the salvation of their dead.  
Meetinghouses everywhere welcomed the worshiper. Stores, banks, factories, mines, mills,
smelters, came into being.  Flocks and herds peopled the ranges.  Schools and colleges came
early and multiplied.  The hive of industry became the symbol of a great commonwealth. 
Faith and strength and righteousness bore their fruit of comfort and safety and the joy of
living.
</p><p>
All through the years the people have been blessed, even in their most dire need, blessed, they
feel, beyond all other peoples on earth&mdash;blessed in their right to get and safely to keep the
fruits of their own labors: blessed in their right peaceably to assemble, to discuss their
grievances, to speak fully their minds, to print without let or hindrance what they thought and
said: blessed to live under a reign of law and order: blessed to worship God according to the
dictates of their consciences under the law of the land.
</p><p>
So we honor these men and women of iron will, of surpassing spirituality, of a trusting,
living, simple faith.  They have done their work: they have earned their reward, which God is
bestowing upon them. None can rob them of the fruits of their labors.  They are secure.
</p><p>
And now the natural, obvious question: 
</p><p>
What of us?  Can we keep and preserve what they wrought?  Shall we pass on to our children
the heritage they left us, or shall we lightly fritter it away?  Have we their faith? . . . Can we
do the thousands of little and big things that made them the heroic builders of a great church,
a great commonwealth?  (<i>To Them of the Last Wagon</i>, pp. 43-45.)
</p><p>
I bow in reverence, I humbly pray it shall ever be kept alive within my heart, a deep and
abiding appreciation for that glorious sacrifice of men and women.  I caught a bit of the spirit
of it last month when I toured the Southwest Indian Mission.  It was great to be down on the
San Juan, down on the Colorado.  It was great to see far-off on the cliff yonder, miles away,
to see four great stalwart trees that the Pioneers had planted years ago. It humbled me greatly
to stand at the graveside of those who sacrificed in the opening up of that great western
country. Somehow I wished that I might have lived with them.
</p><p>
One day on this recent trip of the Southwest Indian Mission, a Navajo Indian boy, with a
group of his little friends, was being taken to Southern California to live for the winter in the
comfortable homes of Latter-day Saint people, to enjoy their hospitality and spiritual
friendship.  One little fellow with a little shattered suitcase was crying while his Navajo
mother was drying her eyes, yet stoically standing by his side without a word to say, and
another son, not so small, he was about sixteen years of age, courageously stood by. Great
things have been accomplished by the boys of fourteen, fifteen, and sixteen: these are great
years in a young man's life, and "Benjamin," the older Navajo boy, put his hand on the head
of his little brother and said, "We don't cry." That was all.  The little fellow braced himself to
what was to him a great task, leaving mother and the other children.  They drove away to a
new home.
</p><p>
Thank God for "Come, come, ye Saints." Thank God for the people who pioneered the great
wasteland of the Southwest and in many places restored it.  I have in my heart also great
gratitude toward the leadership of these early days in our Church.
</p><p>
When Brigham Young and Joseph Smith met for the first time, here are the words describing
that meeting: 
</p><p>
We proceeded to Kirtland and stopped at John P. Greene's, who had just arrived there with
his family. We rested a few minutes, took some refreshments and started to see the Prophet.
We went to his father's house and learned that he was in the woods chopping. We
immediately repaired to the woods, where we found the Prophet, and two or three of his
brothers, chopping and hauling wood.  Here my joy was full [said Brigham Young] at the
privilege of shaking the hand of the Prophet of God, and receiving the sure testimony, by the
spirit of prophecy, that he was all that any man could believe him to be as a true prophet
(<i>DHC</i>, I, p. 297, Note).
</p><p>
Greatness meets chopping wood.  No pomp, no ceremony!  Brigham Young receives the true
testimony.
</p><p>
Be thou humble; and the Lord thy God shall lead thee by the hand, and give thee answer to thy
prayers (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/10#10">D&amp;C 112:10</a>).
</p><p>
May I note other great attributes of the Latter-day Saint people:
<i>A great heritage, a humble, noble leadership; an all-participating membership.</i>  My, how we should thrill.  It was inspiring
to me yesterday, when President McKay said: "Every member of this Relief Society Singing
Mothers Chorus has one other Church service job besides singing in this chorus." How lovely
it is&mdash;<i>nearly all members participating</i>.  That is the Latter-day Saint way.
</p><p>
Drive on the hillside here in Salt Lake City, if you have not done it before, and see the
Primary Hospital, built for little children.  It is a beautiful structure, and as you drive along
think of its being built by pennies and the love of people and children&mdash;<i>an all-participating membership!</i>
</p><p>
Finally, these few words: The great objective, said President Richards to us the other day, of
this conference, is the building of the kingdom of God on earth.  Yes, missionaries by the
thousands, the welfare program reaching out its aims to help and bless, temples being erected
throughout the world, as we labor we are blessed.
</p><p>
"There are bridges, young men and young women, to be built, and we will build them.  There
are houses to make and we will light their windows. There are those who suffer, and we will
ease their sorrow.  There are divine blessings ever hovering about us."
</p><p>
I humbly pray that we may worthily continue these great blessings, in the name of Jesus
Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
