<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">What Shall I Do to Inherit Eternal Life?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder ElRay L. Christiansen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">ElRay L. Christiansen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1955, pp. 121-123</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I am so grateful, my brothers and sisters, for the blessings that have come to me from this
conference.  I have thought of it in this way: "If thy brother ask thee to go with him one
mile, go with him twain" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/41#41">Matt. 5:41</a>).
As someone put it: "The first is an obligation; the
second, a consecration."
</p><p>
I have made up my mind that henceforth, because of the marvelous things that have been said
here, I will be more determined to dedicate that which I have in the way of energy and
substance to the work of the Lord here upon the earth&mdash;more determined than I have ever
been before.
</p><p>
It seems to me that the life of a Latter-day Saint is intended to be a life of dedication and of
consecration to the things of God.  The gospel of Jesus Christ is a program for the perfecting
of the individual member by his adherence to the principles of that gospel.  It is designed to
teach us to forget ourselves, to be unselfish.  I have come to think that selfishness on the part
of those of us who are inclined that way is one of the great deterrents to our progress and to
the realization of a divine destiny.  Let us be determined to overcome selfishness and personal
aggrandizement by sharing with others that which we have, by dedicating ourselves to the
work at hand which we have to do, through dedication of our talents, our time, our substance,
our tithes, and our offerings, our love, our goodness and kindness one to another, always
seeing the good that always may be found in others.
</p><p>
When we partake of the sacrament, brothers and sisters, we presumably take upon us the
name of Christ.  We agree to do as he would do, to act as he would act: 
</p><p>
. . . by love serve one another.
</p><p>
For all the law is fulfilled in one word, even in this; Thou shalt love thy neighbour as
thyself (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/5/13-14#13">Gal. 5:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
The reward of unselfish service has been told us by the Lord when he has said that ". . .
whosoever will save his life shall lose it: and whosoever will lose his life for my sake [I take
it, in his service and the service of his fellow men] shall find it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/25#25">Matt. 16:25</a>). The sweetness
and the joy of life is found when we are willing to deny ourselves for the good and the
benefit of others.  Service to others, service in the Church, giving of our substance, is part of
the life of a Latter-day Saint.  We are taught that sacrifice brings forth the blessings of
heaven.  In no other way, as I see it, can the Lord raise up a people who will be fit for the
kingdom, who will have it ready for his coming. By offering himself as a sacrifice for the
sins of the world and the redemption of mankind from death, Jesus set an incomparable
example to us in the way of sacrifice and of love for others.
</p><p>
Again, when Abraham and Sarah were commanded of the Lord&mdash;requested at least&mdash;to give
as a sacrifice their son Isaac (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/22/2#2">Gen. 22:2</a>),
we can imagine what must have gone through their minds.
Nevertheless, they met the test. The Lord did it to see how much they loved him. Abraham
was sustained, I am sure, by an unwavering trust in God. I am sure that Abraham knew that
to accomplish his purposes, God could, if he desired, raise up Isaac from the dead, even after
he had died. But what a lesson that is in service, of dedication, of consecration of that which
he dearly loved!  No wonder that Abraham was called a "friend of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/23#23">James 2:23</a>).
</p><p>
An opportunity to demonstrate his love of the Lord was given to another man.  He had great possessions,
and he had a chance to test his unselfishness when he asked of the Lord, "What shall I do to
inherit eternal life?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/25#25">Luke 10:25</a>).
Now this man had done many good things. He had kept
most of the commandments, I understand, but he had become selfish because of his great
possessions.  Evidently he thought more of them than he did of eternal life, because when told
by the Savior that in order to gain eternal life he should sell whatsoever he had and give to
the poor and take up the cross and follow him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/21#21">Mark 10:21</a>), he was sad, and according to the record, ". . .
went away grieved: for he had great possessions"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/10/22#22">Mark 10:22</a>). He had not learned the
meaning of dedication and of consecration.
</p><p>
Contrast this man with a certain poor widow who cast into the treasury her two mites, which
made a farthing&mdash;all that she had. Her contribution amounted to very little in monetary
value, about one half of a penny of our money, but it was not the smallness of her offering
that made it especially acceptable unto the Lord as he witnessed her placing her money in the
treasury, but it was the spirit of sacrifice that she had shown.  As he observed others throwing
their money into the treasury, the record states: 
</p><p>
. . . he called unto his disciples, and saith unto them, Verily I say unto you, that this
poor widow hath cast more in, than all they which have cast into the treasury: 
</p><p>
For all they did cast in of their abundance; but she of her want did cast in all that she
had, even all her living (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/12/43-44#43">Mark 12:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
Dedication, it seems to me, in some form, is the real essence of all religion. Dedication to the
will of the Lord and to his work is the religion of the Latter-day Saints.  In this dispensation
of the gospel, thousands have met the test when called upon to sacrifice their personal
positions, their time, and even their lives, in order to establish and defend the kingdom of
God upon the earth.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith permitted himself to be taken by the mob and be put to death, and
along with him, Hyrum, whose life was lost by an assassin's bullet, and in the same room at
the same time, Dr. Willard Richards and John Taylor, who refused to leave him, and Dan
Jones, and others who were loyal and devoted and would have given their lives gladly in
preference to the Prophet's life.  They set an example for us in this dispensation! There is
scarcely an end to the list of those who have done likewise or who stand now willing to do
all that is required of them.  A spirit of dedication, willingness to serve in any capacity and to
sacrifice, if necessary, characterizes the true Latter-day Saint.
</p><p>
It was not long ago that I was in one of the stakes in southern Idaho.  I was asked to
interview five young men between twenty-five and thirty-five years of age, most of them
married and having one or two children, to see if they were ready to receive an office in the
Melchizedek Priesthood for which they had been recommended. I received the thrill of my
life.  Somehow, I decided&mdash;I don't know whether I made a mistake or not&mdash;but I decided to
see what the depth of their willingness to sacrifice was.  As each one came into the room, I
sat down with him, introduced myself, and became better acquainted with him. Then I stated
that the Church had acquired a great tract of land in Brush Creek and wished to prepare it for
settlement for the Saints.  The water had to be brought on to it, the brush had to be cleared
and the land leveled, homes built, schools erected, and all things must be done from scratch. 
It will be no easy thing. I said: "If you were asked to go, would take your wife and family
and leave what you have and go to Brush Creek and settle it?" Every one of those young men
said yes.
</p><p>
I said: "What would your wife think about it?" In every case they said, in effect, "I am sure
she would feel as I do, that if the Church required it, we would go." Then I explained that I
had concocted the story.
</p><p>
I felt like putting my arms around each of those young men. I commended them, and then I
got down on my knees, and I thanked the Lord for such young men of this day who were
ready to dedicate, to consecrate, to leave all that they had and go, no matter where they may
be called to go and build up Zion. That is the test that we all should be ready to meet.
</p><p>
There is a veritable army of men and women such as these in the quorums, in the missions,
and in the wards and stakes, and in all places, where they serve without a thought of
compensation. There is no end to the list&mdash;the ward teachers, who do good jobs, all of those
who serve, all of you.  It is commendable, and it must be pleasing in the sight of the Lord. 
Among them, not to be overlooked, are those much unnoticed, unsung men and women, who
day after day, month after month, year after year, labor in the temples of the Lord, giving
vicarious service on behalf of the dead.  Along with them are those who do research work,
hiding behind desks and files, where nobody knows about them, spending hours and money
and time and energy that the work might be perfected.  It is one thing, you know, to do
something for those who can return the goodness and who can thank you, but these people&mdash;this
great arm of those who do vicarious service, with do not expect a return in thanks, at this
time at least&mdash;I think win our most sincere commendation and our admiration for that type of
dedication.
</p><p>
Paul has said that ". . . He which soweth sparingly shall reap also sparingly; and he which
soweth bountifully shall reap also bountifully.
</p><p>
". . . let him give, not grudgingly, or of necessity: for God loveth a cheerful giver"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/9/6-7#6">2 Cor. 9:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
With the Apostle Paul, brothers and sisters, let us say, as we go from this conference,
</p><p>
For I am persuaded, that neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor
powers, nor things present, nor things to come,
</p><p>
Nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate us from the love of
God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/8/38-39#38">Rom. 8:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
May it be so with us.  I testify that this is the work of God; that his power is within this
Church&mdash;the power to bring redemption to the dead and salvation to the living, and I am
honored to be affiliated with the membership of this Church and to do my little bit in
furthering the work.  God bless you and keep you and comfort you when you need comfort, I
pray humbly, in the name of Jesus Christ, our Lord.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
