<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">God Intervenes in Human Affairs</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1952, pp. 111-113</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: I trust and I pray that the good spirit which has been present
throughout these conference sessions may continue with us during the few moments I stand
here. I am convinced that there is something greater than man's wisdom back of the great
conference system, which was inaugurated by Joseph Smith, the Prophet in the early days of
the Church. We have come here, you and I, to be refreshed and to be strengthened; to be
edified and reassured in our faith. We have never gone away disappointed. The Lord has
blessed his people abundantly and will continue to bless them in the future. Who can estimate
the influence and the spiritual power which emanate from these inspiring conference sessions?
We come here full of eagerness and anticipation; we listen to the sermons, to the fervent
prayers, to the music and the songs of Zion, to the stirring hymns sung by the congregation
and last but not least to the anthems and the renditions by our great choir. We are deeply
touched and uplifted. Surely, it is good to belong to a Church that is progressive, farseeing,
and inspirational in its program&mdash;a program that is calculated to prepare us as members for
the eventualities which are sure to come.
</p><p>
We recognize and are aware of a similar power and influence emanating
from the missionary system of the Church. Who can measure the influence of just one
missionary who goes into the world to proclaim the gospel message? The missionary spirit
which rests upon him, somehow or other, reaches out to the home from which he comes, to
his relatives and friends and to all with whom he comes in contact. His life becomes a great
missionary force in the world.
</p><p>
The Latter-day Saints believe in a God who is not only the Creator, but who is also the Ruler
of the universe. He intervenes in great crises when God's plan is in jeopardy and his divine
purposes are threatened. I recall, as an example, an incident in the Civil War. It occurred
when the Confederates brought out the strange battleship known as the <i>Merrimac</i>. The people
of the North were alarmed. The advisers of Lincoln became hysterical. Fear and apprehension
took hold of the people. Many complaints came to President Lincoln. "They will shoot down
the Capitol," they said. He replied, "God will not permit it. This is his fight." I am sure
Lincoln prayed. I feel certain he trusted in God, for on one occasion he is reported to have
said, "I have been driven to my knees with the overwhelming conviction that I had nowhere
else to go." Lincoln's prayer was answered, because on a beautiful morning, there appeared in
the same waters opposite the nation's Capitol, another strange battleship. It was John
Ericson's <i>Monitor</i>. The battle that ensued between these two ships was not unlike the battle
between David and Goliath. The <i>Merrimac</i> was defeated as was the great giant, Goliath.
</p><p>
I recall, four years ago, driving through the ruined city of Dunkirk, the city which has become
famous in world history, because it has suffered ruin and devastation so many times. As we
drove through the city, I remember the road led us along a narrow canal. On the right of us
lay the ruined city, almost entirely destroyed, on the left was the open country over which the
German army approached. Three hundred and fifty thousand British soldiers lay with their
backs to the ocean behind improvised fortifications. It looked like annihilation, capture, or
defeat for the British army, but at the crucial moment when Britain's soldiers needed help, the
God of heaven intervened. What happened? At that moment, a dark, black mist settled down
directly over the narrow canal. All visibility disappeared and military operations ceased. How
long? Just long enough for Britain's soldiers to escape and make their way across the channel
to English shores. I firmly believe that the Almighty can and does intervene in great crises for
the benefit of his children, especially when freedom and liberty are at stake.
</p><p>
Another incident is recorded in world history. It happened in the year 1588 when King Philip
of Spain sent his "invincible armada" out to destroy the inferior British navy. The British
navy was no match for the powerful Spanish fleet of one hundred and twenty ships armed and
equipped for battle. Once again the Almighty came to the rescue of the British. At the right
moment a storm arose on the high seas, and the Spanish fleet was scattered. A few of them
made their way into the French harbor of Calais, but were forced to leave. They were
eventually overtaken and destroyed by the British. Thus the tyranny of Spain came to an end,
and a new era in human history was begun. Do you question this intervention of God who
presides over the destiny of nations?
</p><p>
When President Levi Edgar Young and Bishop Joseph L. Wirthlin referred to Christopher
Columbus as the discoverer of the New World, I thought of him standing high on his little
craft fighting and defying, not only the elements and the turbulent waves, but also the
superstition and ignorance of his crew to discharge his God-appointed mission. It was no
accident that he was permitted to reach the shores of San Salvador in the flimsy vessels he
had at his disposal. He was right when he said he was "moved by the Holy
Ghost" to achieve his ambition (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/12#12">1 Ne. 13:12</a>).
And thus a new world, new opportunities, and new ideas were
given to men to be developed and to be used for God's purposes. Neither can we doubt that
Brigham Young, prophet, statesman, and colonizer, was similarly called and inspired in his
great pioneer achievement. He and his people were protected in their migrations. By every
law of probability they should have perished in the desert. But they did not perish, for God's
protection was upon them.
</p><p>
I pray that we may appreciate our membership in the Church and that we may be true and
faithful to the standards by which we are guided. An investigator once said to me, "Your
Church is the only Church on the face of the earth that advocates high standards and noble
ideals." His conclusion I hope, was not correct, but we must preserve the standards, the ideals,
and the faith committed to us through Jesus Christ. May we do so, I pray in his name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
