<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1960, pp. 15-19</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren, this is a great privilege and indeed a great responsibility. I ask very humbly and
sincerely for an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
Victor Hugo once wrote, "There is nothing in the world so powerful as an idea whose time
has come." I say the time to strike is here. The foundation for a new era in proselyting
throughout the world has been laid for these many years past. This work involves all of
us&mdash;Priesthood, Auxiliary organizations, and newly converted members. Through united action
the revealed gospel of Jesus Christ can be presented to the world.
</p><p>
We are indeed preparing for the Second Coming of Christ. This is the Dispensation of the
Fulness of Times. We have the task of representing our Heavenly Father in this preparation.
We have as tools all that has gone before in all generations of time, including the revelation
given to Enos <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/enos/1/10#10">Enos 1:10</a>.
In Section 27 of the Doctrine and Covenants we read, speaking of
the Priesthood of the Church, what the Lord has said: "Unto whom I have committed the keys
of my kingdom, and a dispensation of the gospel for the last times; and for the fulness of
times, in the which I will gather together in one all things, both which are in heaven, and
which are on earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/13#13">D&amp;C 27:13</a>).
</p><p>
And in the 124th Section we read: "For I deign to reveal unto my church things which have
been kept hid from before the foundation of the world, things that pertain to the dispensation
of the fulness of times" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/41#41">D&amp;C 124:41</a>).
</p><p>
President John Taylor once said, "Where the Kingdom of God is not there is nothing." Let me
paraphrase this statement of Victor Hugo's which I read in the beginning: "There is nothing in
the world so powerful as truth whose time has come," and that is exactly the position in
which we find ourselves in the Church today. I do not know where we can find a more
wonderful description of the world today and the need for the work and the power, loyalty
and devotion of the Priesthood than we do in the 84th Section of the Doctrine and Covenants:
</p><p>
"And the whole world lieth in sin, and groaneth under darkness and under the bondage of sin.
</p><p>
"And by this you may know they are under the bondage of sin, because they
come not unto me.
</p><p>
"For whoso cometh not unto me is under the bondage of sin.
</p><p>
"And whoso receiveth not my voice is not acquainted with my voice, and is not of me.
</p><p>
"And by this you may know the righteous from the wicked, and that the whole world
groaneth under sin and darkness even now" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/49-53#49">D&amp;C 84:49-53</a>).
</p><p>
It is our responsibility as brethren holding the Priesthood of God to bring light and knowledge
and understanding into the lives of people who thus live in darkness. They are literally our
brothers and sisters, the children of our Heavenly Father. And especially is it our task not
alone to call the world to repentance, but to seek out those who are striving after light and
after knowledge and after understanding, and to give to them the gospel of Jesus Christ and
instill in their hearts a courage to accept the same and lend obedience thereto.
</p><p>
This thought has come to me: That in the very act of calling those in darkness to repentance,
we may perform a service which will not wholly mature in mortality. I think that this
quotation from the 76th Section of the Doctrine and Covenants explains clearly what I mean.
</p><p>
"And also they who are the spirits of men kept in prison, whom the Son visited, and preached
the gospel unto them, that they might be judged according to men in the flesh; 
</p><p>
"Who received not the testimony of Jesus in the flesh, but afterwards received it.
</p><p>
"These are they who are honorable men of the earth, who were blinded by the craftiness of
men.
</p><p>
"These are they who receive of his glory, but not of his fulness"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/73-76#76">D&amp;C 76:73-76</a>).
</p><p>
I remember that President Ivins once preached the gospel to a very good man&mdash;good in his
own way&mdash;and I heard this good man say more than once before he passed away that
President Ivins had converted him to all of the principles of the Church save one&mdash;the
principle of tithing. Except for that principle he would have joined the Church. I believe he
was one of those who received not the testimony of Jesus in the flesh. He was an honorable
man, but he was blinded by the craftiness, and I might add, the pride of men.
</p><p>
And so as we go about in our missionary work with the living, there is at least the possibility
that we might make it easier for those who have passed into the Spirit World to accept the
benefits of that which we do for them vicariously in the temples of the Lord, whereas without
that experience that might not be the case. So we need not always despair if every contact we
make is not immediately successful, but certainly we have an added reason to utilize every
facility and every opportunity we have to bear witness to the testimony which we have in our
hearts that God lives and that Jesus is the Christ, and that the gospel of Jesus Christ in its
purity has been restored once again to the earth through the instrumentality of the Prophet
Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
We read in the Pearl of Great Price, in the Book of Abraham: "And we will prove them
herewith, to see if they will do all things whatsoever the Lord their God shall command
them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/25#25">Abr. 3:25</a>).
</p><p>
If we do that in this life, then, the Apostle John says, that He will give us power to become
the sons of God, even to them that believe on his name. And this thought contained in the
gospel of John is repeated in the Doctrine and Covenants in the 39th Section: 
</p><p>
"But to as many as received me, gave I power to become my sons; and even so will I give
unto as many as will receive me, power to become my sons.
</p><p>
"And verily, verily, I say unto you, he that receiveth my gospel receiveth me; and he that
receiveth not my gospel receiveth not me.
</p><p>
"And this is my gospel&mdash;repentance and baptism by water, and then cometh the baptism of
fire and the Holy Ghost, even the Comforter, which showeth all things, and teacheth the
peaceable things of the kingdom" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/4-6#4">D&amp;C 39:4-6</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith, on one occasion, said: "Now I will give my testimony. I care for
no man. I speak boldly and faithfully and with authority. How is it with the Kingdom of
God? Where did the Kingdom of God begin? Where there is no Kingdom of
God there is no salvation. What constitutes the Kingdom of God? Where there is a prophet, a
priest, or a righteous man unto whom God gives his oracles, there is the Kingdom of God,
and where the oracles of God are not, there the Kingdom of God is not."
</p><p>
In the Doctrine and Covenants in the 5th Section we read: "And their testimony shall also go
forth unto the condemnation of this generation if they harden their hearts against them; 
</p><p>
"For a desolating scourge shall go forth among the inhabitants of the earth, and shall continue
to be poured out from time to time, if they repent not, until the earth is empty, and the
inhabitants thereof are consumed away and utterly destroyed by the brightness of my coming"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/5/18-19#18">D&amp;C 5:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
Now the execution of our duty is to call the world to repentance, and to do so effectively we
must follow a plan. Our present procedure throughout the missions of the world and in the
stakes is inspired. It comes to us as the result of a hundred and thirty years of inspired work,
and it is not to be set aside or changed or altered by anyone lightly. We plead with you, my
brethren, that in all of your Church work that has the remotest bearing upon missionary work
that you seek to learn and understand, and then to teach the plan which has the approval of
the General Authorities of the Church for use throughout the world in the preaching of this
precious gospel, in order that every minute, every hour of devoted service on the part of our
Priesthood may bear the maximum fruit.
</p><p>
Now for a moment I should like to discuss some of the phases of this program which can
bring such wonderful blessings into the lives of men, a promise that we will be saved and
exalted in the Kingdom of our Heavenly Father as his sons. We have the further promise that
step by step, through our faithfulness we may receive all of the blessings that the Lord has in
store for those who serve him.
</p><p>
First of all, I should like to say without any equivocation that the preaching of the gospel is
the obligation of the Priesthood. It is one of those primary obligations. Every man who holds
the priesthood can consider himself a part of the work. He meets the requirements of our Fifth
Article of Faith, because he has the power and the authority given him by the laying on of
hands by those who are in authority to preach the gospel and administer in the ordinances
thereof (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/5#5">A of F 1:5</a>).
When we either shirk or shrink from this responsibility we are not doing justice to
ourselves and we are certainly depriving ourselves of the blessings which we should cherish
above life itself.
</p><p>
In every activity of the Church, there is no reason why we should not have uppermost in our
minds the fact that the Lord has told us that, "this is my work and my glory to bring to pass
the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
We cannot accomplish this if we do not open our
lips and exert ourselves to bear that testimony with which the Lord has blessed us.
</p><p>
There is a dual blessing which attends every missionary effort direct and indirect. First a
blessing to the one who preaches the gospel, and second to the one who listens and is affected
and converted thereby. There is nothing which strengthens men in their priesthood, develops
the power of the priesthood within them, more than exercising their priesthood in behalf of
others.
</p><p>
We should be alert to every opportunity. We have some indirect methods as well as direct
methods. We have a great program which is spreading rapidly through the Church, and should
be encouraged at every turn of sharing the gospel with others. Sometimes we call it the
"referral" program. It is really a program of sharing the gospel, and when circumstances may
be such that you cannot accomplish this purpose alone, you need only utilize one of these
cards which we are so happy to supply to you throughout the Church to give us the data by
which we may send our missionaries&mdash;those who are directly engaged in this work&mdash;to call
upon your friends and associates, and to supplement and to augment the work which you have
started.
</p><p>
It is not enough to send this card alone. Let us make use of our own homes. What is more
wonderful than to invite a neighbor and his family into our home, and have
our own family join with them in hearing these lessons that are given so ably by the
missionaries. Teach the gospel to your family in the most direct way, as well as give to your
friends a knowledge of the gospel. This will be satisfying to you and give you the feeling that
you have done your duty in large measure toward these friends and neighbors who might
otherwise live and die in our midst without the benefit of having heard the gospel.
</p><p>
Let me say that the Lord in his wisdom, I am sure, has brought these multitudes of people to
our door. Many times we have a receptive person in our next door neighbor. It is just as
important, if not more so, to bless him than to go out into the world and seek someone whom
the Lord may not have specially prepared for this message. I think we should strengthen the
feeling within us that people who come in our midst have not come blindly. They may not
have known why, but I am sure our Father in Heaven has had a purpose in directing their
lives into our midst. We should never let one of them come and go without hearing in an
effective manner our message.
</p><p>
We have been told that in one mission 40 percent of these referrals result in baptisms,
whereas in that same mission only three percent of those contacted directly by tracting from
door to door are converted. We have something over 6000 missionaries in the Church today,
and brethren, we need 12,000. I would not be satisfied with 10,000 because I am sure the
Church needs 12,000 and the Lord expects us to produce. I believe this is our challenge
today.
</p><p>
President McKay has it in his mind that other missions should be opened up in other parts of
the world in which we have done little or no missionary work. There are tremendous fields of
opportunity, but we have not enough missionaries today to properly man the missions that are
already organized. One mission president this week in our conferences with them said that he
was short 30 missionaries, and others need comparable numbers.
</p><p>
It is our feeling, brethren, that every auxiliary organization of the Church should put aside
many other objectives for the moment at least, and concentrate in their auxiliary work in
building up the desires of our people, certainly our parents, to have their sons and daughters
go on missions. The auxiliary organizations cannot do this alone. They need the help of the
home.
</p><p>
I told the Primary conference Friday that I thought their slogan ought to be, "Every member
baptized at eight, and a missionary at twenty." Now we are getting not more than one out of
four, 25 percent. We need 50 percent. We should have a hundred percent. But to get this
12,000 we need 50 percent of the young men when they become 20 years of age, and not 25
percent.
</p><p>
This responsibility falls directly upon every home, every father, every mother, and every
bishop, and I say every auxiliary organization. None of the auxiliary organizations of the
Church, none of the Priesthood quorums of the Church, can feel that they have accomplished
their purpose unless we can so train and inspire our young people that they will answer these
missionary calls.
</p><p>
We have another need for missionary work. We have called the high priests quorums of the
Church into action, and they have performed a marvelous work, but have only scratched the
surface. Since 1957 they have distributed 114,000 copies of the Book of Mormon, and sold
56,000, making a total of 170,000 copies of the Book of Mormon. We ask every bishop and
every high priest quorum president, if you do not already have in your file the memorandum
of May 25, 1956 sent out by Brother Spencer W. Kimball's Committee on the distribution of
the Book of Mormon, to please get a copy.
</p><p>
Out of the meetings we have held this week with these wonderfully inspired mission
presidents, we have learned that it is doubly effective to distribute marked copies of the Book
of Mormon. Brother Kimball is ready to give you the list of passages which should be
marked. He suggests, with the Missionary Committee's approval, that it would be a wonderful
undertaking for the Senior Aaronic Priesthood, under the direction of the high priests
quorums, to so mark the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
Do you see what it would do? They could not mark many without reading the marked
passages themselves. It is also the practice in some of our missions to have converts recently
baptized render this service, and thus insure their familiarity with these wonderful passages of
scripture contained in the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
So I say, brethren, let us speed up this program, and through the instrumentality of the high
priests quorums to redouble these sales, and to do so in keeping once again with this inspired
program which has come to these inspired Brethren, and not undertake to deviate too far from
the program. As long as you will go as far as the program goes, we will encourage you to go
as much farther as your wisdom and inspiration will lead you, but do not stop short of that
which we have found so effective by those who have followed the plan of presenting the
gospel implicitly.
</p><p>
Now the next and final subject that I would like to call to your attention in reference to this
missionary work is the fellowshipping of converts. It is one thing to convert to the point of
baptism. We do not expect every convert to have a perfect knowledge and understanding of
the gospel at that time of baptism. They need only to have received the witness in their hearts
that the message which they have heard is true. They are prepared, even though it be for the
moment, to put aside the things of the world and to humble themselves, to be baptized in the
waters of baptism, and to receive the gift of the Holy Ghost through the laying of hands.
They can receive thereby an added force, and power, to assist them in carrying out the
covenants they make with the Lord in the waters of baptism. I am sure the Lord intends us to
be right on hand&mdash;every one of us&mdash;to give them a helping hand, and to teach them day by
day the principles of the gospel that they might grow in strength and in knowledge and in
understanding.
</p><p>
We have areas in the Church where large numbers are being baptized, and at the same time
80 percent or more of them are remaining true to the Church year after year. It is this 20, or
this 30 percent, that somehow or other we neglect. We fail to take hold properly just at the
right moment. Sometimes there is a little difficulty, or a little time-lapse between baptism by
the full time missionaries on the one hand and integrating them into the ward or stake in
which they live. We are all one Church. We are not worrying about statistics or who gets
credit for a baptism. The thing we are concerned about is that when a person is baptized and
accepted into the Church, that we fellowship him wholeheartedly and see to it that he is given
every opportunity to progress.
</p><p>
Here again is an individual opportunity for service&mdash;an opportunity to call others to a simple
service&mdash;so that every convert can have not only some specific individual or committee on
hand to take care of his needs, but every member of the ward can make it a point to
fellowship them in the meeting house, to visit and to know them in the community; and to
encourage them in endless ways to do as we should do.
</p><p>
It is wonderful, my brethren, to have the opportunity to work in the service of the Lord. I
think sometimes it is even more wonderful than that, to think that every worthy man in the
Church has the same opportunity for service. It makes no difference whether you are working
in the ward or as a General Authority, you are in the same service. Those of you who hold
the Higher Priesthood hold the same Priesthood, and those of you brethren who are holders of
the Aaronic Priesthood may soon hold the Melchizedek Priesthood if you desire and but live
for it.
</p><p>
May God bless us to so live day by day that we may be worthy to be his mouthpieces in
declaring the gospel of Jesus Christ as it has been restored in these latter days through the
Prophet Joseph Smith, I pray humbly in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
