<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Destiny of This Church</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960,  pp. 109-111</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I believe I speak for the Assistants to the Quorum of the Twelve
when I express my goodwill and my good feelings towards the three men who have been
called to associate with us in our work. I know these men personally. I know they are good
men. I know they are capable, and I know, too, their willingness to lay upon the altar any
worldly possessions they have in order to serve the Lord in spirit and in truth.
</p><p>
I believe in the future of the Church. I believe it has a great destiny. I believe in its moral
standards. I believe its program is effective and the Church will grow and develop as the
missionary effort increases in the world. I believe faith in God is the
very foundation of right living, and I believe in the missionary system of the Church, which
has proved so successful in recent years, and I believe the work will continue to go forward.
</p><p>
I also believe that many of the old barriers and obstacles are crumbling and giving way, and
that we have a better opportunity than we have ever had to proclaim the gospel truths. I
believe there are people in the world who are very anxious to hear the gospel message as it is
proclaimed by humble men and women sent out from the headquarters of the Church to bear
their testimonies.
</p><p>
I want to read a word from President Brigham Young. He said:
</p><p>
"The Lord will never suffer this people to dwindle down, and be hid up in a corner; it cannot
be; neither does he want any person to help them but himself" (<i>Discourses of Brigham Young</i>, p. 676).
</p><p>
In other words, God is directing his work. It is not man-made, neither is it the creation of a
human mind. The pioneer prophet Brigham Young was face to face with a gigantic task when
he undertook to colonize the West and to keep alive the missionary movement. It was not an
easy thing to set up a commonwealth and to transform a desert into cities, towns, and villages,
and to provide homes, schools, and churches. It required more than ordinary skill to build up
faith and hope and to develop a solid citizenship out of a people who came from many parts
of the world.
</p><p>
Brigham Young could not have done it without God's help. He knew this, and never once did
he claim the credit for this achievement. When he died in 1877, his enemies saw the end of
Mormonism. There was no one, they argued, to take his place. He had presided over the
Church for thirty years. Those who had stood by him in the early emergencies and difficulties
had passed on. Willard Richards had died in 1854. Heber C. Kimball, the great prophet, and a
stalwart, who had stood by his side in all the days of colonization and settlement, had died in
1868. Parley P. Pratt had met an untimely death in 1857. George A. Smith, who was regarded
as a great leader of courage and wisdom, had died in 1875. And many others who stood
valiantly by his side during the exodus and the colonization effort, also had passed on.
Mormonism could not survive, at least that was the verdict of those who did not and could
not understand. There was no leader, they claimed, to take his place. They saw the disruption
and disorganization of the Church, and many would repudiate their allegiance and follow a
divided leadership.
</p><p>
The enemies predicted the same thing when the Prophet Joseph and his brother Hyrum Smith
were murdered. The great enterprise launched by them, they thought, would burst like a
bubble, but God will always have in reserve someone to take the place of him who is gone.
Brethren and sisters, God's work will triumph in the earth.
</p><p>
Speaking of pioneer days, I should like to read a statement from the journal of Brother
Richard Ballantyne, the organizer of the first Sunday School in the Rocky Mountains. Brother
Ballantyne wrote this just five years before his death. Speaking of pioneering days, he said:
</p><p>
But those times are now past, and I believe never to return. A brighter day is now awaiting,
but it will have its dangers.
</p><p>
"As wealth flows into the hands of the Church, and with its learning and refinement, pride is
apt to enter the hearts of the children of Zion, as it entered into the hearts of the Nephites.
</p><p>
"God has signified by his servant that the day to favor Zion has come. The powers of the
heavens are to be exerted in a way they never were before. The time for the uplifting of Zion
has come. Kings and rulers will favor her. Her beauty and righteousness are beginning to
appear in the world. She will not be looked upon as she has been in the past. The shadows
are passing away, and the light is breaking in upon us."
</p><p>
I bear my testimony that God's work will stand, that Joseph Smith was his divine Prophet
appointed to usher in the Dispensation of the Fulness of Times. I bear testimony that his
successors in the high office were all men of God, and that they were full of faith and
prophecy. I bear testimony that the authority of the Holy Priesthood is operating in the
Church as it has always done and that it will continue to do so until
every knee shall bend and every tongue confess that Jesus is the Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/10-11#10">Philip. 2:10-11</a>), the Savior of the
world, and that the Latter-day Saints comprise his Church and kingdom about which the
ancient prophets spoke; and that the Church will continue to grow and extend itself, even
beyond our imaginations, for it will surely reach to the uttermost parts of the earth.
</p><p>
I pray that his Spirit may continue with us, and that we may serve him always with a
singleness of purpose, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
