<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Time of Preparation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 96-97</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have just been handed a paper giving the general priesthood conference count, April 8,
1961. These reports have come in early. Attendance in the Salt Lake Tabernacle, 8,097. In the
Assembly Hall, Barratt Hall, and grounds, 2,688. A total attendance on these two blocks,
10,785. Attendance in other places is to be reported by mail later. For comparison, in April
1960, we had 10,432 on the grounds; in October, 1960, 9,911; so we have 10,785 tonight, the
largest we have ever had.
</p><p>
We have had a remarkable meeting. We shall report to you tomorrow how many are in the
other chapels listening in to this inspirational missionary meeting. In the congregations there
are thousands, tens of thousands of young men of the Lesser Priesthood&mdash;our future
missionaries. I shall just ask the bishops to call their attention to the following.
</p><p>
To render service for two or three years in the mission field is a blessing to anyone. It is
recognized as such by thousands of parents throughout the Church who appreciate the value
of such labor to their sons and daughters, in whom this experience awakens an appreciation of
home and of the gospel. Parents know also that missionary activity brings into the plane of
consciousness a knowledge of the truth of the gospel, which the young men have perhaps felt
but not expressed.
</p><p>
Bishops, it is well for us to have in mind not so much the benefit to those representatives as
their preparation and fitness to carry on the responsibilities entailed in a missionary call. In
choosing a missionary it is well to keep in mind questions as follows: 
</p><p>
Is he worthy to represent the Church?
</p><p>
Has he sufficient will power to resist temptation?
</p><p>
Has he kept himself clean while he has been home and by that standard proved himself
capable of resisting possible temptation in the field?
</p><p>
Has he taken active part in Church organizations at home?
</p><p>
Does he at least glimpse what the Church has to offer the world?
</p><p>
Has he glimpsed that the Church is the greatest thing in the world, and the only authorized
group to represent the Lord Jesus Christ in the salvation of mankind? I use the word <i>glimpsed</i>
because many of our young men hesitate to bear their testimonies. They say they don't
know&mdash;they believe. But if they will just stop to analyze what this Church does to the individual,
first in keeping himself <i>clean and unspotted</i> 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/27#27">James 1:27</a>);
<i>second</i>, in <i>keeping the Word of Wisdom</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/1-21#1">D&amp;C 89:1-21</a>); <i>third</i>,
in keeping <i>chaste and pure</i>; if he just studies and realizes and even just glimpses what it does
for the home&mdash;no drunken father, if he is a member of the Church; no disloyal husband; no
mother who makes home unhappy by her infidelity&mdash;a home keeping the standards of the
Church, is a happy home; an unbroken home&mdash;a home where boys and girls take turns in
offering prayer, in courtesy and mutual helpfulness. That is what we mean by "glimpsing."
</p><p>
Has he taken active part in Church organizations? I do not have time to elaborate upon that.
</p><p>
Has he, through prayer, or experience, felt God's nearness to him, so that he can approach the
Lord as he would his earthly father?
</p><p>
Young men, please keep those questions in mind as you take part in your
deacons' quorums, teachers' quorums, priests' quorums, elders' quorums; and as you prepare
in activity at home, in personal life, and in your schoolwork to qualify yourselves to go out as
representatives. May you be among those who can be trusted&mdash;a representative of the Lord
Jesus Christ, I humbly pray in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
