<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">We Should Improve Our Communities</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 60-65</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I wish it were possible this morning for me to express to my
Heavenly Father the gratitude there is in my heart for the restoration of the gospel of Jesus
Christ in these latter days. I am sure that if we serve all the days of our life and render to this
work the utmost of our ability in furthering its progress, that we will not have shown fully the
appreciation which I know we all hold. It is glorious for me to contemplate the possibilities
that the gospel gives to us in life, the blessings that it has bestowed upon us thus far in our
lives. I marvel as I go through the Church and receive of your kindness and your hospitality
and your faith and prayers in my ministry, at the growth and the development which I, in
turn, see in you, who are faithful to the offices and callings which you fill and who are
rendering the service that you do render to the children of our Heavenly Father. I am certain
that I can never do enough in my life to compensate my Heavenly Father for the testimony
that he has given me of the divinity of the work in which we are engaged. More priceless
than all else is the knowledge that I have that Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the Living God,
and that he called upon the boy Joseph Smith to be his prophet in these latter days and to
restore to this earth his gospel for the salvation, and, through our obedience, the exaltation of
mankind.
</p><p>
ADVERSARY AT WORK
</p><p>
We may sometimes feel that this work is purely spiritual but there is no phase of life that we
can afford to overlook in fulfilling our obligations to our Heavenly Father and to the
priesthood which we hold. We must be conscious of the fact that the adversary is at work,
utilizing every agency of which he can conceive. I am sure we are all agreed that his
imagination is almost limitless, to bring about the downfall of the work of truth and
righteousness here upon this earth. Where he finds us to be vulnerable either in our thinking
or in our lives, there is where he is going to get in his work most effectively. He is causing us
in our thinking to be led to adopt the philosophies of the world. We are easily led. I am sure
that flattery is one of the greatest implements or tools that the adversary has at his command.
You and I, today, must fortify ourselves against unrighteous flattery, in fact, I feel to say, any
kind of flattery at all, to keep our feet on the ground and our thinking clear and to see to it
that we devote our spare time to studying the principles of the gospel, that no philosophies of
men will have any room in our thinking, nor shall we have time to devote to the reading of
such.
</p><p>
RIGHTS OF CITIZENSHIP
</p><p>
We are called upon in our daily lives, in this great country in which we live, to exercise our
rights of citizenship. I wonder sometimes if all of us are conscious of the power that we
possess in this respect. We have had a great deal said at this conference, to which I can very
happily say amen, concerning the family. I wish we could all take to heart every word that
Elder Ezra Taft Benson said in his address on the "Church of the Air." I rejoice in his
courage to tell the people of the world that which is destroying the home. To point out to
them the way in which the home can be built up and strengthened. What I want to emphasize
today, if I may, is the fact that the home in which we live and in which we rear our children
is located in a community or vicinity, or city. We cannot keep out of our home the influences
which we find in these centers in which we live. We need to call upon our Heavenly Father
to give us the inspiration and the foresight, first of all, to know what to do and then the
courage to accomplish it.
</p><p>
STATE LEGISLATURE
</p><p>
I want to say a commendatory word to those who sat in our last state legislature. May the
Lord bless them for their efforts to make of our state and of our communities a better place in
which to live and a better place in which to rear our families. I owe a debt of gratitude
beyond measure to my parents, to my brethren and sisters who lived in this state when I was
a boy for the fact that they kept the town in which I was reared as clean as it was kept. It is
now our duty to keep the youth of Zion from as many temptations as possible and to give
them the same opportunity that many of us have had to develop faith and to grow in
righteousness and to overcome the weakness of the flesh in an atmosphere peculiarly adapted
to such purposes. I feel to commend all of the Latter-day Saints today for the efforts that they
have extended to make of their communities, in a civic sense, a proper place to live. But I am
certain that you will all agree with me that we still have a great work to perform in this
connection, and we cannot delay nor overlook the slightest opportunity.
</p><p>
COMMUNITY LIFE
</p><p>
We sometimes permit ourselves, around election time, to become concerned with politics. We
should always be active. Now is the time to prepare for the next election. It is upon politics
we must rely in large measure for the kind of government that we have. In turn we must rely
upon that government for the protection of our rights, for the enforcement of our laws, and
for the protection of our principles. Now these things go to the very root of life itself and of
our growth and development in the gospel. We cannot afford to neglect to do our duty as
citizens of this great United States and as citizens of the state in which we live. Those of you,
my brethren and sisters, who come from the countries outside the United States, so far as the
laws of those countries permit, should exercise the same influence there as we undertake to
exercise here under our laws. We have the power, we have the leadership and the strength in
this Church to make our views known. Even though we may be a minority, in some places,
we have the power to convert every person who thinks right and who desires the right, to our
cause. I have the abiding conviction within me that there are none of us living in any
communities anywhere but what the great majority of the people&mdash;our friends, our neighbors,
our associates&mdash;even though they be they be not of our faith, nevertheless they, the majority,
desire righteousness rather than evil to predominate in the communities in which they live.
And so it is up to you and me, where we are minorities, to make ourselves majorities by
converting those who need converting to these specific programs, programs which we have in
mind to bring about the kind of suitable conditions under which we can establish our homes
and rear our children. Our efforts should not be confined to the times of political elections.
We should be on duty always.
</p><p>
I want to say again, I commend the legislature from the bottom of my heart. Our fine stalwart
brethren stood in this last state legislature and raised their voices under the inspiration of their
priesthood to uphold and sustain righteousness in the enactment of laws. We had a conflict, in
our own legislature here last time, which I want to mention for a moment, on two or three
issues, specifically which came before them. We should have them in mind as we go back to
our homes and begin to devise ways and means by which we can accomplish our righteous
purposes. I might say at the outset that what we undertake to do for ourselves is not with any
selfish purpose in mind. It is not to obtain any power or dominion over others. It is to bring
to them, in effect, the same blessings that we seek for ourselves, those God-given rights
secured to us by the laws of this great nation. And so we can go forward. If any of us have
any doubts as to our rights in this matter, we need only to read the 134th section of the D&amp;C
to find all of the instruction and inspiration that any righteous man needs to go forth and do
his duty (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/1-12#1">D&amp;C 134:1-12</a>).
We must all strengthen the community in which we live, from a civic and political
as well as a religious standpoint. I tell you, my brethren and sisters, that when we exercise
this kind of faith and courage in behalf of our neighbors as well as our own members we will
accomplish a great missionary work in this world. There will be men and women brought to
investigate the principles of the gospel because they will see the kind of fruits in us which
this gospel has borne. Their doors will be opened to us through our civic activities to preach
the gospel of the restored kingdom and to bring the same joy and happiness into the hearts of
our neighbors with which the Lord has blessed us all our lives.
</p><p>
OBSERVANCE OF SABBATH
</p><p>
We had a conflict up there in the legislature about the Sabbath day. I would like to go into
some of the things that have been said about the Sabbath day from the time of Adam on. So
far as I know the Lord has never changed the law of the Sabbath. In the days of early Israel
with all of Israel's faults they kept the Sabbath day holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>), and they did the Lord's work on the
Sabbath day. They literally closed the gates of Jerusalem. They did not permit vendors to
bring their wares to the gates to be sold on the Sabbath day. We have had the gospel of the
Sabbath day proclaimed to us through all generations of time. Should there be any doubt in
our minds as to what course the Latter-day Saints should take with reference to the Sabbath
day? Are we to open our stores, are we to carry on our commercial transactions on the
Sabbath day the same as we do on a weekday, or are we to close our establishments? Well,
the answer is obvious. Now, why isn't any law which has for its purpose the maintaining of
the Sabbath day sacred, a law which we should uphold and sustain and support and vote for
on every occasion that we have a legal right so to do? To hold otherwise would be to tell us
that we have not the right to use our own free agency so far as the affairs of government are
concerned.
</p><p>
LIQUOR LAW
</p><p>
We've had another law on our books with reference to liquor, and there was an effort made to
expand the present liquor law to the detriment of the people. Nobody had to ask anybody any
questions as to where the right and the wrong were to be found. If there are any Latter-day
Saints today who think that the old open saloon is uplifting or would help us build a better
community, it must be because they are not old enough to remember the days when we had
those institutions in our midst and saw from actual experience the results and the evils, the
deterioration that set in, the sorrow and the hardships, that such places of vice brought. So I
feel again to commend those in our state legislature who saw fit to vote against any act which
had for its purpose the bringing back of the open saloon. They do not call it that now, but
that is what it would have been had we had sale of liquor by the drink, and do not let any of
us forget that. Let us raise our voices whenever we have the opportunity, and create the
opportunity, my brothers and sisters. Let us elect men to office who will be opposed to the
institution in our midst of such places of vice as the open saloon. It is bad enough to have to
traffic in liquor at all. We certainly should not go farther than we have. If it is necessary, in
order to fight this evil, to meet the opposition on the other side, why, then I say to you from
the bottom of my heart, let us start fighting for prohibition, for after all, that is what we
ought to have to maintain the kind of communities our Heavenly Father would have us
maintain in this world, and on this continent, and in this land of his. We cannot hope to
receive the blessings of our Heavenly Father here, in as rich abundance as he is willing to
give them to us if we do not exercise every power that we have to make this a land choice
above all others (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/20#20">1 Ne. 2:20</a>).
Prohibition would help to make it that, and the open saloon would make it the contrary.
</p><p>
HORSE RACING BILL
</p><p>
We had one other bill that I would like to speak about in conclusion and that is the horse
racing bill. I suppose there is no harm in horse racing, but there is no more insidious vice on
earth than gambling. It is destructive of the morals. The man does not live who is strong
enough in the faith, I do not care what his past record has been, to start in gambling and
continue therein and keep the faith. If there are any people in this state who desire horse
racing and the gambling that is incident thereto, we invite them to leave and to go to places
where those things can be had. We do not have to have them in our midst. I feel to say that
no man can maintain his full standing in this Church and keep his faith and at the same time
have anything to do with horse racing and gambling.
</p><p>
Now, brethren, let us take this seriously. In those communities, in this state, where horse
racing and gambling have become more or less of an institution, let us use our faith and our
courage to eradicate them as such and to elect men to the legislature who will not open the
doors to the element that follows horse racing with all the vice and corruption that would
come into this state.
</p><p>
Well, now, my brethren and sisters, I hope that you will accept this admonition in the spirit in
which it has been given. I love the Latter-day Saints; I am indebted to all of you for your
faith and prayers and the support that you have given me as I have gone through the Church
attending your quarterly conferences. I have learned to love you. I look forward with the
greatest of pleasure every week of my life to coming into your stakes and into your homes
and enjoying your spirit. I want our communities, in which we live, to be maintained in
keeping with the spirit which we have here in these conferences and in our quarterly
conferences and the spirit that we can have in our homes if we will say our prayers daily.
May the Lord bless us to this end, I humbly pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
