<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Sharing the Blessings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Clifford E. Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Clifford E. Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 93-95</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Last Friday the General Authorities met with the mission  presidents who had been serving in
this country and in Central America. It was an inspiring meeting, and they who were there
expressed their gratitude and appreciation for the privilege of coming here to the headquarters
of the Church and meeting with their brethren and reporting their labors, feeling the spirit of
testimony as expressed by their associates and by all who were privileged to speak in the
meeting which was held in the temple.
</p><p>
Then we have had our brethren who have offered prayers or spoken, express
their gratitude for the privilege of being in attendance at this conference.  We, ourselves, have
partaken of that spirit, grateful to the Almighty that we are here, that we can sit under the sound
of the voice of the prophets of God and of the other General Authorities as they have spoken
and listen to their counsel, and partake of their spirit.  We are grateful for this privilege and
blessing.
</p><p>
You people who are listening in and who are watching on television are also grateful. 
Yesterday this latter privilege was extended wider than ever before in the history of the
Church, and I know we were all thrilled as we heard President McKay tell of the extent of
these televised and broadcasted services.
</p><p>
But this raised a question in my mind, as did our meeting with the mission presidents.  I
thought of some of our mission presidents over in the old country who are working faithfully,
who are devoted to this work, giving of their time and their means, faithful to their trust, and
yet they could not be with us.
</p><p>
I thought too, of the thousands of Saints, in the islands of the sea, and in the old country, and
even in this country, who cannot partake of the spirit of these services because they are not
able to be here or to come within the radius of television or of the radio, and yet they are just
as anxious as are we, and they are just as devoted as are we, The Lord will not forget the He
will in his own way bless them, and they learn of these services; as they read the testimonies
of these meetings, they will partake of the same spirit, perhaps not so potently as we; but the
Lord will bless them, and they too will share with us because he will not leave them alone,
</p><p>
Brother Christiansen has been telling us of our obligations to those who have gone, of the
revelations of the Lord that the hearts of the children shall be turned to their fathers, and the
hearts of the fathers to their children, for "were it not so the whole, earth would be wasted at
his coming" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/2/3#3">D&amp;C 2:3</a>).
In listening to Brother Christiansen we have been impressed with the magnitude
of this work, and we have been given an insight into the mercies of our heavenly Father.
</p><p>
As we are permitted to enjoy the blessings of being here and are made aware of the blessings
and privileges that come and will come to us through the atonement, we cannot help being
made aware of and be concerned with the thousands of God's children who, through no fault
of their own, are not blessed as are we.
</p><p>
I was in the home two weeks ago of one of our brethren where there is a little girl who is
deficient, a little child who never will have the opportunity in this life to fulfil the purposes of
the lord for which she was paced here, unless God shall intervene with a miracle and heal her
little body and her mind.  Her mind apparently through some physical pressure and through
no fault of her own, nor is it through any failure of her parents to do the will of the Lord is
not able to grasp the things that you and I are able to grasp, and thus she will go through life
underprivileged, not physically only, but lacking in the expression of mental powers.  It is not
her spirit that is injured, but her body, and the body is the medium of expression of the spirit
in this life; and when the body is injured either in birth or before or afterwards, and as a
result the spirit cannot give expression to a normal life here, then we speak of such as being
defective, and handicapped.
</p><p>
And there are thousands of such everywhere.  I wish you could go with me to our state
training school in Utah County and see the hundreds of little children and men and women
who are thus afflicted. As I have observed these, the question has arisen in my mind, "What
is the answer to this problem of these underprivileged children, these people who are not
blessed as are we?" come back to the same conclusion that as those who are not here
will also sometime share in the blessings that we are enjoying in these
meetings, and as those who do not know the law will be judged without the law, even so will
the Lord grant to these who are not privileged, his blessings so that nothing will be withheld
from them if it is through no fault of their own.
</p><p>
The Lord has said that those who live without law shall be judged without law
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/8/22#22">Moro. 8:22</a>), and by the
same token those who are not privileged to have the blessings in this life that you and I have
who are mentally and physically able and strong, they also shall ultimately receive blessings
from our heavenly Father, and through the atonement of Jesus Christ, blessings that are
withheld from them through no fault of their own shall not be withheld from them.
</p><p>
The Book of Mormon prophet has told us that the atonement is an infinite atonement
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/7#7">2 Ne. 9:7</a>).  This
means that there is no limit to its blessings and privileges, and these blessings and privileges
will be extended to all who have not received them in this life.  What these afflicted ones lose
in this life will be made up to them in the life to come.
</p><p>
And so I am grateful with you, my brethren and sisters, for the gospel of the Lord Jesus
Christ It is not narrow in its application.  It is unlimited in its privileges and blessings to all
of God's children who <i>will</i>/ to do right when once they understand.  For those who are
mentally deficient, through no fault of their own, someday these pressures will be lifted.  The
healing power of the Almighty will come to their bodies, just as it will come to ours, and as
it came to the body of the Savior; and their spirits, which are the offspring of God, will have
the privilege of inhabiting bodies, their own bodies that will be healed and free from pressures
and affliction so that there will be no limit to possibilities of the spirits, their minds, and their
souls.
</p><p>
Now these are blessings that are ours.  They are a part of the gospel of Jesus Christ, and just
as the gospel provides for those who will not have the privilege, and who have not had the
privilege, of hearing it in times past, and who may not in the future, just as the gospel will be
ultimately made possible for them through the great vicarious work, the atoning sacrifice of
Jesus Christ, so through this infinite atonement will there come blessings to those who now
are deficient and from whom are withheld blessings that you and I enjoy.
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to appreciate these things.  To me this is one of the great blessings of
the gospel of Jesus Christ.  It is one of the great revelations that have come down through the
Prophet Joseph, as expressed by the prophets in the Book of Mormon.  We do not understand
the processes, as we do not understand the processes in many things, but that does not make
the fact untrue.  It is as real and true as are many of the things that are apparent to us today.
</p><p>
May the Lord help us to understand these things better than we have in the past, and may he
give comfort to the hundreds and thousands of mothers whose hearts are bleeding because of
the deficiencies in their children, deficiencies that have come through no fault of the parents
or no fault of the child, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
