<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John H. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">John H. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1942, pp. 46-47</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The Lord has said, "I have warned you and forewarned you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/4#4">D&amp;C 89:4</a>)&mdash;He has warned us attain today
through His servants. Perhaps some of us will continue to say that there is a tomorrow when
we will repent and lead a finer life, but we all know that as far as each one of us is concerned
the time comes when for us there is no tomorrow. The Lord has also said that today is the
time to repent.
</p><p>
You remember that the Lord told His prophet, Noah, that he should go out and warn the
people and tell them of the coming destruction
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/6/13#13">Gen. 6:13</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/41#41">D&amp;C 138:41</a>).
But the people, seemingly because they
thought there would always be a tomorrow and because the floods did not come that day or
the next day, thought they would never come; therefore, they ridiculed the prophets and went
their way. But the floods came and they were destroyed, because they would not listen to the
prophets of the Lord.
</p><p>
I remember hearing a story of a man who had just lost his oldest son. The father was not a
very religious man. In fact, he had disregarded most of the Lord's commandments. Because of
his son's being called to the other side, a good man went into the house to talk with the father
and to the family. The son had been unfaithful in every way. He had been disobedient unto
his parents, to his country, to his God. As the good man talked with the father and the family,
the father said, "I think that this is a time for prayer." Perhaps we all think that only when the
emergency comes to us it is the time to pray. The efficiency of a prayer is dependent on the
type of life we have lived and the way we have made progress upon the earth. When the time
comes for the summons, to ourselves or to our family, if we have not repented, if we have
not done the things that should have been done, the praying comes rather late.
</p><p>
I trust, brethren, that as we continue traveling along the way of life, we will try to do the
things that God through His servants wants us to do. The time is short and there is no telling
when it might be too late for us to repent and do the things that we ought to do. It is very
easy in an emergency, such as we have in war today, to build big buildings and to make steel
and to make airplanes and to build hospitals, Perhaps we can do these things in a material
way, but we cannot all of a sudden build character, build decent homes, or have a family who
have such confidence in us that they will listen to our words and listen to the words of the
servants of the Lord. 
</p><p>
May we be humble as we live upon the earth. May we repent of our sins. May we take this
message seriously as it comes to us today, and live better and finer than we have ever lived
before, I humbly pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
