<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Meeting Your Goliath</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas S. Monson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas S. Monson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 129-133</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, the peace that we feel in this historic tabernacle this morning is in
stark contrast to the situation that prevailed some many miles from here on the 5th day of
June this past year.  On that day, the quiet air of Sinai's desert was broken as jet aircraft
streaked toward their targets, cannons sounded, tanks lumbered, men fought and died, women
wept, children cried. The Holy Land, once the personal province of the Prince of Peace (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>), again
was shattered by war.
</p><p>
<b>Sounds of conflict and war</b>
</p><p>
This troubled land has witnessed much conflict; its peoples have suffered terrible trials and
tribulations. No single battle is better remembered, however, than occurred in the Valley of
Elah during the year 1063 B.C. Along the mountains on one side, the feared armies of the
Philistines were marshaled to march directly to the heart of Judah and the Jordan Valley. On
the other side of the valley, King Saul had drawn up his armies in opposition.
</p><p>
Historians tell us that the opposing forces were about evenly matched in number and in skill.
However, the Philistines had managed to keep secret their valued knowledge of smelting and
fashioning iron into formidable weapons of war.  The sound of hammers pounding upon
anvils and the sight of smoke rising skyward from many bellows as the smiths went about the
task of sharpening weapons and fashioning new ones must have struck fear into the hearts of
Saul's warriors; for even the most novice of soldiers could know the superiority of iron
weapons to those of brass.
</p><p>
As often happened when armies faced each other, individual champions challenged others
from the opposing forces to single combat.  There was considerable precedent for this sort of
fighting; and on more than one occasion, notably during the tenure of Samson as judge,
battles had been decided by individual combat.
</p><p>
<b>Single combat&mdash;Goliath vs. David</b>
</p><p>
Now, however, the situation was reversed as far as Israel was concerned, and it was a
Philistine who dared to challenge all others&mdash;a veritable giant of a man called Goliath of
Gath.  Old accounts tell us that Goliath was ten feet tall.  He wore brass armor and a coat of
mail.  And the staff of his spear would stagger a strong man merely to lift, let alone hurl. 
His shield was the longest ever seen or heard of, his sword a fearsome blade
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/4-7#4">1 Sam. 17:4-7</a>).
</p><p>
This champion from the Philistine camp stood and cried unto the armies of Israel: "Why are
ye come out to set your battle in array? am not I a Philistine, and ye servants to Saul? choose
you a man for you, and let him come down to me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/8#8">1 Sam. 17:8</a>).
</p><p>
His challenge was that if he were overpowered by the Israelite warrior, then all the Philistines
would become servants to the Israelites.  On the other hand, if he were victorious, the
Israelites would become their slaves. Goliath roared: "I defy the armies of Israel this day; give
me a man, that we may fight together" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/10#10">1 Sam. 17:10</a>).
</p><p>
And so, for 40 days came the challenge met only by fear and trembling. And all the men of
Israel, when they saw the man Goliath, "fled from him and were sore afraid"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/24#24">1 Sam. 17:24</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Faith of a shepherd boy</b>
</p><p>
There was one, however, who did not quake with fear nor run in alarm. Rather, he stiffened
the spine of Israel's soldiers by his piercing question of rebuke toward them: ". . . Is there
not a cause? . . . Let no man's heart fail because of him; thy servant will go and fight with
this Philistine" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/29,32#29">1 Sam. 17:29,32</a>). David, the shepherd boy, had spoken.  But he did not
speak just as a shepherd boy, for the hands of Samuel, God's prophet, had rested upon his
head and anointed him, and the Spirit of the Lord had come upon him.
</p><p>
Saul said to David: "Thou art not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him: for thou
art but a youth, and he a man of war from his youth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/33#33">1 Sam. 17:33</a>). But David persevered
and, bedecked with the armor of Saul, prepared to meet the giant.  Realizing his helplessness
so garbed, David discarded the armor, took instead his staff in his hand, chose five smooth
stones out of the brook and put them in a shepherd's bag; and with his sling in hand, he drew
near to the Philistine.
</p><p>
All of us remember the shocked exclamation of Goliath: "Am I a dog, that thou comest to me
with staves? . . . Come to me, and I will give thy flesh unto the fowls of the air, and to the
beasts of the field" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/43-44#43">1 Sam. 17:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
Then David said: "Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a shield: but I
come to thee in the name of the Lord of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel, whom thou
hast defied.
</p><p>
"This day will the Lord deliver thee into mine hand . . . that all the earth may know that there
is a God in Israel.
</p><p>
"And all this assembly shall know that the Lord saveth not with sword and spear: for the
battle is the Lord's, and he will give you into our hands.
</p><p>
"And it came to pass, when the Philistine arose, and came and drew nigh to meet David, that
David hasted, and ran toward the army to meet the Philistine.
</p><p>
"And David put his hand in his bag, and took thence a stone, and slang it, and smote the
Philistine . . . that the stone sunk into his forehead; and he fell upon his face to the earth.
</p><p>
"So David prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and smote the
Philistine, and slew him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/45-50#45">1 Sam. 17:45-50</a>).
</p><p>
The battle had thus been fought.  The victory had been won.  David emerged a national hero,
his destiny before him.
</p><p>
<b>Acclaimed hero</b>
</p><p>
Some of us remember David as a shepherd boy divinely commissioned by the Lord through
the prophet Samuel. Others of us know him as a mighty warrior, for doesn't the record show
the chant of the adoring women following his many victorious battles, "Saul
has slain his thousands, and David his ten thousands" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/18/7#7">1 Sam. 18:7</a>)? Or perhaps we look
upon him as the inspired poet or as one of Israel's greatest kings.  Still others recall that he
violated the laws of God and took that which belonged to another&mdash;the beautiful Bathsheba.
He even arranged the death of her husband, Uriah.
</p><p>
I, however, like to think of David as the righteous lad who had the courage and the faith to
face insurmountable odds when all others hesitated, and to redeem the name of Israel by
facing that giant in his life&mdash;Goliath of Gath.
</p><p>
<b>A Goliath in your life?</b>
</p><p>
Well might we look carefully into our own lives and judge our courage, our faith. Is there a
Goliath in your life?  Is there one in mine?  Does he stand squarely between you and your
desired happiness?  Oh, your Goliath may not carry a sword or hurl a verbal challenge of
insult that all may hear and force you to decision.  He may not be ten feet tall, but he likely
will appear equally as formidable, and his silent challenge may shame and embarrass.
</p><p>
One man's Goliath may be the stranglehold of a cigarette or perhaps an unquenchable thirst
for alcohol. To another, his Goliath may be an unruly tongue or a selfish streak that causes
him to spurn the poor and the downtrodden.
</p><p>
Envy, greed, fear, laziness, doubt, vice, pride, lust, selfishness, discouragement&mdash;all spell
Goliath.
</p><p>
The giant you face will not diminish in size or in power or strength by your vain hoping,
wishing, or waiting for him to do so.  Rather, he increases in power as his hold upon you
tightens.
</p><p>
The poet Alexander Pope truly describes this truth: 
</p><p>
"Vice is a monster of so frightful mien,<br />
      As, to be hated, needs but to be seen; <br />
      Yet seen too oft, familiar with her face,<br />
      We first endure, then pity, then embrace."
</p><p>
The battle for our immortal souls is no less important than the battle fought by David.  The
enemy is no less formidable, the help of Almighty God no farther away.  What will our
action be?  Like David of old, "our cause is just." We have been placed upon earth not to fail
or fall victim to temptation's snare, but rather to succeed.  Our giant, our Goliath, must be
conquered.
</p><p>
David went to the brook and carefully selected five smooth stones with which he might meet
his enemy (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/40#40">1 Sam. 17:40</a>).  He was deliberate in his selection, for there could be no turning back, no second
chance&mdash;this battle was to be decisive.
</p><p>
<b>Equipment essential to victory</b>
</p><p>
Just as David went to the brook, well might we go to our source of supply&mdash;the Lord.  What
polished stones will you select to defeat the Goliath that is robbing you of your happiness by
smothering your opportunities?  May I offer suggestions: 
</p><p>
The stone of <i>courage</i> will be essential to your victory.  As we survey the challenge of life,
that which is easy is rarely right. In fact, the course that we should properly follow at times
appears impossible, impenetrable, hopeless.
</p><p>
Such did the way appear to Laman and Lemuel.  When they looked upon their assignment to
go unto the house of Laban and seek the records according to God's command, they
murmured, saying it was a hard thing that was required of them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/5#5">1 Ne. 3:5</a>).  Thus, a lack of courage
took from them their opportunity; and it was given to courageous Nephi, who responded, "I
will go and do the things which the Lord hath commanded, for I know that the Lord giveth
no commandments unto the children of men, save he shall prepare a way for them that they
may accomplish the thing which he commandeth them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/7#7">1 Ne. 3:7</a>). Yes, the stone of
courage is needed.
</p><p>
Let us not overlook the stone of <i>effort</i>&mdash;mental effort and physical effort.
</p><p>
"The heights by great men reached and kept<br />
      Were not obtained by sudden flight,<br />
      But they, while their companions slept.<br />
      Were toiling upward through the night."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;      ("Ladder of St. Augustine.")
</p><p>
<b>Decisive action</b>
</p><p>
The decision to overcome a fault or correct a weakness is an actual step in the process of
doing so.  "Thrust in thy sickle with thy might" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/4#4">D&amp;C 4:4</a>) was not spoken of missionary work alone.
</p><p>
Then there must be in our selection the stone of <i>humility</i>, for haven't we been told through
divine revelation that when we are humble, the Lord, our God, will lead us by the hand and
give us answer to our prayers?
</p><p>
And who would go forth to battle his Goliath without the stone of <i>prayer</i>, remembering that
the recognition of a power higher than oneself is in no way debasing; rather it exalts.
</p><p>
Finally, let us choose the stone of <i>duty</i>.  Duty is not merely doing the thing we ought to do,
but doing it when we should, whether we like it or not.
</p><p>
Armed with this selection of five polished stones to be propelled by the mighty sling of faith,
we need then but to take the staff of virtue to steady us; and we are ready to meet the giant
Goliath, wherever, and whenever, and however we find him.
</p><p>
<b>Marshal resources for battle</b>
</p><p>
The stone of <i>courage</i> will melt the Goliath of fear; the stone of <i>effort</i> will bring down the
Goliaths of indecision and procrastination.  And the Goliaths of pride, of envy, of lack of
self-respect will not stand before the power of the stones of <i>humility, prayer</i>, and <i>duty</i>.
</p><p>
Above all else, may we ever remember that we do not go forth alone to battle against the
Goliaths of our lives. As David declared to Israel, so might we echo the knowledge, ". . . the
battle is the Lord's, and he will give [Goliath] into our hands" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/17/47#47">1 Sam. 17:47</a>).
</p><p>
<b>No victory by default</b>
</p><p>
The battle must be fought.  Victory cannot come by default.  So it is in the battles of life. 
Life will never spread itself in an unobstructed view before us.  We must anticipate the
approaching forks and turnings in the road.
</p><p>
However, we cannot hope to reach our desired journey's end if we think aimlessly about
whether to go east or west.  We must make our decisions purposefully.  Our most significant
opportunities will be found in times of greatest difficulty.
</p><p>
The vast, uncharted expanse of the Atlantic Ocean stood as a Goliath between Christopher
Columbus and the new world.  The hearts of his comrades became faint, their courage
dimmed, hopelessness engulfed them; but Columbus prevailed with his watchword,
"Westward, ever Westward, sail on, sail on."
</p><p>
<b>Power of calm conscience</b>
</p><p>
Carthage jail; an angry mob with painted faces; certain death faced the Prophet Joseph Smith. 
But from the wellsprings of his abundant faith he calmly met the Goliath of death.  "I am
going like a lamb to the slaughter, but I am as calm as a summer's morning. I have a
conscience void of offense toward God, and toward all men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4#4">D&amp;C 135:4</a>).
</p><p>
Gethsemane, Golgotha, intense pain and suffering beyond the comprehension of mortal man
stood between Jesus the Master and victory over the grave. Yet he lovingly assured us, ". . .
be of good cheer: I have overcome the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>). "I go to prepare a place for you,
. . . that where I am, there ye may be also" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/2-3#2">John 14:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
And what is the significance of these accounts?  Had there been no ocean, there would have
been no Columbus. No jail, no Joseph. No mob, no martyr. No cross, no Christ!
</p><p>
Should there be a Goliath in our lives or a giant called by any other name, we need not "flee"
or be "sore afraid" as we go up to battle against him.  Rather we can find assurance and
divine help in that inspired psalm of David: "The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want . . .
</p><p>
"Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear
no evil: for thou art with me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/23/1,4#1">Ps. 23:1,4</a>).
</p><p>
May this knowledge be ours, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
