<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Kingdom of God or Catastrophe</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 5-12</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Elder Joseph W. Anderson has just read the vital statistical data, the changes in ward and
stake organizations, and the obituaries of the Church.
</p><p>
There are a few more items which might be mentioned, in which you will probably be
interested.
</p><p>
The Church construction of chapels, classrooms, and recreation halls continues without
abatement, indeed, with acceleration. During the last nine months, the Church has spent
$5,568,000.00 in stakes, and $2,109,000.00 in missions, a total of $7,677,000.00, or a total to
date this year, including local funds contributed for this purpose, in stakes, $10,337,000.00,
and in the missions, $2,704,000.00 (I am not reading the full amount), or a total of
$13,041,000.00.
</p><p>
TEMPLE CONSTRUCTION
</p><p>
You already know about the dedication of two temple sites in Europe&mdash;the first in the history
of the Church&mdash;one at Berne, Switzerland, and another between London and Brighton,
England.
</p><p>
The construction of the temple in Los Angeles is proceeding satisfactorily. We wish to
commend the members of the Church in the Los Angeles Temple district for their
magnanimous contribution to this edifice. As has already been announced, they volunteered to
contribute over a million dollars towards the construction and completion of this edifice, and
their payments are practically up-to-date. In addition to giving this large cash contribution
they recently volunteered to assist in the landscaping, and even now they are planting
shrubbery and getting trees so that at the time of dedication of the temple, the grounds will be
properly and beautifully landscaped. May the Lord bless these faithful people and enable them
to fulfil their promise in order that this edifice may be completely paid for by its dedication
within a year and a half or two years.
</p><p>
The plans already are drawn for the temple in Switzerland, and the architect and contractor
are proceeding so that that edifice will be completed without delay.
</p><p>
STAKE MISSIONARY WORK
</p><p>
You will be interested to know that the stake missionary work is meeting with unprecedented
results: 6518 stake missionaries are now working within the organized stakes. To date there
have been 3441 who have accepted the gospel through the efforts of these stake missionaries,
and the work is continuing with unabated zeal.
</p><p>
YOUTH PROGRAM
</p><p>
We might mention, too, for your interest, that the youth program is being carried on most
ably. I shall not take time to weary you with statistics, but in the girls' program, covering all
the girls from twelve to nineteen, for August 1953, there were 56,332 enrolled. We believe
that is one hundred percent of all the girls between those ages. The average attendance of the
girls at the three meetings for this month, August, were as follows: Of those young girls,
forty-nine percent of them attended sacrament meetings; fifty-nine percent attended the
Sunday Schools; and fifty-four percent attended the MIA meetings. We commend you, sisters.
A very definite program is carried out by the MIA for getting in touch with inactive girls and
in trying to interest them in the Mutual Improvement Association.
</p><p>
In YMMIA during the past three years there has been an increase of 11,872 in enrolment in
the scouting program. According to a report (we have this from Brother D. L. Roberts, who is
director of the Mormon relationships in the Boy Scouts, and from Brother Elbert R. Curtis,
general superintendent), on Sunday evening, during the jamboree at Los Angeles, July 19, a
great convocation was held. Attending were more than forty-five thousand Boy Scouts, and
there were present fifty thousand or more visitors. During the convocation great attention was
paid to the churches of America, and religious training, and our Church received favorable
attention. This made us happy to see an organization such as scouting bring such favorable
comments about the work that is being done for the young in the Church.
</p><p>
I have notes before me emphasizing particularly what the Primary Association is doing for
our eleven-year-old boys who are now taking up preliminary Scout work, also commending
the high percentage of attendance at Primary meetings, and the most excellent work that is
being done by the Primary hospital.
</p><p>
UNIFICATION OF CHURCH SCHOOL SYSTEM
</p><p>
Since our meeting of last April there has been a unification of the Church school system. We
have had, heretofore, as you know, a Church board of education with a commission presiding
over the colleges, institutes, and seminaries. Then we had a board of trustees presiding over
Brigham Young University. Those two great branches of education are now
united under the direction of Dr. Ernest L. Wilkinson, who is appointed administrator of the
Church board of education, in addition to his presidency over Brigham Young University.
</p><p>
Here I wish to say a word of commendation for the excellent service rendered by
Commissioner Franklin L. West. For years he has devoted his entire time to the advancement
of the institutes and seminaries and colleges of the Church. His heart has been in the work.
He has expressed and radiated a fervent testimony of the divinity of the restored gospel, and
his heart has been centered upon the instructing of the youth in the fundamentals and ideals of
the Church of Jesus Christ. He retires with the confidence and blessing of the Authorities of
the Church.
</p><p>
Under his direction there has been a steady increase in the number enrolled in our institutes
and seminaries. Last year there were enrolled 36,081 seminary students, 4202 institute
students, 1140 in the schools of the islands of the Pacific, or a total of 41,423.
</p><p>
I am glad to report to you that the Church is moving on with great rapidity and its influence
being extended throughout the world.
</p><p>
PASSING OF TWO GENERAL AUTHORITIES
</p><p>
Since our last meeting, as already reported by Brother Anderson, two members of the General
Authorities have passed away: Elder A. E. Bowen of the Council of the Twelve, and Elder
Stayner Richards, Assistant to the Twelve&mdash;two stalwarts, clear in vision, sound in judgment;
men loyal and true to their callings, to the ideals and doctrines of the Church! We pay respect
to their memory. May their acts and services during their lifetime continue to reverberate for
good in the hearts not only of all members of the Church, but of all those outside of the
Church who were fortunate enough to come in contact with these two great men.
</p><p>
COMMENDATION OF TEACHERS AND CHURCH GROUPS
</p><p>
I have mentioned particularly the work of the Church among the youth, because the future of
this world is largely determined, as Goethe says, "upon the opinions of its young men under
five and twenty."
</p><p>
If that be true, to awaken in the minds of the youth of the land a desire to achieve life's truest
values is to render the greatest of all great services to our country.
</p><p>
With this thought in mind, I commend the teachers in our public schools, who under present
difficulties, are remaining true to their post of duty. Let us hope that they will continue to do
so, and not go off on a tangent vainly seeking redress in unions, which will only aggravate a
condition already regrettable. We have confidence in the teachers. They will be loyal to their
profession, teaching the young to be loyal and true to our country, to love the best in life,
rather than to seek that which leads to selfishness.
</p><p>
This morning I want, also, to commend the Presiding Bishopric, the bishops of the wards, the
presidencies of the Aaronic Priesthood quorums, for their efforts to bring into activity all the
boys between the ages of 12 and 19, and what is equally commendable, they are reaching out
to incorporate in this great spiritual uplift those who are classified as the "senior members of
the Aaronic Priesthood," a group of potential power for great good, not only in the Church,
but in the world, many of them leading businessmen and professional men. I commend you,
brethren, for organizing these able men into groups that their influence may be felt for good.
</p><p>
THE KINGDOM OF GOD OR CATASTROPHE
</p><p>
With this in mind, I should like to give the following message, feeling as I do this morning,
the potency and divinity of the gospel of Jesus Christ. With all my soul I feel this morning
that there is truly ". . . none other name under heaven given among men,
whereby we must be saved" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/4/12#12">Acts 4:12</a>).
I cannot see how men can doubt that.
</p><p>
When I was a boy, there hung above the pulpit in the chapel in Huntsville, (Utah), a picture
of President John Taylor. Under it in gold letters were these words:
"<i>The Kingdom of God or Nothing</i>."
</p><p>
In childhood I gave little if any thought to its implication, nor in youth did I try to
comprehend its significance.
</p><p>
This morning, with world conditions in mind&mdash;international suspicion and
enmities&mdash;threatening war clouds&mdash;"man's inhumanity to man," and other discouraging aspects of human
relationships, I am inclined to paraphrase that motto to read: "The kingdom of God or
catastrophe."
</p><p>
Tradition tells us that Peter, when on the Appian Way going toward Rome, was met by this
question "<i>Quo Vadis?</i>" (Whither goest thou?) Were that question put to people today, many
pessimists would answer that we are headed for catastrophe, if not total destruction. One has
already said of Europe: 
</p><p>
"On the whole, during many generations, there has been a gradual decay of religious influence
in European civilization. Each revival touches a lower peak than its predecessor, and each
period of darkness, a lower depth. The average curve marks a steady fall in religious tone.
Religion is tending to degenerate into a decent formula wherewith to embellish a comfortable
life.
</p><p>
"Russia officially sanctions irreligion, and approves a system of sex relations lower than any
sanctioned by the lowest African tribe.
</p><p>
"The paleolithic savages so far as we know had no such practices" (<i>Man's Social Destiny</i>, p. 23).
</p><p>
WHAT MEN THINK
</p><p>
And Hayden, writes as follows: "Today, as never before, mankind is seeking social
betterment. Today, as seldom if ever before, human society is threatened with disintegration,
if not complete chaos. All the ancient evils of human relationships, injustice, selfishness,
abuse of strength, become sinister and terrible when reinforced by the vast increase of
material power. The soul of man cowers, starved and fearful, in the midst of a civilization
grown too complex for any mind to visualize or to control. Joy and beauty fade from human
living. Yet life, abundant, beauteous, laughing life, has been our age-long labor's end. What
other conceivable worth has the mastery of the material world, the exploitation of the
resources of nature and the creation of wealth, except as a basis for the release of the life of
the spirit. We are witnessing either the crumbling of civilization under the weight of its
material mechanism or the birth of a new organization with a spiritual ideal."
</p><p>
Oswald Spengler thinks, and has so written: "This machine technics (referring to the world)
will end with the Faustian civilization and one day will lie in fragments, forgotten&mdash;our
railways and steamships as dead as the Roman roads and the Chinese Wall, our giant cities
and skyscrapers in ruins like old Memphis and Babylon. The history of this technics is fast
drawing to its inevitable close. It will be eaten up from within like the grand forms of any
and every culture. When, and in what fashion, we know not."
</p><p>
These references indicate what some men are thinking about the present-day conditions, and
where such conditions are leading. Whether you accept them as true, or not, we must face the
fact that we are in a changing world, and that the destruction of present-day civilization is a
possibility.
</p><p>
But, brothers and sisters, the Lord has something better in store for his children than complete
destruction. Nations may be born, live, flourish for a time, and through internal corruption or
other causes, die or be destroyed; but the human race will continue, and the kingdom of God
be established.
</p><p>
" . . . behold," said Daniel, "one like the Son of man came with the clouds
of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days . . .
</p><p>
"And there was given him dominion and glory, and a kingdom, that all people, nations, and
languages, should serve him: his dominion is an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass
away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/13-14#13">Dan. 7:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
The paramount need in the world today is a clearer understanding by human beings of moral
and spiritual values, and a desire and determination to attain them.
</p><p>
Never before in the history of the world has there been such a need of spiritual awakening.
Unless there is such an awakening, there is danger of catastrophe among the nations of the
world.
</p><p>
But I feel this morning, with all my soul, that the sun of hope is rising. Many thinking men
and women are recognizing the need of man's looking up towards the heavens instead of his
groveling in response to his animal nature. One man commenting on this said, that "If all the
destroyers of civilization could be eliminated, and the traits of the rest of us could be
eliminated, an approach to the millennium some hundred years hence is by no means
inconceivable."
</p><p>
The Savior of the world said: "I am come that they might have life, and that they might have
it more abundantly" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/10#10">John 10:10</a>).
</p><p>
Whether we live miserably or live abundantly depends upon ourselves. Look introspectively,
young man and young woman, and determine whether your innermost thoughts hold you on
the animal plane or whether they tend to lift you into the mental, moral, and spiritual realm.
And you be your own judge. Are you scheming to exploit another for personal gain? Are you
justifying a lie? Are you entertaining the thought of robbing a young woman of her virtue?
Are you, young woman, justifying an act of unchastity in exchange for the attention or favor
of a male companion? If these or any other selfish sinful thoughts obsess you, then you are
not following the path of the abundant life, but are contributing to the continuance of a
sordid, unhappy world.
</p><p>
FOUR FUNDAMENTAL TRUTHS
</p><p>
In the brief sojourn of Jesus upon the earth, he marked clearly "the way the truth, and the
life" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>).
</p><p>
I shall take time this morning to call your attention to four incidents in his life, and mention
probably, but of course, briefly, some connotations of those incidents, I repeat, because I feel
and know, that through him and through him only, and by obedience to the gospel of Jesus
Christ, can we find happiness and salvation in this world and eternal life in the world to
come. But I am thinking particularly of happiness and joy here and now, in this atomic age.
</p><p>
First, recall His experience on the Mount of Temptation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/1-11#1">Matt. 4:1-11</a>).
In that experience we find taught the
sublime necessity of subordinating the animal part of our natures to the spiritual. Man is a
dual being&mdash;he is human, physical, of the earth, earthy, but he is, also, divine the offspring
of God.
</p><p>
Well might Carlyle say: "There are heights in man which reach the highest heaven, and
depths that sink to the lowest hell&mdash;for are not both heaven and hell made out of him,
everlasting miracle and mystery that he is?"
</p><p>
"Beloved," said John, "now are we the sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we shall
be: but we know that, when he shall appear, we shall be like him; for we shall see him as he
is" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/3/2#2">1 Jn. 3:2</a>).
</p><p>
On the Mount of Temptation Jesus resisted every appeal to his physical appetite&mdash;" . . .
command that these stones be made bread"; every appeal to his vanity&mdash;"If thou be the son of
God cast thyself down"&mdash;from the pinnacle; every appeal to his selfishness and pride, every
bribe offered by way of power and wealth in exchange for spiritual companionship with his
Father (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/3,6,9#3">Matt. 4:3,6,9</a>).
Resisting all he said to the tempter: "Get thee hence, Satan: for it is
written, Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/10#10">Matt. 4:10</a>).
</p><p>
VALUE OF NOBLE THOUGHTS
</p><p>
Then during his brief mission among men, he emphasized the value of entertaining noble
thoughts, what you think will determine your character, not alone what you do, and knowing
that what one thinks about in one's secret moments determines what he is
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/28#28">Matt. 5:28</a>). He "decried the
fatal effects of hatred and jealousy in the mind of the individual more vehemently than he did
the acts that hate and jealousy prompt. Modern physiology and psychology confirm the
practical wisdom of his teachings. These evil passions destroy a man's physical vigor and
efficiency&mdash;they pervert his mental perceptions and render him incapable of resisting the
temptations to commit acts of violence. They undermine his moral health. By insidious stages
they transform the man who cherishes them into a criminal. On the other hand, if they are
banished, and wholesome, kindly thoughts and emotions take their place, the man is incapable
of crime. Right thoughts and feelings, if persistently kept in the forefront, inevitably lead to
right acts." "A good tree bears good fruit; an evil tree, evil fruit" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/17#17">Matt. 7:17</a>). A good
tree, he says, cannot bring forth evil fruit, nor an evil tree bring forth good fruit
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/18#18">Matt. 7:18</a>). That
teaching lies at the very bottom of Christ's ethical teachings. His whole effort was to make
the tree good, for when that end was achieved, the good qualities of the fruit were assured.
Resist evil, members of the Church, young and old, and the devil will flee from you.
</p><p>
The <i>second</i> incident I take from the Sermon on the Mount&mdash;a mountain in the vicinity of the
Sea of Galilee. "No man can serve two masters: for either he will hate the one, and love the
other; or else he will hold to the one, and despise the other. Ye cannot serve God and
mammon" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/24#24">Matt. 6:24</a>).
Then he added, "But seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his
righteousness; and all these things shall be added unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>). Do you believe
that? I believe in every word that Jesus spoke and to me the teaching is applicable in my life
and yours.
</p><p>
Keeping in mind the fact that we are the children of our Father in heaven, when we seek the
kingdom of God, first we become conscious of a new aim in life. To nourish and delight the
body with its appetites and passions, as animals do, is no longer the chief end of mortal
existence. Spiritual attainments not physical possessions become the chief goal. God is not
viewed from the standpoint of what we may get from him, but what we may give to him.
Only in the complete surrender of our inner life may we rise above the selfish sordid pull of
nature.
</p><p>
"Giving God the glory" is a sure means of subduing selfishness&mdash;a willingness on the part of
the individual to keep God as the ideal in his life. Faith, therefore, is a foundation element in
true character building; for an upright character is the result only of continued effort and right
thinking, the effect of long-cherished associations with Godlike thoughts. He approaches
nearest the Christ spirit who makes God the center of his thoughts; and he who can say in his
heart, "Not my will, but thine be done"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/42#42">Luke 22:42</a>),
approaches most nearly the Christ ideal.
</p><p>
TWO GREAT COMMANDMENTS
</p><p>
The <i>third</i> incident is the scene with the Pharisees when a lawyer asked him: "Master, which is
the great commandment in the law?
</p><p>
"Jesus said unto him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy
soul, and with all thy mind.
</p><p>
"This is the first and great commandment.
</p><p>
"And the second is like unto it. Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36-39#36">Matt. 22:36-39</a>).
</p><p>
For two thousand years, practically, men have considered this sublime doctrine as
impractical&mdash;too ideal, they say, but if we sincerely believe in Christ's divinity, that he is "the way, the
truth and the life" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/6#6">John 14:6</a>),
we cannot consistently doubt the applicability of his
teachings to everyday life.
</p><p>
True, there are weighty problems to solve&mdash;evils of the slums, the ever-recurring conflicts
between labor and capital, drunkenness, prostitution, international hatreds, and a hundred other
current questions. But if heeded, Christ's appeal for personal integrity, honor, fair-dealing, and
love is basic in the proper solution of all these social and economic difficulties.
</p><p>
CHANGE MEN'S HEARTS
</p><p>
Most certainly before the world even approaches these ideals, men's hearts must be changed.
Christ came into the world for that very purpose. The principal reason for preaching the
gospel is to change men's hearts and lives, and you brethren who go from stake to stake and
hear the evidence and testimony of those who have been converted recently through the stake
missionary work, can testify how the conversion has changed their lives, as they have given
their testimonies. By such conversion they bring peace and good will to the world instead of
strife, suffering. On changing men's hearts Beverly Nichols, author of <i>The Fool Hath Said</i>,
writes truly: 
</p><p>
"You <i>can</i> change human nature. No man who has felt in him the spirit of Christ even for a
half minute can deny this truth, the one great truth in a world of little lies. You do change
human nature, your own human nature if you surrender it to him... Human nature must be
changed on an enormous scale in the future unless the world is to be drowned in its own
blood. And only Christ can change it."
</p><p>
"Live in all things outside yourself by love," says Browning through Paracelsus, "and you
shall have joy. This is the life of God; it ought to be our life. In him it was perfect, but in all
created things, it is a lesson learned slowly and through difficulty."
</p><p>
LESSON FOR YOUTH
</p><p>
The <i>fourth</i> scene I name is with his disciples just before Gethsemane, when he said, "And
now I am no more in the world, but these are in the world...
</p><p>
"I pray not that thou shouldest take them out of the world, but that thou shouldest keep them
from the evil" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/11,15#11">John 17:11,15</a>).
</p><p>
There is your lesson, young folk! You are in the midst of temptation, but you, as Christ on
the Mount of Temptation, can rise above it.
</p><p>
We <i>can</i> so live, it is possible, that as members of the Church we can say to all the world in
the words of Thomas Nixon Carver: "Come, our way of life is best because it works best. Our
people are efficient, prosperous and happy because we are a body who aid one another in the
productive life. We waste none of our substance in vice, luxury, or ostentation. We do not
dissipate our energy in brawling, gambling, or unwholesome habits. We conserve our
resources of body and mind and devote them to the upbuilding of the kingdom of God, which
is not a mystical but a real kingdom. We believe that obedience to God means obedience to
the laws of nature, which are but the manifestations of His will; and we try by painstaking
study to acquire the most complete and exact knowledge of that will, in order that we may
conform ourselves to it."
</p><p>
Yesterday, in this Tabernacle, seven or eight thousand women gathered&mdash;our mothers,
members of the Relief Society. I wish the whole Church might have partaken of the spirit of
that great conference. If so, we should have greater assurance in our souls that these ideals to
which I have made brief mention will be effective throughout the world in bringing about a
desire for greater spirituality, a greater need for the testimony that God lives, that his Son
Jesus Christ is the Savior of the world, and that divine beings restored to the
Prophet Joseph Smith the gospel of Jesus Christ as he established it in the Meridian of Time.
</p><p>
I bear you that testimony this morning and pray that the influence of priesthood quorums, of
auxiliaries, and of the missionaries may be more effective from this time on than ever before
in leading the honest in heart of the whole world to turn their eyes upward to the worship of
God, our eternal Father, and give them power to control the animal nature and live in the
spirit, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
