<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Train Up a Child . . ."</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Victor L. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Victor L. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 19-20</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President David O. McKay has said: "The home is truly the first unit of society, and
parenthood is next to Godhood. The relationship of the children to the parents should be one
which would enable those children to carry out ideal citizenship as they become related to the
state and to the larger forms of society. The secret of good membership in the Church or good
citizenship in the nation lies in the home.  If and when the time ever comes that parents shift
to the state the responsibility of rearing their children, the stability of the nation will be
undermined, and its impairment and disintegration will have begun . . .
</p><p>
"Would you have a strong and virile nation?&mdash;then keep your homes pure. Would you reduce
delinquency and crime?&mdash;lessen the number of broken homes. It is time that civilized people
realize that the home largely determines whether children shall be of high or low character.
Home-building, therefore, should be the paramount purpose of parents and of the nation."
(<i>The Improvement Era</i>, April 1963, pp. 252-53.)
</p><p>
<b>Troubled parents&mdash;troubled children</b>
</p><p>
As I travel about the Church and discuss various problems of youth, I invariably get the
response: "If we did not have trouble with the parents, we would not have trouble with the
children."
</p><p>
A national Explorer leader emphasized this point when be said, "One of our greatest problems
is to know how to teach boys to be honest when their parents are dishonest."
</p><p>
Today I should like to direct my remarks to parents.
</p><p>
If I understand the teachings of the Church, one of the greatest of all responsibilities we have
as members is that of parenthood.  We hear this statement repeated frequently: "The family is
the most important unit in time and in eternity." This I accept as truth.
</p><p>
<b>Through the eyes of youth</b>
</p><p>
There probably is not a parent in the Church but who would be offended if accused of not
loving his or her children, and yet, when looking at parent-child relationships through the eyes
of a teenager, many questions arise.
</p><p>
Take, for instance, the young man who had almost reached the state of incorrigibility when he
came to a counselor for help.  He was drinking excessively; he was a chain smoker; he was
continually in trouble with the law; and yet he came from a good LDS home. I'm sure his
parents loved him and would have done anything in the world to help him, but let us see what
the counselor discovered.
</p><p>
When asked if he liked the taste of liquor, the boy replied that he hated it.  When asked if he
enjoyed smoking, he said he detested the taste of tobacco.  When asked why he was
constantly in trouble with the law, he answered that he really didn't want to do many of the
things he did.
</p><p>
The counselor delved deeper and found that the boy's bedroom was in the basement, directly
under the living room.  When his father walked across the room, the boy could hear his
footsteps overhead, the sound of which made him acutely nauseated.
</p><p>
Further interviews revealed that the boy loved his father but felt that he was a total failure in
his father's eyes. You see, he simply could not satisfy him, no matter how hard he tried. His
father was a perfectionist, and no matter what the son did, the father pointed out how he
could have done better. Never did he compliment him. The result: a boy lost in a confused,
frustrating, and difficult world with no one to help him.
</p><p>
His father was a good man, active in the Church.  I am sure he loved his son, but did he
really?  Was his love unselfish? Was it the kind of love that gave nourishment and
encouragement to those less able than he, or was it the kind that demanded perfection to
satisfy himself?
</p><p>
<b>Analyze relationships with children</b>
</p><p>
Parents, I believe it behooves us to analyze closely our relationship with each of our children
to see if our actions reflect true love.  Do we want to teach and train our children to take their
proper places in society and become better parents than we are?  If so, we must be aware of
our shortcomings and overcome them.  You see, this father had had the same kind of strict,
overbearing father himself. Like father, like son.  Surely, we must encourage our children to
develop their talents and to achieve to the greatest extent of their ability.  I hope, however,
our motive is for their own development, growth, and happiness and not to satisfy our
personal pride.
</p><p>
A few months ago I had a most revealing interview with a lovely young college student.  This
young lady was the youngest in her family. All her brothers and sisters had married and left
home.  Her father was a farmer.  She had worked on the farm each summer plowing and
doing other farm work generally done by boys and men. This she did not mind, but now she
was 19.  She said she loved her parents with all her heart and would never do anything to
hurt them. She said, "Bishop Brown, my folks expect me to come back home this summer
and help on the farm, but I have simply got to find out if I am really Susie Jones or just
Brother Jones' little girl, as I have always been. I have got to find out if I am a real person, if
I can stand on my own feet and make decisions, or be totally dependent upon my parents."
</p><p>
Here was a lovely young lady loved by her parents&mdash;there is no doubt about that because of
the respect and love she had for them&mdash;but in the process of growing up, it would appear
that decisions she should have been making for herself were made by her parents.  Had their
love smothered their daughter?  Were they preparing her for the day when she would, of
necessity, have to make decisions on her own?
</p><p>
<b>Give children training and experience in decision-making</b>
</p><p>
There are some parents who feel their children just are not capable of making decisions.  How
can children ever develop this capacity if, as they grow up, they are not taught and given wise
guidance?
</p><p>
Of course, good sense must be used in determining how far to go in letting a child make his
own decisions.  Recently, I visited with a young woman who is having marital difficulty with
her third husband.  This young lady has a mother who is still making her decisions for her.
</p><p>
<b>In taking responsibility</b>
</p><p>
Parents, may I suggest that we analyze our relationships with our children.  Are we teaching
them in such a way as to prepare them for the responsibilities of life, or are we protecting
them to the point that when they find themselves on their own, they are lost?
</p><p>
I should like to quote a few excerpts from a discussion Dr. Dana L. Farnsworth had with
Lester David regarding parent-child relationships: 
</p><p>
"Your prime goal as a parent is to help your child grow up with the good inner feeling that he
or she is a perfectly capable, worthwhile human being, able to stand on his or her own feet."
</p><p>
Here are some of the rules he gives toward accomplishing this objective: 
</p><p>
<b>"Give emotional support"</b>
</p><p>
First: <i>"Give them emotional support when they need it most&mdash;right at the start of their life.</i>
</p><p>
"A baby comes into the world utterly dependent upon other human beings. If the help he
needs is forthcoming promptly and consistently, accompanied by love, he learns very early
one of the most important lessons of his entire life&mdash;that he can rely upon people.  The baby
whose first basic needs are met begins to develop a positive, confident outlook essential for
later emotional health.  Chances are that through life, he will have the feeling that things are
going to work out well for him.
</p><p>
"If parents are not warmly responsive to an infant, he is apt to develop a suspicion and a
mistrust of people. He may later withdraw from them, refusing to be their friend, in order to
protect himself from hurt. Such a person cannot become a warm and loving wife or husband.
</p><p>
"Of course, when I suggest parents respond to their infants' needs, I certainly do not mean
that babies must be hovered over and entertained every minute.  Strike a happy medium."
</p><p>
<b>"Early start to independence"</b>
</p><p>
Second:  "<i>Start them early on the road to independence.</i>
</p><p>
"Once I watched a very small child trying to button his coat.  His mother,
suddenly aware he was having difficulties, quickly said: 'Here, let Mommy fix it.' And she
did.  But she also did nothing to help her son feel capable . . .
</p><p>
"You can help [a child achieve] balance by permitting him to try his own wings, while at the
same time protecting him from real dangers. Let him stand, walk, climb, do as much as
possible for himself, and praise him for his accomplishments.  Have you seen the smile of
triumph that lights up a toddler's face when he's done something all by himself&mdash;fixed a toy,
carried a package or even just stood up? He glows inside, too, with a wonderful feeling of 'I
can.'
</p><p>
"As he grows, the child becomes more and more concerned with doing useful things.  The
things he achieves himself become crucially important to him.  He gains confidence by trying
and succeeding. So let him try out his basic knowledge and skills.  Let your son try to climb
that fence, build a tree house, manage his affairs.  Let your daughter arrange her own social
activities, even plan her own party.
</p><p>
"Be sure, of course, that you do not expect too much of your child, criticize him with undue
harshness, or permit activities that are unsafe at his age."
</p><p>
<b>"To make up their minds"</b>
</p><p>
Third: "<i>Teach children to make up their minds.</i>
</p><p>
"A twelve-year-old boy came home from school one day and told his mother he wanted to
run for class president, but wasn't quite sure.  That evening at dinner, while the boy sat
quietly, his parents debated whether he ought to make the race, discussing the pros and cons
and, finally, deciding that he should not because his schedule for the next year would be too
heavy.
</p><p>
"Too many parents do all or most of the problem-solving for their children. As a result, the
child never learns how to make up his mind about things, crucial for good mental health.
Every human being must make decisions all through life, and those who never learn how are
seriously handicapped.
</p><p>
"A child can be taught to make decisions by allowing him to do so as often as possible and to
profit by his mistakes.  In all of his day-to-day problems, let him understand you have faith in
his ability to unravel them. Listen to and discuss the facts with him.  Suggest approaches and
give the child the benefit of your wisdom and experience.  But avoid taking over his
independent right to decide upon the clothes he should wear, school problems and the like.
</p><p>
"Common sense should dictate the kind of problems best left to a child's judgment.  Those
with potentially serious consequences, of course, must still be decided by Mother and Father."
</p><p>
<b>Foster understanding</b>
</p><p>
Fourth: "<i>Keep the lines of understanding open</i> . . .
</p><p>
". . . [Realize] that each of your children is an individual, with his own abilities, personalities
and needs. Don't expect one to match another's accomplishments; rather, help him take pride
and pleasure in what he does well.
</p><p>
"[Be] courteous to your child, listening when he speaks, respecting his rights and feelings.
</p><p>
"[Present] logical arguments for your decisions.  'Because I say so' is a poor reply when a
child asks why he is required to do something.  Giving sensible reasons makes you a fair and
reasonable person in your child's eyes. He may not acquiesce gracefully, but inwardly, in
most cases, he will probably see your point."
</p><p>
<b>Commendation for doing well</b>
</p><p>
Fifth: "<i>Commend them for what they do well instead of condemning them for what they don't.</i>
</p><p>
". . . A 21 year-old college co-ed, under treatment for a severe neurosis, told her therapist: 'If
I came home from kindergarten with two stars, Mother wanted to know how come I didn't
get three like the day before.  If I got four marks over 90, she wondered how come the fifth
was only 80.
</p><p>
"Psychiatrists know that many persons with personality problems report they too seldom
received praise at home for their accomplishments.  Rather, their areas of
weakness were constantly being pointed out.  Over and over, they say, 'I grew up feeling I
couldn't do anything right' . . .
</p><p>
"Many parents feel guilty when their children do not turn out as well as they think they
should. This is not justified unless they really haven't tried to train their children or haven't
loved and respected them.  Even then it is of no help unless it motivates efforts to try to learn
how to develop better relations with them.  Being a parent is not easy and mistakes are
always made: they will not be too harmful if love and respect prevail." (<i>This Week</i>, June
19, 1966.)
</p><p>
<b>Sacred responsibility to children</b>
</p><p>
I pray that we as parents will accept the sacred nature of our responsibility to our children and
that we will endeavor to apply love in a wise and intelligent manner, and, of course, to do
this, the first requirement is that there is love and harmony between mother and father.  Our
homes must be a bulwark against the confusion and trials of the world.  If this generation is
to fulfill its destiny, it must be strong in the most important of all places and that is the home,
for in Proverbs we read, "Train up a child in the way he should go: and when he is old, he
will not depart from it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/22/6#6">Prov. 22:6</a>).
</p><p>
I leave you my testimony, my brethren and sisters, that God lives, that this is his Church, and
I do so in the name of Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
