<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Plea for Living the Gospel Expressed</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 131-133</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We have just listened to Elder Marion D. Hanks, whom, as I stated a few moments ago, you
have this day sustained as a member of the First Council of the Seventy.
</p><p>
Messages of appreciation of the television service rendered this forenoon to the people of the
Northwest and on the Pacific Coast, still come in. Knowing your interest, I will read two
more.
</p><p>
This is from Seattle, Washington signed by Wilford H. Payne, Seattle Stake: "Please accept
appreciation of the first television broadcast conference session to Saints and friends in the
Northwest."
</p><p>
From Los Angeles, signed by the President of the California Mission Bryan L. Bunker:
"Televised conference messages received perfectly. Marvelous missionary opportunity in the
future. Gratefully, President of the California Mission."
</p><p>
And now at the conclusion of this great conference, may we express again the gratitude of our
hearts to these men and companies, who have so graciously contributed of their means, with
so little expense to the Church, to broadcast by radio and by television, the proceedings of
this great conference. We want them to know that you and the Church generally deeply
appreciate their co-operative efforts.
</p><p>
EXPRESSES APPRECIATION
</p><p>
We express gratitude, also, to the public press. I want to name especially the reporters on our
papers, who have given such accurate and careful, complete accounts of the various meetings,
speakers of our conference since last Wednesday, including the great Relief Society
conference.
</p><p>
We wish to express appreciation to the audience here in the Tabernacle, your responsiveness
and your reverence, may it be an example to the audiences, to the congregations throughout
the Church when they enter our places of worship: Very little moving about, no leaving of the
services, I have been favorably impressed and commend you.
</p><p>
We appreciate the co-operation of our city officials, their ready and efficient service, wherever
it is needed; our traffic officers in handling the crowds. I have noticed new precautionary
measures taken and the presence of the members of the police force on the corners,
courteously, carefully protecting the crowds surrounding this block and throughout the city.
</p><p>
We wish to mention again these beautiful flowers sent from Oahu and others furnished by our
local florists. We appreciate our singers, and although we have already expressed it to each
choir, I repeat again your appreciation of the Relief Society Singing Mothers, the members of
the Swiss-German Choir, the Men's Chorus, who rendered such good service last evening in
the Tabernacle, and finally, and of course not least, the members of our Tabernacle Choir. To
all of these and to all others, including our ushers, we extend heartfelt appreciation.
</p><p>
And now, this great conference draws to a close. Our anticipation, our hopes, our prayers that
it might prove to be uplifting and inspirational, have been realized, and for that we are
grateful to our heavenly Father, grateful for the inspiration he has given to the General
Authorities who have spoken to you. What great messages they have given to us and to the
world! Truly our hearts have been filled with gratitude that the Lord has magnified each one,
to the end that his word has been spoken.
</p><p>
In conclusion, may I leave just one closing thought. This Church of Jesus Christ commonly
known as "Mormonism," is in the world to make people happy. Happiness is the end, really,
of our existence. That happiness comes most effectively through service to our fellow men,
and the Church is the most effective means in the world through which that service may be
rendered.
</p><p>
There is no happiness without peace. Today, the President of the United States, his Cabinet,
Congress, the Senate the House of Representatives, the Judiciary, are all seeking peace in the
world. Nations are longing for it Mothers and fathers, grandmothers and grandfathers who
have children and grandchildren in the armed forces are praying daily that we might have
peace.
</p><p>
Peace is the message that came when the Savior was born a Babe in Bethlehem. It was
heralded by the angel choir, singing, "Glory to God in the highest, and on earth peace, good
will toward men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/14#14">Luke 2:14</a>).
</p><p>
"Peace," he said to his disciples toward the close of his ministry, "These things I have spoken
unto you that in me ye might have peace. In the world ye shall have
tribulation: but be of good cheer; I have overcome the world"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/33#33">John 16:33</a>).
</p><p>
After his resurrection, when the doors were closed and the ten disciples were in session, as he
greeted them, his first salutation was, "Peace be unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/21#21">John 20:21</a>).
And eight days later, when the eleven were there, the same salutation,
"Peace" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/26#26">John 20:26</a>).
</p><p>
What a glorious thing it is, brethren and sisters, and this is my message: Peace cannot be
found in external things. Peace comes from within. "There is no peace except by the triumph
of principles," said the wise Emerson. Peace is within the individual soul. There is no peace
when one's conscience is seared or when one is conscious of having committed some
untoward act.
</p><p>
There was certainly no peace in that young girl's soul who came and confessed the other
night, fearful of the disgrace she had brought upon her loving parents, fearful of how she
could again meet the world. She was experiencing the pangs of retribution&mdash;the antithesis of
peace.
</p><p>
Peace springs from righteousness in the soul, from upright living. If we are going about in the
world to establish peace, let us begin at home, first with each individual. If you want peace
tonight, remember yours is the responsibility to obtain it, and it is my responsibility, and it is
your privilege and mine to attain it.
</p><p>
Certainly, let us establish peace in our household. We are sending out missionaries, it is true,
to proclaim peace and universal brotherhood. That is one great mission of our Church. May
all the world recognize it and co-operate with us in spreading the glad news, the glad tidings
of great joy. That is the paramount purpose of our missionary work. May God guide the boys
and the girls, the young men and women who go out, paying their own expenses or receiving
support from their parents, in thus proclaiming peace to a disturbed and unsettled world. What
a glorious concept, but let us set the example by having peace in our homes.
</p><p>
Paraphrasing the author of <i>The Simple Life:</i> "Let our homes become sanctuaries for
ourselves." (I commend the appeal made by Elder Benson.)  Sanctuaries! A sanctuary is
where we have peace. May our homes become warm nests where children may be protected
and grow into noble men and women; where love may find privacy, old age repose, prayer an
altar, and the nation a sure source of strength and perpetuity.
</p><p>
With all my soul at the close of this great, inspirational conference, my dear fellow workers, I
say God bless you, that in your hearts and in your homes you may have peace. I say to all
our friends who have been listening in, may the peace that comes from obedience to the
gospel of Jesus Christ find lodgment in your hearts, through your acceptance of the truth.
</p><p>
May the spirit of peace be poured out upon all nations, that the threatening clouds of
destruction may be dissipated, and the sunshine of peace shine once more all over the world, I
pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
