<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Words to Live By"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1958, pp. 68-70</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Thank you, my brethren and sisters, those of you who were here this morning for your
sustaining vote.  I assure you that I will do everything within my power to be worthy of that
vote as I go about the Church serving the membership, our Heavenly Father and his Son,
Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I would be ungrateful if I did not mention something about one of our colleagues, Elder
Clifford E. Young. It was not my privilege to be here when he passed away, so I did not
attend his funeral service. I was touring a mission at the time. I am most grateful for his
companionship, for the splendid characteristics exemplified in his life, integrity to his calling,
his faith and testimony of the gospel, and his unselfish service, many times, I am sure, filling
his assignments when he was suffering physically though he did not indicate it.
</p><p>
I pray that I may imbibe and partake of these excellent lessons.
</p><p>
Then I welcome and look with joy and great anticipation toward associating with these two
splendid men you sustained this morning, Elders Critchlow and Dyer.  I have known them
both for many years, thirty or upwards. Having been employed by the same company that
Elder Critchlow has been with for so many years, I have seen him under fire, but he has
always come through a devoted son of God.
</p><p>
Likewise with Brother Dyer.  I have known of his work in the Church and just recently as I
had the privilege of attending the Kansas City Stake conference, I felt of his spirit there and
the spirit of many of his missionaries.  So I am looking forward to closer association with
these splendid servants of the Lord.
</p><p>
And now I would give you words to live by if the spirit will so dictate.  I am reminded of an
experience that happened in the life of President George Albert Smith.  Several years before
he became President of the Church, he gave a home for some months to a couple from
Holland.  They could speak but a few words of English and could understand very little
English. However, the Dutch brother insisted on going to the English-speaking fast meetings
and after about the third fast meeting as President Smith and he were walking back to the
Smith home, President Smith asked, "Why is it that you insist on going to the
English-speaking fast meeting when you understand so little of what is being said?" Here was
the significant reply from the Dutch brother, "It is not what I see that makes
me happy.  It is not what I hear that makes me happy. It is what I feel that makes me happy,
and I can feel just as good as anybody."
</p><p>
Yes, there are many who hear and yet do not hear. There are many who see, yet do not see. 
If our lives are in tune with the glorious teachings of the gospel of Jesus Christ, then we can
feel just as good as anybody.  We feel as good as anybody because we have a witness and a
conviction that Jesus is the Christ.  "If any man will do his will, he shall know of the
doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of myself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>). There is no
hesitancy, no surmising, no groping, but an assurance that God lives, that he is the Father of
our spirits and that Jesus is his Divine Son, that they have again appeared in the earth in this
dispensation as we have so gloriously sung a few moments ago.
</p><p>
Yes, I am grateful for the testimony of Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
It is interesting that I should have copied that testimony and his witness and that this song
should be sung just previous to my being called to occupy this position.  May I give it to
you? He likened his experience to that of Paul when he said: 
</p><p>
"However, it was nevertheless a fact that I had beheld a vision.  I have thought since, that I
felt much like Paul, when he made his defense before King Agrippa, and related the account
of the vision he had when he saw a light, and heard a voice; but still there were but few who
believed him; some said he was dishonest, others said he was mad; and he was ridiculed and
reviled. But all this did not destroy the reality of his vision.  He had seen a vision, he knew
he had, and all the persecution under heaven could not make it otherwise; and though they
should persecute him unto death, yet he knew, and would know to his latest breath, that he
had both seen a light and heard a voice speaking unto him, and all the world could not make
him think or believe otherwise"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/24#24">JS&mdash;H 1:24</a>).
</p><p>
Then Joseph further says: 
</p><p>
"So it was with me.  I had actually seen a light, and in the midst of that light I saw two
Personages, and they did in reality speak to me; and though I was hated and persecuted for
saying that I had seen a vision, yet it was true; and while they were persecuting me, reviling
me, and speaking all manner of evil against me falsely for so saying, I was led to say in my
heart: Why persecute me for telling the truth?  I have actually seen a vision; and who am I
that I can withstand God, or why does the world think to make me deny what I have actually
seen?  For I had seen a vision; I knew it, and I knew that God knew it, and I could not deny
it, neither dared I do it; at least I knew that by so doing I would offend God, and come under
condemnation" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/25#25">JS&mdash;H 1:25</a>).
</p><p>
My, what a powerful testimony! And there are thousands throughout the Church today, yes,
thousands upon thousands who have a witness within their hearts that God lives, that Jesus is
the Christ, that they did appear to the boy Joseph Smith, even though they have not seen or
experienced a like privilege. The Holy Spirit bears witness to this in the hearts of young and
old alike.  They feel good inside because they are living the truths of the gospel which have
been revealed in this day.
</p><p>
I should like to give you the witness from a young girl, seventeen years of age, a beautiful
young lady, growing into womanhood.  There was a period in her life when she might not
have been too sure of her religious convictions, but she is being reared in a good home where
the tenets of the gospel are lived, where parents (the father now passed away) feel good
because they are in tune.  Then she has some wonderful teachers and instructors in the
organizations of the Church.  Today she feels good because she has a burning testimony.
</p><p>
May I read her witness?
</p><p>
First, she said a group of MIA young folk invited some young people of another church to
visit a fireside. Sixty of them responded; there were only forty members of our Church
present. She says there was a great impression made upon many of the young folk, both
members and nonmembers. They loved their teacher, Sister Nona Dyer, who happens to be
the daughter of Brother and Sister LeGrand Richards. Here is her witness: 
</p><p>
"I really love the gospel, and it is the most powerful influence in my life. It seems that the
older I get, the deeper the spirit of the gospel penetrates my soul, and the more beautiful life
becomes.
</p><p>
"I certainly do admire Daddy for the way he lived the gospel and the example he set for
others, and Mother, who is so unselfish.  I just hope that someday I can learn to be that kind
of person and give something to others in return for what has been given to me."
</p><p>
These words we have heard, my brethren and sisters, are words to live by. They bring peace
and joy and hope in our hearts, regardless of what the conditions in the world may be.  As we
follow truth and abide by gospel teachings, we have no need to fear, I assure you.  Regardless
of who we are, we must keep alive this testimony in our hearts.
</p><p>
In conclusion, I will give you an experience that came to me from my colleague, Elder
Clifford E. Young, a year or so ago. It seems that before President Heber J. Grant passed
away, and many of you know that he was ill for many months, but three or four weeks before
he passed away, Brother Young was in his home visiting him. President Grant uttered this
prayer: "O God, bless me that I shall not lose my testimony and keep faithful to the end!"
Here was the prophet of the Lord at that time, holding the keys of the kingdom, praying that
he would not lose his testimony, that he would remain faithful to the end, even though he lay
on his sickbed and must have known that he would never be well again.
</p><p>
Does it behoove us, then, brothers and sisters, to be faithful to the end that we may keep alive
our testimonies through our works?  The Holy Spirit will keep us feeling good if we do our
part and remain faithful to the end.
</p><p>
I bear witness to you that I know that good feeling because I know God lives, that Jesus
Christ is his divine Son, that Joseph Smith was and is a prophet of God and those who have
succeeded him down to President David O. McKay are prophets of God, and he, President
McKay, has the mantle of authority and holds the keys of the kingdom of God in the earth. 
And I bear this testimony in the name of Jesus Christ our Savior. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
