<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Applying the Missionary Program</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President S. Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 43-44</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I shall begin by quoting a scripture that you all know very well: 
</p><p>
"Therefore, let every man stand in his own office, and labor in his own calling; and let not the
head say unto the feet it hath no need of the feet; for without the feet how shall the body be able
to stand?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/109#109">D&amp;C 84:109</a>)
</p><p>
The scriptures declaring the prime importance and necessity of the seventies being in the
missionary service are clear and to the point. I shall give you but one example: 
</p><p>
"The Seventy are to act in the name of the Lord, under the direction of the Twelve or the
traveling high council, in building up the church and regulating all the affairs of the same in all
nations, first unto the Gentiles and then to the Jews." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/34#34">D&amp;C 107:34</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Stake missionary system</b>
</p><p>
However, the application of the missionary program of the Church changes as generations and
conditions change. For example, we stressed the doctrine of gathering in a previous generation,
so it did not matter much where converts were made, rural or urban. They gathered to Zion.
Today we do not gather. Converts are encouraged to build the Church in their home districts;
and so we stress proselyting in ever-widening concentric circles with the meetinghouse as a
center. Where once the missionaries had no help from the ward or branch, its auxiliaries or its
people, now the whole stake missionary system is organized around the wards and branches,
their buildings and their people, to work within the framework of priesthood correlation.
</p><p>
Where once members helped missionaries by giving them meals, now members are the best
sources of finding people to whom the missionaries might teach the gospel. Because of the
growth of the Church, we can correlate the vast missionary system with the wards and stakes and
use these units to accelerate and implement our proselyting purposes.
</p><p>
<b>Ward proselyting program</b>
</p><p>
There have been great changes in the organization of our units. Where once the bishop had
inadequate help and felt no responsibility for missionary work, now the whole missionary
program centers in the bishop and his helpers in the highly functional meetinghouse and
well-organized auxiliary programs. How, then, can the proselyting purposes of the Lord be best
served in our present situation, keeping in mind the special calling of the seventies? Here are
some suggestions: 
</p><p>
1. <i>Have seventies presidents serve as group leaders</i>. The presidents of the quorums of seventy
should be so selected that, as nearly as possible, they can serve as group leaders in their wards.
Remember that all the missionary work in a stake is done in its wards. Certainly the seventy
presidents should direct the missionary work of their own quorum members in the wards in
cooperation, of course, with the bishops.
</p><p>
2. <i>Implement effective methods for finding investigator families</i>. The effort to find prospective
converts usually takes up to 80 percent of a missionary's time in any mission. Fifty years ago it
took from 90 to 100 percent. I as a missionary spent a hundred percent of my time finding
people. The seventies in the quorum are living in the various wards and should be the backbone
of the finding program in each ward. At all times each seventy and his family should be making
friends with and warming up two or more families of nonmembers.
</p><p>
Furthermore, because of the every-member-a-missionary program of the Church, each home
teacher should be urging the families under his care to find and make friends with non-member
families also. He should also teach his families the techniques to help them cultivate these
nonmember families. The group leader of the seventy who is the ward missionary representative
should be alert to this need in the whole ward and keep the bishop not only informed, but help
him to acquaint the other ward priesthood groups with methods whereby they also can assist in
this great finding program.
</p><p>
3. <i>Use correlation principles in quorum organization</i>. To make missionary correlation effective
in the wards of the stake, it follows that the stake mission presidency should be included among
the presidents of the quorum of the seventy. It would be expected that this mission presidency
would be chosen from the best available seventies or elders. If elders, they would be ordained
seventies and placed in the quorum presidency. In those stakes where the nonmember population
is so large that the members of the stake mission presidency would have their time fully taken
with the work of proselyting, they should be excused from group leadership. The quorum
presidents should then recommend group leaders from among the members of the group, and
after approval of the stake presidency, should install them. These group leaders should meet with
the quorum council on a regular basis to correlate the work of the quorum in all wards.
</p><p>
4. <i>Enlist aid of auxiliary organizations</i>. The seventy group leader would be expected to lead out
with suggestions to the ward auxiliary leaders about correlating their programs to assist in
finding prospective members. These programs may also be of great help in preparing people for
baptisms if they are used with wisdom. I do not have time to give an illustration of that
particular point.
</p><p>
5. <i>Understand functions of missionary work in a stake</i>. Missionary work is divided into three
main functions:</p><p>
a. <i>Finding</i>. The objective of "every member a missionary" makes every member responsible for
finding investigators and for preparing them to receive the missionary lessons. To prepare the
members for this important function is the duty of the home teachers serving those members,
who should, themselves, be prepared with helps and guides by the seventies group leader.
</p><p>
b. <i>Teaching</i>. The stake and full-time missionaries are responsible for teaching the gospel to
those whom the finders have made ready. This centers in the presentation of the lessons with
such additional or preliminary discussions as circumstances may warrant.
</p><p>
C. <i>Fellowshipping</i>. This is the responsibility of the home teachers. It might be well to assign
seventies to these new families to help orient them, preferably the same seventies who helped to
convert them.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of seventies</b>
</p><p>
One of the great responsibilities of home teachers is to convert the non-members in the
part-member families. These teachers should be seventies where available. With these families,
the seventies can use their missionary finding techniques to good advantage.
</p><p>
Missionary work may be done by priesthood holders other than seventies and by women, but the
chief responsibility rests on the seventies.
</p><p>
The stake president has the basic responsibility for the successful operation of the missionary
work in the stake. This missionary work is administered through the stake priesthood executive
committee and the stake correlation council, with the high counselor assigned to work with the
seventies and the stake mission serving as adviser to the stake president on missionary matters.
</p><p>
The bishop has the responsibility for successful operation of missionary work in the ward,
including the fellowshipping of new converts. Missionary work in the ward is administered
through the ward priesthood executive committee and the ward council, with the seventies group
leader as adviser to the bishop on missionary matters.
</p><p>
<b>Missionary correlation meetings</b>
</p><p>
In wards where full-time missionaries are working, the seventies group leader should hold a
ward missionary correlation meeting. It might well be attended by all stake and full-time
missionaries working in the ward area.
</p><p>
In every ward it should be determined how many possible investigators are available to be
taught, and then a program should be set up which will cause, so far as possible, an even flow of
investigators for the stake and full-time missionaries. Families who are cultivating nonmembers
under the inspiration of their home teachers, and seventies who are engaged in the program for
finding families, should correlate their efforts through the ward executive committee to bring
this about.
</p><p>
On the stake level, the quorum council should invite the attendance of full-time mission district
and zone leaders when correlating missionary work in the stake.
</p><p>
Do you not see, my brethren of the seventies, that when the great majority of all missionary work
is devoted to finding people and persuading them to listen&mdash;and you are charged with that
finding&mdash;you are for all practical purposes the stake mission. The other smaller percentage, and
the very important percentage&mdash;the teaching&mdash;is yours as soon as you will qualify yourselves
for that part. Some of you are now qualified. The members of the mission presidency are your leaders.
</p><p>
<b>Experience in rounding-up cattle</b>
</p><p>
Many years ago I worked for a period of time on a cow ranch, at the art of working with cattle. I
was a cow-puncher. In a corral set to one side was a fine-looking, pureblood horse with a
well-cared-for coat, pared hoofs, and combed mane and tail. He was the pride of the boss, who
rode him when he went on fence inspection or in rodeo parades in town. There came a day,
however, when there was an emergency. He had to ride after cattle, and he had to use this horse.
For an hour and a half the horse led the roundup and then, all lather, sweat, and foam, gave out
and could not be pushed another step. The rattail cayuses of the other punchers, hardened and
toughened from daily, hard driving, easily passed the pureblood horse.
</p><p>
The sad thing is that the pureblood had more real quality than the range horses, but by nonuse
was soft muscled and had no endurance. Had he been used, learned to dodge gopher holes,
rushed pell-mell downhill, over and through brush, been skinned and bumped, fallen down,
gotten up, been toughened by adversity and some failures, he would have outworked and
outdistanced the other horses.
</p><p>
The moral is clear, I suppose. Don't leave your cow horses in the corral or hitch them to wagons
doing other things if you want them to find and round up the cattle.
</p><p>
I testify that the Lord has spoken in this day and has given us the precious charge of preaching
the gospel to the world under the direction of the First Presidency and the Twelve. I sustain them
with all my heart, and the First Council sustains them with all its heart. I bear my witness that
President Joseph Fielding Smith is the chosen successor to President McKay, and that his
counselors are also called of God. They have not only my support, but also they have my deep
and abiding love. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
