<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Thou Shalt Love the Lord</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Taylor</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Taylor, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1969, pp. 36-38</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
From its beginning, the Church has constantly stressed the importance of the home. Homes
can be heaven here on earth. Where love is present in a home, it can and will be a happy
home.
</p><p>
<b>The principle of love</b>
</p><p>
When the Savior was here filling his earthly mission, he gave strong emphasis to the principle
of love. At one time a learned man, a lawyer, approached him and asked: "Master, which is
the great commandment in the law?
</p><p>
"Jesus said to him, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul,
and with all thy mind.
</p><p>
"This is the first and great commandment.
</p><p>
"And the second is like unto it, Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself."
</p><p>
Then, to give added strength to his words, he added: "On these two commandments hang all
the law and the prophets" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/36-40#36">Matt. 22:36-40</a>).
</p><p>
On another occasion the Lord taught that in addition to loving God our Father in heaven and
our neighbor, we should also love even our enemies. With our human frailties and prejudices,
that becomes a real challenge. Here is the counsel of the Lord: "Love your enemies, bless
them that curse you, do good to them that hate you, and pray for them which despitefully use
you, and persecute you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
</p><p>
An American statesman once made this remark: "Destroy your enemies by making friends of
them."
</p><p>
Then another has said: "You should be kind to your enemies, because you are the one who
made them."
</p><p>
The Lord has given strong counsel to husbands concerning their wives. Here is his command:
"Thou shalt love thy wife with all thy heart, and shalt cleave unto her and none else"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/22#22">D&amp;C 42:22</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Charity and love</b>
</p><p>
Consider now another phase of this great virtue&mdash;love&mdash;and its relationship to charity.
</p><p>
Charity and love, in some respects, seem to be synonymous. The ancient prophet Moroni
made this point clear when he quoted his father, Mormon: ". . . if ye have not charity, ye are
nothing . . . But charity is the pure love of Christ, and it endureth forever; and whoso is found
possessed of it at the last day, it shall be well with him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/46-47#46">Moro. 7:46-47</a>).
</p><p>
Charity can and should mean not only the pure love <i>of</i> Christ, but it should also mean pure
love <i>for</i> him and his love for us.
</p><p>
The Savior has demonstrated that his words concerning love are not empty, for he has shown
his love for us in his willingness to lay down his life, thus making it possible for us to receive
salvation through his atoning sacrifice and to achieve exaltation and eternal life through our
obedience to his commandments. His atonement gave meaning to his teaching that "greater
love hath no man than this, that a man lay down his life for his friends"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/13#13">John 15:13</a>). No
man could willingly give his life for a friend without sincerely loving him.
</p><p>
The Lord's unselfish act added great weight to his further words: "A new commandment I
give unto you, That ye love one another; as I have loved you, that ye also love one another"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/34#34">John 13:34</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Missionary experience</b>
</p><p>
A lonely young Persian student was in Munich, Germany, struggling to find a meaning to life.
He was deeply disturbed by the materialism and selfishness that seemed to fill the world, and
especially postwar Europe. He heard a knock at the door, and two humble Mormon elders
stood before him. He was not the least interested in religion. In fact, cynicism and doubt had
filled his soul until he was very nearly persuaded that there was no God nor any real meaning
to life. The only thing that interested him about these two young men was their English
accent. He had mastered four languages, but English was not one of them.
</p><p>
He invited them in, but as they started their discussion, he cautioned: "I don't want to hear
about your God, nor do I want to hear about how your religion got started. I only want to
know one thing: what do you people do for one another?" He waited, and a look of doubt
crossed his dark features, as the elders exchanged glances.
</p><p>
Finally, the spokesman for the two said softly, "We love one another."
</p><p>
Nothing he could have said would have been more electrifying than this simple utterance had
upon this young Persian, for the Holy Ghost immediately bore testimony to his soul that these
missionaries were true servants of the Lord. Shortly thereafter he was baptized, and he
presently is in this country receiving his doctorate degree at a local university&mdash;all because a
young Mormon missionary declared a simple truth, "We love one another."
</p><p>
<b>Ways to demonstrate love</b>
</p><p>
Virtually all religions tell us to love one another, but the restored Church tells us <i>how</i> to love
one another. The home teaching visits, the inspired Welfare Program, the unselfish service
performed in the temples, and the worldwide missionary system demonstrate in a very
practical way the teaching of the Savior: "Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>).
</p><p>
At this Easter time we are mindful of the Redeemer's sacrifice and acknowledge with heartfelt
gratitude and appreciation our debt to him.
</p><p>
In granting approval for the Savior's atonement, our Father in heaven has manifested his love
for us, his children. A prophet has made this plain in this statement: "For God so loved the
world, that he gave his only begotten Son, that whosoever believeth in him should not perish,
but have everlasting life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/16#16">John 3:16</a>).
</p><p>
How do we show our love for our Heavenly Father, and our love and appreciation for the
Savior? The Lord has given us the key. Listen to his admonition: "If thou lovest me thou
shalt serve me and keep all my commandments"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/29#29">D&amp;C 42:29</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Love an eternal principle</b>
</p><p>
Love is an eternal principle, an everlasting virtue. It operated before this earth life and will
continue to do so throughout the eternities. President McKay has made it clear in this
magnificent declaration: "Love is the most divine attribute of the human soul, and if you
accept the immortality of the soul, that is, if you believe that personality persists after death,
then you must believe that love also lives" (<i>Man May Know for Himself</i>, p. 221).
</p><p>
However, love is a virtue that can be lost. It may wither up and die as a result of neglect,
carelessness, and indifference. So President McKay has beautifully cautioned with the
following words: "Love must be fed . . . love must be nourished; love can be starved to death
just as literally as the body can be starved without daily sustenance" (<i>Ibid.</i>, p. 221).
</p><p>
<b>Solution for major ills</b>
</p><p>
Many of the major ills and disturbances that plague mankind in this unsettled world today and
are causing unhappiness and sorrow would disappear if the principle of love were manifested
and practiced.
</p><p>
If we would love the Lord our God, and show that love by keeping his commandments, we
would be law-abiding citizens, and there would be no need for law officers nor for prisons.
</p><p>
If we would but love one another and our neighbors as ourselves, there would be no need for
conventions and gatherings to be held behind barbed wire fences and protected by guards with
rifles and bayonets.
</p><p>
If we truly loved those who persecute us, they would no longer be enemies, but friends, and
there would be no wars or bloodshed.
</p><p>
If men sincerely loved their wives, wives loved their husbands, parents loved and understood
their children, and children loved and respected their parents, there would be no infidelity and
unfaithfulness, no quarreling or bickering found among mankind; divorce, juvenile
delinquency, broken homes, and frustration of youth would he eliminated; and other social,
moral, and economic ills would cease. Peace would abide in the world.
</p><p>
General Eisenhower was a person who not only expressed his love, but also demonstrated it in
behalf of others. Among his last words were these: "I have always loved my wife, I have
always loved my children, I have always loved my grandchildren, and I have always loved
my country."
</p><p>
<b>Power to change world</b>
</p><p>
Some years ago President McKay told the brethren assembled in this building that if the 9,000
or so priesthood bearers present would go forth from here and fully live the teachings of the
Master, they would have the power to change the world. This I believe. And I also believe
that if those of us who are here and those of you of the vast television and radio audience
would live fully the principle of love&mdash;and there's no greater principle&mdash;we would have the
power to change our lives, our homes, our neighborhoods, then this nation, and eventually the
world, for in the words of that stirring contemporary song, "Let there be peace on earth, and
let it begin with me." We do have the power to change our lives and surroundings by first
realizing our own worth and loving and valuing ourselves, and then by loving those with
whom we live and labor.
</p><p>
May we have the desire and courage to so act, I humbly pray, in the name of the Lord, Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
