<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Six Days May Work Be Done"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Oscar A. Kirkham</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Oscar A. Kirkham, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1956, pp. 26-28</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I pray for the blessings of the spirit of the Lord.  It has been my high privilege through
the years to address myself largely to the young people of this Church.  Today, with fathers
and mothers and grandfathers and grandmothers&mdash;I want to take the liberty of speaking to them
all.  Through the years one commandment has been intensified because of my travel in many
lands, and my association with many people, to make it really part of my life. I recite briefly
the fourth commandment: Keep the Sabbath day holy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8-11#8">Ex. 20:8-11</a>).
</p><p>
In the Old Testament we read that keeping the Sabbath was made a sign between Jehovah and
the Israelites: 
</p><p>
Six days may work be done; but in the seventh is the sabbath of rest, holy to the Lord . . .
</p><p>
(May I inject, for I sense deeply to whom I am talking.  Yes, I appeal to you to keep the
Sabbath day holy. Meetings, meetings, meetings, but never lose sight of the great
commandment of God to keep the Sabbath day holy.)
</p><p>
Wherefore the children of Israel shall keep the sabbath, to observe the sabbath
throughout their generations, for a perpetual covenant.<br />
It is a sign between me and the children of Israel for ever: for in six days the Lord
made heaven and earth, and on the seventh day he rested, and was refreshed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/31/15-17#15">Ex. 31:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
This counsel still remains with us today, and brings its many blessings to us.  Elder John A.
Widtsoe has said: "Keeping the Sabbath day builds a man physically, mentally, and
spiritually.  Physically he may rest and have a change of occupation.  Mentally, because he is
engaged in quorum and other meetings, private reading and studying. Spiritually, because the
day is dedicated to the Lord. Spiritual communion, contemplation, these are two essentials of
the Sabbath: It is a day of rest.  It should be kept holy."
</p><p>
On the Sabbath day every person shall attend religious meetings; fast, if desired, but always
fast on the day designated as fast day; partake of the Sacrament, another opportunity, with all
its great teachings; bear testimony of the Lord's truth and goodness.  I call your attention
especially to the next: Make right any misunderstandings with your fellow men.  Do all things
with singleness of heart toward the divine purpose of the Sabbath day.  It then becomes a day
of blessing, rejoicing, and prayer. When this is done, life-giving satisfaction comes from a
Sabbath well kept.
</p><p>
Latter-day Saints of today often face the question: "Are we expected to observe the Sabbath
day in the spirit in which the original commandment was given, or have changing conditions
modified and liberalized our living so that we may engage in some activities which in the past
have been banned?" To every Latter-day Saint the answer is: <i>Keep the Sabbath day holy</i>.  The
command to observe the Lord's day was first given as one of the Ten Commandments to the
children of Israel from Mt. Sinai.  Since that time it has been reiterated in every dispensation.
</p><p>
The Bible is clear, but as far as that record is concerned, to its very end Sabbath
observance continues to be the law of the Lord. The Book of Mormon definitely makes the
same commandment a part of the gospel teaching. The Doctrine and Covenants, the most
modern scripture, confirms this teaching, and enjoins strict observance of the Sabbath day. At
no time has there been any pronouncement, scriptural or otherwise, to change the
commandment. Therefore, regardless of what other churches may sanction, Latter-day Saints
are under the obligation to give strict observance, to rest from their labors, and to pay
devotion to the Most High.
</p><p>
Advance preparation could limit even household duties to a minimum.  On Saturday in my
grandmother's home the shoes were polished and placed in rows. Pies were baked, and the
weekly bath was taken care of.
</p><p>
Pioneers observed the Sabbath day as they crossed the plains.  From Rebecca Winters' diary I
quote: 
</p><p>
We camped early on a Saturday in August.  We had broken our wagons, and we
wished to mend our shoes. Washing and cooking to be done, for Sunday was always
observed. All retired early for rest, waiting for that lovely dawn, the hour when we
sang praises to God. As we sat and waited in our church in the forest for words of
inspiration, the men wore their clean hickory shirts, and the women and children had
clean starched bonnets.  "How Firm a Foundation" was sung.  Prayer was offered. 
Testimonies were borne.  The gospel was preached, and counsel and instruction given
by our Captain.  All felt to renew their diligence in serving the Lord, and with fresh
hope in their hearts they would soon meet with the faithful in the Valley.  So was
spent the Sabbath on the plains.
</p><p>
So important did this principle become a part of family life in a southern Utah city that a
good mother, although very ill, called her boys to her bedside and said: "Never put a harness
on a horse on the Sabbath day." This counsel has been kept, and this family has become one
of southern Utah's most prosperous families, and all have enjoyed living the good life.
</p><p>
The spirit of rest, worship, and prayer should be fostered and made a part of every Latter-day
Saint home.  May we live and enjoy this commandment of the Lord, and especially give it to
our children, our neighbors' children, and friends: "Six days may work be done;" but on the
seventh, may we keep it a day holy to the Lord, I humbly pray.
</p>
</div>
</div>
