<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Priesthood Correlation and the Home Evening</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 80-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
A week ago this afternoon I spent a glorious hour in President McKay's apartment office
considering the subject about which he wished me to talk: the presentation of what he said
our leaders have been talking about for fifty years&mdash;the importance of teaching the gospel in
the home. He indicated that this would be something of a theme in this general priesthood
meeting tonight.
</p><p>
<b>Theme of Fifty Years</b>
</p><p>
With that much of a lead or a guide to what I might say, I thought it wise to take a look
backward to pick up the thread of thinking of our leaders over this fifty-year period and glean
from the wisdom of the past a guide to our plans for the present as well as the future.
</p><p>
I thought to begin that review most properly we should give to you again what you have
heard and read in some of our official handbooks, the letter from the First Presidency a few
years ago which actually laid the foundation and indicated the direction that the correlation
program should take. And so I thought that probably I should read again one or two
paragraphs by which you can follow the plan by which the correlation is being developed. I
quote from that letter:
</p><p>
<b>"Home the Basis of the Righteous Life"</b>
</p><p>
"The home is the basis of a righteous life and no other instrumentality can take its place nor
fulfil its essential functions; the utmost the auxiliaries can do is to aid the home in its
problems, giving special aid and succor where such is necessary, that in aiding the home the
auxiliaries may well consider thinking of the home-life of the people as having three periods,
the first, from birth to twelve years of age or the childhood period; then the youth period
from twelve years up to the early twenties; and then adulthood, from the early twenties on to
the end of life.
</p><p>
". . . We feel assured that if the whole Church curricula were viewed from the vantage point
of what we might term the total purpose of each and all of these [priesthood quorums and
auxiliaries], it would bring about such a collation and limitation of subjects and subject
matters elaborated in various Auxiliary courses as would tend to the building of efficiency in
the Auxiliaries themselves in the matter of carrying out the purposes lying behind their
creation and function.
</p><p>
"We would therefore commend to you Brethren of the General Priesthood Committee the
beginning of an exhaustive, prayerful study and consideration of this entire subject, with the
cooperative assistance of the Auxiliaries themselves so that the Church might reap the
maximum harvest from the devotion of the faith, intelligence, skill and knowledge of our
various Auxiliary Organizations and Priesthood Committees." (<i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963,
pp. 82-83.)
</p><p>
<b>Correlation to Strengthen the Home</b>
</p><p>
That's the end of the quotation.
</p><p>
In those instructions there were four important factors named in developing effective
correlation. First, we must see that the whole effort of correlation is to strengthen the home
and to give aid to the home in its problems, giving it special aid and succor as needed.
</p><p>
<b>Priesthood Totally Employed</b>
</p><p>
Second, the strength of the priesthood must be fully employed within the total responsibility
of priesthood quorums as clearly set forth in the revelations.
</p><p>
<b>Auxiliary Organizations Also</b>
</p><p>
Third, we must survey the purposes lying behind the creation and purpose of each auxiliary
organization.
</p><p>
<b>Knowledge of Gospel to be Enhanced</b>
</p><p>
And fourth, the prime and ultimate objective of all that is done is the
building up of a knowledge of the gospel, a power to promulgate the same, a promotion of
the faith, growth, and stronger testimony of the principles of the gospel among the members
of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>Correlation</b>
</p><p>
Now, to give you just a quick statement as to the progress that has been made up until now.
We have endeavored to proceed as a Correlation Committee in an orderly and logical manner:
first, by placing the priesthood quorums as the Lord has directed us in his revelations; second,
by giving strength to the home in ways that I will presently outline as they have been
approved by the First Presidency and the Twelve; and third, by a total correlation of the
curricula and activities of all the organizations, priesthood, auxiliaries, institutes, and
seminaries. This last phase is now in its final stages of development looking toward full
implementation.
</p><p>
<b>Organization and Functioning</b>
</p><p>
One of the musts in this fully coordinated church program is to get our leaders&mdash;the General
Authorities, general boards, stake, mission, ward, and branch authorities&mdash;to "think"
correlation through these three heaven-ordained institutions instead of diverting to a fringe
committee of some sort for a certain activity or instruction which might well have been
encompassed within the boundaries of the completely correlated priesthood, home, and
auxiliary responsibilities.
</p><p>
We have witnessed a tendency to use in some cases the correlation program of home teaching,
for example, as the "whipping boy" for any deficiencies in the performance of the various
organizations as compared to its previous figures, and some would have us believe that it is
the home teaching program that has caused that downgrading of comparative statistical
figures.
</p><p>
Every auxiliary and priesthood leader in the Church is given a voice in the functioning of
each organization with the home teachers to see that every church member is given attention
as needed.
</p><p>
The real fault in many cases is with the leader who in the monthly ward council meeting
should have aided in perfecting the most effective correlation of his particular organization
with home teaching. We would like those things kept in mind by all of you leaders as you
move these programs forward.
</p><p>
In all this we recognize that we must teach and reteach with patience and long-suffering until
the basic fundamentals of correlation are fully understood and applied in every ward,
priesthood quorum, and auxiliary organization, to the end that, hopefully, every General
Authority, and stake, and mission authority will catch the vision of the possibilities of a
concentrated effort of church organization in a mighty answer to the problems afflicting the
world in which we live.
</p><p>
<b>Restatement of Fundamentals</b>
</p><p>
Now, we should make a restatement and recitation of those fundamentals which are essential
always to our learning in the Lord's work. In defining the fields in which the priesthood
quorums must take precedence: First, by a careful reading of the revelations we have found
this:
</p><p>
"The duty of the elders, priests, teachers, deacons, and members of the church of Christ&mdash;An
apostle is an elder, and it is his calling to baptize . . .
</p><p>
"And to teach, expound, exhort, baptize, and watch over the church . . .
</p><p>
"The priest's duty is to preach, teach, expound, exhort, and baptize, and administer the
sacrament,
</p><p>
"And visit the house of each member, and exhort them to pray vocally and in secret and
attend to all family duties . . .
</p><p>
"The teacher's duty is to watch over the church always, and be with and strengthen them . . .
</p><p>
"And is to be assisted always, in all his duties in the church, by the deacons, if occasion
requires" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/38,42,46-47,53,57#38">D&amp;C 20:38,42,46-47,53,57</a>).
</p><p>
After the Lord had given these plain instructions, one of the great revelations on priesthood
closed with this great admonition with which you should be familiar.
</p><p>
"Wherefore, now let every man learn his duty, and to act in the office in which he is
appointed, in all diligence.
</p><p>
"He that is slothful shall not be counted worthy to stand, and he that learns not his duty and
shows himself not approved shall not be counted worthy to stand"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100#99">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Watching Over the Church"</b>
</p><p>
Home teaching then means "watching over the Church" as the scriptures have defined it.
Missionary work is but home teaching to those who are not now members of the Church, and
home teaching is nothing more or less than missionary work to church members.
</p><p>
<b>Missionary Function, to the Seventy</b>
</p><p>
The major responsibility in missionary work has been given to the seventies quorums, aided
by the Aaronic Priesthood. Quorums of seventy, we have heard during our entire lifetime, are
one day to be called out as quorums to preach the gospel, and some of us thought that meant
to some faraway country. The day is here when seventies are being called as quorums, where
every member of the seventies quorum can engage in some phase of missionary work. We
remember again what the Lord said, that the Council of the Twelve should call upon the
seventies when in need of assistance (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/38#38">D&amp;C 107:38</a>) to fill the various calls for preaching and administering
the gospel instead of any others. This is not to be construed to lessen the feeling of every
member of the Church to be a missionary. The missionary plan calls for the Saints to
cooperate fully as requested and led by their leaders. In stakes which presently have few
seventies, other priesthood holders must be assigned to these prime missionary duties.
</p><p>
First, before I pass this subject, I should call attention to the fact that our Aaronic Priesthood
was given a very vital place in the revelations where the Lord told us:
</p><p>
"Therefore, take with you those who are ordained unto the lesser priesthood, and send them
before you to make appointments, and to prepare the way, and to fill appointments that you
yourselves are not able to fill.
</p><p>
"Behold, this is the way that mine apostles, in ancient days, built up my church unto me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/107-108#107">D&amp;C 84:107-108</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Youth Missionary Assignment</b>
</p><p>
And that becomes now the Aaronic Priesthood youth missionary committee&mdash;a priest, a
teacher, and a deacon, with the bishopric heading up the Aaronic Priesthood, aided by the girls
of comparable ages. They now are to enlist and to, shall I say, proselyte their friends and
bring them into church activity programs.
</p><p>
<b>Genealogical Assignment</b>
</p><p>
In the genealogical work, we recall the words of the Prophet Joseph: "The greatest
responsibility in this world that God has laid upon us is to seek after our dead"
(<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, p. 356.) And then in a great revelation the Lord said:
</p><p>
"Now the great and grand secret of the whole matter, and the <i>summum bonum</i> of the whole
subject that is lying before us, consists in obtaining the powers of the Holy Priesthood. For
him to whom these keys are given there is no difficulty in obtaining a knowledge of facts in
relation to the salvation of the children of men, both as well for the dead as for the living"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/11#11">D&amp;C 128:11</a>).
</p><p>
To provide an effective relationship with the priesthood, the high priests group leader in each
ward has been designated as an adviser to the genealogical work. While all quorums have
responsibility in genealogical work, the leadership and coordination in the ward rest with the
bishop and the high priests group leader. Melchizedek Priesthood quorums are right now
engaged in studying their place in the genealogical program in their Melchizedek Priesthood
quorum classes.
</p><p>
<b>Welfare Assignment</b>
</p><p>
A scripture quoting King Benjamin has long been quoted describing our welfare program.
Now we apply it to the priesthood quorums: ". . . I would that ye should
impart of your substance to the poor," he said, "every man according to that which he hath,
such as feeding the hungry, clothing the naked, visiting the sick and administering to their
relief, both spiritually and temporally, according to their wants"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/26#26">Mosiah 4:26</a>).
</p><p>
Here again, while all quorums are to participate, the great strength of the elders quorums of
the Church are specifically charged with advisory coordination of church welfare under the
direction of the bishop.
</p><p>
<b>Correlation of Curricula</b>
</p><p>
Moving now to a correlated curriculum and the activities of the priesthood quorums, the
fundamentals of this program, as I have told you, have already been predetermined; what will
be taught, subjects taught from three-year-olds up to the oldest adult, and the general plan
have already been approved. Our committees are now working on a fully coordinated program
to present to the First Presidency. We are hopeful that this will be accomplished within the
next year or so.
</p><p>
<b>Parents and the Home</b>
</p><p>
In all of these studies we have never had absent from our minds the responsibilities the Lord
has placed upon the parents in the home in the teaching of our children. You recall what the
Lord said:
</p><p>
<b>The Divine Charge to Parents</b>
</p><p>
"And again, inasmuch as parents have children in Zion, or in any, of her stakes which are
organized, that teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance, faith in Christ the
Son of the living God, and of baptism and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the
hands, when eight years old, the sin be upon the heads of the parents.
</p><p>
"For this shall be a law unto the inhabitants of Zion, or in any of her stakes which are
organized.
</p><p>
"And their children shall be baptized for the remission of their sins when eight years old, and
receive the laying on of the hands.
</p><p>
"And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord.
</p><p>
"And the inhabitants of Zion shall also observe the Sabbath day to keep it holy.
</p><p>
"And the inhabitants of Zion also shall remember their labors, inasmuch as they are appointed
to labor, in all faithfulness; for the idler shall be had in remembrance before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25-30#25">D&amp;C 68:25-30</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"Home Evening" Statement of 1915</b>
</p><p>
The instructions to which I have made reference and about which President McKay spoke
were given about fifty years ago. I read from a letter sent out to the Church in 1915 over the
signature of President Joseph F. Smith, Anthon H. Lund, and Charles W. Penrose. But I
suppose it is something like Mark Twain said about the weather: "We talk a lot about the
weather, but we don't seem to do anything about it." Now we have talked a lot about family
home evenings, and this is the announcement which was made. After I have given you this I
will make a few comments and then outline the program by which we are now to give
strength to the teaching of the family by the parents in the home. This is a quote from the
letter.
</p><p>
"We advise and urge the inauguration of a 'Home Evening' throughout the Church, at which
time father and mother may gather their boys and girls about them in the home, and teach
them the word of the Lord . . . This 'Home Evening' should be devoted to prayer, singing
hymns, songs, instrumental music, scripture reading, family topics, and specific instructions on
the principles of the gospel, and on the ethical problems of life, as well as the duties and
obligations of children to parents, the home, the Church, society, and the nation."
</p><p>
Then to those who would put this family home hour or evening into practice the Presidency
made this promise:
</p><p>
"If the Saints obey this counsel, we promise that great blessings will result. Love at home and
obedience to parents will increase. Faith will be developed in the hearts of the youth of
Israel, and they will gain power to combat the evil influences and
temptations which beset them."
</p><p>
<b>Assignment to Sunday Schools</b>
</p><p>
Our Sunday School organization has been helping to emphasize this important responsibility
by articles in <i>The Instructor</i> and by a program which they have entitled, "Gospel Living in the
Home."
</p><p>
<b>Assignment to Primary Association</b>
</p><p>
Our Primary organization has had what they have called a Primary Home Partnership, by
which the lessons taught in Primary are carried into the home, hopefully to become a part of
the family home evening.
</p><p>
President Joseph F. Smith, in commenting about the responsibility of parents in teaching their
children, said this:
</p><p>
<b>Counsel of the Prophets on Teaching Children</b>
</p><p>
"Do not let your children out to specialists in these things, but teach them by your own
precept and example by your own fireside. Be a specialist yourself in the truth. Let our
meetings, schools and organizations, instead of being our only or leading teachers, be
supplements to our teachings and training in the home. Not one child in a hundred would go
astray, if the home environment, example and training, were in harmony with the truth in the
gospel of Christ, as revealed and taught to the Latter-day Saints." (Joseph F. Smith,
<i>Gospel Doctrine</i>, p. 302.)
</p><p>
About this same matter President Wilford Woodruff said:
</p><p>
"It is one of the greatest blessings that God ever bestowed upon children that they have had
parents who were in possession of true principles in relation to their Heavenly Father,
salvation, eternal life, and were qualified and capable of teaching and traditionating their
children in the same that they may be qualified to fulfil the object of their creation . . .
Ninety-nine out of every hundred children who are taught by their parents the principles of
honesty and integrity, truth and virtue, will observe them through life"
(<i>Discourses of Wilford Woodruff</i>, pp. 266-268).
</p><p>
And then from President Heber J. Grant:
</p><p>
"I have heard men and women say that they were going to let their sons and daughters grow
to maturity before they sought to teach them the principles of the gospel, that they were not
going to cram the gospel down them in their childhood, before they were able to comprehend
it. When I hear men and women say this, I think they are lacking faith in the principles of the
gospel and do not comprehend it as they should. The Lord has said it is our duty to teach our
children in their youth, and I prefer to take His word for it rather than the words of those who
are not obeying His commandments. It is folly to imagine that our children will grow up with
a knowledge of the gospel without teaching . . . I may know that the gospel is true, and so
may my wife, but I want to tell you that our children will not know that the gospel is true,
unless they study it and gain a testimony for themselves. Parents are deceiving themselves in
imagining that their children will be born with a knowledge of the gospel." (Heber J. Grant,
<i>Gospel Standards</i>, p. 155.)
</p><p>
<b>Lessons for Teaching in the Homes</b>
</p><p>
This next year will see some definite steps taken to strengthen the hands of the parents in
carrying out these great God-given admonitions in placing stress upon the teaching of the
gospel in the home. The first step will be to give every parent a set of lessons, one for each
week throughout the coming year, for them to teach the gospel to their family in the home.
As we have talked about the frequency of this, we are not sure whether one for every week,
or three for a month, or two for a month, or one a month may be the desirable, but we call
your attention to this. I have studied the proposed lessons which we are going to have studied
by the priesthood quorums on the subject of what the father's responsibility is in teaching the
gospel in the home. The Relief Society will teach a similar lesson once a
month in the Relief Society for the mothers. As I read these proposed lessons, the more of
these weekly home lessons we can have taught in the home, the better we will be able to
correlate with the priesthood instruction and the Relief Society lessons.
</p><p>
<b>Auxiliary Supporting Publications Monthly</b>
</p><p>
There will be, we suppose, some optional activity. We are asking auxiliary heads to publish
month by month next year suggestions for suitable activities for each age group
represented&mdash;the Primary for little children, the Era for teenage children, the Sunday School for both old
and young, and the Relief Society for mothers primarily. The time has now come when the
General Authorities have decided to correlate and coordinate all of these efforts under the
direction of the priesthood, and we announce, then, a new program to assist parents in the
teaching of the gospel in the home. This program, "Teaching and Living the Gospel in the
Home," is to be inaugurated throughout the Church in January 1965. As an example, the first
four lessons for Primary children are as follows:
</p><p>
"I Am a Child of My Heavenly Father."<br />
    "I Am a Child of My Heavenly Father
       with Special Gifts from Him."<br />
    "I Am a Child of My Heavenly Father
       &mdash;His Heir."<br />
    "As a Child of My Heavenly Father
    I Have the Right to Pray to Him."
</p><p>
<b>Melchizedek Priesthood Lessons</b>
</p><p>
The Melchizedek Priesthood lessons, as I have said, will be given throughout the entire year
of 1965 designed to help the fathers and every priesthood holder become better fathers and
husbands. The general theme of these lessons is "Magnifying the Priesthood in the Home." As
an example, the first ten lessons are as follows:
</p><p>
"Why the Church Has Initiated a Family Home Evening Program."<br />
"Studying the Scriptures."<br />
"Carrying Out the Challenge Relating to the Program Given in Priesthood Meeting."<br />
"Activities Outlined in Home Program."<br />
"The Eternal Family Is One of the Most Important Ways to Obtain Lasting Joy."<br />
"The Family and the Patriarchal Order."<br />
"Providing Opportunities and a Proper Environment for the Spirit Children of Our Heavenly
Father to Come to this Earth."<br />
"Teaching the Gospel of Jesus Christ to Children."<br />
"A Basic Unit of Society."<br />
"Making Satisfactory Adjustments in Marriage."
</p><p>
<b>Relief Society Lessons for Mothers</b>
</p><p>
I came across one of the lessons for the Relief Society to teach mothers what their role is in
teaching the gospel in the home, and I found this rather interesting observation, "How often in
past years have we heard a Latter-day Saint mother say, 'I wish my husband could have heard
the discussion today. Had he done so, I am sure he would feel differently about a particular
problem we have in our home.'" It is a realistic observation that with widely divergent points
of view the efforts of one parent often may nullify the efforts of the other parent, sometimes
with great detriment to the persons involved and to the problems which need to be resolved.
The first Relief Society lesson is entitled "Introduction for Teaching the Gospel in the Home";
the second one, "The Eternal Family."
</p><p>
<b>Home Evening Manual</b>
</p><p>
Simultaneously fathers and mothers will be taught, and the home teachers in their visits to the
homes of members in December 1964 will explain the new program and will present the
parents with the <i>Home Evening Manual</i>. Additional instructions and suggestions will be given
to the home teachers during 1965 so that they can be of assistance to the parents in
strengthening home relationships.
</p><p>
<b>The Program's Introduction</b>
</p><p>
In order to introduce this program, it is proposed that at one of the first priesthood meetings
after this general conference there be a program carried out to introduce to the priesthood in
each stake in the Church the family home evening program. We have now material which will
be sent to you to give you suggestions on that program.
</p><p>
In introducing the program in each ward we have prepared a filmstrip on the family home
evening program which may be available to every stake and through the stake to every ward.
The major objectives of the filmstrip are to explain the family home evening program, to
interest and motivate parents in implementing the program, and to demonstrate to parents
methods by which they can carry out the program in their own families.
</p><p>
These lessons can be adapted, and suggestions will be made in order to fit every age child in
the home.
</p><p>
With that much having been said, we would like to call your attention to what the Lord has
said:
</p><p>
"How long can rolling waters remain impure? What power shall stay the heavens? As well
might man stretch forth his puny arm to stop the Missouri river in its decreed course, or to
turn it up stream, as to hinder the Almighty from pouring down knowledge from heaven upon
the heads of the Latter-day Saints" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/33#33">D&amp;C 121:33</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Priesthood to Point the Way</b>
</p><p>
We have discovered an interesting fact at our Mormon Pavilion at the World's Fair in New
York: that the great strength of our pavilion as a missionary project is not in the paintings, not
in the sculpture work, not in the film, but in the presentation of the missionaries who have the
priesthood of God and in the wonderful spirit which our missionaries have.
</p><p>
As you go out tomorrow look to the east, just underneath the west towers of the great Salt
Lake Temple, and see a depiction of the dipper pointing toward the North Star, which
Truman O. Angell said in an article in the Millennial Star was to symbolize to the Church
"that through the priesthood of God, the lost might find their way." May every priesthood
holder remember that responsibility.
</p><p>
<b>"No Fallen Lighthouse!"</b>
</p><p>
I was at Boston Stake conference a few weeks ago. We installed a young pilot who had
served in the Air Force, a fighter pilot, as a counselor in the stake presidency. I was very
much impressed by his feeling of responsibility. He said something which I want to impress
upon you leaders throughout the entire Church. He said, "I am very fearful of this
responsibility now as a member of the stake presidency, because I have come to know that the
most dangerous of all traffic aids is a fallen lighthouse, since so many people depend upon it
for guidance and for safety."
</p><p>
<b>To Guarantee Success</b>
</p><p>
To have a leader that fails, a "fallen lighthouse" upon whom God depends in a ward or stake
or in a general capacity, is the most dangerous thing in the world, because so many are
depending on the functioning of that particular man. And so we propose to give out to the
Church now these plans which we ask you as stake leaders to be prepared to announce in
your stakes as soon as you can after this conference. We will give you materials to help train
your ward people and home teachers in order that we may get off at the beginning of the year
in this great project of the Lord, that for fifty years has been waged and now is to be
strengthened by a set of planned lessons for the parents in the home, actually outlined for the
parents to teach their children and to carry out appropriate activities to aid in the
strengthening of the home. As I have thought of home night, I have thought of my own
family, and I suppose all of you have as you have been listening. When our oldest daughter
was to be married to a fine Latter-day Saint boy the two mothers were in the corner of the
room talking to each other, and the mother of our oldest daughter said, "You know, from the
time my little girl was born, I have been praying all my life that somewhere a mother
would be preparing a son worthy to marry my daughter." And this other
mother smiled and said, "Isn't that strange? This is my only son who is being married to your
daughter, and ever since he was born, I, too, have been praying that somewhere there would
be a mother preparing a daughter worthy to meet and to marry my son."
</p><p>
It is that kind of home attention&mdash;mothers preparing daughters, fathers and mothers,
sons&mdash;that will make us and our homes stronger today.
</p><p>
<b>Four Standard Works for Everyone</b>
</p><p>
One of the hopes we have in this program is that the four standard works will be in the
possession of every boy and girl deacons age and older and that on Easter, on birthdays, on
Christmas, on New Year's, you make this a part of your family giving to your children, so
they may have the joy of personally owning the Bible, the Book of Mormon, the Doctrine and
Covenants, and the Pearl of Great Price, and from these precious pages begin to be instructed
in the ways of the Lord.
</p><p>
As I thought of what we are doing now and its possible impact, the words of the Prophet
Micah came, "But in the last days it shall come to pass, that the mountain of the house of the
Lord shall be established in the top of the mountains, and it shall be exalted above the hills;
and people shall flow unto it.
</p><p>
"And many nations shall come, and say, Come, and let us go up to the mountain of the Lord,
and to the house of the God of Jacob; and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in
his paths: for the law shall go forth of Zion, and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/micah/4/1-2#1">Micah 4:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Unity, the Way</b>
</p><p>
I say to you Latter-day Saint mothers and fathers, if you will rise to the responsibility of
teaching your children in the home&mdash;priesthood quorums preparing the fathers, the Relief
Society the mothers&mdash;the day will soon be dawning when the whole world will come to our
doors and will say, "Show us your way that we may walk in your path."
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us all. We thank the Lord tonight for a prophet leader who has the vision
and courage to continue to guide us and to point the way to the strengthening of the Church
through the priesthood of Almighty God which I bear testimony in his power and in his
authority for the salvation of all mankind within the limitations as indicated by each setting
apart by the laying on of hands. To that I bear humble testimony in the name of Jesus Christ.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
