<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Private Ownership...under the United Order</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1942, pp. 54-59</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Brethren:
</p><p>
I have been trying for a week to relieve you of this experience, but Brother McKay, so kind,
so sweet, and so merciful, has been perfectly adamant. So I stand before you here, not to
preach, but to counsel with you.
</p><p>
There is a great deal of misapprehension among our people regarding the United Order.
</p><p>
I have not been able to believe that the United Order meant what some people have thought it
meant, so within the last months I have spent quite a little time reading the revelations
thereon, also reading our history, and at the same time giving some consideration to a
dissertation which has been written regarding the Order.
</p><p>
There is a growing&mdash;I fear it is growing&mdash;sentiment that communism and the United Order are
virtually the same thing, communism being merely the forerunner, so to speak, of a
reestablishment of the United Order. I am informed that ex-bishops, and indeed, bishops, who
belong to communistic organizations, are preaching this doctrine. So I thought that perhaps if
I said just a few words to you tonight regarding the way I interpret the revelations that are
printed about this in the D&amp;C (if there are other revelations about the Order, I do not know
of them), I thought if I said something about it, it might be helpful. I recommend that you,
my brethren, read a few of the Sections of the D&amp;C which cover this matter, beginning with
Sections 42 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/1-93#0">D&amp;C 42:1-93</a>)
and 51 (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/1-20#0">D&amp;C 51:1-20</a>, see also
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/70/1-18#0">D&amp;C 70:1-18</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/1-22#0">D&amp;C 78:1-22</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/1-24#0">D&amp;C 82:1-24</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/1-6#0">D&amp;C 83:1-6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/85/1-12#0">D&amp;C 85:1-12</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/1-37#0">D&amp;C 90:1-37</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/92/1-2#0">D&amp;C 92:1-2</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/96/1-9#0">D&amp;C 96:1-9</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/1-86#0">D&amp;C 104:1-86</a>). If you will
go over these sections, I feel sure that you will find that my explanation of the United Order
will be substantially accurate.
</p><p>
EARLY DEVIATIONS
</p><p>
I may say to begin with, that in practice the brethren in Missouri got away, in their attempts
to set up the United Order, from the principles set out in the revelations. This is also true of
the organizations set up here in Utah after the Saints came to the Valleys. So far as I have
seen there has been preserved only one document that purports to be a legal instrument used
in connection with the setting up of the United Order, and that document is without date. It is
said to have been found among the papers of Bishop Partridge. It was a "lease-lend"
document. You may have heard that phrase before. Under this instrument the Church leased to
Titus Billings a certain amount of real estate and loaned him a certain amount of personal
property.
</p><p>
This instrument is not in accordance with the principle laid down in the revelations touching
upon the United Order.
</p><p>
The basic principle of all the revelations on the United Order is that everything we have
belongs to the Lord; therefore, the Lord may call upon us for any and all of the property
which we have, because it belongs to Him. This, I repeat, is the basic principle
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/14-17,54-57#14">D&amp;C 104:14-17,54-57</a>).
</p><p>
One of the places in which some of the brethren are going astray is this: There is continuous
reference in the revelations to equality among the brethren, but I think you will find only one
place where that equality is really described, though it is referred to in other revelations. That
revelation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/3#3">D&amp;C 51:3</a>)
affirms that every man is to be "equal according to his family,
according to his circumstances and his wants and needs"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/17#17">D&amp;C 82:17</a>, see also
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/5-6#5">D&amp;C 78:5-6</a>).
Obviously, this is not a case of "dead level" equality. It is "equality" that will vary as much
as the man's circumstances, his family, his wants and needs, may vary.
</p><p>
CONSECRATION
</p><p>
In the next place, under the United Order every man was called to consecrate to the Church
all of the property which he had; the real estate was to be conveyed to the Church, as I
understand the revelations, by what we would call a deed in fee simple. Thus the man's
property became absolutely the property of the Church
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/30#30">D&amp;C 42:30</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/72/15#15">D&amp;C 72:15</a>). Then the
bishop deeded back to the donor by the same kind of deed, that is, in fee simple, and also
transferred to him by an equivalent instrument, so far as personal property was concerned,
that amount of real and personal property, which, the two being taken together, would be
required by the individual for the support of himself and his family "according to his family,
according to his circumstances and his wants and needs." This the man held as his own
property (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/32#32">D&amp;C 42:32</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/4-6#4">D&amp;C 51:4-6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/3#3">D&amp;C 83:3</a>).
</p><p>
In other words, basic to the United Order was the private ownership of property, every man
had his own property from which he might secure that which was necessary for the support of
himself and his family. There is nothing in the revelations that would indicate that this
property was not freely alienable at the will of the owner. It was not contemplated that the
Church should own everything or that we should become in the Church, with reference to our
property and otherwise, the same kind of automaton, manikin, that communism makes out of
the individual, with the State standing at the head in place of the Church.
</p><p>
Now, that part of a man's property which was not turned back to him, if he had more than
was needed under this rule of "equality" already stated, became the common property of the
Church, and that common property was used for the support of the poor of the Church. It is
spoken of in the revelations as the "residue" of property
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/34-36#34">D&amp;C 42:34-36</a>).
</p><p>
LAND PORTIONS
</p><p>
Furthermore, it was intended, though apparently it did not work out very well, that the poor
coming into Zion, and by Zion I mean, here, Missouri&mdash;the poor coming into Zion were to
have given to them a "portion" of land, which land was to be either purchased from the
Government (and it was planned to purchase large areas from the Government), or purchased
from individuals, or received as consecrations from members of the Church. The amount of
this "portion" was to be such as would make him equal to others according to his
circumstances, his family, his wants and needs.
</p><p>
The land which you received from the bishop by deed, whether it was part of the land which
you, yourself, had deeded to the Church, or whether it came as an outright gift from the
Church as just indicated, and the personal property which you received, were all together
sometimes called a "portion" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/4-6#4">D&amp;C 51:4-6</a>),
sometimes a "stewardship" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/11-12#11">D&amp;C 104:11-12</a>),
and sometimes an "inheritance" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/3#3">D&amp;C 83:3</a>).
</p><p>
As just indicated, there were other kinds of inheritances and stewardships than land or mere
personal property; for example, the Prophet and others had a stewardship given to them which
consisted of the revelations and commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/70/1-4#1">D&amp;C 70:1-4</a>); others had given to them a
stewardship involving the printing house
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/29-30#29">D&amp;C 104:29-30</a>);
another stewardship was a mercantile establishment
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/39-42#39">D&amp;C 104:39-42</a>).
</p><p>
SURPLUS
</p><p>
I repeat that whatever a steward realized from the portion allotted to him over and above that
which was necessary in order to keep his family under the standard provided, as already
stated above, was turned over by the steward to the bishop, and this amount of surplus, plus
the residues to which I have already referred, went into a bishop's storehouse
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/13#13">D&amp;C 51:13</a> and citations above),
and the materials of the storehouse were to be used in creating portions,
as above indicated, for caring for the poor
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/3#3">D&amp;C 78:3</a>),
the widows and orphans (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/6#6">D&amp;C 83:6</a>),
and for the elders of the Church engaged in the ministry, who were to pay for what
they received if they could, but if not, their faithful labors should answer their debt to the
bishop (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/72/11-14#11">D&amp;C 72:11-14</a>).
</p><p>
OTHER INSTITUTIONS
</p><p>
Now, as time went on and the system developed, the Lord created two other institutions
besides the storehouse: one was known as the Sacred Treasury, into which was put "the avails
of the sacred things in the treasury, for sacred and holy purposes." While it is not clear, it
would seem that into this treasury were to be put the surpluses which were derived from the
publication of the revelations, the Book of Mormon, the Pearl of Great Price, and other
similar things, the stewardship of which had been given to Joseph and others
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/60-66#60">D&amp;C 104:60-66</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord also provided for the creation of "Another Treasury"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/67-78#67">D&amp;C 104:67-78</a>), and into that other
treasury went the general revenues which came to the Church, such as gifts of money and
those revenues derived from the improvement of stewardships as distinguished from the
residues of the original consecrations and the surpluses which came from the operation of
their stewardships (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/72/11-14#11">D&amp;C 72:11-14</a>).
</p><p>
The foregoing is the general outline as it is gathered from the revelations of the law of the
United Order which the Lord spoke of as "my law"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/44/6#6">D&amp;C 44:6</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/51/15#15">D&amp;C 51:15</a>). There are passages
in the revelations which, taken from their context and without having in mind the whole
system, might be considered as inconsistent with some of the things which I have set out, but
all such passages fall into line if the whole program is looked at as contained in all of the
revelations.
</p><p>
PRIVATE OWNERSHIP FUNDAMENTAL
</p><p>
The fundamental principle of this system was the private ownership of property. Each man
owned his portion, or inheritance, or stewardship, with an absolute title, which he could
alienate, or hypothecate, or otherwise treat as his own. The Church did not own all of the
property, and the life under the United Order was not a communal life, as the Prophet Joseph,
himself said (<i>History of the Church</i>, Volume III, p. 28). The United Order is an
individualistic system, not a communal system.
</p><p>
THE WELFARE PLAN AND THE UNITED ORDER
</p><p>
We have all said that the Welfare Plan is not the United Order and was not intended to be.
However, I should like to suggest to you that perhaps, after all, when the Welfare Plan gets
thoroughly into operation&mdash;it is not so yet&mdash;we shall not be so very far from carrying out the
great fundamentals of the United Order.
</p><p>
In the first place I repeat again, the United Order recognized and was built upon the principle
of private ownership of property; all that a man had and lived upon under the United Order,
was his own. Quite obviously, the fundamental principle of our system today is the ownership
of private property.
</p><p>
In the next place, in lieu of residues and surpluses which were accumulated and built up under
the, United Order, we, today, have our fast offerings, our Welfare donations, and our tithing,
all of which may be devoted to the care of the poor, as well as for the carrying on of the
activities and business of the Church. After all, the United Order was primarily designed to
build up a system under which there should be no abjectly poor, and this is the purpose, also,
of the Welfare Plan.
</p><p>
In this connection it should be observed that it is clear from these earlier revelations, as well
as from our history, that the Lord had very early to tell the people about the wickedness of
idleness, and the wickedness of greed, because the brethren who had were not giving
properly, and those who had not were evidently intending to live without work on the things
which were to be received from those who had property
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/16-20#16">D&amp;C 56:16-20</a>).
</p><p>
STOREHOUSES AND PROJECTS
</p><p>
Furthermore, we had under the United Order a bishop's storehouse in which were collected
the materials from which to supply the needs and the wants of the poor. We have a bishop's
storehouse under the Welfare Plan, used for the same purpose.
</p><p>
As I have already indicated, the surplus properties which came to the Church under the Law
of Consecration, under the United Order, became the "common property" of the Church
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/18#18">D&amp;C 82:18</a>)
and were handled under the United Order for the benefit of the poor. We have
now under the Welfare Plan all over the Church, ward land projects. In some cases the lands
are owned by the wards, in others they are leased by the wards or lent to them by private
individuals. This land is being farmed for the benefit of the poor, by the poor where you can
get the poor to work it.
</p><p>
We have in place of the two treasuries, the "Sacred Treasury" and
"Another Treasury," the general funds of the Church.
</p><p>
Thus you will see, brethren, that in many of its great essentials, we have, as the Welfare Plan
has now developed, the broad essentials of the United Order. Furthermore, having in mind the
assistance which is being given from time to time and in various wards to help set people up
in business or in farming, we have a plan which is not essentially unlike that which was in the
United Order when the poor were given portions from the common fund.
</p><p>
Now, brethren, the Church has made tremendous advances in the Welfare Plan. We shall have
to make still greater advances. As the Message of the First Presidency said this morning, we
are being told by Government officials that we face what we used to call "hard times." If the
Welfare Plan is fully operative, we shall be able to care for every destitute Latter-day Saint
wherever he may be.
</p><p>
THE CONSTITUTION
</p><p>
Now, I would like to say something else, brethren, again by way of counsel I shall be
accused, when I do, of talking politics, and perhaps on this point I may say I do not read
anonymous letters. When they come in I just throw them into the wastebasket. I only read
enough of the signed scurrilous letters that are sent to know that they are scurrilous, and then
they follow along. So it is useless for anyone to try to take out any personal feeling in that
way.
</p><p>
You and I have heard all our lives that the time may come when the Constitution may hang
by a thread. I do not know whether it is a thread, or a small rope by which it now hangs, but
I do know that whether it shall live or die is now in the balance.
</p><p>
I have said to you before, brethren, that to me the Constitution is a part of my religion. In its
place it is just as much a part of my religion as any other part. It is a part of my religion
because it is one of those institutions which God has set up for His own purposes, and, as one
of the brethren said today, set up so that this Church might be established, because under no
other government in the world could the Church have been established as it has been
established under this Government.
</p><p>
I think I would be sale in saying that my fellowship with you in the Church depends upon
whether or not I accept the revelations and the principles which God has revealed. If I am not
willing to do that, then I am not entitled to fellowship. Anyone else who fails to accept the
revelations and the principles which God has revealed stands in precisely the same situation.
</p><p>
In the 101st Section of the D&amp;C, which contains a revelation received by the Prophet in
1833, when the persecution in Missouri was at its highest, the Lord told the brethren that they
should appeal for help. Then He added these verses, which I want to read to you:
</p><p>
According to the laws and constitution of the people, which I have suffered to be established,
and should be maintained for the rights and protection of all flesh, according to just and holy
principles;
</p><p>
That every man may act in doctrine and principle pertaining to futurity, according to the
moral agency which I have given unto him, that every man may be accountable for his own
sins in the day of judgment.
</p><p>
Therefore, it is not right that any man should be in bondage one to another.
</p><p>
And for this purpose have I established the Constitution of this land, by the hands of wise
men whom I raised up unto this very purpose, and redeemed the land by the shedding of
blood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/77-80#77">D&amp;C 101:77-80</a>).
</p><p>
INFLUENCE IN THE AMERICAS
</p><p>
I suppose you brethren will all know, but I will recall it to your attention, that the
Constitution of the United States is the basic law for all of the Americas, or Zion, as it has
been defined by the Lord. 
</p><p>
You brethren from Canada know that, your great British North America Act, in its
fundamental principles, is based upon our Constitution, and you know that in the courts of
Canada, the reports of our Supreme Court, and our Federal courts generally, are just as
persuasive as the decisions of the courts of England, and even more so, where questions of
constitutional law and constitutional interpretation are involved.
</p><p>
You brethren also know that from the Rio Grande down to the Horn there is no constitutional
government except those that are founded primarily upon our own Constitution. In Mexico the
revolutionary party which more than a century and a quarter ago rebelled against the king of
Spain and established a republic, copied almost verbatim, and practically overnight, our
Constitution, and made it their own. Neither Mexico nor the others to the South interpret their
Constitutions as we interpret ours. They have different standards and different canons of
interpretation, for their fundamental system is the civil law, while ours is the common law.
But the great essentials of that document, the Constitution of the United States, which God
Himself inspired, is the law of Zion, the Americas.
</p><p>
THE LAW OF ZION
</p><p>
So, brethren, I wish you to understand that when we begin to tamper with the Constitution we
begin to tamper with the law of Zion which God Himself set up, and no one may trifle with
the word of God with impunity.
</p><p>
Now, I am not caring today, for myself, anything at all about a political party tag. So far as I
am concerned, I want to know what the man stands for. I want to know if he believes in the
Constitution; if he believes in its free institutions; if he believes in its liberties, its freedom. I
want to know if he believes in the Bill of Rights. I want to know if he believes in the
separation of sovereign power into the three great divisions: the Legislative, the Judicial, the
Executive. I want to know if he believes in the mutual independence of these, the one from
the other. When I find out these things, then I know who it is who should receive my support,
and I care not what his party tag is, because, brethren, if we are to live as a Church, and
progress, and have the right to worship as we are worshipping here today, we must have the
great guarantees that are set up by our Constitution. There is no other way in which we can
secure these guarantees. You may look at the systems all over the world where the principles
of our Constitution are not controlling and in force, and you will find there dictatorship,
tyranny, oppression, and, in the last analysts, slavery.
</p><p>
ALLEGIANCE
</p><p>
I have said enough. I believe you understand what I have said. Today, our duty transcends
party allegiance; our duty today is allegiance to the Constitution as it was given to us by the
Lord. Every federal officer takes an oath to support that Constitution so given. The difference
between us and some of those to the South of us is this: down there, their fealty runs to
individuals; here, our fealty and our allegiance run to the Constitution and to the principles
which it embodies, and not to individuals.
</p><p>
God give us wisdom and enable us in these times of trouble and strife clearly to see our way,
that we may be instrumental in sustaining the Constitution, in upholding our free institutions,
our civil rights, our freedom of speech, of press, of religion, and of conscience. If we shall
stand together we shall save the Constitution, just as has been foreseen, and if we do not stand
together, we cannot perform this great task.
</p><p>
God grant that we may be true, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
