<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 80-83</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Though Brother Clark felt a little irked when his assigned duty to direct was slightly
modified, he has set a good example to us all. He did as he was told.
</p><p>
There are in attendance tonight, as reported, a total of 15,050 members of the
Priesthood&mdash;10,250 in seats, aisles, and doorways of the Tabernacle: 300 in the Baptistry; 2,200 in the
Assembly Hall; 1,000 in the Barratt Hall, and an estimated 1,300 on the grounds.
</p><p>
Six months ago, we were blessed with the presence of our beloved President, George Albert
Smith. Tonight we are deprived of his earthly companionship. How uncertain life is. The
silent, inaudible foot of time is marching on bringing each of us nearer and nearer to the end
of our earthly careers. Before his passing there were a few items scheduled for presentation at
this priesthood meeting, and I shall just mention them briefly before making a few concluding
remarks.
</p><p>
MISSIONARY RECOMMENDATIONS
</p><p>
One relates to the interviewing of prospective missionaries by bishops. Will you please be
more careful about recommending men about whose health may be a question. Missionary
work is strenuous when it is done properly, and we do not like missionaries to go out and not
do it properly. If there is any question about their health, please sit down and have a talk with
them and tell them that their services here in the home missions will be just as acceptable to
the Lord as their labors out in a foreign mission. The Lord would like them to live and serve.
Do not put them under an environment that will probably aggravate some physical weakness.
It is surprising how eagerly the young women and some married women seek calls to go on
missions. We commend them for it, but the responsibility of proclaiming the gospel of Jesus
Christ rests upon the priesthood of the Church. It is quite possible now, in view of the present
emergency, that we shall have to return to the standard age for young women, which is
twenty-three. The last few months we have been calling young women twenty-one years of
age when they have special qualifications. Bishops and presidents of stakes will please bear in
mind that from now on they should not recommend young women under the age of
twenty-three. That is merely returning to the standard already approved by the brethren. Now,
that does not mean that the young girls who have already received calls or whom you have
already interviewed who are only twenty-one may not have their recommendations completed.
In this connection, we advise that mothers who have dependent children, that means children
who are in their teens or under or unmarried, should not be called on missions even though
the grandparents are willing to take care of the children. No nobler work in this world can be
performed by any mother than to rear and love the children with whom God has blessed her.
That is her duty, and that is far greater than going out into the world to proclaim the gospel,
because somebody else can do that who does not bear the responsibility of rearing and loving
the children who call her mother.
</p><p>
TEMPLE WORKERS
</p><p>
Last evening we held a long meeting with temple presidents and out of that meeting comes
this recommendation, and there are strong reasons back of it, brethren! Will the bishops please
take more care in recommending members to do temple work, to perform temple ordinances.
Now the great majority of those who are going through the temple are worthy, and it is a
glorious work. But if one or two unworthy get into the company and make some
objectionable remark or leave an objectionable sign somewhere it tends to retard the spirit and
to discourage some young man or young woman who came anticipating a glorious spiritual
feast.
</p><p>
SUNDAY SCHOOLS
</p><p>
Next, it has already been recommended that Sunday Schools be not dismissed on quarterly
conference day. If the conference is held in the ward house, of necessity, Sunday School will
have to be adjourned, but that is the only exception. The reason for that will be readily seen if
I read you the following letter without giving the name.
</p><p>
"Last Sunday I was in X town visiting my son. Feeling that I should like to visit a Sunday
School in X town on Easter, I drove there. Calling at the home of a friend I was informed
that stake conference was being held and that Sunday School had been canceled. I informed
the lady of the house that Sunday Schools are conducted on conference Sundays. She then
called one of the Sunday School teachers and was given definite assurance that no Sunday
School service would be conducted in that ward. Three women in the vicinity dressed their
little girls in their Easter outfits and sent them to the Community Church."
</p><p>
INSPIRATION OF PRIESTHOOD MEETING
</p><p>
Now, just a few concluding remarks: One of our business men, non-member, who attended
the funeral this afternoon, looked over the audience and said, "Look at that audience. It
cannot be duplicated anywhere else in the world." I wish it were possible for him to see this
audience tonight. Ten thousand men who hold the priesthood of God. What an inspiration!
What an opportunity is ours to succeed in life!
</p><p>
Bishop Wirthlin referred to some who are discouraged. We have heard from Bishop Richards
also, and others, young men now being called into the field and into the armed forces, so
many young women without close companionship of young men of their age, some entered in
their school and missions are discouraged. But let me just give two suggestions that will lead
to success in any boy's life or any woman's life, will lead to the success of any person in the
world and particularly those who hold the priesthood.
</p><p>
ATTENDANCE TO DUTY
</p><p>
The first is, attend to the immediate duty in hand. No person living in this Church can say he
or she has not an immediate duty. It may be attendance at a priesthood meeting; the Aaronic
Priesthood or Melchizedek. It may be fasting on the first Sunday and giving fast offerings for
the poor. Do not say those are insignificant duties; it may be the duty of attending worship on
the Sabbath day, either in Sunday School, Priesthood meeting or Sacrament meeting or
Mutual at night; it may be visiting a sick neighbor; or it is the payment of tithing. Whatever
the immediate duty, perform it. That is the first step.
</p><p>
Outside of the Church you have a problem before you in your business or in social or
political circles. Before you take that step ahead, ask yourself whether you can justify taking
it if you were called into the presence of your Father in Heaven. If you can, take it. One of
our American writers, some do not call him a poet, expressed this thought very impressively: 
</p><p>
Who does his task from day to day,<br />
And meets whatever comes his way<br />
Believing God has willed it so<br />
Has found true greatness here below.
</p><p>
Who guards his post no matter where<br />
Believing God must need him there,<br />
Although but lowly toil it be<br />
Has risen to nobility.
</p><p>
For great and low there's but one test,<br />
'Tis that each one will do his best.<br />
Who works with all the strength he can<br />
Shall never die in debt to man.
</p><p>
LOVE FOR FELLOWMEN
</p><p>
The second great guide to success has been illustrated during the last week particularly, or last
few days, more impressibly right in our midst than perhaps we have ever seen it before and it
may be a long time before we see it again. It is the power of the greatest thing in all the
world&mdash;love for fellow men. The poet Browning who has Paracelsus say to his friend Festus,
"There was a time when I was happy; the secret of life was in that happiness."
</p><p>
"When, when was that?" asked Festus. "All I hope that answer will decide."
</p><p>
Paracelsus: "When, but the time I vowed myself to man?"
</p><p>
Festus: "Great God, thy judgments are unscrutable."
</p><p>
And then Paracelsus concluded: "The answer to the passionate longings of the human heart
for fullness is this: Live in all things outside yourself by love and you will have joy. That is
the life of God; it ought to be our life. In him it is accomplished and perfect; but in all
created things it is a lesson learned slowly and through difficulty."
</p><p>
I will conclude that thought by reading to you that wonderful statement of Paul on love: ". . .
charity is the pure love of Christ, and it endureth forever"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/47#47">Moro. 7:47</a>). Love suffereth long
and is kind. Love envieth not, love vaunteth not itself, is not puffed up, doth not behave itself
unseemly, seeketh not her own, is not easily provoked, thinketh no evil, rejoiceth not in
iniquity but rejoiceth in the truth, beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things,
endureth all things. Love never fails"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/13/4-8#4">1 Cor. 13:4-8</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/45#45">Moro. 7:45</a>).
</p><p>
God help us to exemplify in our lives that love which was so well exemplified, ideally
exemplified, in the life of our beloved leader, President George Albert Smith, who sought to
approach the love of Christ, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
