<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Vision of Lehi</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1966, pp. 23-27</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters and friends, it is a privilege always to attend the general conferences
of the Church.
</p><p>
<b>Lehi's vision</b>
</p><p>
My message is taken from the Book of Mormon account of the vision God gave to the
Prophet Lehi, who, with his family, lived in Jerusalem about 600 years before the birth of
Christ. This prophet was warned concerning the destruction of Jerusalem by invading
Babylonian armies (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/1/13#13">1 Ne. 1:13</a>). God therefore commanded Lehi to take his family and a small select
group and to depart from the city (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/1-2#1">1 Ne. 2:1-2</a>). The Lord gave assurance that he would lead them to a
promised land&mdash;the Americas as we know them today. These families belonged to the house
of Israel, and Lehi was a descendant of that Joseph who was sold into Egypt.
</p><p>
After their departure from Jerusalem and while in the Valley of Lemuel, near the border of the
Red Sea, God blessed the prophet with an inspiring vision (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/1-38#1">1 Ne. 8:1-38</a>). In this vision Lehi
beheld a dark and dreary wilderness. He was led by a messenger from God, a man clothed in a
white robe. It seemed to Lehi they were moving deeper into the wilderness of darkness, and he
therefore earnestly petitioned his God for mercy. Following his supplication the dream
unfolded to his vision important and significant events. Lehi beheld a large and spacious field
and a tree, the fruit of which was desirable to make one happy. He went forth and partook of
the fruit and in ecstasy declared it to be the most sweet above all that he had before tasted.
When Lehi partook of the fruit, he described it as filling his soul with exceeding joy and he
therefore desired that his family should partake of the fruit also, for he knew it was most
desirable above all other fruit. As he cast his eyes about to discover his family, he beheld a
river of water that ran along near the tree. As he looked toward the source of the stream, he
saw his wife, Sariah, and two of his sons, Nephi and Sam. It seemed to Lehi that this part of
his family were uncertain as to the way they should go. Being anxious about the welfare of
his family, he beckoned unto them to come and partake of the fruit, which invitation they
willingly accepted.
</p><p>
Lehi had two other sons, both of whom were wayward. He was desirous that they also should
come and partake of the fruit. When he located them, they refused his invitation.
</p><p>
As the vision continued, Lehi beheld a rod of iron that extended along the bank of the river
and led to the tree by which he stood. He also beheld a straight and narrow path that
paralleled close to the rod of iron and also led to the tree and continued on to the head of the
fountain unto a large and spacious field, as if it were a world. Lehi saw numberless
concourses of people, many of whom were pressing forward that they might obtain the path
that led to the tree laden with desirable fruit. Some commenced in the path, but there arose a
mist of darkness of exceeding intensity insomuch that they who had commenced in the path
did lose their way and wandered off and were lost.
</p><p>
In the vision Lehi beheld others pressing forward, and they caught hold of the rod of iron and
continued through the mists of darkness, clinging to the rod of iron, and moved along the
straight and narrow path until they reached the tree and partook of its fruit. After partaking of
the fruit they cast their eyes about as if they were ashamed. This caused Lehi to wonder, so
he cast his eyes round about also and beheld on the other side of the river a great and
spacious building. It was filled with people, both old and young, both male and female, who
were well dressed, and they were in the attitude of mocking and were pointing fingers of
scorn toward those who had partaken of the fruit. These wavering souls had made
considerable progress toward their goal, but they could not withstand the scoffing of the
multitudes and therefore they fell away into forbidden paths and were lost.
</p><p>
Lehi saw another concourse of people, and they did press their way forward, continually
holding fast to the rod of iron until they reached the tree and partook of its fruit. He saw
other multitudes feeling their way toward that great and spacious building. Many strayed and
were drowned in the depths of the fountain, and others were lost from his view, wandering
into strange roads. Great were the multitudes that entered the strange building, and after doing
so they pointed the finger of scorn and did scoff at Lehi and the others who were partaking of
the fruit. ". . . but," said Lehi, "we heeded them not" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/33#33">1 Ne. 8:33</a>). So closed the vision of
Lehi.
</p><p>
<b>The vision teaches:</b>
</p><p>
Now, having the details of the vision in mind, let us consider the teachings and the lessons of
this unusual vision. We learn that people must pray for light and truth to know the way to
eternal life and happiness. Only by humility and prayer, with a heart open to truth, can one
escape the dominant influence that Satan is exerting so strongly and effectively today in all
areas of the world to destroy the souls of men.
</p><p>
Nephi, the son of Lehi, although fully believing the words of his father regarding his vision,
was nevertheless desirous that he might see and hear and know for himself of those things
witnessed by his father (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/1#1">1 Ne. 11:1</a>). He had faith that the vision of his father could be shown him by the
gift and power of the Holy Ghost. Nephi was granted his wish after he, too, had humbly and
diligently supplicated the Lord in prayer for this privilege.
</p><p>
An angel of God appeared before Nephi and asked if he knew the meaning of the tree which
his father saw. Nephi answered in the affirmative, stating, ". . . it is the love of God, which
sheddeth itself abroad in the hearts of the children of men, wherefore, it is the most desirable
above all things." And the angel added, "Yea, and the most joyous to the soul"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/22-23#22">1 Ne. 11:22-23</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The "Tree of Life" a recurring symbol</b>
</p><p>
The tree of life was not unknown to the descendants of Lehi, part of whom are the Indian
tribes of the Americas, for it is found in the pictorial hieroglyphics that were carved upon
rocks in regions of the past civilizations of Lehi's posterity. The tree of life is not something
new taught in our day, for there are many references to it in the scriptures. The significance
of this representation may not be understood fully, except by few, yet it has real and
important spiritual value. In the book of Revelation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/2/7#7">Rev. 2:7</a>) we learn that "the tree of life . . . is
in the midst of the paradise of God." In Genesis 2:9 we are informed that a tree of life was
placed by God in the midst of the Garden of Eden (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/9#9">Gen. 2:9</a>). Adam and Eve were privileged to partake
of the fruit of this tree until they transgressed God's law. Thereafter the fruit of the tree was
denied them, if they had partaken, they would have lived forever in their fallen state (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/28#28">Moses 4:28</a>). Death
was in the great plan of God, and the hope of man became centered in Jesus Christ, who gave
his life on Calvary to redeem and save man from the effects of the fall.
</p><p>
Alma, a Nephite prophet, quotes the Christ as saying, "Come unto me and ye shall partake of
the fruit of the tree of life" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/34#34">Alma 5:34</a>).
</p><p>
John the Revelator, speaking of the tree of life in the New Jerusalem that is to come down
from heaven, said: "Blessed are they that do his commandments, that they may have right to
the tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the city" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/22/14#14">Rev. 22:14</a>).
</p><p>
Lehi taught there must be an opposition in all things. ". . . even the forbidden fruit in
opposition to the tree of life; the one being sweet and the other bitter" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/15#15">2 Ne. 2:15</a>).
</p><p>
Nephi advises, "Wherefore, the wicked are rejected from the righteous, and also from that tree
of life, whose fruit is most precious and most desirable above all other fruits, yea, and it is
the greatest of all the gifts of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/36#36">1 Ne. 15:36</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"The rod of iron"</b>
</p><p>
Nephi learned from the angel that the rod of iron seen by his father was the word of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/25#25">1 Ne. 11:25</a>),
which word, if accepted and lived, will lead mankind to the tree of life and to the fountain of
living waters, which waters are a representation of the love of God. Nephi beheld also that the
tree of life is a representation of the love of God.
</p><p>
Man's duty, therefore, is to seek earnestly for the word of the Lord; and when he finds it, if
he is sincere in his desires, he will enter into that straight and narrow path that will take him
to the tree of life where he can partake of the fruit thereof. Remaining true, he will not fall
into the byways of wickedness and sin but continue on to the eternal mansions prepared of
God for the faithful and worthy of his children.
</p><p>
<b>Other symbols</b>
</p><p>
The river of water spoken of in the vision represents filthiness
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/27#27">1 Ne. 15:27</a>). The mists of darkness are the
temptations of the devil, which blind the eyes and harden the hearts of the children of men
and lead them away into broad roads, where they perish and become lost. The great and
spacious building was the pride of the world which fell and said the angel, "Thus shall be the
destruction of all nations, kindreds, tongues, and people, that shall fight against the twelve
apostles of the Lamb" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/36#36">1 Ne. 11:36</a>). The building was filled with human beings&mdash;fools and
scoffers&mdash;who, with their ribaldry, succeeded in making apostates and transgressors of some
of those who had tasted of the fruit of the tree of life. The inmates of the building delighted
in mocking and scoffing at those who desired to do right.
</p><p>
Inasmuch as Laman and Lemuel did not partake of the fruit of the tree of life, Lehi feared
lest they would be cast off from the presence of the Lord forever. As their father, he had
great concern for their eternal welfare, and his love was manifest in his exhortation to them
with all the feeling of a tender parent, that they would hearken unto his words and not be cast
off (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/35-37#35">1 Ne. 8:35-37</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Parable of the Sower</b>
</p><p>
The parable of Jesus dealing with the sower who went forth to sow parallels in teaching the
lessons given Lehi in the vision that I have described (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/1-9#1">Matt. 13:1-9</a>). The Savior, after
applying the parable of the sower to those whom he was teaching, interpreted it to the
understanding of his disciples by saying: 
</p><p>
"When any one heareth the word of the kingdom, and understandeth it not, then cometh the
wicked one, and catcheth away that which was sown in his heart. This is he which received
seed by the wayside.
</p><p>
"But he that received the seed into the stony places, the same is he that heareth the word, and
anon with joy receiveth it; 
</p><p>
"Yet hath he not root in himself, but dureth for a while: for when tribulation or persecution
ariseth because of the word, by and by he is offended.
</p><p>
"He also that received seed among the thorns is he that heareth the word; and the care of this
world, and the deceitfulness of riches, choke the word, and he becometh unfruitful.
</p><p>
"But he that received seed into the good ground is he that heareth the word, and
understandeth it; which also beareth fruit, and bringeth forth, some an hundred fold, some
sixty, some thirty" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/19-23#19">Matt. 13:19-23</a>).
</p><p>
<b>"The Power of God unto Salvation"</b>
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul declared that he was not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, because, said he,
"it is the power of God unto salvation" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16#16">Rom. 1:16</a>).
</p><p>
No man, following the example and dedication of the Christ, should become ashamed or
afraid of his true Christian status and lack courage and strength, in the face of opposition or
the taunting of men, to remain true, firm, and steadfast to his conviction of what is right in
the sight of God. This life is a probationary state wherein men and women are tried and
proven in the crucible of mortal existence.
</p><p>
The vision of Lehi and the parable of the sower presented by the Christ suggest the
weaknesses of men and the many avenues of personal indifference, lack of faith, wickedness,
and sin which, if left uncontrolled, will destroy their very souls and lead them down to the
depths of hell (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/12/16#16">1 Ne. 12:16</a>).
</p><p>
Lehi's love and concern for the eternal welfare and happiness of his family is applicable to all
parents. They too, feelingly, kindly, and in love, must give children the opportunity of good
moral and spiritual teaching and training with righteous and ethical parental example in order
to create the desire and the strength within their children's hearts to love God and to serve
him and keep his commandments.
</p><p>
The pitfalls of temptation and evil today are many. These evils are dressed up attractively and
cunningly to deceive the very elect (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/24#24">Matt. 24:24</a>). Unless parents and youth are grounded in the basics of
good behavior and the fundamental principles and standards of the gospel, which is the true
Christian way of life, they can stumble and fall by the wayside and thus never reach the goal
of eternal life.
</p><p>
The teachings of Lehi, his son Nephi, the Apostle Paul, and Jesus, to which I have referred,
are guidelines and directions toward the tree of life. The vision of Lehi blesses all of us with
its understanding of God's purposes for his children and the responsibility of parents to their
families. The Church and its families are synonymous: one does not exist without the other,
and both serve each other, and all belong to God the Father.
</p><p>
<b>The vision of Lehi summarized</b>
</p><p>
Now in closing I wish to summarize the vision of Lehi with the following brief comments: 
</p><p>
Dreams or visions are often used as a teaching principle, unfolding the secrets of heaven to
the prepared mind and prayerful heart.
</p><p>
The love of God suggests the good and wholesome things of life.
</p><p>
The tree of life is indicative of eternal life&mdash;or celestial life&mdash;life in the full enjoyment of
God's love.
</p><p>
The fountain of living waters is representative of the love of God. All spiritual graces and
refreshment communicated by the Spirit are compared to a fountain. We learn from Jeremiah,
". . . they have forsaken the Lord, the fountain of living waters" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/17/13#13">Jer. 17:13</a>).
</p><p>
God, then, is called the fountain of living waters. The Savior taught that those who drink of it
shall never thirst (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/4/14#14">John 4:14</a>).
</p><p>
The numberless concourses of people seen by Lehi in his vision represent the different races
of men on earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/21#21">1 Ne. 8:21</a>).
</p><p>
The river of water, which is representative of the filthiness of sin, wickedness, and
contamination (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/27-29#27">1 Ne. 15:27-29</a>),
separates the wicked from the tree of life and from the Saints of God and is a
prototype of the condition called hell.
</p><p>
Notwithstanding the numerous institutions of secular and theological learning, the human
family, by and large, are groping in the mists of moral and spiritual darkness. Sin and vice,
prideful exaltation of the human mind, and the pursuit of harmful pleasures blur men's
perception, dull their sense of values, and obscure their vision of the rod of iron, or the word
of God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/25#25">1 Ne. 11:25</a>), which alone leads to eternal life.
</p><p>
The great and spacious building (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/11/35-36#35">1 Ne. 11:35-36</a>), in addition to representing the pride and vain imaginations of
men, stands for the mockery and ridicule of the world. Our generation should be reminded
that scoffers are far from the kingdom of God. Those who allow the ridicule of men to make
them embarrassed by the cause, the standards, or the obligations that they have espoused as
true followers of Christ, and are turned thereby from the straight and narrow path of truth and
righteousness, are those who form the stony ground in which the seed sown soon withers and
dies (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/5-6#5">Matt. 13:5-6</a>). Those who are drowned
in the depths of the fountain (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/8/32#32">1 Ne. 8:32</a>) refer to those who are engulfed in
the quagmire of evil-mindedness, sin, and corruption; therefore, the wicked sink to destruction
in the river of filth, and the depths thereof are the depths of hell (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/12/16#16">1 Ne. 12:16</a>).
</p><p>
Passing through the mist and clinging steadfastly to the iron rod, the faithful pass
triumphantly through the temptations that beset man's mortal pilgrimage to the cherished goal
of eternal life with God.
</p><p>
In man's search for happiness and his climb to eternal joy, there can be no relaxation, no
deviation from the straight and narrow path; nor can he lose a firm hold upon the iron rod,
which is the word of God. He must set aside the things of the world as he travels the path
which leads to exaltation and glory in the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
I bear witness to you, my brothers and sisters, to the truthfulness of these things. I know the
teachings of this vision are important to us and to all the world. May God bless us that we
may so live and set the type of example that will incline the hearts of men and women to the
restored Church of our Lord, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
