<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Symbolism in Irrigation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1952, pp. 32-35</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters: It is good to be here. The ancient words of those who dwelt in
the presence of the Savior are our words today.
</p><p>
Six months ago circumstances combined so that I was not here, and I have felt since a sense
of loss, loss of the spiritual power, the spiritual support and elevation that come to all
Latter-day Saints who attend Church gatherings in the name of the Lord, whether in general
or stake or ward capacity.
</p><p>
With you, I have been thrilled to note that the Church of Jesus Christ is not standing still but,
guided by heavenly forces, is growing and increasing and becoming mightier in the service of
God's children here upon earth. With you, too, I enjoyed the spirit of the sermon of the man
who has been called by God to preside over the Church. It is well for me, it is well for you
and it is well for all in the world to listen to the chosen head of the Church as he speaks from
time to time. Therein lies the path to safety.
</p><p>
Six months ago I was not here because, with the approval of the First Presidency, I had
accepted an invitation from the Canadian government to assist in solving some of their
problems relating to the reclamation of the dry lands of the Dominion. Canada is much like
the United States, with two seaboards, one on the Atlantic and the other on the Pacific, with
ample rainfall, and a dry section between, in the interior, such as we have here. The prairie
provinces of Canada offer only scant and difficult living to those who attempt to cultivate
them because of the lack of the plentiful rainfall on either coast. So the practice of irrigation
has gradually grown in the province of Alberta, where many of our people live. It has been
found that the enlivening power of water used in irrigation increases the crops many-fold and
what is better, permits a close settlement, and in time the building of a state. There is water
aplenty in the land of our neighbors to the north. Great streams filled with water to
overflowing, usually, roll into the oceans on both sides of the Dominion, and the problem is
how to use that water on the dry lands of Alberta, Saskatchewan, and other neighboring
provinces, to build the Dominion of Canada, now great, into a greater country.
</p><p>
The commission to which I was appointed was given the responsibility of passing on one of
the huge projects proposed by the country, one that will redeem and bring into cultivation
nearly half a million acres of land and involve an expenditure running from $100,000,000 to
$200,000,000. Sometime it has to be done, for these dry lands when irrigated offer future
possibilities of happy homes for thousands of families, not to be overlooked in the process of
statesmanship.
</p><p>
It has always been a curious thing to me, curious is not really the right word when I reflect
upon the history of our own people, how we were led by the hand of God, as a people, and
were brought over the deserts and over the mountains to be settled in this country. We did not
know at that time, and the world did not know, that one-half or more of all the land surface
of the earth lies under low rainfall. These vast stretches of land can be reclaimed only by the
twin arts of dry farming and irrigation, best of all by irrigation for dry farming at its very best
is only a minor practice to be followed by people who live near the cultivated areas. But our
people came here and for the first time in the history of civilization demonstrated that a
successful manner of community living might be built with the irrigation ditch. The Lord
guiding us took us to a protected home, but not only that, he made us teachers of the world in
these twin arts of successful soil conservation. In this state, from which we have spread over
the west and are spreading over the world, has come the birth of modern irrigation. Most
countries which lie in part under low rainfall have sent agents or representatives here to find
out what we did and how we did it, and whether they can do it also. We have a worldwide
reputation in reclaiming desert lands by the use of water. Our work has served humanity
greatly. We have preached the everlasting truths of the gospel by thousands of missionaries,
but we have also preached by our example here, before the great nations of the world, how
their resources may be utilized more fully and more completely and how the needs of
humanity may be more fully met.
</p><p>
It has never seemed to me a mere chance that the Lord brought us here. There seems to lie in
that part of our history a distinct evidence of the divine guidance of this people. It may be of
interest to us here today, as many of you know, that not only did we as a people begin to
show how a modern civilized group of people could live under irrigation, but that here, also
beginning in our own Utah State Agricultural College at Logan, experiments and tests were
and are made to place this art of irrigation on a scientific orderly basis. This is not the place
to discuss that, perhaps, but we do have the honor of being not only the generators of
modern-day irrigation, but also of placing that ancient art on a modern scientific basis.
</p><p>
Some very remarkable things have been discovered from time to time in this field that are
tremendously interesting. Our farmers are gradually learning more and more about these
precious truths. The farming people, you know, move slowly. They want to know before they
do anything, but little by little that which we have garnered and gained throughout the years
will be used.
</p><p>
And so a Latter-day Saint, working as I had to work last fall in behalf of a great agricultural,
irrigation project, is stirred in his feelings when he looks back upon what the Lord has asked
his people to do&mdash;to toil, to struggle, to compel the desert to yield; and also to teach all the
world that which the world is hungry to know.
</p><p>
Well, perhaps that is all I should say about my irrigation work and why I was not here in
attendance six months ago. But you know there is a great symbolism in irrigation. As a
lifelong student of the subject I have always been impressed by the fact that the dry desert
soil contains nearly all the elements of fertility. All that it needs is the enlivening power of a
stream of water to flow over that soil. Suddenly the land begins to yield, and it becomes
powerful. Is it not so in our spiritual lives, I wonder? Men according to our theology are
children of God not created under the old idea, but being literally children of Almighty God,
contain all the elements under the law of eternal progression that will lead them into the
likeness of their Father in heaven. When this being, this divine being, because in one sense
we are all divine, is touched by the power of the Holy Ghost, the Holy Spirit, the power that
flows from God, suddenly a man blossoms into a new life, new possibilities arise, new
powers develop. As I have lived in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints as a
member since my very early boyhood, I have come to understand that perhaps the greatest
miracle in the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ is the transformation that comes to a man or a
woman who in faith accepts the truth of the gospel and who then lives it in his or her life.
That transformation is marvelous. I have seen it in the mission field, where I first heard the
gospel. I have seen it here at home. I see it every day. Every person has a measure of God's
Spirit given to him. We are all in God's presence through his Holy Spirit. As new and greater
truths come, as the understanding of them develops within us if we accept and live them, we
are transformed from ordinary men into new powers and possibilities.
</p><p>
The weavers of the midlands in England, the coal miners of Wales, the fishermen in Norway,
the trudging farmers of Denmark, very common ordinary people, who accept the gospel from
the lips of some humble Mormon missionary become so changed by those enlightening truths
of the gospel that they are not the same people any longer. They have been fertilized, so to
speak, by the Spirit of God that flows from eternal truth, just as in irrigation the barren, dry
soil is fertilized by diverting the stream of water from the irrigation ditch onto the thirsty
land.
</p><p>
It is a comparison worthy of our thought, because we are the bearers of the irrigation message
to all the world.
</p><p>
I remember the man who baptized me into the Church, a very common, ordinary man to
begin with, a ropewalker with a jug of beer two or three times a day, a glass of whiskey a
little later, and a cud of tobacco mostly all day long, living a useless, purposeless life, except
for three meals a day, and the satisfaction of some of the carnal appetites. He heard the gospel
and accepted it. It was good. It was something he had been longing for. The man grew in
power and stature in the Church. As I recall it, he filled five or six missions and presided
over one of the missions of the Church. He was the same man, with the same arms, same
feet, same body, same mind, but changed because of the Spirit that comes with the acceptance
of eternal truth. Have not we seen this in our own families and friends, in the little towns in
which we live? Have not we felt our own strength grow mightier in love for our fellow men,
in love for our daily tasks, in love for all the good things of life? If you question yourself or
question us here who have the responsibility of conducting this conference, we will all bear
witness to it. But remember, when irrigation began in Utah, it was a struggle with the earth. It
required toil. The water did not flow down these canyon streams to the farms just by asking it
to do so, but men dug and drilled and shoveled and made canals. We have a remarkable
illustration of that in one of our enterprises in Utah. It was called the Hurricane enterprise.
The story of that has never been told quite fully, but it is stirring and thrilling. And to some
degree in every enterprise in the building of this state toil had to be faced and used. And so to
get that spiritual stream that I have been talking about, it must be sought for; it must be
fought for; it must be labored for. It will come, but we must ask for it and seek it and labor
for it. Then comes that great change&mdash;an overwhelming change. It changes men to a Godlike
phase of life and living.
</p><p>
Well, you know the comparison as well as I do. I must not take any more of your time. It is
good to be a Latter-day Saint. It is good to be here. It is good to hear the words of inspiration
that come from the mouths and lives of these inspired men. I am glad to feel the responsive
spirit from the thousands of people who are here and who listen over the radio.
</p><p>
May we all so live as to have a great measure of the enlivening, spiritual, fertilizing stream
that comes from God because of our virtuous lives, our earnest actions in seeking after truth.
May we all be blessed according to our needs. Let us determine to cling to our heritage here
in this land where we were led by the guiding power of God, and may the descendants of our
pioneer fathers refuse to sell their birthright for gold lest it turn to a "mess of pottage"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/25/34#34">Gen. 25:34</a>). May
we remember our heritage in this Church of land, of water, and of spiritual power, I pray in
the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
