<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Kingdom of God Is Here</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder George Q. Morris</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Q. Morris, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1953, pp. 104-106</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters, I thank the Lord for the privilege of being one with you here
this morning, and during this whole glorious conference. I pray earnestly that the Spirit of the
Lord may direct all that I shall say.
</p><p>
I have been impressed as I have looked out over this audience and been conscious of the
atmosphere of this great Tabernacle and listened to the impressive and inspired testimonies
and exhortations that have been given, that this is truly an historic and sacred building. Here
for nearly a century the word of God has been preached by the authority of God, proclaiming
the last Dispensation of the Fulness of Times. In this remarkable building, so unique in its
structure, so simple, with the absence of all the ornamental and gilded appointments of great
cathedrals, humble, brave, and devoted men and women have met to worship God. One
prominent feature in this building is the great organ, and the choir seats, from which, as the
choir occupy them, the glorious music comes, typical of harmony and heaven. The feature
perhaps of greatest significance is this stand&mdash;this series of pulpits&mdash;a token of the
priesthood of God, for here is assembled this morning the authoritative presiding servants of
God in this last dispensation, men chosen of him, who possess the power and authority to
speak in the name of almighty God.
</p><p>
As President Richards was speaking of the world situation and of our relation to it, I could
not help feeling, though it may seem presumptuous and some may take offense, that this,
nevertheless, is the spiritual capitol of this world. From here God speaks to this world, and his
Authorities are officially seated this day in this sacred Tabernacle, and their word is binding
on all the world; and they are calling this world to repentance, to accept the gospel of Jesus
Christ, the only power  in the world that will save it, that will enable men and women to
shape acceptable lives before our Father in heaven. Men and women by it are led to love the
truth, to love God and to keep his commandments, and by their example and by their word,
spread this glorious gospel.
</p><p>
I have before me a very simple statement from the Prophet Moroni, I think a statement of
very great significance. He is addressing himself to this generation and all other generations
where this idea prevails.
</p><p>
And again I speak unto you who deny the revelations of God, and say that they are done
away, that there are no revelations, nor prophecies, nor gifts, nor healing, nor speaking with
tongues, and the interpretation of tongues; 
</p><p>
Behold I say unto you, he that denieth these things knoweth not the gospel of Christ; yea, he
has not read the scriptures; if so, he does not understand them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/7-8#7">Morm. 9:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
That simple statement has tremendous implications.
</p><p>
That's the key to the history of Christendom for seventeen centuries. Following the death of
the apostles, religious leaders set up the principle which persists to this day&mdash;perhaps to the
best of their knowledge and understanding&mdash;that revelation had ceased and was finished, and
that prophets and apostles were things of the past. And that is in itself definite and conclusive
proof that, so far as the world is concerned during seventeen hundred years,
such was the case. For when revelation is shut off, and when all the preachers of religion (and
this is and was their well-nigh universal opinion) deny its existence, then the Church and
kingdom of God is not there, and has not been during this eclipse of seventeen hundred years;
and that is the simple reason why men did not know what the gospel was, and why,
consequently, when they read the scriptures they could not understand them because they are
only understood by the spirit and power by which they were written. The ministrations of the
authorized servants of God produce scripture; the scripture cannot produce authorized
ministers of God, nor authority to preach, nor are they bringing new revelations to a living
Church. That must be done by living oracles. And they were killed off. The world would not
accept them. The world would not accept the Lord Jesus Christ himself; he was crucified.
And then his Apostles, chosen and sent out to preach the gospel to the world, in the main,
met the same fate. Revelation did cease, and the world went into an eclipse, a spiritual
eclipse&mdash;seventeen hundred years of darkness. Men were left to themselves to do the best they
could. But no man knows the gospel of Jesus Christ by his natural wisdom, nor by the
wisdom and learning of the world. It must be taught by one sent of God. No man knew how
the Church should be set up and organized, how its priesthood should function, nor what
priesthood is. There was no priesthood operating for them to see or be instructed by and no
organized church for them to see in operation during this seventeen hundred years of darkness
and of night. There was, for perhaps a century or so, the afterglow of a sunset as this night
set in, a reflection from the ministry of the Savior and his Apostles, but then darkness came.
Churches were established by men not called of God (as the Apostle Paul said, "Having a
form of godliness, but denying the power thereof"
[<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/5#5">2 Tim. 3:5</a>]), and doctrines were
formulated without authority, and the significant and unhappy thing is that the prevailing
doctrines of Christendom today found their origin in this spiritual darkness. Unfortunately,
they still persist.
</p><p>
But later on after what historians in general agreement have called the Dark Ages, when these
doctrines were being crystallized into creeds and man-made churches were increasing, the
dawn began to break. The first rays of light appeared with the development of human
freedom and the enlightenment of the human mind in the Renaissance and with the discovery
of America&mdash;America, the Promised Land&mdash;which in the providences of God had been held
in reserve, hidden from men, on which it was his declared purpose to set up a free
government, so that he might restore again the kingdom of God to the earth. And the sun
arose, and the night was past, and this Church, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints, was set up in the earth. All this the scriptures had clearly foretold.
</p><p>
Three very important things occurred. I will mention them in just the moment of time
remaining. First of all, and most essential, God again revealed himself to man. The Father and
the Son stood in the presence of a fourteen-year-old boy and talked with him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>). He saw these
celestial Personages. He heard their heart-penetrating voices. He received their glorious
instructions. That swept away all the erroneous ideas, the false teachings and conceptions as to
the identity and nature of God, and restored the true and living God to the knowledge of man.
The second thing was that new scripture was brought forth. The Book of Mormon was given
to the world by the power of God, containing a fulness of the gospel, which explains gospel
doctrines and teachings and substantiates the teachings of the Bible and makes possible their
correct interpretation. Also through the Prophet Joseph Smith a volume of revelations was
brought forth, containing today's instructions of God to his Church. And
then, third, was restored the priesthood of God, which exists in his Church in all generations,
and is the power of God which administers the gospel and manifests godliness to men in the
flesh. Without this priesthood the Church of God does not and cannot exist.
</p><p>
The absence of these three things had brought on the dark ages. They were now restored, and
the sun has again risen. The Church and kingdom of God is here. Its sun is in the heavens to
be seen by all men who will open their eyes to see its light, and here is its center place in the
tops of the Rocky Mountains. May God help us to live its principles and proclaim its
doctrines and devote our lives and our means and all that we have and are to the
establishment of this cause in the earth for the happiness and the salvation of mankind. I
humbly bear witness that Jesus is the Christ, the Redeemer of the world, and Joseph Smith
was his prophet, and through them this Church has come into existence and will continue, and
no power can stay it, for by the power of God it will cover the earth, and Jesus Christ will
come and reign in the world. May God give us power to be true to this great revelation of
truth, I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
