<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 58-60</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
When President Robertson referred to the freedom we enjoy in this great country, and gave us
a glimpse of barbarism going on in China and other places, these lines came to my mind: 
</p><p>
"Breathes there the man, with soul so dead,
     Who never to himself hath said
     This is my own, my native land?"
</p><p>
Let us thank God every morning, every night, in our family prayers, that we live in the
United States of America, the Constitution of which vouchsafes individual freedom, and let us
pray also, that the Lord will frustrate the plans of the Communists who would deprive us of
that freedom.
</p><p>
There are in the Tabernacle tonight, 10,432; in the Assembly Hall 2,932; in the Barratt Hall
1,220; on the grounds 1,792; the Field House at Provo reports 839; making a total of over
17,000 men of the Priesthood assembled tonight.
</p><p>
It has always been my nature to enjoy the company of my associates. I love to be with my
friends. The older I grow the more intense becomes my appreciation of fellowship in the
Brotherhood of Christ. I sense that tonight more deeply, more sincerely than ever before. As I
have looked into your faces, partaken of your spirit, as I picture those in the Assembly Hall in
the Barratt Hall and on the grounds and down in the Field House, I feel that it is one of the
greatest privileges, one of the most inspirational experiences in life to associate with men who
hold the Holy Priesthood.
</p><p>
I have nothing but blessing in my heart for you. I love you. I like to call you my beloved
associates and fellow workers, and that love is akin to the love we have for our wives and our
children, and if we can keep this unity, this confidence, nothing in the world can stop the
progress of this work.
</p><p>
You note tonight that the theme has largely been missionary. We have called these brethren
from China, Australia, and Switzerland merely illustrative of how wide-spread our Gospel is.
We have had them from the Islands, from South Africa. They are calling, calling for
missionaries. Within the last few weeks, prominent visitors from India, Indo-China, from
Hong Kong, have extended a cordial invitation to us to come to these places. This is a
world-wide religion, brethren. It is the Gospel that must be preached to every nation, kindred,
tongue and people.
</p><p>
Let me thank you and those of your families who have sent in checks by the scores, recently,
with promises to repeat those checks monthly, to aid local missionaries in spreading the
Gospel. We do not want any missionary in Australia or New Zealand or in any of the
American nations, or in Mexico to have his or her expenses paid entirely but we will assist
whenever possible local missionaries who need supplementary assisting. The response to
suggestions of some of the brethren for such missionary funds is surprising and gratifying. As
far as possible we let the donors know the names of those to whom this money is sent.
</p><p>
How the way opens up for the preaching of the Gospel! The calling of the boys into the
military service has of course crippled our missionary work, more than it should have done. If
anybody tells you that members of this Church are not carrying their share in the military
work, you may just tell them that they do not know what they are talking
about. I just take this opportunity to thank all who are contributing to the missionary cause.
</p><p>
Another phase of this missionary work tonight&mdash;Professor James L. Barker for years has urged
that we give classes in foreign languages, that our young men may have an opportunity to
study at home and get at least the fundamentals before going to a foreign country. Well, it is
a good suggestion, but we have not yet been able to make it practical. It seems now that the
time has come when we must do something. I have here before me an appeal for the teaching
of languages in our high schools. I have a note from one who says that among all our senior
high schools, only 15 offer one or more courses in foreign languages. In the Church there are
men and women from every country in the world, in which there are missionaries. I should
like to encourage our young men and young women, young men particularly, to include in
their high school and college courses, some of these languages.
</p><p>
President Wilkinson informs me that twelve foreign languages are taught in the
B.Y.U.&mdash;German, French, Portuguese, Greek, Syrian, Russian, Arabic, Latin, Swedish,
Norwegian, Finnish, Dutch. In the University of Utah I learn that they have <i>810</i> students
registered in 12 languages, and so the opportunity is at hand.
</p><p>
Recently there appeared in a local paper here an excellent editorial on the necessity, on the
advisability of teaching languages here in our State, and in the United States. "Modern
languages are not as widely or as successfully taught in United States schools as they should
be to meet the requirements of the nation's position. The high school student who <i>takes</i> a
language often finds he has practically forgotten it within a year or so. That may be due, in
large part, to the fact that there is little opportunity to exercise language skills. The need to
learn foreign languages should be accented and the acquisition and use of such languages
stimulated. When men can talk together, they can get together."
</p><p>
The responsibility of preaching the Gospel rests upon us. When the people in Macedonia
called to Paul, and the spirit told him to go over, he answered that call
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/16/9-10#9">Acts 16:9-10</a>). They are calling for
us in various nations they are calling for more missionaries now in the missions already
established, and we must answer that call.
</p><p>
Brethren, in conclusion, let me urge more diligence in living the principles of the Gospel. We
may preach, we may write, and publish books, but the most effective way of preaching the
Gospel to the nations of the world, is by example.
</p><p>
"Therefore whosoever heareth these sayings of mine," said the Savior, "and doeth them, I will
liken him unto a wise man, which built his house upon a rock: 
</p><p>
"And the rain descended, and floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and
it fell not: for it was founded upon a rock.
</p><p>
"And every one that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth them not, shall be likened unto
a foolish man which built his house upon the sand: 
</p><p>
"And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house;
and it fell: and great was the fall of it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/24-27#24">Matt. 7:24-27</a>).
</p><p>
May God add his blessings to the instructions and the reports given this night, may we depart
with greater determination in our hearts to serve the Lord and keep his commandments, may
we go forth with greater resolution to defend and keep his commandments, may we go forth
with greater resolution to defend one another in righteous living, to defend the Church, not to
speak against our neighbors, nor against authorities of the Church, local, stake or general. Let
us avoid evil speaking, let us avoid slander and gossip. These are poisons to the soul to those
who indulge. Evil speaking injures the reviler more than the reviled. I heard a recent convert
who came from Europe say, "I am surprised to hear how many people talk
against the Authorities here in Salt Lake City." She was grieved, she had the right ideal of the
Gospel of Jesus Christ, that we should speak well of one another.
</p><p>
Brethren, peace be in your hearts peace and harmony be in your homes. God bless every man
and every woman who has entered the waters of baptism with a testimony of the truth, I bear
that testimony to you tonight with all my soul. I know that the power of God rests with his
servants. I know that he will reveal and does reveal his mind and will to them. The
communications of man's spirit, of one holding the Priesthood, with our Father in Heaven
through the Holy Spirit is real. Is there anything in the world more precious than that
knowledge! It is more precious than life, because it gives assurance that if death does come,
that spirit continues. I bear you that testimony, that communication with our Heavenly Father
is real, that Jesus Christ, our Lord, stands at the head of this Church. and that he desires the
members so to live that this truth, this Gospel, may be preached in all the world as a witness
and then the end will come
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>).
</p><p>
With all my soul I bless you my fellow workers and pray that his inspiration will abide in
your hearts and that peace and harmony and love may abide in your homes, in the name of
Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
