<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">How Are We Worshiping</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 27-28</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My testimony has been strengthened and my faith increased in the glorious truths of the
gospel of Jesus Christ to which we have listened today.  It does answer the questions:  why
these general conferences, why these quarterly conferences, why these conferences of the
auxiliary organization&mdash;"For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the
edifying of the body of Christ" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12#12">Eph. 4:12</a>),
until we all come to a knowledge of the truth.
</p><p>
I have reminisced as Brother Hanks has been speaking. I am sure he will pardon me if I make
reference to him and his marvelous family.  It was my privilege to live in the Nineteenth
Ward in the Salt Lake Stake.  On October 12, 1921, I left for my mission to the Central
States.  The day after, there came into the home of Brother and Sister Hanks, not a small 
boy&mdash;he was rather large, I understand&mdash;I was not there, but I have heard&mdash;and he was named
Marion.  Well, you have seen his works; you have felt his spirit.  There are others in this
family just as good and just and devoted to building up the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
Theirs in an example of a good Latter-day Saint home, wherein are taught the truths of the
gospel of Jesus Christ; wherein they gather in humble prayer and thanksgiving for the
blessings which have come into their lives; wherein they are taught the true joys of service to
God and our fellow men.  My, what a contrast to the story he has just related to us.
</p><p>
There is another anniversary this week&mdash;if I may be pardoned for making reference to 
it&mdash;just fifty years ago on the 7th of October my father and I arrived in Salt Lake City&mdash;a boy
of ten, coming to a new world with one purpose in mind, to be close to the center of the
Church and to serve the Lord.
</p><p>
I am grateful for that father who listened to the missionaries some sixty-three years ago in
England, about two years before I was born, who accepted these truths and for about
forty-five years was associated with the Scout program of the Church.
</p><p>
I shall ever be grateful for my membership in the Church of Jesus Christ, and to the young
people today may I say that there is no obsolescence in the teachings of the gospel.  As I
understand the definition of <i>obsolete</i> it means something that is old-fashioned, that we have
outgrown, something that is ancient or antiquated and maybe, in the terms of modern
language, "old stuff" or "for the birds."
</p><p>
The gospel of Jesus Christ is just as vital and essential today as it was when it was instituted
in our pre-existent estate.  Jesus Christ is the Author of salvation.  I know this as I know I am
standing here today.  I have that witness.
</p><p>
We may be termed peculiar, but that is nothing new.  Whenever there has been a dispensation
of the gospel of Jesus Christ in the earth, the followers have been referred to as "a peculiar
people."  Moses so declared (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/19/5#5">Ex. 19:5</a>).
Peter and Paul so declared (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/titus/2/14#14">Titus 2:14</a>).
I would recall the words of Peter: 
</p><p>
"But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, a peculiar people; that ye
should shew forth the praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvelous
light" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/9#9">1 Pet. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
It is wonderful to bask in the light of the gospel of Jesus Christ which banishes fear, which
banishes confusion and frustrations, and, oh, the need for remembering these things today.
</p><p>
So I pray that we will acknowledge the hand of God as we have listened to his mouthpiece
and prophet in his keynote address to us this great conference, admonishing us to teach the
word.  We make no apology for teaching truth, we need make no compromise with the
philosophies and teachings of men.  The only time we are on dangerous ground is when we
pull away from the teachings of the Master, for I assure you the Master does not pull away
from us.  As individuals we are prone to pull away from him because of things we do and say
not in harmony with his teachings.
</p><p>
May we have a desire reburnished in our minds and our hearts as we leave this conference, to
be more dedicated in the service of the Master, putting our own homes in order, having
family prayer, our individual prayer, paying our tithes and offerings, keeping
the Word of Wisdom, and being chaste and benevolent. As I speak of putting our homes in
order, I should like to suggest that we take note of what comes into the hands of our youth,
our own children. We must make sure they are not having their minds poisoned by the
garbage, if you please, that is on many of the newsstands and available through other channels
throughout the nation.
</p><p>
Time will not permit me to go into this subject further, but I call to mind a headline which I
read just recently as I visited one of the stakes in the East and it told of this sad story: 
</p><p>
As the story was told, a man, an employee of the city of New York for some thirty years, a
respected employee, married, with grown children who were married, had working with him a
young man about twenty-five, also married. Unknown to their wives, they had been in the
dastardly business of producing vile film, pornography, and were arrested with over $500,000
worth of the filthy stuff in their possession in one of their garages. I mention again, they were
married men with children of their own, deliberately poisoning the minds of young people,
taking advantage of living in a land where our forefathers came to worship God according to
the dictates of their own conscience, a land built upon freedom and liberty.
</p><p>
I call to mind a statement made by a minister a couple of weeks ago as the Premier from
Russia visited in the United States. He said he hoped that Mr. Khrushchev would come to his
church ". . . to see how we worship."
</p><p>
How are we worshiping? Are we the followers of Jesus Christ only on the Sabbath day, or
just when we are in priesthood meeting, or is it that worship which reflects good and his
peace as we go forth in our various travels, endeavors, and walks of life, truly being an
influence every day, every hour, every minute for good to our fellow men?
</p><p>
I pray that we as parents will seek to know what our children are feeding upon, and see that
they feed upon the truths found in the Bible, the Book of Mormon, the Doctrine and
Covenants, the Pearl of Great Price, the four Standard Works of the Church. Then they will
not suffer from malnourishment of the Spirit, and we will be fitting them to withstand the
buffeting of Satan.
</p><p>
I bear you my witness and testimony that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, the Divine Son
of our Heavenly Father, that Joseph Smith was and is a Prophet of God, and that those who
have succeeded him as Presidents of this Church down to President David O. McKay today,
have been and are mouthpieces and prophets of our Lord.
</p><p>
I bear you my solemn witness that President McKay holds the keys and authority, the keys of
the kingdom, and that the mantle of authority is upon him. I am so thankful for that witness,
and I pray that I may be able to continue to bear this testimony as the Lord permits. I pray
his peace and blessing upon us humbly, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
