<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Power of Truth</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 44-51</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I would like to introduce the few remarks that I shall make by recalling a few scriptures, one
of which has been repeated by two previous speakers today.
</p><p>
The Lord declared:
</p><p>
All truth is independent in that sphere in which God has placed it, to act for itself, as all
intelligence also; otherwise there is no existence
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/30#30">D&amp;C 93:30</a>).
</p><p>
FREEDOM OF CHOICE 
</p><p>
And the other, quoted by Elder Romney as one of the great teachings from the Book of
Mormon, was Father Lehi's explanation of this same great principle to his son Jacob:
</p><p>
And to bring about his eternal purposes in the end of man, after he had created our first
parents, and the beasts of the field and the fowls of the air, and in fine, all things which are
created, it must needs be that there was an opposition; even the forbidden fruit in opposition
to the tree of life; the one being sweet and the other bitter.
</p><p>
Wherefore, the Lord God gave unto man that he should act for himself. Wherefore, man
could not act for himself save it should be that he was enticed by the one or the other
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/15-16#15">2 Ne. 2:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
There were those who seemingly, as evidenced by their conduct, think of this principle of free
agency as a matter of license to do what they please to do. But again Father Lehi explains this
matter to his son:
</p><p>
Wherefore, men are free according to the flesh; and all things shall be given them which are
expedient unto man. And they are free to choose liberty and eternal life, through the great
mediation of all men, or to choose captivity and death, according to the captivity and power
of the devil; for he seeketh that all men might be miserable like unto himself
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/27#27">2 Ne. 2:27</a>).
</p><p>
We must teach men everywhere that liberty and freedom are to be obtained only by yielding
obedience to truth. We must teach Latter-day Saints the meaning of the words of the Savior:
</p><p>
And ye shall know the truth, and the truth shall make you free
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/32#32">John 8:32</a>).
</p><p>
Anyone who looks about him and thinks about this matter will see great evidence of the
power of evil enticing men to do evil. It must be understood by us as a Church that if we are
to build a force that will nullify the power of evil, we must develop the God-given agencies
placed in his Church to entice men to seek the paths that lead to eternal life.
</p><p>
GENERAL SERVICEMEN'S COMMITTEE
</p><p>
I have recalled these scriptures I have quoted many times during the last few years because of
the feeling and weight of responsibility that has rested upon me in the assignment of the First
Presidency as a member of the general servicemen's committee directing the work of the
Church among our Latter-day Saint boys in military service and as a member of the general
priesthood committee. It was with a prayer of relief that we thanked the Lord that we had
come through the war with as few casualties, spiritually speaking, as we did, but it was with
considerable anxiety that we again saw marshaled into the ranks of the military, our young,
untrained boys, many of them without experience and with not too much faith developed, in a
so-called peacetime draft. We came soon to see and learn, to our dismay, that the moral
hazards in such a situation were even greater than during the fighting part of the war. Then
there was something of a moral discipline that boys had when ahead of them there was the
prospect of imminent death.
</p><p>
It is true today that the draft situation has eased somewhat, but we view with fear and anxiety
the forces that are at work which would have a universal military draft of all able-bodied
young men in this country, which will come except God in his mercy shall deliver us
therefrom. It is because of that anxiety and that possibility and the fact that we still have
many of our young men in service that have caused me to think of these matters which the
Lord has called to our attention.
</p><p>
VIEWS OF CHAPLAIN
</p><p>
With respect to the matter of war and the processes of war, a chaplain who served in two
wars and longer, writes this:
</p><p>
War (and by inference the training for it) makes for few conversions. War only makes people
more strongly what they were when the struggle began. If they were intemperate when they
went into uniform, they will usually have become much harder drinkers by the time they
come back home. If they were careless in sex morality, they are almost sure to have become
more slimy in that respect. If they were noisy braggarts, you may expect them to return
intolerable boasters. If they were selfish, their selfishness will have increased. If they were
honest, decent, modest men, the war will usually have improved those qualities. If they
despised God, they will have come out more sure in scorn; if they loved God a little, they
will have learned to love him a lot. But there will be no more conversions than in peacetime,
rather less. All history shows it true that no religious revival ever began or was fostered by
battle.
</p><p>
What is said here by this chaplain about those away from their homes in military service
might in part be said about all who are away from their homes and away from the influence
of the Church.
</p><p>
As we scan the priesthood reports from quarter to quarter, there is evidence that there are
many of our priesthood members not in military service but likewise away from home and
away from the ties and influences of the Church. There are also reports of many girls who are
away from their homes at school and at work and, therefore, shorn of the influences that
otherwise would tie them close to the influence of the Church.
</p><p>
PLACE OF REFUGE
</p><p>
When the Lord revealed the name by which his Church was to be called, he gave some other
instructions as to what that Church was to do. He said:
</p><p>
And that the gathering together upon the land of Zion, and upon her stakes, may be for a
defense, and for a refuge from the storm, and from wrath when it shall be poured out without
mixture upon the whole earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/6#6">D&amp;C 115:6</a>).
</p><p>
As I have thought of that refuge which the Lord designed his organization to be, I have
thought of those agencies within it, one of which Elder Benson spoke so eloquently about in
his Church of the Air address this morning, the home. He quoted the scripture which we have
had repeated time and time again as a quotation from the revelation of the Lord. After the
Lord had declared it a sin upon the heads of the parents if they failed to teach the law of
repentance and have their children baptized when eight years of age
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25#25">D&amp;C 68:25</a>), he said:
</p><p>
And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord.
</p><p>
And the inhabitants of Zion shall also observe the Sabbath day to keep it holy.
</p><p>
And the inhabitants of Zion also shall remember their labors, inasmuch as they are appointed
to labor, in all faithfulness; for the idler shall be had in remembrance before the Lord
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28-30#28">D&amp;C 68:28-30</a>).
</p><p>
PURPOSES OF CHURCH ORGANIZATION
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul has defined another one of the purposes of the Church organization in his
writings to the Ephesians. He declared that the Lord gave this organization ". . . to edify the
body of the church," (or, in other words to educate the members of the Church until they
would) "all come unto a unity of faith" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12-13#12">Eph. 4:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
Clearly the Apostle Paul saw the importance of the teacher and those who would instruct our
members in the doctrines of the Church as another of those divine agencies in the Church to
entice against the power of evil. It would be well if all the teachers would understand what
the Apostle Paul meant when he said to the Corinthians:
</p><p>
And I . . . came to you, came not with excellency of speech or of wisdom, declaring unto you
the testimony of God.
</p><p>
For I determined not to know any thing among you, save Jesus Christ, and him crucified
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/1-2#1">1 Cor. 2:1-2</a>).
</p><p>
OBJECTIVE OF TEACHERS
</p><p>
That should be the only objective of instructors and teachers in this Church to teach "Jesus
Christ, and him crucified." We need not the "excellency of speech nor of wisdom," but we
need the testimony of God, as Paul said. And then this warning came in his later writings:
</p><p>
For if the trumpet give an uncertain sound, who shall prepare himself to the battle?
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/8#8">1 Cor. 14:8</a>).
</p><p>
President Joseph F. Smith, in commenting about this and decrying the fact that there were
some apparently trying to confuse our people and lead them away by destroying faith rather
than by building a testimony of God, said:
</p><p>
Among the Latter-day Saints the preaching of false doctrine disguised as truths of the gospel
may be expected from people, of two classes and practically from these only; they are: First,
the hopelessly ignorant, whose lack of intelligence is due to their indolence and sloth, who
make but feeble effort, if indeed any at all, to better themselves, by reading and study; those
who are afflicted with a dread disease that may develop into an incurable malady&mdash;laziness.
</p><p>
Second, the proud and self-vaunting ones, who read by the lamp of their own conceit; who
interpret by rules of their own contriving; who have become a law unto themselves, and so
pose as the sole judges of their own doings, more dangerously ignorant than the first.
</p><p>
Beware of the lazy and the proud; their infection in each case is contagious; better for them
and for all when they are compelled to display the yellow flag of warning, that the clean and
uninfected may be protected.
</p><p>
I wish that we could have in all our classes and meetings the spirit which characterized one of
our missionary meetings down at Ventura, California, where I visited recently with President
Oscar W. McConkie, of the California Mission, when a woman who had sat in one of our
Latter-day Saint meetings for the first time in her life made this comment at the close of the
meeting:
</p><p>
I have studied the scriptures all my life, but today the words of the scriptures have been made
to live.
</p><p>
So can be all the instructions of inspired teachers of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
DUTIES OF THE PRIESTHOOD
</p><p>
And now there is a third agency in the Church to entice men away from evil.
</p><p>
The Lord has set up the priesthood, and to them he gave the injunction to elders, priests,
teachers, deacons, that they were to "watch over the Church"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>)&mdash;and in more detailed
explanation to the teachers&mdash;"to see that there is no iniquity, no evil speaking, and that all
Church members do their duty" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/54#54">D&amp;C 20:54</a>).
</p><p>
But, even after instructions have gone out from the General Authorities, concerning the
servicemen, to our bishops and stake presidents as how the boys away from home may be
contacted and directed; and after our instructions have gone out about the girls who likewise
are away from home, and how we ought to shepherd them and keep in touch with them; and
how the quorums should look after their absent members, we regret to say our reports indicate
that sometimes quorum leaders take too lightly the exercise of those agencies which our
Heavenly Father has caused to be set up here for the enticement to do good of those who
otherwise are being enticed by evil.
</p><p>
At the beginning of the war there was an interesting newspaper account of a boy flying in
from a training trip over the air field who suddenly shouted through his radio device to the
man in the control tower below: "I can't see. I've lost my eyesight."
</p><p>
And the man in the control tower said: "Now, Son, you get a grip on yourself, and I will tell
you what to do."
</p><p>
Quietly the man in the control tower guided him and had him circle the field many times,
losing altitude by manipulating the controls, and finally the pilot rolled to a stop safely in
front of the control tower on the ground.
</p><p>
It is that kind of calm wisdom and counsel that we need so much today. I would like to
illustrate what I mean by bringing you parts of two letters from two of our boys who came
through a period of spiritual "blindness" because of the steadying influence of wise counselors
in the Church. One of these boys wrote a letter just recently and began his letter by saying:
</p><p>
EXPERIENCE OF SERVICEMAN
</p><p>
"My bishop is the best bishop in this Church." He then explained that when he became a
priest, his bishop taught him, among the first things, that God answered prayer. So the bishop
instructed him before he went away into military service, and he went away strengthened by
these teachings, but when he got out there, he learned to his dismay that some of those who
claim membership in the Church did not act as the servants of the Lord should. They were
rowdy. There was irreverence. And he got to thinking, "Could it be the Church of Jesus Christ
if they don't reverence his name and are irreverent in his house?" He went to visit other
churches and found a spirit of worship that sometimes was not to be found in his own. In his
own way he formed the conclusion that therefore the Church must be wrong. He wrote home
to his bishop and said: "Bishop, I have decided to join another church. I feel that this must be
wrong or our people would be more reverent in their meetings."
</p><p>
His bishop wrote back and said: "Well, my boy, do not act too hastily. You study about this
matter, and think about it. You pray to your Heavenly Father, and everything will be all
right." The boy then wrote this:
</p><p>
"On Thanksgiving night, I was very tired as I had just come off a watch at night, and when I
had gone to bed, all I wanted to do was sleep. That night God answered my prayer. It was
late, and what to me was a vision and to the common people would be a dream came to me. I
saw a beautiful garden, and in the middle of this garden was a golden path. Coming down the
path was my grandfather who had died in 1937. On the other side was my uncle who had
died on a mission in 1939.
</p><p>
"Now I had gone to bed very tired, and I had never thought of my uncle or my grandfather as
they had died when I was still under ten years of age.
</p><p>
"But that was not all. In the middle of them was Joseph Smith. They all talked to me, and the
final thing that I can remember distinctly as being said was Joseph Smith telling me to stick
to the truth, no matter what the other people said or did and to listen to the truth even though
others did not listen to it.
</p><p>
"Then he said that there was still work to be done there as I had work to do here, and they
faded away, and it seemed that I was in the garden alone until the garden began to fade, and I
seemed to fall.
</p><p>
"When I awoke, it was still the middle of the night, and it was also cold, yet I had a feeling
of warmth within me, and I knew that God had answered my prayers. I finished the night in
restful sleep.
</p><p>
"Now you may think I was dreaming, too, but I still feel and know that I had an answer to
my prayer.
</p><p>
I recalled that boy's letter when we heard a group of missionaries down in the California
Mission say: "When we get discouraged and downcast and blue, we have made a practice to
go away fasting into the mountains before daylight and stay there all day and return after dark
at night, and we have never failed to come from that experience strengthened by the power of
God."
</p><p>
WOUNDED MAN REMEMBERED
</p><p>
Another of our men coming back from combat service overseas was thrown into the middle
of the ocean when his ship was torpedoed. He was seriously burned and was sent to a
sanitarium, with his mind greatly disturbed and upset. He writes this testimony:
</p><p>
"While in the hospital, word came to me that my son had been gravely wounded in the South
Pacific. I could not go to him. My world had collapsed. No, again, it is not the usual story. I
did not remain steadfast in the faith. I became rebellious. I blamed my Heavenly Father for all
of the misery and distress which was mine. I concluded that he had let me down. I turned
away from him. I even got to the point where I could no longer pray. It seemed as if my line
of communication had been broken, and I had lost all contact with God. That was the depth
of human misery. Utter futility and resentment were mine. There is no destitution like that of
being out of contact with our Heavenly Father. It is like receiving a busy signal when you call
your doctor in an emergency.
</p><p>
"But then a miracle happened! My friends in the Church had not forgotten me! They prayed
with faith for my recovery. My name was placed in the temples of our Lord where prayer was
said in my behalf. My children continued to pray even as I had taught them to do. My parents
prayed with an unwavering faith.
</p><p>
"The elders of the Church sought me out and gave me a blessing. I had little faith in them,
but God had not forgotten me. He heard those prayers, and he turned not away. And health
soon returned to my body."
</p><p>
I ask you members and leaders of the Church: Suppose that the bishop had been too busy to
write to his boy who was disturbed by the irreverence of many who attended meetings where
he had been. Suppose that he had not been taught as a priest the things which the bishop had
taught him about prayer and how he could get an answer to his problems. Suppose that this
other man's elders' quorum had failed, and they had forgotten to pray back home. I ask you
to consider the seriousness of our responsibility in these matters.
</p><p>
DAY OF DECEPTION
</p><p>
Today is a day of clever deception, a day when the Master declared one of the signs of his
coming should be that even the very elect, according to the covenant, would be deceived
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/24#24">Matt. 24:24</a>).
</p><p>
One of our boys now studying in a large university on the coast declared that the "thing that
had kept him from losing faith in the Bible which the higher critics have decimated almost to
a point of non-recognition," he said, "the thing that has kept my faith is that I know the Book
of Mormon is true, and because of that testimony I know that what they are saying about the
Bible is false and not the truth."
</p><p>
The Lord has given us a sure guide as to how we might discern truth from error. He said:
</p><p>
And that which doth not edify is not of God. . . .
</p><p>
That which is of God is light; and he that receiveth light and continueth in God, receiveth
more light; and that light groweth brighter and brighter until the perfect day
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/22-24#22">D&amp;C 50:22-24</a>).
</p><p>
KEEP GOD'S COMMANDMENTS
</p><p>
I wish we could take a lesson from the testimony of a man in this city who conducts a
business here, who wrote and told me about a little experience he had when during the
so-called depression of the past years, he thought he was going to lose everything that he had,
and so he fasted and prayed that the Lord would show him how to save his business, and he
said: "One morning just as it was breaking daylight I felt the still small voice which said to
me: 'If you will only but keep God's commandments, you will be given all the wisdom
necessary to save your business.
</p><p>
Simple, but a great powerful truth&mdash;if we will only keep God's commandments, the wisdom
sufficient to our needs will be given us!
</p><p>
In the words of one, may we not forget the great truth which he has put in these words:
</p><p>
Isn't it strange that princes and kings<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        And clowns that caper in sawdust rings<br />
And just plain folks like you and me<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        Are builders for eternity?
</p><p>
To each is given a bag of tools,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        A shapeless mass and a book of rules,<br />
And each must build ere life has flown,<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;        A stumbling-block or a steppingstone. <br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;                               ("Stumbling-Block or Stepping Stone,"<br />
&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;                                by R. L. Sharpe.)
</p><p>
God grant us strength. May we rise to our responsibilities, to do our job, to entice the
membership of this Church and the world to seek the things that bring eternal life and
happiness here and in the world to come, I pray humbly, in the name of the Lord Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
