<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1943, pp. 99-100</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, I am full of fear and apprehension as I face this large audience of Church
leaders. I have been deeply touched, as you have, by the stirring messages which have come
to us in song and in sermon. I have been trying to summarize the messages which we have
received, and as I have done so, the words of Jesus have come to my mind with force and
persistence:
</p><p>
Man shall not live by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/4#4">Matt. 4:4</a>).
</p><p>
The Master's words never grow old and trite. They come with the freshness of today, and are
never outworn and obsolete. They are always vital and timely. I have seen men grow wealthy
and influential in worldly things and at the same time grow exceedingly poor in spiritual
things. I do not discount material achievements, but deplore the acquisition of such power and
influence at a loss of the higher goal in life.
</p><p>
In 1846, Brigham Young stood on the fringe of the great western desert. He looked to the
eastward and saw the cities abandoned by the Saints. He jotted down in his diary a statement
something like this:
</p><p>
Our homes, our orchards, our farms, our schools, our churches, our temples, and our public
buildings, we leave as a monument to our patriotism, our toil, our devotion, our industry, our
integrity, and our honesty of purpose.
</p><p>
And he might have added, "our faith."
</p><p>
With Brigham Young first things came first. He knew there were things, even more important
than lands and homes and worldly comforts, things like freedom, the right to worship, the
right to grow and develop under the inspiration and guidance of Christian ideals. What better
testimony could he give of their integrity and their faith? Here was the workmanship of their
own hands. Here were the fruits of their labors, the results of their strivings and sacrifice and
struggle. All of it they placed on the altar rather than compromise, and rather than forsake
their standards and the guiding principles which sustained them.
</p><p>
I read an article recently, written by George E. Sokolsky and appearing in The Deseret News.
He discusses the Bible as a guide to human progress. Said he:
</p><p>
I am sure that one of our major difficulties, and when I say "our," I mean the whole of
mankind, is that we have lost guidance, moving rapidly without compass, for the man without
guidance lives in a vacuum, nothing has come before and he can find no road to the future. I
turn to the wisdom of the ages, and find there a transcendent comfort, for those who would
destroy are a multitude, but the builder is often and wearily alone.
</p><p>
The wisdom of the ages to which he refers is the holy Bible. History has proved that
humanity needs guidance and enlightenment. Without guidance man is a law unto himself. He
falters and fails. There are signposts everywhere, but men, in their eagerness to pursue their
own course, pass them by. God knows His children. He has made provision for their safety
and their security. Christ's gospel is the beacon light to guide humanity. It points the way of
salvation. It has come to earth in its fulness to lead the children of men back to God. The true
end and felicity of man lies in the enjoyment of God's favor, and His saving power.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith brought to light a great revelation given to Abraham of old. "We will prove
them herewith," said God to Abraham, "to see if they will do all things whatsoever the Lord
their God shall command them; and they who keep their first estate shall be added upon; ...
and they who keep their second estate shall have glory added upon their heads forever and
forever" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/25-26#25">Abr. 3:25-26</a>).
</p><p>
Divine guidance for a wise and holy purpose is thus assured to Abraham and his children to
the latest generation. One of the most powerful sermons ever delivered by man was preached
by Peter to the Jews on the day of Pentecost. It was persuasive and convincing and touched
deeply the hearts of the listeners. They were pricked in their hearts and said unto Peter and to
the rest of the apostles, "Men and brethren, what shall we do?"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37#37">Acts 2:37</a>). It was a cry of despair and
remorse, an appeal for enlightenment. Said Peter:
</p><p>
. . . Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus Christ for the remission of
sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38-39#38">Acts 2:38-39</a>).
</p><p>
May we heed the counsel and the guidance which we receive as members of Christ's Church,
I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
