<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Prophet of God</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1948, pp. 24-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is an awe-inspiring sight to stand here this morning on this beautiful Sabbath day and face
this vast audience. I humbly pray that the Spirit of God will attend me and direct what I shall
say. During the few moments that I occupy, it is my desire to give an interpretation of a
prophet of God, with special emphasis upon the Prophet Joseph Smith. I am always thrilled to
hear that beautiful song, "We Thank Thee, O God, for a Prophet," that was sung a few
moments ago, because I know that we have today prophets standing at the head of the Church
of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
DEFINITION OF A PROPHET
</p><p>
If I were to ask you the question, "What is a prophet of God?" it is probable that your
immediate reply would be: "A prophet of God is an individual who through divine inspiration
or revelation predicts future events." You may even quote the Apostle Peter, wherein he said:
</p><p>
For the prophecy came not in old times by the will of man: but holy men of
God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21#21">2 Pet. 1:21</a>).
</p><p>
How does Joseph Smith compare with the great prophets of all ages as a predictor of future
events? When we consider the fact that the D&amp;C is filled with revelations from the Lord to
the Prophet and that many of them deal with future events which certainly could be regarded
as prophecies; also, when we consider the fact that other scriptures were brought forth in this
dispensation through Joseph and that they contain many prophecies; and in addition to this,
that he uttered numerous other predictions, we are forced to conclude that few, if any,
prophets who ever lived have made more prophecies than did Joseph Smith. I, therefore,
would rate him among the greatest of all the prophets as a predictor of future events.
</p><p>
We should also keep in mind the fact that the prophecies of true prophets of God, uttered as a
result of divine inspiration, or revelation, must and will all be fulfilled. In fact, in the holy
scriptures we are told that the way to distinguish between true and false prophets is whether
or not their predictions come to pass. To quote the words of Deuteronomy:
</p><p>
And if thou say in thine heart, How shall we know the word which the Lord
hath not spoken?
</p><p>
When a prophet speaketh in the name of the Lord, if the thing follow not, nor
come to pass, that is the thing which the Lord hath not spoken, but the prophet
hath spoken it presumptuously; thou shalt not be afraid of him
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/18/21-22#21">Deut. 18:21-22</a>).
</p><p>
JOSEPH SMITH A TRUE PROPHET
</p><p>
According to the word of the Lord, Joseph Smith was a true prophet because the prophecies
and promises revealed to him "shall all be fulfilled." In this respect he compares very
favorably with any or all of the holy prophets of old. God declared in his preface to the D&amp;C
the following:
</p><p>
Search these commandments for they are true and faithful, and the
prophecies and promises which are in them shall all be fulfilled
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/37#37">D&amp;C 1:37</a>).
</p><p>
Let us consider a few examples of prophecies made by Joseph Smith and their fulfilment.
When but a boy slightly past fourteen years of age, Joseph returned to the house from .the
Sacred Grove on that memorable spring morning in 1820. He told the members of his family
that he had seen the Eternal Father and his Only Begotten Son in a vision
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-20#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-20</a>). During the course
of that vision, he had been informed by the Savior that the true Church was not upon the
earth (<i>DHC</i> 1:2-6) and that if he lived a worthy life he was given:
</p><p>
. . . a promise that the fullness of the gospel should at some future time be
made known unto [him] me. ("The Wentworth Letter," cited in <i>DHC</i> 4:536.)
</p><p>
Imagine a boy, untrained and unschooled as far as earthly schooling is concerned and at such
a tender age, making such a prophecy. As all of you know, this prophecy was soon fulfilled.
The gospel of Jesus Christ was revealed to him, and he did establish a Church&mdash;the Church
which God declared to be:
</p><p>
. . . the only true and living church upon the face of the whole earth, with which
I, the Lord, am well pleased, speaking unto the church collectively and not
individually (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30#30">D&amp;C 1:30</a>).
</p><p>
NAME KNOWN FOR GOOD AND EVIL
</p><p>
Three and one-half years later, at the time of the visitations of the angel Moroni to Joseph
Smith, he made another prophecy which I believe was just as astounding in its nature as was
the prediction that he should establish the "true and living Church." Joseph said that the
heavenly messenger had told him that he would receive an ancient record, and that he would
translate it and publish a book. Also, to quote Joseph's own words:
</p><p>
. . . <i>that my name should be had for good and evil among all nations, kindreds,</i>
<i>and tongues, or that it should be both good and evil spoken among all people</i>
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/33#33">JS&mdash;H 1:33</a>;
<i>DHC</i> 1:11-12; italics speaker's).
</p><p>
Imagine an obscure frontier youth who had probably no more than a casual acquaintance with
perhaps a few hundred people at the most, not only prophesying that he would translate and
publish a book but that his name would be had for good and evil among all nations. Again,
time has proved Joseph Smith to be a true prophet of God. He did publish that book under the
title of the Book of Mormon; and, as all of you know, it has for more than a century baffled
thousands of its avowed enemies.
</p><p>
Almost immediately after receiving his earliest visitation from heavenly beings, the Prophet
Joseph Smith began to be persecuted for the claims that he had made. Throughout the entire
course of his life many people hated him to the point of trying to bring about his death. This
fact they finally accomplished by bringing him to a martyr's grave. As early as 1834 the first
of almost an innumerable procession of books, written by evil people inspired by the devil for
the purpose of destroying the Prophet, his influence and the work of the Lord, came from the
press. Each of these books has been short-lived; but the work of God and the honor and glory
of his great Prophet will go on unhampered forever.
</p><p>
On the other hand, throughout Joseph's lifetime many other people loved him so dearly that
they would have laid down their lives willingly for him if necessary. They maintained that the
Holy Ghost had borne positive assurance to their souls of Joseph's divine appointment and of
the restoration of the true gospel of Jesus Christ. Thus thousands of intelligent converts have
allied themselves with the Prophet Joseph and have adhered to the cause of Mormonism in the
face of persecution, poverty, loss of homes and property, and even threats of martyrdom. In
fact, many of the Saints have sacrificed their lives for the cause of righteousness.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith's testimony has divided the world into two camps. Whenever he is being
considered, there is no neutral ground upon which to stand. His claims are so vital that people
either accept them in their entirety without reservations or flatly reject them. There are
individuals, however, who are completely indifferent to his claims, and ofttimes to religion in
general. Those individuals must be classed with the group that reject Joseph's claims.
</p><p>
Thus throughout the entire course of more than one hundred years, this prediction uttered by
the Prophet Joseph Smith, that is, that his name should be known
"<i>for good and evil among all nations, kindreds, and tongues</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/33#33">JS&mdash;H 1:33</a>), has been continuously fulfilled.
</p><p>
REVELATION GIVEN IN MISSOURI JAIL
</p><p>
In the spring of 1839, after the Prophet had spent several months lying in a dungeon in a
Missouri jail, the voice of God came unto him saying:
</p><p>
My son, peace be unto thy soul; thine adversity and thine afflictions shall be
but a small moment;
</p><p>
And then, if thou endure it well, God shall exalt thee on high; thou shalt
triumph over all thy foes.
</p><p>
And they who do charge thee with transgression, their hope shall be blasted, and
their prospects shall melt away as the hoar frost melteth before the burning rays
of the rising sun;
</p><p>
Cursed are all those that shall lift up the heel against mine anointed, saith
the Lord. . . (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/7-8,11,16#7">D&amp;C 121:7-8,11,16</a>).
</p><p>
The ends of the earth shall inquire after thy name, and fools shall have thee
in derision, and hell shall rage against thee;
</p><p>
While the pure in heart, and the wise, and the noble, and the virtuous, shall
seek counsel, and blessings constantly from under thy hand.
</p><p>
And thy people shall never be turned against thee by the testimony of
traitors.
</p><p>
. . . Thy days are known, and thy years shall not be numbered less; therefore, fear
not what men can do, for God shall be with you forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/122/1-3,9#1">D&amp;C 122:1-3,9</a>).
</p><p>
PREDICTIONS FULFILLED
</p><p>
Such predictions as the Civil War prophecy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/87/1-8#1">D&amp;C 87:1-8</a>),
the Stephen A. Douglas prophecy, the Rocky
Mountain prophecy referred to by the President of the Church this morning, and numerous
other predictions and their fulfilment could be cited to show that Joseph Smith was truly a
great prophet of God. Evidence impels us to rank this man of God as one of the greatest
prophets that have ever lived. In fact, in the D&amp;C we read:
</p><p>
Joseph Smith, the Prophet and Seer of the Lord, has done more, save Jesus only,
for the salvation of men in this world, than any other man that ever lived in it
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3#3">D&amp;C 135:3</a>).
</p><p>
THE CALLING OF PROPHETS
</p><p>
Another distinctive characteristic of a prophet of God is that he is chosen, appointed, and
called by the Lord. He draws his knowledge from the divine fountain of truth; therefore, he
speaks in the name of the Lord and as one having authority
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/29#29">Matt. 7:29</a>). Let us give a few examples. The
Prophet Amos, in his masterful discourse at Bethel, prefaced each of his predictions by "Thus
saith the Lord" 
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/1/3,6,9,11,13#3">Amos 1:3,6,9,11,13</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/2/1,4,6#1">Amos 2:1,4,6</a>).
Isaiah relates his call to be a prophet as follows:
</p><p>
. . . I saw also the Lord sitting upon a throne, high and lifted up, and his
train filled the temple.
</p><p>
Also I heard the voice of the Lord, saying, Whom shall I send, and who
will go for us? Then said I, Here I am; send me.
</p><p>
And he said, Go, and tell this people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/6/1,8-9#1">Isa. 6:1,8-9</a>).
</p><p>
The call of Jeremiah to be a prophet illustrates beautifully the fact that prophets are chosen,
appointed, and called by the Lord. To use Jeremiah's own words:
</p><p>
Then the word of the Lord came unto me, saying,
</p><p>
Before I formed thee in the belly I knew thee; and before thou camest forth
out of the womb I sanctified thee, and I ordained thee a prophet unto the nations.
</p><p>
Then said I, Ah, Lord God! behold, I cannot speak for I am a child. But the Lord
said unto me, Say not, I am a child; for thou shalt go to all that I shall send thee,
and whatsoever I command thee thou shalt speak.
</p><p>
Then the Lord put forth his hand, and touched my mouth. And the Lord
said unto me, Behold, I have put my words in thy mouth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/1/4-7,9#4">Jer. 1:4-7,9</a>).
</p><p>
In the book of Moses we read about Enoch's call to be a prophet as follows:
</p><p>
And it came to pass that Enoch journeyed in the land, among the people;
and as he journeyed . . .
</p><p>
. . . he heard a voice from heaven, saying: Enoch, my son, prophesy unto
this people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/26-27#26">Moses 6:26-27</a>).
</p><p>
In addition to being called of the Lord, true prophets teach the people what the Lord
commands them Jesus Christ, the greatest of all the prophets, declared:
</p><p>
For I have not spoken of myself; but the Father which sent me, he gave me
a commandment, what I should say, and what I should speak.
</p><p>
And I know that his commandment is life everlasting: whatsoever I speak
therefore, even as the Father said unto me, so I speak
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/12/49-50#49">John 12:49-50</a>).
</p><p>
Throughout history many of the great prophets have been visited by holy angels and some of
them have seen God and have conversed with him as one man converses with another. For
example, we read in the Pearl of Great Price:
</p><p>
And I, the Lord God, said unto Adam, (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/17#17">Moses 4:17</a>)
</p><p>
Again we read:
</p><p>
And I, the Lord God, spake unto Moses,
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1#1">Moses 4:1</a>)
</p><p>
And he saw God face to face, and he talked with him, and the glory of God
was upon Moses; therefore Moses could endure his presence
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/2#2">Moses 1:2</a>).
</p><p>
Abraham wrote:
</p><p>
Thus I, Abraham, talked with the Lord, face to face, as one man talketh
with another (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/11#11">Abr. 3:11</a>).
</p><p>
Referring to the Prophet Alma, Amulek said:
</p><p>
As I was journeying to see a very near kindred, behold an angel of the Lord
appeared unto me and said: Amulek, return to thine own house, for thou shalt feed
a prophet of the Lord; yea, a holy man, who is chosen man of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/10/7#7">Alma 10:7</a>).
</p><p>
"THUS SAITH THE LORD"
</p><p>
After the death of the Savior and his apostles, the heavens were closed, and for many
centuries God ceased to appoint holy prophets among men. Finally, as I have already stated, a
living oracle was sent to earth again in the person of the Prophet Joseph Smith. The Eternal
Father, his Only Begotten Son, and numerous holy angels talked with Joseph face to face,
even as they had done with the prophets of old. Thus the word, the will, and the
commandments of God came from heaven to mortals again in exactly the same manner as
they had come in past ages. At the beginning of the majority of the revelations received by
the Prophet Joseph, such statements as the following appear:
</p><p>
Hearken unto the voice of the Lord your God, while I speak unto you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/25/1#1">D&amp;C 25:1</a>).
</p><p>
And again:
</p><p>
Listen to the voice of Jesus Christ, your Lord, your God and your
Redeemer (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/1#1">D&amp;C 27:1</a>;
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/1#1">D&amp;C 29:1</a>).
</p><p>
Also:
</p><p>
Thus saith the Lord God, the Mighty One of Israel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/36/1#1">D&amp;C 36:1</a>).
</p><p>
As an example of the numerous visions of heavenly beings that Joseph beheld, I quote the
following:
</p><p>
And we beheld the glory of the Son, on the right hand of the Father, and
received of his fulness; And saw the holy angels, and them who are sanctified
before his throne, worshiping God, and the Lamb, who worship him forever and
ever (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/20-21#20">D&amp;C 76:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith, like all the holy prophets, who preceded him, always prefaced his
teachings with the divine dictum of "Thus saith the Lord." Truly of him it can be said as it
was said of the Man of Galilee, ". . . Never man spake like this man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/46#46">John 7:46</a>). Since
Joseph Smith received what he gave to the people directly from Jesus Christ, such should be
the case.
</p><p>
The Lord declared in modern revelation that the words spoken by prophets when they were
moved upon by the Holy Ghost should be considered as scripture. To quote:
</p><p>
And whatsoever they shall speak when moved upon by the Holy Ghost shall be scripture,
shall be the will of the Lord, shall be the mind of the Lord, shall be the word of the Lord,
shall be the voice of the Lord, and the power of God unto salvation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/4#4">D&amp;C 68:4</a>).
</p><p>
LIVING ORACLES
</p><p>
I wish to emphasize the fact that this revelation is not limited to Joseph Smith and the other
great prophets who preceded him. We have standing at the head of the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints today living oracles through whom God reveals his will. Certainly the
words of this revelation apply to President George Albert Smith, to his Counselors, to the
Twelve Apostles, and to me Patriarch to the Church just as much as they did to Joseph Smith,
or to Isaiah, Jeremiah, Moses, Nephi, Alma, Peter, Paul, or to all of the other ancient prophets
of God.
</p><p>
A TEACHER OF DIVINE TRUTHS
</p><p>
The greatest job that a prophet has to accomplish is to be teacher of the divine truths revealed
to him from on high. He is to God's mouthpiece here on earth&mdash;God's spokesman, the
revelator of the plan of salvation. Through the keys and power of the priesthood which he
holds, the kingdom of God is established upon earth and all the ordinances requisite for the
salvation and exaltation of the human family are performed. It is in their capacity of teacher
and dispenser of the mind and will of God that the holy prophets in all ages have made their
greatest contributions. During his three short years of missionary service, Jesus Christ did
more to affect the destiny of the human family than have all the kings that ever sat upon the
thrones or all the armies that ever marched. Moses' great contribution was in giving Israel the
law. Nephi, Paul, Alma, and the other prophets perpetuated the true Church in their times.
And Joseph Smith was the prophet of God who was called and foreordained to usher in the
last dispensation of the gospel, the greatest of the dispensations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/1-25#1">2 Ne. 3:1-25</a>).
</p><p>
When we consider the three volumes of scripture given to the world through the Prophet
Joseph Smith, and when we consider that all the knowledge, powers, keys, doctrines, and
ordinances that had ever been given to the prophets from the time of Adam to the present day
were restored to him, then we can fully realize that Joseph certainly was one of the greatest
prophets that ever lived. I make the claim that he was the greatest of the prophets except
Jesus Christ (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3#3">D&amp;C 135:3</a>).
</p><p>
LOVE OF FELLOWMEN
</p><p>
Finally, a prophet of God loves his fellow men intensely, even to the point of giving his life
willingly for them if necessary. Before the death of the Savior, he had full knowledge that the
Jews had rejected him, and that they would bring about his crucifixion. Yet, as he sat upon a
hill overlooking Jerusalem a few days prior to his death, he prophesied to his apostles
regarding the destruction of the holy city and the scattering of his people because they had
rejected their Lord and Savior. So intense was his love for those who had become his enemies
that "Jesus wept" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/35#35">John 11:35</a>).
He had taught the people:
</p><p>
. . . Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you,
and pray for them which despitefully use you, and persecute you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
</p><p>
While hanging on the cross he put those teachings into effect. He looked down upon the
jeering mob standing at the foot of the cross and then, casting his eyes toward heaven, prayed:
</p><p>
. . . Father, forgive them, for they know not what they do
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/34#34">Luke 23:34</a>).
</p><p>
So it was with the Prophet Joseph Smith. When he, Hyrum and others were making plans to
flee to the Rocky Mountains for safety, Emma sent word for Joseph to return because the
Saints were accusing him of being a coward. Knowing full well that they would be killed if
they should return, he turned to his brother Hyrum and said: "If my life is of no value to my
friends it is of none to myself," (<i>DHC</i> 6:549) and so they returned to Nauvoo. It was his
deep love for the Saints that impelled him to return and voluntarily to give his life as a
sacrifice for them. The following day while on their way from Nauvoo to Carthage, Joseph
made this memorable statement:
</p><p>
<i>I am going like a lamb to the slaughter, but I am as calm as a summer's morning.</i>
<i>I have a conscience void of offense toward God and toward all men. If they take</i>
<i>my life I shall die an innocent man, and my blood shall cry from the ground for</i>
<i>vengeance, and it shall be said of me, "He was murdered in cold blood!</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4#4">D&amp;C 135:4</a>; <i>DHC</i>,
6:555).
</p><p>
TESTIMONY SEALED WITH BLOOD
</p><p>
Three days later the assassins' bullets found lodgment in the body of the Prophet of God. As
he fell from the windows of Carthage jail, he died with the words on his lips, "O Lord, my
God!"
</p><p>
He began his career as a prophet with the glorious vision of the Father and the Son and ended
his earthly career with the name of Deity on his lips. As did the Savior of the world, he
sealed his testimony with his blood. Regarding Joseph's death, God revealed to Brigham
Young the following:
</p><p>
Many have marveled because of his death; but it was needful that he
should seal his testimony with his blood, that he might be honored and the wicked 
might be condemned (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/39#39">D&amp;C 136:39</a>).
</p><p>
And like all of the great and holy prophets of old, the Prophet Joseph, being dead, yet lives
on forever. Today a million people sing:
</p><p>
Hail to the Prophet, ascended to heaven!<br />
Traitors and tyrants now fight him in vain;<br />
Mingling with Gods, he can plan for his brethren;<br />
Death cannot conquer the hero again.
</p><p>
From the bottom of my heart I want to bear my testimony that I know that Joseph Smith was
one of the greatest prophets that ever lived upon this earth. May the Spirit of God be with
you and me that we might live according to the teachings that he gave us, I humbly pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
