<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Principles of Cooperation</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 159-164</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I have felt confident that this time would come. This is a sobering experience, my brothers
and sisters. Our great benefactor and leader said at one time regarding this great
responsibility: "You cannot hide the heart when the mouth is open. If you want to keep your
heart secret, keep your mouth shut." But he also added that when it becomes our duty to talk,
we ought to be willing to talk.
</p><p>
QUESTIONS BEING ASKED
</p><p>
I desire to repeat one sentence from the revelation which Brother Romney indicated has
already been quoted two or three times in this conference:
</p><p>
And it is my purpose to provide for my saints, for all things are mine
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/15#15">D&amp;C 104:15</a>).
</p><p>
During recent weeks it has been my pleasure to visit with many young men and some older
men, during which time they have asked several questions regarding some of the temporal
matters pertaining to the Latter-day Saints. They have asked questions regarding the Church's
interest in agriculture and farming. They have commented that they do not hear as much now
about these things as was once spoken in the Church. Some of them have suggested that they
would like to know whether or not the Church looks with favor on young men going abroad
to various parts of the country to establish themselves in farming and in business, or whether
they should remain close to Church headquarters. Others have asked regarding cooperative
business enterprises, and other cooperative activities.
</p><p>
I realize, my brethren and sisters, that in discussing temporal matters, the Lord has said:
</p><p>
. . . all things unto me are spiritual, and not at any time have I given unto you a law which
was temporal (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/34#34">D&amp;C 29:34</a>).
</p><p>
MAN'S PLACE IMPORTANT IN THE WORLD
</p><p>
The objective, of course, is spiritual. We live, however, in a material, physical, temporal
world. Man is the center in Mormon philosophy.
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of
man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
The earth upon which we live was established for man. The Church is for man, not man for
the Church.
</p><p>
We are blind until we see that in the human plan <br />
Nothing is worth the making if it does not make the man. <br />
Why build these cities glorious if man unbuilded go;<br />
In vain we build the world unless the builder also grow.
</p><p>
But to us man is a dual being, temporal and spiritual, and in the early revelations to this
people, the Lord took occasion, many times, to give direction and commandment regarding
temporal matters. He directed the Saints and the leaders of the Church in the purchase of land
and other property; in the construction of temples; even in the establishment of a printing
press, and a store, and in the building of a boardinghouse for the "weary traveler"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/23#23">D&amp;C 124:23</a>). In the
great revelation known as the Word of Wisdom, he not only indicated what is good and what
is not good for man, but he outlined a plan for the feeding of livestock
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/14#14">D&amp;C 89:14</a>), which, through more
than a hundred years, has gradually been sustained through the scientific investigation of man.
Whatever affects human welfare has always been and ever will be the concern of the Church.
Our people have always been counseled in temporal affairs.
</p><p>
COOPERATION IMPORTANT IN TEMPORAL MATTERS
</p><p>
I read again recently some of the early discourses of President Brigham Young and other
Church leaders as the Saints came into these valleys. The people were truly counseled in
temporal affairs. Various types of projects were inaugurated under their direction. They were
taught to conserve ranges and forests and to conserve water. They were taught also to
conserve food and feed and other materials. They were encouraged in the production of more
profitable crops and in more efficient methods of production. They were taught to work
together, to cooperate, to sustain each other. Listen to the words of President Young:
</p><p>
Any people who will cooperate on correct principles will increase in material wealth and
prosperity. . . If the people called Latter-day Saints do not become one in temporal things, as
they are in spiritual things, they will not redeem and build up the Zion of God upon the earth.
This cooperative movement is a stepping stone. We say to the people, take advantage of it, it
is your privilege (<i>Journal of Discourses</i> 13:3).
</p><p>
Later he gave cooperative support to private enterprise and encouraged men to enter private
business. Should not the counsel given by President Brigham Young in the early days of the
settlement of these valleys be heeded today? The principles of cooperation and working
together were used to develop the resources of these valleys and permit people to survive. We
need to adopt these same principles, which have been tried and tested by the experience of the
last hundred years, to preserve and conserve these resources and to raise our economic
standards. I do not mean by this that our people should go out and in every priesthood
quorum and in every ward organize cooperative business organizations. A warning has been
given, and wisely so, that cooperative enterprises, business cooperatives, require efficient
business management and direction. At the same time it is recognized that there is a place for
cooperative endeavor, among our agricultural and rural groups particularly, as there is also an
opportunity and a place for private enterprise.
</p><p>
ZION EMBRACES ALL OF AMERICA
</p><p>
We live in an area, my brothers and sisters, where we face rather peculiar problems, and to
some extent, some limitations. Water is our most limited factor in the agriculture of the area
in which the Latter-day Saints are concentrated. The topography of our country presents other
serious problems. We have, in many areas where the Latter-day Saints live, a very serious
pressure of population on the land. There is a tendency for our farms and farming units to be
divided and redivided until many times they have become somewhat uneconomic because of
their limited size. Because of this pressure there has been a tendency for many of our young
people to go out into other areas where land seems to be more abundant and probably where
the opportunities are greater. This is not a thing to be discouraged if they act wisely. All of
America is the land of Zion.
</p><p>
I was pleased in visiting the Northwestern States Mission recently to find that many of our
young people have gone into that fertile area, have established themselves in agriculture and
in business, and are sinking their roots deep, becoming a part of the community life and a
support to the branches of which they are loyal members. To me this is a condition that will
likely increase as the years pass. As the Church grows and increases in numbers, no one state
or area will be able to contain the Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
ADVICE IN MATTER OF DEBT
</p><p>
There are some things, my brethren and sisters, those who live in the rural communities
particularly, that I would like to call to your attention which I think might be helpful in aiding
us to improve the efficiency of our operations. One of them was referred to by Brother
Clifford Young in his excellent address yesterday: the matter of debt. We face at the present
time a great adjustment period. If history repeats itself, we may expect a declining price level
in the case of agricultural products particularly. That will mean that more bushels of wheat,
more tons of sugar beets and more farm products generally will be required to pay off a given
amount of debt. It is well for Latter-day Saints to make a special effort during this period
when prices are relatively high, to reduce our debts to the very minimum in order that we
might be prepared to meet the adjustment period as it comes without losing our farms and
without making undue sacrifices.
</p><p>
WAYS OF MORE EFFECTIVE FARMING
</p><p>
There are many things that we could do to enlarge our farming units, not only by the
acquisition of land, but by the more effective use of irrigation water, much of which is wasted
through seepage and excessive irrigation. More acres on given farms can often be brought
under irrigation through a wiser and more efficient use of water. We can add intensive units
to our farming program without enlarging the area with such units as poultry, livestock
feeding, production of truck crops, seed production, new crops, and other things. On many of
our farms I believe we could reduce waste areas, corners, fence lines, ditch banks, and yard
space.
</p><p>
There is a need to increase forage production to supplement our ranges, which, in many areas,
are becoming seriously depleted. We need to use the information which has been developed
by the United States Forest Service, by our agricultural colleges, and tested by leading
ranchers, to plant improved grasses on our ranges, and thereby increase the number of
livestock that can be carried. Many of our communities are built largely on a livestock
economy.
</p><p>
Ofttimes the rearrangement of fields and the enlargement of fields, permits the more efficient
use of power and heavy, horse-drawn farm machinery, which is a common need on many
farms. The use of better breeding stock and better feed and seed will all tend towards a more
efficient type of agriculture, a more profitable farming enterprise, and a more satisfactory
community life.
</p><p>
We need to work together more than we do. In the joint ownership of heavy equipment such
as combines, balers, tractors, drills, and in the cooperative ownership of breeding sires, and in
many other ways, we can join together as farmers in our communities in order to make our
farming operations more efficient and more effective.
</p><p>
In many areas our system of marketing and distributing our farm products and purchasing
farm production supplies needs to be improved. Farmers need to improve their bargaining
power. There is a tendency among many of our people, and not confined alone to our people,
to sell their products in rather large quantities at wholesale, and to buy back in small dabs,
here and there, their needed supplies at retail prices. As one of our distinguished financiers,
Bernard M. Baruch, has said:
</p><p>
The farmer selling in unlimited competition with himself, has been buying at more or less
controlled prices from industries which have organized their production and marketing.
</p><p>
We need to improve the distribution of our farm products. That does not mean that in every
area we need to organize cooperative associations. There are limitations on these
organizations. The need should be determined. Possibly the work is being done efficiently
through private channels. We should determine whether or not there is a need for
improvement in the marketing and distribution of our products in a given area.
</p><p>
The farm is largely a manufacturing plant where land, labor, fertilizer, supplies, seed, and
feed are combined to produce a product for market. It is no easy matter to become an
efficient farm operator today.
</p><p>
It is important that we keep our thinking straight, my brothers and sisters. Let us ever keep in
mind that all material things are but a means to an end, that the end is spiritual, although the
Lord is anxious and willing to bless his people temporally. He has so indicated in many of the
revelations. He has pointed out, time and time again, that we should pray over our crops, over
our livestock, over our households, our homes, and invoke the Lord's blessings upon our
material affairs. And he has promised that he will be there and ready and willing to bless us.
</p><p>
THE SOUNDNESS OF PRINCIPLES OF SELF-HELP
</p><p>
Let us stand together on our own feet. Let us cooperate to accomplish these so-called material
objectives. A sound agriculture is vital to the national economy. I like the words of that great
Irish pioneer in cooperative effort, Horace Plunket, who labored for many years among the
poor, down-ridden farmers of Ireland, when he said:
</p><p>
For the longer I live, the more certain do I become that what the best of governments can do
for farmers is of insignificant importance compared with what, by carefully thought out and
loyal cooperation, they can do for themselves.
</p><p>
Let us as Latter-day Saints stand on our own feet. Let us not be inclined to run to a
paternalistic government for help when every problem arises, but to attack our problems
jointly, and through effective cooperative effort, solve our problems at home.
</p><p>
To me one of the greatest bulwarks we have in this country against all the foreign isms,
"crackpot" theories, and the unsound social reforms is the people who live on the land, close
to the soil. Dr. Widtsoe emphasized a year ago at our conference the important part which the
rural people of America play in the safety and security of this great land. Certainly no group
of people in all the world know so well that, "As ye sow, so shall ye reap"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gal/6/7#7">Gal. 6:7</a>). And as
Brother Widtsoe said in that excellent address, which I commend to you, "A strong rural
membership brings safety to the Church, not otherwise obtainable. It is so in the nation."
</p><p>
The principles of self-help are economically, socially, and spiritually sound. The Lord will not
do for us what we can and should do for ourselves. But it is his purpose to take care of his
Saints. Everything that concerns the economic, social, and spiritual welfare of the human
family is and ever will be the concern of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us with inspiration to guide us in all of our material affairs that we might
be successful. And may we ever keep in mind the great objective of life and the purposes of
God in establishing us here in the earth, namely, to bring to pass our immortality and eternal
life in the celestial kingdom, I pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
