<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Share the Gospel</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Franklin D. Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Franklin D. Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 83-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren, I pray that the beautiful prayer that was offered by President Lewis may be
answered in my behalf. I am aware of the responsibility that rests upon me, and I appreciate
the opportunity of speaking to you tonight.
</p><p>
I rejoice in the wonderful messages that we have heard from President McKay and others who
have spoken to us during this conference, and I am inspired by the great vision of our leaders.
I am grateful for the knowledge that I have of the restored gospel and for the knowledge that
I have of my Father in heaven and his Son Jesus Christ. The Prophet Joseph Smith is a great
inspiration to me, and I thrill in testifying that God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ did
actually appear to him in the Sacred Grove
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-19#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-19</a>).
</p><p>
I thrill throughout my body, mind, and spirit when I testify to the truthfulness of that great
vision&mdash;the first vision of the Prophet Joseph, and I appreciate the wonderful things that the
Prophet did in restoring the Church&mdash;he was an instrument in the hands of the Lord in
restoring the gospel and the priesthood to the earth in this dispensation. I, like you, love and
respect our great prophet and leader, President David O. McKay, and I know and testify that
he is indeed the prophet of the Lord and the head of the Church of Jesus Christ on this earth
today.
</p><p>
Now, brethren, truly the kingdom of God is going forward that the kingdom of heaven may
come. President McKay has counseled us that every member of this Church should be a
missionary. Tonight my heart is really filled with the missionary spirit.
Heretofore the missionary work has been performed chiefly by full-time missionaries and
stake and district missionaries. Now as President McKay has told us, each and every one of us
has the opportunity of being a missionary. What a glorious opportunity this really gives us
when we appreciate what we can do as members of this Church in spreading the gospel.
</p><p>
Another great prophet, President George Albert Smith, said on the anniversary of the first
hundred years of the Church: "As we stand on the threshold of a new century, as
representatives of the Church of Jesus Christ in all walks of life, we have the responsibility to
go among the people at home and abroad, and great will be our happiness as we participate in
this new era of growth and development that lies ahead."
</p><p>
Yes, brethren, we are truly in a new era of growth and development, and personally I am
grateful and thankful to be a part of it. Realizing this new era, the leaders of the Church are
doubling the number of full-time missionaries, and more stake and district missionaries are
being called today than ever before. Formerly, the missionaries spent a large part of their time
in finding someone to teach, but now with every member of the Church being a missionary,
by using the "share the gospel" program, the members, in effect, find the people to teach, and
the missionaries now can spend a very large part of their time in teaching, mainly in groups.
</p><p>
This group teaching we have found to be very effective, both in saving time in teaching and
in the psychology that results from teaching in groups. But, you may say, how can I be a
missionary and participate in the "share the gospel" program? Well, there are several ways.
</p><p>
First, you can invite your nonmember friends, relatives, neighbors, business associates, or
others that you might casually contact, into your homes, preferably in groups, and then let the
full-time, the stake, or the district missionaries teach them the gospel.
</p><p>
Second, you can do missionary work by using the referral system. By the referral system we
mean sending the names of those friends or relatives who live outside of the area that you are
living in, who you think would be interested in the Church, to the stake or mission president
in the area in which the people live.
</p><p>
This morning we heard of the referral that resulted in the conversion and baptism of President
John Taylor. Many wonderful people are being brought into the Church now through this
referral system.
</p><p>
Third, invite your nonmember friends to attend auxiliary meetings and other Church meetings
with you. Fourth live your religion, love your neighbor. "Let your light so shine before men,
that they may see your good works, and glorify your Father which is in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>).
</p><p>
Elder Harold B. Lee, in touring the Northwestern States Mission last summer, said, "This
means let your light so shine that men shall be led to join the Church, or the kingdom of
God."
</p><p>
But I can hear many of you say, "I know my friends and relatives wouldn't be interested. I
have tried for years to talk to members of my family about religion, and it seems to irritate
them," and other such things. But I ask you, do you really know that your friends would not
be interested? Have you asked them? I suggest that you do ask them.
</p><p>
The people of the Northwestern States Mission, where I presided as president during the year
1960, as well as in many other places, have found thousands of people who are interested,
who they thought were not interested, and this by merely asking two important questions,
which you can do. First, "What do you know about the Mormon Church?" And regardless of
their answer, "Would you like to know more?"
</p><p>
We found that approximately two out of every three that are asked these questions say, "No, I
am not interested." In that event, just pass them off, possibly with a casual, "Well, maybe
some day you will be." But don't irritate them or press the situation. There are thousands and
thousands that are waiting and wanting to hear this message, and they have a right to hear it.
</p><p>
The one out of three who says, "Yes, I would like to know more," is the one to invite into
your home for a group meeting with the missionaries. Or if that is not possible, give that
name to the missionaries. I personally regularly ask these two questions: "What do you know
about the Mormon Church?" and then, regardless of the answer, "Would you like to know
more?"
</p><p>
By doing this almost daily I find many, many fine people who say, "Yes, I would like to
know more," and I have never been embarrassed yet in asking that question. I have turned
many, many fine referrals over to our missionaries. In fact, there is hardly a day goes by that
I do not get a referral by asking these questions.
</p><p>
In asking groups of members all over the country to ask these questions, many times I have
sensed a feeling of skepticism, but almost always afterwards someone has written me or sent
word to me saying that although he was doubtful at first, he tried asking the questions, and
was happily surprised to find many saying, "Yes, I would like to know more."
</p><p>
The opportunity will present itself to you as you go about from day to day if you are thinking
about it. So I suggest, do think about it, and try it. Let's assume that a hundred members in a
ward or branch asked these two questions only once every other day. They would ask on an
average of three hundred a week, and experience has shown that approximately one out of
every three will answer that he would like to know more. On this basis the missionaries
would have about one hundred new people to teach each week in that ward or branch,
probably many more than all of the full-time and part-time missionaries could possibly
handle.
</p><p>
Keep in mind also that the young people as well as the old ask these questions, and the
younger ones do not seem to hesitate like some of us older ones. I have some remarkable
instances that I wish I had time to tell you about. Sometime maybe I can.
</p><p>
Speaking of referrals, I would like to read from a letter that I received just about two or three
days ago from a person who apparently thought I was still president of the Northwestern
States Mission. I have sent the letter on to President Don C. Wood. She said: "Dear President
Richards: Ever since I joined the Church three and a half years ago I have wished all my
friends and relatives had the same opportunity to investigate the gospel, and I have decided
it's time that I asked to have missionaries sent to my relatives. Most of them seem interested
and curious about our Church since my brother and I joined it, so I am hoping and praying
that they will recognize the truth when they hear it. It certainly leads to the happiest way of
life, and I know I could have avoided pitfalls if I had only found it sooner. It's wonderful to
have the true gospel to guide your children through their lives, and so dangerous to try and
raise them without it." Then she listed the names and addresses of twenty-five friends and
relatives, saying she would appreciate very much having the missionaries call on these
twenty-five people, and she would be praying that they would be as happy to receive the
gospel message as she had been.
</p><p>
As I left the Northwest in December, more than a thousand referrals were passing through our
office each month, members wanting to share the gospel with friends and relatives, knowing
the joy it would bring into their lives. Brethren, this is the "share the gospel" plan at work
through the referral system.
</p><p>
I would like to say a few words about the auxiliaries as missionary aids. Invite your friends to
attend the auxiliary meetings with you. I would say that this is one of the easier ways that we
have of sharing the gospel. As an officer or teacher, or even a member of one of these
auxiliary groups, you can be a missionary by following this program. You and the members
of your family not only invite these people but make appointments to pick them up to attend
Sunday School, Relief Society, Mutual, Primary, Sacrament meeting, or any other of the
Church meetings.
</p><p>
Likewise, you can take these people to the social functions being given by the auxiliary
organizations. They offer very pleasant occasions for these nonmembers, and when they come
to feel the warmth and friendship that they find in this association, they are much
more susceptible to the teachings of the gospel.
</p><p>
This is a very practical way that you can participate. A striking example of this is an incident
that happened last year in the Northwest. Sister Freeman, a convert of about two years, was
serving as president of the Relief Society in one of the branches. There had been no
missionaries in this branch for some time. In the spring, we discussed the "share the gospel"
plan with the members of the branch, and we sent two missionaries in with instructions to use
the "share the gospel" program. Soon after they arrived, they got in touch with Sister
Freeman, and she wrote to me saying this: "A special thanks for sending these fine
missionaries to our branch. We are thrilled and very thankful, and we are reorganizing our
visiting teachers so that the presidency will be free to visit any contacts that the missionaries
ask us to."
</p><p>
About six months later I was interviewing one of the elders working in the area. I asked him
how things were going in the branch. He said, "Simply great. Do you know how many
nonmember women were out to the opening Relief Society meeting in the branch?" I guessed
six or eight, which I thought would be pretty good. He said, "Thirty-four!" This, brethren, is
the "share the gospel" plan in action in the Relief Society. Thanks to Sister Freeman and her
fine members, because of this activity many wonderful members are now enjoying the
benefits of the gospel.
</p><p>
As a result of the "share the gospel" plan, actually thousands of people are being brought into
the Church every month. The effectiveness of this plan is especially impressive in the
Northwestern States Mission, where we adopted it early last year. By the members of the
stakes and districts working with the full-time missionaries, 775 converts were baptized in
January and February of this year, compared with 106 a year ago&mdash;nearly seven and a half
times as many. This figure does not include many more baptisms by stake missionaries.
</p><p>
In the eight eastern United States and Canadian missions that Sister Richards and I visited
during January, February, and March of this year, the "share the gospel" plan has been
introduced, and the number of baptisms so far this year is approximately double that of a year
ago for a comparable period. But amazing as these figures sound and are, the important thing
is that a great many more of God's children are enjoying the blessings of the gospel than
otherwise might be.
</p><p>
And what is our responsibility? It is to give every one of God's children the opportunity of
enjoying the blessings of immortality and eternal life. As Jesus said to Nicodemus, a ruler of
the Jews, ". . . Verily, verily, I say unto thee, Except a man be born of water and of the
Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5#5">John 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, baptism is necessary, and we must be baptism conscious. On several occasions bishops
and branch presidents have said to me, "President, having all of these people coming into the
Church is wonderful. We need them." But also another great blessing is received by members
participating in this "share the gospel" plan. Many who had been relatively inactive became
active again. An increased spirituality is definitely noticeable among the ward members who
are sharing. It is like love, as you give it to others it increases in yourself.
</p><p>
Further, by members sharing the gospel with friends a great many very fine converts are
coming into the Church, many who are making wonderful leaders almost immediately after
baptism.
</p><p>
Brethren, remember the word of the Lord to the Prophet Joseph: "And if it so be that you
should labor all your days in crying repentance unto this people, and bring, save it be one
soul unto me, how great shall be your joy with him in the kingdom of my Father!
</p><p>
"And now, if your joy will be great with one soul that you have brought unto me into the
kingdom of my Father, how great will be your joy if you should bring many souls unto me!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15-16#15">D&amp;C 18:15-16</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, the "share the gospel" plan is really here. Every member of the Church a missionary!
This also means group teaching to a very large extent, and this plan is very
simple and extremely effective. President Moyle has said: "We can go out into the mission
field, we can go out into the world we can go into our lives, and accomplish anything that we
desire to accomplish. Whenever the Lord calls upon us to do anything, he makes us equal to
the task."
</p><p>
I know this is true. Let everyone of us be a missionary. It is wonderful. And may we have the
faith and the determination and the courage to make this "share the gospel" plan an effective
vehicle in bringing great numbers of souls into the kingdom of God. Let us always keep in
mind that the purpose of missionary work is to bring souls into the kingdom of God through
the ordinance of baptism.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us to this end, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
