<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Obedience Brings Happiness</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Eldred G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Patriarch to the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">Eldred G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 24-27</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brothers and sisters, I wish to express my feelings along with others in this conference
regarding the passing of our late President, George Albert Smith. I, for one, have lost a great
friend. I don't think anyone has been more able to take the place of my earthly father than
President George Albert Smith has done. I think he emulated in his life all of the principles of
the gospel, and no matter what subject is selected during this conference by the General
Authorities or any of those who speak here, it will be a subject of which President George
Albert Smith was an excellent example.
</p><p>
KEY TO HAPPINESS
</p><p>
And I pray the Lord will be with me as I express today what thought I have had in mind on
the principles of the gospel and the foundation upon which we may have happiness in this life
and happiness in the life to come; for no happiness comes without success, or without growth
and progress.
</p><p>
Reading from the Doctrine and Covenants, Section twenty-nine, verses 36 to 40,
</p><p>
And it came to pass that Adam, being tempted of the devil&mdash;for, behold, the devil
was before Adam, for he rebelled against me, saying, Give me thine honor, which is
my power; and also a third part of the hosts of the heaven turned he away from me
because of their agency; 
</p><p>
And they were thrust down, and thus came the devil and his angels; 
</p><p>
And, behold, there is a place prepared for them from the beginning, which
place is hell.
</p><p>
And it must needs be that the devil should tempt the children of men, or they could
not be agents unto themselves; for if they never should have bitter they could not
know the sweet&mdash;
</p><p>
Wherefore, it came to pass that the devil tempted Adam, and he partook of the
forbidden fruit and transgressed the commandment, wherein he became subject to the
will of the devil, because he yielded unto temptation
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/36-40#36">D&amp;C 29:36-40</a>).
</p><p>
And reading from Moses: 
</p><p>
And in that day the Holy Ghost fell upon Adam, which beareth record of the Father
and the Son, saying: I am the only begotten of the Father from the beginning,
henceforth and forever, that as thou hast fallen thou mayest be redeemed, and all
mankind, even as many as will.
</p><p>
And in that day Adam blessed God and was filled, and began to prophesy concerning
all the families of the earth, saying: Blessed be the name of God, for because of my
transgression my eyes are opened, and in this life I shall have joy, and again in the
flesh I shall see God.
</p><p>
And Eve, his wife, heard all these things and was glad, saying: Were it not for our
transgression we never should have had seed, and never should have known good and
evil, and the joy of our redemption, and the eternal life which God giveth unto all the
obedient (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/9-11#9">Moses 5:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
In both these references we are given the key to happiness in this life and happiness in the
life to come to carry throughout all eternity.
</p><p>
Adam fell that men might be; and men are, that they might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
PRESENCE OF GOOD AND EVIL
</p><p>
Joy comes as a result of progress, as a result of accomplishment for good. That is why we all
shouted for joy (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/38/7#7">Job 38:7</a>)
when the opportunity was given to us to come to this earth and partake of the
blessings through obedience, made possible to us through exercising free agency. For man to
exercise free agency he must have both sides to choose from. In every decision made there
must be both a good and an evil influence; for if we had all of the good or all of the evil we
would be right in the same path which Satan tried to establish in the first place, that of
predestination. And so there must be both sides to choose from in every case.
</p><p>
As the Lord said in the Doctrine and Covenants in the verse from which I previously read: 
</p><p>
And it must needs be that the devil should tempt the children of men or they could not
be agents unto themselves; for if they never should have bitter they could not know
the sweet (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/39#39">D&amp;C 29:39</a>).
</p><p>
Therefore, in all that we do we must be tempted. Then our growth depends upon our
obedience. The first step in our progress for the eternities is accepting the gospel of Jesus
Christ. We do not convert others; missionaries do not convert others. We teach them to think
for themselves; and when they have a desire within themselves to receive knowledge and
express that desire in action, by being obedient to the desires of God, then they have fulfilled
that law upon which that blessing is predicated
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/20-21#20">D&amp;C 130:20-21</a>),
which brings a knowledge of the gospel to them through the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
Baptism is the fulfilling of an ordinance which is an act of testifying that we will be obedient
in keeping the commandments of God. The greatest blessing promised in the Word of
Wisdom is that of knowledge. The promises given are: 
</p><p>
And all saints who remember to keep and do these sayings, walking in obedience to
the commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones; 
</p><p>
And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-19#18">D&amp;C 89:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
DESIRE TO BE OBEDIENT
</p><p>
I am reminded of a story of a man who once tried to discontinue the use of tobacco. He
became almost a nervous wreck. He worried himself sick about how much he was going
without tobacco. It was on his mind constantly until he became so nervous and so shaky that
he couldn't hold his hands still. Then later on, the elders&mdash;the missionaries&mdash;contacted him
and told him about the Word of Wisdom and he said, "If that's what the Lord wants, then I'll
do it." And with the idea in his mind that he was going to do it because of obedience to the
commandments of the Lord, he discontinued the use of tobacco; and he held his hands out in
front of the visitors with him and said, "Look how steady I am; I'm as steady as any of them
and I have gone without tobacco for some months."
</p><p>
Our mental attitude has much to do with whether or not we want to be obedient to the
commandments of the Lord.
</p><p>
The same is true in respect to paying tithing. If a man pays his tithing because he wants to be
obedient to the commandments of God he will receive more blessings as a result, and it will
be much easier to pay. And so it is with all other requirements of the gospel; for example,
attendance at sacrament meetings. What is said at Church is not always remembered, but we
receive the blessing for being obedient. As a result we carry the Spirit of the Lord with us in
our work between meetings and in our various activities until we again gather with the Saints.
</p><p>
BLESSINGS FOLLOW OBEDIENCE
</p><p>
Some people sacrifice all the blessings of the temple endowment and sealing, including the
blessings of godhood and exaltation just because they do not want to be obedient in wearing
the temple garment. The greatest blessing that comes from wearing the garment is the result
of obedience. Then the Lord will bless us. The success of our entire earth life depends upon
how well we learn to be obedient. There can be no obedience without free agency which
gives us both good and evil to choose from. Thank God for the gospel plan and the power
God gives us to resist evil and choose the right.
</p><p>
And may the Lord be with us and give us those blessings that we need, to carry us through
these troubled times, for as long as we are obedient to his will and do that which is in our
power, the Lord will take care of the rest of it. And we needn't worry about distressed times,
for as long as we have the gospel plan and live it with the idea of being obedient to the
desires of our Heavenly Father, his way is the best way, and all other things will be taken
care of. Seek ye first the kingdom of heaven and all else shall be added unto it.
</p><p>
May the blessings of the Lord be upon this people and those at this conference and those who
shall follow me in occupying the time here, I ask in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
