<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">I Bear Witness</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Delbert L. Stapley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Delbert L. Stapley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 47-49</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I can think of easier ways, my brothers and sisters, to commence Church activity, than
standing before you today.
</p><p>
I am grateful to be with you.  A few days ago it was rather doubtful whether I could appear
in conference, but I chanced to meet President McKay.  He informed me I was scheduled to
speak, and I felt if it were President McKay's desire that I speak to you, the Lord would bless
and sustain me.  When I arrived this morning, he suggested that I might be called on in this
meeting, and of all things, I left my talk at home.  I told him, however, that I was not sure
that was the talk I should give. I therefore, need the inspiration and the blessings of the Lord
with me.  I ask for an interest in your faith and prayers.
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, I would be most ungrateful if I failed to express gratitude and
appreciation for the faith and the prayers of the Saints throughout the Church for my recovery
from the illness that has inactivated me the past four months.  I have been cognizant in many
ways of your appeals for divine favor in my behalf, and I acknowledge to the Lord before
you the healing blessings of his holy Spirit I am here today because of his blessings.
</p><p>
I want to express appreciation to my brethren of the General Authorities, whose brotherhood,
love, affection, and faithful devotion I shall always remember with tender emotions and fond
memories for the benefit of their administrations, their faith and prayers, in which all of you
have taken a part and confirmed by your own supplications to God, the eternal Father of us
all.  From the depths of my heart I thank all of you, and express profound gratitude and
appreciation for your kindness and for your love.  I sincerely hope my appreciation can be
adequately evidenced by my faithful devotion to the ministry of our Lord and Savior, Jesus
Christ, whose servant I am.
</p><p>
I bear witness to you that Jesus is the Christ, the Only Begotten
Son of the living God, our Lord, Redeemer, Savior, and Advocate with the Father, the Light
and Life of men, and the only name under heaven, given among men whereby salvation can
be obtained.
</p><p>
I like these words from the Apostle John quoting the Savior to his disciples: 
</p><p>
If I bear witness of myself, my witness is not true.
</p><p>
There is another that beareth witness of me; and I know that the witness which he witnesseth
of me is true.
</p><p>
Ye sent unto John, and he bare witness unto the truth.
</p><p>
But I have greater witness than that of John: for the works which the Father hath given me to
finish, the same works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath sent me.
</p><p>
And the Father himself, which hath sent me, hath borne witness of me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/31-33,36-37#31">John 5:31-33,36-37</a>).
</p><p>
John the Baptist so early bore witness that Jesus was the Christ.  He had that most wonderful
of opportunities of baptizing his Lord and witnessing the Holy Ghost descend upon him in the
sign of a dove, confirming the Lord's Messiahship.  The Apostle John later
said, "If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/5/9#9">1 Jn. 5:9</a>).
</p><p>
The God and Father of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ, spoke from the heavens on the
occasion of Christ's baptism and said, "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>).
I think of that other occasion when Christ took Peter, James, and John with him
on the Mount and was transfigured before them, Elias and Moses appeared, and then the voice
of God from heaven again declared: "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased;
hear ye him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/5#5">Matt. 17:5</a>).
</p><p>
If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/5/9#9">1 Jn. 5:9</a>).
</p><p>
The ministry of Jesus of Nazareth is itself a witness and testimony that he was the Son of the
living God.  As we have heard this morning, Christ was crucified and arose from the grave in
a glorious resurrection.  He first appeared unto Cephas after his resurrection and then to his
disciples, members of the Twelve.  Later he appeared unto about five hundred brethren at
once (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/5-8#5">1 Cor. 15:5-8</a>).
For forty days following his resurrection
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/3#3">Acts 1:3</a>),
he personally ministered among men and
taught them; he counseled and directed them in the ministry.  They went forth testing of him
that he was the Redeemer and Son of the living God.  Later he was seen of Paul the Apostle,
who also testified of him gloriously.  The Savior stated: ". . . for the works which the Father
hath given me to finish, the same works that I do, bear witness of me, that the Father hath
sent me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/36#36">John 5:36</a>).
</p><p>
There is the other witness, spoken of by Jesus, the witness of the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/16-17#16">John 14:16-17</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13-15#13">John 16:13-15</a>), that testified to
the spirit of his disciples, that this was the Son of God who had called them, and whom they
served.  The two angels who stood by as he was received into heaven said he should so come
in like manner as they had seen him go into heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/9-11#9">Acts 1:9-11</a>).
</p><p>
Shortly thereafter followed the long period of spiritual darkness, and then came the time for
the last and most important of all God's dispensations to be ushered in; therefore, because of
its importance, God the eternal Father and his Son Jesus Christ personally appeared to the
boy, Joseph Smith, and informed him of his holy calling
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).  Later Moroni, a resurrected prophet
of the living God, from the Nephite nation, came to him and showed him where the plates
were deposited that contained a record of a branch of God's people
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/30-33#30">JS&mdash;H 1:30-33</a>).  This record Joseph later
translated by the gift and power of God.
</p><p>
Three men were shown these plates by an angel of God and the voice of the Lord declared
from heaven that the record was true and the translation correct, and they should to all the
world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/thrwtnss">BM Three Wit.</a>).
And then later eight men had the privilege of seeing these plates
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/eghtwtnss">BM Eight Wit.</a>). All these men are
witnesses to the divine calling of the Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
The Lord gave revelations to the
Prophet Joseph singly upon many occasions; also to Joseph and Oliver Cowdery; also to
Joseph and Martin Harris.  Heavenly resurrected beings manifested themselves unto him and
them and conferred upon them the gifts, the authorities, and the powers to officiate in all the
affairs of God's kingdom.  It seems fitting that the man who testified of the Savior, John the
Baptist, has come and conferred upon Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery, the Aaronic
Priesthood (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/68-72#68">JS&mdash;H 1:68-72</a>),
and that later the three men, Peter, James, and John, who were with the Savior on
the Mount when he was transfigured before them, and God again testified of his Son, should
come and confer upon the Prophet Joseph and Oliver Cowdery the Melchizedek Priesthood
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/12#12">D&amp;C 27:12</a>),
the priesthood after the order of the Son of God that has to do with the spiritual endowments,
authorities, and blessings of God's church.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, the Prophet, unschooled, unlearned, could not have given to the
world what he was privilege to reveal unless God were with him.  God inspired him in all
that he did.  There were living witnesses who testified to his divine calling for heavenly
messengers had manifested this truth to several brethren.  Surely if we receive the witness of
men, the witness of God is more certain.  The office of the Holy Ghost is to testify of the
Father and Son, it is also the spirit of truth, and when it testifies to the spirit
of men there comes an inward feeling whether a thing is true or whether it is not true.  In the
case of the Prophet, Joseph Smith, it was true, for men in his day and since have received that
witness and testimony which the Holy Ghost itself manifests unto those who seek after truth.
</p><p>
And again the works of Joseph Smith&mdash;analyze them; everything about them indicates his
prophetic calling.  Where a testament is, there must of necessity be the death of a testator
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/9/16#16">Heb. 9:16</a>), and
surely this was a testament unfolding and revealing again God's kingdom with all of its
saving ordinances, principles, and divine powers.  A testament is not of force until after men
are dead (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/9/17#17">Heb. 9:17</a>).
The Prophet gave his life to seal that testimony, and thus the sacrifice of his life
becomes a witness to all men of the truth and power of his holy calling and ministry.
</p><p>
My brothers and sisters, before the Prophet Joseph Smith departed this life he conferred upon
the Twelve all the keys, powers, and authority to carry forward this important work of the
latter-day; that work has not stopped in its progress; it has gone forward; and the fruits of it
are a witness to all people of its truth.
</p><p>
I bear testimony to you that the Presidents of the Church, our spiritual leaders who have
followed Joseph Smith, are prophets of God.  I cannot quote the exact words, but in the
Thursday temple meeting of all the General Authorities, where we had gone in fasting and
prayer in preparation for this great conference, President McKay said, "Brethren, I want to say
to you that Christ is at the helm of this Church, and he is guiding it by his holy power."
</p><p>
I received a witness from the Spirit that President McKay's statement was true.  I bear that
witness to you, my brothers and sisters. I know that leaders of other churches might make
similar statements, but would the Holy Ghost manifest the truth of it to their listeners?  If we
receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/5/9#9">1 Jn. 5:9</a>), which witness all can receive from
the Holy Ghost, for which I humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
