<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Peace Built Upon the Solid Foundation of Eternal Principles</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">(Read by his son, Robert McKay)</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 4-6</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren and sisters:
</p><p>
Only at the last moment have I given in to the pleas of the doctors and members of the
family not to put the added strain on my heart by attempting to go over to the Tabernacle to
meet with you in this conference. However, I am with you in spirit and watching the
proceedings of the meeting over television.
</p><p>
It is over fifty-eight years ago that I stood at the pulpit in the Tabernacle for the first time as
one of the General Authorities of the Church. I remember well then my trembling and
humility at facing such an audience and accepting a position as one of the General
Authorities. The passing of over one half a century has made it no easier to discharge the
responsibility that one holds as a General Authority. This morning, as then and during the
intervening years, I ask for your sympathy and prayers.
</p><p>
<b>Blessings of the Decade</b>
</p><p>
Evidences of progress in the Church give us true cause for rejoicing. The Lord has blessed us
with eventful and prosperous years during the past decade. The loyalty of the
members to the ideals and teachings of the Man of Galilee has been evidenced in many ways:
by the response of tens of thousands to the message of the restored gospel as proclaimed by
messengers at home and abroad; by ready and willing response to "calls" and "assignments";
and by increased tithes and offerings. Surely with these and other equally meritorious services
the Lord is pleased, for he has said, ". . . this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the
immortality and eternal life of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Eternal Vigilance and Righteous Effort the Price of Peace</b>
</p><p>
But let us ever remember that peace and progress are attained only at the price of eternal
vigilance and constant righteous efforts. The forces of evil and misery are still rampant in the
world and must be resisted. The powers of darkness have increased in accordance with the
spread of the gospel. Whole nations are declaring atheism to be the law of the land. Atheism
has become the greatest weapon Satan has to use, and its evil influence is bringing
degradation to millions throughout the world. Even at this moment as the sun throws warm,
genial rays on snowcapped summits and frost-covered valleys of this western land, the public
press tells of increasing activity on the part of the evil one. Warlike activities and
international misunderstandings prevent the establishing of peace and divert man's inventive
genius from the paths of science, art, and literature, and apply it to human retardation and the
holocaust of war.
</p><p>
<b>Peace When . . .</b>
</p><p>
The rising sun can dispel the darkness of night, but it cannot banish the blackness of malice,
hatred, bigotry, and selfishness from the hearts of humanity. Happiness and peace will come
to earth only as the light of love and human compassion enter the souls of men.
</p><p>
<b>"With Healing In His Wings"</b>
</p><p>
It was for this purpose that Christ, the Son of righteousness, "with healing in his wings"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/2#2">Mal. 4:2</a>), came
in the Meridian of Time. Through him wickedness shall be overcome, hatred, enmity, strife,
poverty, and war abolished. This will be accomplished only by a slow but never-failing
process of changing men's mental and spiritual attitude. The ways and habits of the world
depend upon the thoughts and soul-convictions of men and women. If, therefore, we would
change the world, we must first change people's thoughts. Only to the extent that men desire
peace and brotherhood can the world be made better. No peace, even though temporarily
obtained, will be permanent, whether to individuals or nations, unless it is built upon the solid
foundation of eternal principles.
</p><p>
Men may yearn for peace, cry for peace, and work for peace, but there will be no peace until
they follow the path pointed out by the Living Christ. He is the true light of men's lives.
</p><p>
<b>The Mission of the Church to Establish Peace</b>
</p><p>
The mission of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is to establish peace. The
Living Christ is its head. Under him tens of thousands of men in the Church are divinely
authorized to represent him in variously assigned positions. It is the duty of these
representatives to manifest brotherly love, first toward one another, then toward all mankind;
to seek unity, harmony, and peace in organizations within the Church, and then by precept
and example extend these virtues throughout the world.
</p><p>
I pray that each day may find members of the Church truer, purer, nobler than the last, that
they, with intellect and hearts united, may hasten the day when ". . . the Lord will bless his
people with peace" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/29/11#11">Ps. 29:11</a>)
that they may ". . . lift up an ensign of peace, and make a
proclamation of peace unto the ends of the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/39#39">D&amp;C 105:39</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Blessings of Peace for the Righteous</b>
</p><p>
I invoke upon the righteous everywhere our Father's blessings that peace may be in their
hearts and in their homes, that unity may strengthen their ranks, that they may be blessed with
the desire and means to teach others, that goodness may come into the lives of men
throughout the earth, that our Father's kingdom may be enlarged and
magnified, that his sons and daughters in all the world may find fellowship with the Saints,
that the designs of the wicked may be frustrated and the purposes of the sinful come to
naught, that unrighteous dominion shall be broken, and that truth shall govern the earth, that
God's people&mdash;those who keep his commandments&mdash;may become as a light set upon a hill
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/14#14">Matt. 5:14</a>),
an ensign to the nations (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/5/26#26">Isa. 5:26</a>),
in anticipation of the long-awaited day when the Prince of Peace
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/6#6">Isa. 9:6</a>)
shall reign as King of Kings and Lord of Lords (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/16#16">Rev. 19:16</a>).
This is my prayer, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
