<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">&ldquo;Except the Lord Build the Home&rdquo;</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Gordon B. Hinckley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Gordon B. Hinckley, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 127-130</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
<p>
As I speak to you I am aware that I have come into your
homes as your guest. I should like to talk with you about
our homes. I am confident that you feel some concern, as do
I, for the homes of America.
</p><p>
Recently I thumbed through the summary of the FBI Uniform
Crime Report for 1962. In a few words and with a few charts
it told a disturbing story&mdash;a six percent increase in serious
crimes in the period of a single year, a nine percent
increase in auto thefts, arrests of young people under 18 up
nine percent, with female arrests increasing at a faster
rate than male arrests. The question that came to mind
immediately was how long can we go on with a nine percent
increase in youth arrests each year?
</p><p>
One of our national magazines recently carried these words
on the cover:
"Morality U.S.A. Do we need a new code to solve our crisis
of immorality? Have our churches failed? Has money become
God? Is sexual morality gone?" (<i>Look</i>, September 24, 1963). I
read this provocative article. I have read others of similar
tone written by men of government, industry, and education
who have expressed themselves with deep concern over the
moral crisis that evidently is sweeping across the land.
</p><p>
I am not one to believe that all was good in the long ago,
and that all is bad today. I think this is the greatest age
the world has known. But I am also confident that there is
trouble in the land.
</p><p>
The article referred to above states: "We are witnessing the
death of the
old morality . . . The established moral guidelines have
been yanked from our hands. We are left floundering in a
money-motivated, sex-obsessed, big city dominated society.
We must figure out for ourselves how to apply the
traditional moral principles to the problems of our times. Many
find this burden too heavy" (<i>Idem.</i>, p. 74).
</p><p>
I should like to add that many of our youth will not and
cannot figure out for themselves how to apply the
traditional moral principles. They find this burden much too
heavy. They must have help. They must have guidance. They
must have example.
</p><p>
Private and public morality are rooted in the homes of the
people. No nation is stronger than its homes. It is in the
home that examples of virtue are best caught and lessons of
virtue are best taught.
</p><p>
It was said of old, "Except the Lord build the house, they
labor in vain that build it"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/127/1#1">Ps. 127:1</a>).
</p><p>
And so I welcome this opportunity to talk with you, and
particularly you parents of the youth of America, on a theme
on which I have expressed myself previously, and one which
I feel is timely.
</p><p>
All agree that we need a new emphasis on honesty, character
and integrity. All agree that only as we build again into
the fiber of our lives the virtues which are the essence of
true civilization will the pattern of our times change. The
question that confronts us is, <i>Where shall we begin?</i>
</p><p>
I am satisfied that it must begin with recognition of God as
our Eternal Father, of our relationship to Him as His
children, with communication with Him in recognition of His
sovereign position, and with daily supplication for His
guidance in our affairs.
</p><p>
I submit that a return to the old pattern of prayer, family
prayer in the homes of the people, is one of the simple
medicines that would check the dread disease that is eroding
the fiber of our character. We could not expect a miracle
in a day, but in a generation we would have a miracle.
</p><p>
A generation or two ago family prayer in the homes of
Christian people
throughout the world was as much a part of the day's
activity as were the meals. As that practice has diminished,
our moral decay has ensued. I fear that
as the quality of our housing has improved, the spirit of
our homes has deteriorated.
</p><p>
The discipline that is needed in our lives is the discipline
that comes from within. Many are crying for more legislation
and stricter law enforcement. I do not disparage these as
expedients, but I fear they are only expedients. Virtue,
integrity, honesty do not come of imposition from without.
They are the fruits of good teaching and good example, and
that teaching and that example are best followed when they
are found in the home.
</p><p>
Paul of old declared to Timothy: "This know also, that in
the last days perilous times shall come. For men shall be
lovers of their own selves . . . blasphemers, disobedient to
parents, unthankful, unholy, without natural affection
. . . despisers of those that are good, traitors, heady,
highminded, lovers of pleasure more than lovers of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/1-4#1">2 Tim. 3:1-4</a>).
</p><p>
His words fit in a remarkable way the conditions described
in the magazine article to which I have referred. Simple as
it may sound, I think daily prayer in the homes of the
nation would in a generation lift our heads above the flood
that evidently is engulfing us.
</p><p>
I feel satisfied that there is no adequate substitute for
the morning and evening practice of kneeling together before
the Lord&mdash;father, mother, and children. The very practice of
kneeling together with thankful hearts evaporates some of
those qualities described by Paul: "Disobedient to parents,
without natural affection."
</p><p>
There is something in the very posture of kneeling that
contradicts some of the attitudes he noted: "Proud, heady,
highminded."
</p><p>
The inclination to be unholy, as Paul described it, to be
unthankful, is erased as together the family thank the Lord
for life and peace and all they have. And as they thank the
Lord for one another there is developed within the family a
new appreciation, a new respect, a new affection one for
another.
</p><p>
I know of nothing that will ease family tensions, that in a
subtle way will bring about that respect for parents which
leads to obedience, that will
effect a spirit of repentance which will largely erase the
blight of broken homes, than will praying together, verbally
confessing our weaknesses before the Lord, and invoking the
blessings of the Lord upon the home and those who dwell there.
</p><p>
In remembering together before the Lord the poor, the needy,
and the oppressed there is developed, unconsciously but
realistically, a love for others above self, a respect for
others, a desire to serve the needs of others.
</p><p>
One cannot ask God to help a neighbor in distress, without
feeling motivated to do something oneself. What miracles
would happen in the lives of the children of America if they
would lay aside their selfishness and lose themselves in the
service of others. The seed from which this sheltering and
fruitful tree may grow is best planted and nurtured in the
daily supplications of the family.
</p><p>
I know of no better way to inculcate love for country than
for parents to pray before their children for the land in
which we live, invoking the blessings of the Almighty upon
it that it may be preserved in liberty and in peace. I know
of no better way to build within the hearts of our children
a much-needed respect for authority than remembering in the
daily supplications of the family the President and the
Congress and others who carry the burdens of government.
</p><p>
On the route I travel daily is a signboard which reads: "A
world at prayer is a world at peace." You have seen others
like it. I believe it speaks a fundamental truth. I am
satisfied that we shall not have peace unless and until we
request it in the name of the Prince of Peace and then
reform our lives to be worthy of it.
</p><p>
The hall from which I speak, the great Mormon Tabernacle on
Temple Square in Salt Lake City, was constructed by a
people who loved freedom, who worshipped God, and who
prayed in their simple pioneer homes, as did most of the
pioneers who laid
the foundations of all that we in America today enjoy.
</p><p>
In 1872 Colonel Thomas L. Kane of Philadelphia visited Utah
with his wife
and two sons. They traveled by wagon some three hundred
miles to the southern part of the state, stopping each
night in the homes of the people in the little frontier
settlements along the way. Mrs. Kane wrote a series of
letters to her father in Philadelphia. In one of them she
said: "At every one of the places we stayed on this journey
we had prayers immediately after the dinner-supper, and
prayers again before breakfast. No one was excused . . .
The Mormons kneel at once. while the head of the household,
or an honored guest prays aloud . . . They spend very little
time in ascriptions, but ask for what they need, and thank
Him for what He has given . . . (They) take it for granted
that God knows our familiar names and titles, and will ask a
blessing on (a particular individual by name). I liked this
when I became used to it."
</p><p>
It was so in the pioneer homes across the land. With the
faith that came of these daily invocations these people
grubbed the sagebrush, led the waters to the parched soil,
made the desert blossom as the rose, governed their families
in love, lived in peace one with another and with the world,
and made their names immortal as they lost themselves in
the service of God.
</p><p>
We cannot pray in our public schools, but we can pray in our
homes, and in so doing we shall reweave into the character
of our children the moral strength which will become the
fiber of a better society. "Seek ye the Lord while he may be
found" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/55/6#6">Isa. 55:6</a>).
</p><p>
This simple practice, a return to family worship, spreading
across the land and over the earth, would in a generation
do much to lift the blight that is destroying us. It would
restore integrity, mutual respect, and a spirit of
thankfulness in the hearts of the people.
</p><p>
We do not need a new moral standard in our modern society.
The laws of God have not been abrogated. They were not given
to one generation to be laid aside by another. Their
disregard can result only in trouble, misery, and insecurity
as witness the fruits of the erosion of
morality among us. Their application is the way of life and
peace and progress.
</p><p>
And so to you, who sit in your homes in this great land,
established and
preserved under the hand of the Almighty, I plead for a return
to recognition of Him, and daily supplication to Him. The
Master declared, "Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and
ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7#7">Matt. 7:7</a>).
</p><p>
I give you my testimony that you shall not go away
unrewarded. The changes may not be readily apparent. They
may be extremely subtle. But they will be real, for "God is
a rewarder of them that diligently seek Him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/6#6">Heb. 11:6</a>).
</p><p>
As we change ourselves and our children, developing within
them a new respect, a spirit of gratitude, a becoming
humility, we shall reform our society.
</p><p>
God bless us with the faith to call upon Him, at the altar
of our homes, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
