<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A World Message</p> 
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 127-132</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I presume as we come to the end of a three-day conference, and the
seventh session, those who are present represent the survival of the fittest.
</p><p>
With all my heart I love, support, and sustain President Joseph Fielding Smith as prophet, seer,
and revelator and President of the Church, and the two noble men who stand at his side in the
First Presidency. I know they are great men of God who will lead the Church forward and
upward under the inspiration of heaven.
</p><p>
I talk to the subject "A World Message."
</p><p>
<b>Missionary work</b>
</p><p>
Missionary work&mdash;the preaching of the gospel&mdash;has been the major activity of the true Church
of Christ whenever the gospel has been upon the earth. Prophets of God and numerous other
ambassadors of truth have preached the word "in season, out of season." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/2#2">2 Tim. 4:2</a>)
</p><p>
The resurrected Lord in his final instructions to his apostles, before his ascension, emphasized
the great importance of missionary work. Matthew, in the last two verses of his Gospel,
summarizes these important instructions in these words: 
</p><p>
"Go ye therefore, and <i>teach all nations</i>, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son,
and of the Holy Ghost: 
</p><p>
"Teaching them to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded you: and, lo, I am with you
alway, even unto the end of the world. Amen" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
Mark, in his record, states: 
</p><p>
"Go ye into all the world, and <i>preach the gospel to every creature</i>.
</p><p>
"He that believeth and is baptized shall be saved; but he that believeth not shall he damned"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15-16#15">Mark 16:15-16</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
And so it has been in every gospel dispensation. Preaching the saving principles of the gospel
has ever been a great responsibility of first importance.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of restored Church</b>
</p><p>
It is true in this gospel dispensation. Following the glorious appearance of God the Father and his
Son Jesus Christ to Joseph Smith, it appears that the first great responsibility placed upon the
restored Church was to carry the gospel to the world&mdash;to all our Father's children.
</p><p>
It has truly been a great drama of transcendent importance&mdash;a drama of sacrifice, joy, hardship,
courage, and above all, love of fellowmen. Nowhere upon the face of the earth will you find a
human drama to equal it. Yes, it has cost blood, sweat, and tears to carry forth this labor of love.
And why have we done it? Because the God of heaven has commanded it; because he loves his
children, and it is his will that the teeming millions of the earth shall have opportunity to hear
and, of their own free will, accept and live the glorious saving and exalting principles of the
gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
To the Prophet Joseph Smith he, even Jesus Christ whose name the Church bears, proclaimed: 
</p><p>
"And this gospel shall be preached unto every nation, and kindred, and tongue, and people."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/37#37">D&amp;C 133:37</a>)
</p><p>
"Wherefore the voice of the Lord is unto the ends of the earth, that all that will hear may hear!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/11#11">D&amp;C 1:11</a>)
</p><p>
"And the voice of warning shall be unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I have
chosen in these last days." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4#4">D&amp;C 1:4</a>)
</p><p>
"That the fulness of my gospel might be proclaimed by the weak and the simple unto the ends of
the world, and before kings and rulers." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/23#23">D&amp;C 1:23</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Response of members</b>
</p><p>
These are direct commands of the Lord Jesus Christ, whose second coming is near. In response
to these commands and with a knowledge of the blessings of the gospel, we, as members of his
church, will continue to respond.
</p><p>
This is why hundreds of thousands of missionaries have gone forth to the nations of the earth at
the expenditure of millions of dollars from their modest means. This is why the First Presidency
of the Church even during the last world war declared, "No act of ours or of the Church must
ever interfere with this God-given mandate."
</p><p>
It is in very deed a mandate to his church. It will be carried out. No power on earth or in hell can
stop this work or thwart the purposes of the Lord to have his soul-satisfying gospel message go
to his children. It may take war, commotion, disasters in many forms to bring it about. But the
purposes of God will be achieved. His children will hear the gospel of salvation in his own due
time.
</p><p>
<b>God at the helm</b>
</p><p>
The time must surely come when the Iron Curtain will be melted down and the Bamboo Curtain
shattered. What the Lord has decreed will he fulfilled. To members of the Church and
honest-hearted people everywhere, we remind you that God is at the helm&mdash;he is not dead&mdash;and
he has said, "Be still, and know that I am God." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/46/10#10">Ps. 46:10</a>) To us in this day he has declared: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, lift up your hearts and rejoice, and gird up your loins, and take upon you my whole
armor, that ye may be able to withstand the evil day, having done all, that ye may be able to
stand." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/15#15">D&amp;C 27:15</a>)
</p><p>
To the thousands throughout the world who are accepting the gospel; to faithful missionaries
everywhere and devoted families who support them: go forward with faith and courage. You are
engaged in the greatest work in all the world&mdash;the saving of the souls of the children of men. In
this great work we cannot fail.
</p><p>
<b>Need for gospel</b>
</p><p>
Our Father's children need the gospel. They long for, and want, the security and inner peace that
only the gospel can bring. Our Father's children are essentially good. I have visited with them in
some sixty nations on both sides of the Iron Curtain. True, some are in bondage under despotic,
Godless leaders, but they want to live in peace, to be good neighbors. They love their homes and
their families. They want to improve their standard of living. In their hearts they want to do what
is right. I know the Lord loves them, and as his humble servant I have a love in my heart for the
teeming millions of this world.
</p><p>
<b>Prophecies being fulfilled</b>
</p><p>
I have sensed this feeling anew and more strongly than ever, as I have mingled with the humble,
sweet-spirited people of Asia during the past two years. I have seen, at close range, the manner
in which the Lord has turned disasters&mdash;war, occupation, and revolution&mdash;into blessings.
Prophecies of the Lord are being fulfilled. The gospel is reaching peoples who a few years ago
seemed unreachable. In spite of powerful traditions, religious dogmas, and ancient national
policies, great changes have come over entire nations. Miracles are happening before our very
eyes. The Lord is working great wonders, and his children are rejoicing as the blessings of the
gospel touch their lives. It is marvelous to behold. Let me illustrate.
</p><p>
In the prophetic revelation referred to by the Lord as "my preface unto the book of my
commandments, which I have given them to publish unto you, O inhabitants of the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/6#6">D&amp;C 1:6</a>), the Lord called out in these words: "Hearken, O ye people of my church, saith the voice of
him who dwells on high, and whose eyes are upon all men; yea, verily I say: Hearken ye people
from afar; and ye that are upon the islands of the sea, listen together" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1#1">D&amp;C 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>People in Asian lands</b>
</p><p>
These significant words fit the Asian countries remarkably. "Hearken ye people from afar; and
ye that are upon the islands of the sea, listen together."
</p><p>
Many times reference has been made to these prophetic words in the past two years as I have
made five visits to these Asian lands as a church leader and two earlier visits as a cabinet
official. I thought of the words "ye people from afar" as we visited Thailand, Malaysia, Vietnam,
Singapore, Indonesia, India, and so on, and was told by our travel agent we could return to Salt
Lake City by traveling either east or west&mdash;"the distance is about the same." I thought of this as I
presented the King of Thailand with a copy of Joseph Smith's testimony&mdash;off the press the day
before&mdash;the first Church publication in the Thai language.
</p><p>
<b>"islands of the sea"</b>
</p><p>
". . . and ye that are upon the islands of the sea, listen together." How these words&mdash;and similar
words from the Book of Mormon (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/29/7,11#7">2 Ne. 29:7,11</a>)&mdash;have come to mind in the past two years, in
the island nation of Japan at a youth conference before 800 youth, as we listened to 125 personal
testimonies in a four-hour testimony meeting, which closed in order to permit a scheduled public
meeting to start, leaving 85 young people wanting to add their testimonies.
</p><p>
We were reminded of the words "islands of the sea" as I dedicated the land of Singapore last
April, where we already have two congregations and a new church building underway.
</p><p>
Again we thought of the words of the Lord, "islands of the sea," as we visited Taiwan and
attended a district conference with over two thousand in attendance in Manila in the
Philippines&mdash;some forty million people on seven thousand islands. Again the words "islands of the sea"
crowded in upon us as we were welcomed by friendly leaders to dedicate the land of fourteen
thousand islands in Indonesia&mdash;a land that has recently passed through a blood bath to try to rid
this freedom-loving people of godless Communism.
</p><p>
A visit with the leader of Free China on the island of Taiwan and the increasing membership of
the Church in Hong Kong, Korea, and elsewhere show these friendly, humble, courageous
people are heeding the call of the Lord and are "listen[ing] together."
</p><p>
<b>The door now open</b>
</p><p>
There has never been a time until now when the Church has had the strength and means to reach
out effectively to the Asian nations. In the timetable of the Lord, the door is now open, and this
is apparently the day for work in Asia. Each visit has been more encouraging and inspirational
than the last. The work is expanding, and further expansion is in the offing. In each of the
countries the tremendous truth is an inspiration. This is where tie people are&mdash;by the hundreds
of millions&mdash;one-third of the population of the world. Of course, from the total standpoint of
population, we are just getting started.
</p><p>
My wife and I have just returned from three inspirational but busy weeks in the Asian missions.
The five missions were increased to six four months ago and have just increased to eight, with
the expectation of at least one more within a year. This indicates the growth that is taking place
in these areas.
</p><p>
<b>Expo '70</b>
</p><p>
While in Japan I was joined by three General Authorities and three other leaders who made up
the invited official Church representation appointed by the First Presidency to attend the grand
opening March 14 of the world's fair known as Expo '70&mdash;the first world's fair in Asia and said
to be the largest world's fair ever.
</p><p>
The day before, March 13, the seven of us, members of our families, distinguished fair officials,
mayors of cities, representatives of the press, and as many members and friends of the Church as
space permitted&mdash;some 600-attended the dedication of the Mormon-Pavilion. Because of its
location, architecture&mdash;with a figure of the Angel Moroni atop a high spire&mdash;and our
challenging theme, "Man's Search For Happiness," it will, no doubt, be a popular fair attraction.
Some 20,000 visited our pavilion the first day, and over 43,000 the first Saturday. Our great
concern is to be able to take care of the great numbers&mdash;estimated at five to eight million&mdash;who
are expected to want to enter our building. Already the film <i>Man's Search for Happiness</i>&mdash;filmed
with Japanese characters&mdash;is being shown in cultural halls and elsewhere in an effort to
partially satisfy those who may not be able to gain admission. We confidently expect the
referrals and requests for missionaries to reach into hundreds of thousands.
</p><p>
<b>Interest of officials</b>
</p><p>
As we enjoyed the inspiring dedicatory services, I recalled the several contacts with fair officials
in luncheons, dinners, etc., and their gracious cooperation&mdash;the Osaka, Japan, press conference
the night before the ground-breaking service, when 29 representatives of the press and mass
media kept us for an hour and a half, asking intelligent questions about the Church and our
people and especially our pavilion theme. Later that evening many of the press met us as we
dedicated the new Okainachi Mormon chapel. Again they were with us the next day at the
official ground-breaking service. Here six high Expo '70, government, and civic officials made
speeches and paid tribute to the Church. They told of man's eternal search for happiness and
emphasized they were pleased "the Mormons are coming to Expo '70 to tell us all how to find
happiness." And as the missionaries commented, "We will in very deed show them how to find
happiness."
</p><p>
With one half million copies of the Book of Mormon pledged and ready, millions of pamphlets
and tracts on hand, and scores of dedicated guides and hundreds of missionaries who will follow
up on referrals, truly the "people from afar" on "the islands of the sea" will "listen together" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1#1">D&amp;C 1:1</a>) and
be welcomed to membership in the Church.
</p><p>
<b>Work in Japan</b>
</p><p>
In Japan the Church has been well-established in two missions and several districts. A few days
ago two more missions were organized. Four missions on the islands of Japan and Okinawa will
permit more intensive work in response to the increasing interest. There are nearly fourteen
million people in the immediate vicinity of Tokyo and Yokohama, where we have good
leadership and a stable organization. A new stake was organized in Tokyo, Sunday, March 15.
The leaders of that stake are here at this conference&mdash;as they said, literally walking on air, they
are so happy. A second Asian stake has been authorized in Manila in the Philippines, where we
baptized some fourteen hundred new converts in 1969. Other stakes to carry on the full, rich
program of the Church will be created in other Asian countries. Anticipating the creation of a
separate mission in Free China, construction of a new mission home has been approved for
Taipei.
</p><p>
Japan now has over twelve thousand members of the Church. There are four thousand in Korea,
nearly six thousand in the Philippines, some four thousand in Hong Kong, and more than that in
Taiwan. A beginning has been made in Thailand, Singapore, and Indonesia. We have strong
congregations on Okinawa, and a nucleus of Vietnamese have come into the Church. Our
servicemen in Korea laid the foundation for the Church there; and when peace comes to
Vietnam, we shall find the way prepared for the spreading of truth among that people.
</p><p>
<b>Mormon servicemen</b>
</p><p>
Mormon servicemen, God bless them, throughout these nations are laying the foundation for
effective proselyting as they help to construct chapels and make friends and converts for the
Church. On a recent tour, visits were made to six installations in Thailand. We have three
well-operating districts of servicemen in Vietnam. Some one thousand are registered for the
Asian Servicemen's Conference to be held at Mt. Fuji, Japan, April 9-12, next weekend.
</p><p>
The missions of Asia are getting high-type, devoted, and, in some cases, prominent converts.
One little branch of 50 members in Korea has five college professors. The land of Indonesia,
with 130 million people, was dedicated October 26, 1969, for the preaching of the gospel. The
work has started with a few missionaries in Djakarta. More missionaries are needed. A new
mission has been established with headquarters in Singapore.
</p><p>
<b>Foundation for expansion</b>
</p><p>
We are building up substantial congregations, and the foundation is being laid for a tremendous
expansion of the work in the Asian area. Baptisms for 1969 were over 100 percent ahead of a
year ago, and the trend continues upward.
</p><p>
One of our great needs, in addition to more missionaries, is buildings. In the entire Philippine
Mission, we have only one building. But building sites are being purchased, and plans are going
forward for the building of additional chapels in various parts of these areas. A large six-floor
building is being planned by the First Presidency for central Tokyo. This could house stake and
ward facilities, distribution center, mission offices, construction offices, and other facilities.
</p><p>
In our lifetime we shall see stakes and chapels, converts in great number, local leadership with
power and ability, and perhaps even a temple erected among the good people of Asia. That is
their hope and their prayer.
</p><p>
<b>Encouraging outlook</b>
</p><p>
The outlook is most encouraging. The Lord is blessing the new converts, the missionaries, the
mission presidents. There is a spirit of optimism everywhere among these humble people, as
men of prominence extend the hand of fellowship and cooperation.
</p><p>
May God bless richly these teeming millions in the Asian countries&mdash;these choice "people from
afar and ye that are upon the islands of the sea" as they "listen together" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1#1">D&amp;C 1:1</a>) to the message of
salvation from the humble servants of God&mdash;local members and missionaries, all. Our message
is a world message. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is a world organization.
</p><p>
For the Lord has declared through the Prophet Joseph Smith, "And the voice of warning shall he
unto all people, by the mouths of my disciples, whom I have chosen in these last days.
</p><p>
"And they shall go forth and none shall stay them, for I the Lord have commanded them." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/4-5#4">D&amp;C 1:4-5</a>)
</p><p>
To this I bear humble witness, in deep gratitude for the Lord's blessing on our work in Asia and
throughout the world, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
