<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Our Homes Divinely Ordained</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1949, pp. 194-199</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Americans, from the very inception of our nation, have been lovers of home. It has been our
primary educational institution and the center of economic, social, and cultural interest. Our
homes have been the bulwark of the nation and the most fundamental institution of society.
What fond memories and emotions have surged up in our hearts at the mere mention of home,
family, parents, children, brothers, and sisters! Some of the sweetest, most soul-satisfying
impressions and experiences of life are associated with home and family ties.
</p><p>
THE AMERICAN HOME
</p><p>
But all is not well with this most basic institution, the American home. In fact, it is in grave
danger, if not in deadly peril. There is convincing evidence that a creeping rot of moral
disintegration is eating into the very vitals of this temple of American civilization. It gives
cause for serious concern.
</p><p>
Marriage, the home, and family are sacred institutions. They are not man-made, but have been
established by a kind Providence for the blessing of his children. In the record of that first
marriage recorded in Genesis, the Lord makes four significant pronouncements: first, that it is
not good for man to be alone; second, that woman was created to be a help meet for man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/18#18">Gen. 2:18</a>);
third, that they twain should be one flesh
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/5#5">Matt. 19:5</a>);
and fourth, that man should leave father and mother and cleave unto his wife
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/24#24">Gen. 2:24</a>).
</p><p>
Later, as though to re-enforce the earlier statement, the Lord said:
</p><p>
. . . What therefore God hath joined together, let not man put asunder
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/6#6">Matt. 19:6</a>);
</p><p>
also
</p><p>
Thou shalt love thy wife with all thy heart, and shalt cleave unto her and none else
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/22#22">D&amp;C 42:22</a>).
</p><p>
Children are likewise counseled in holy writ in their duty to parents. Paul the Apostle wrote:
</p><p>
Children, obey your parents in the Lord: for this is right.
</p><p>
Honour thy father and mother; (which is the first commandment with promise),
</p><p>
That it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/1-3#1">Eph. 6:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
RESPONSIBILITY OF PARENTS
</p><p>
Regarding the divinely appointed responsibility of parents, the sobering counsel is given that
</p><p>
. . . they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord . . .
And . . . inasmuch as parents . . . teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance,
faith in Christ, the Son of the living God . . . and the gift of the Holy Ghost . . . the sin be
upon the heads of the parents
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/28,25#28">D&amp;C 68:28,25</a>).
</p><p>
These and other similar scriptures make crystal clear the divine origin of marriage, the home,
and family, the heaven-imposed responsibilities resting upon the parents and the penalties
imposed when laws governing these hallowed institutions are disregarded.
</p><p>
History reveals that the early pioneers of America recognized and honored these obligations.
They were blessed in their homes and families for so doing. Does our record today merit like
blessings? If we fail to accept these obligations and to keep the American home morally and
spiritually sound, the very future of the nation will be in jeopardy The choice is ours as
parents and citizens.
</p><p>
WEAKENING INFLUENCES
</p><p>
The facts are not reassuring as we soberly appraise them. Far-reaching changes, resulting from
industrialization, concentration of populations, commercialization of recreation, and other
activities once performed in the home, all tend to lead away from home associations.
</p><p>
Accompanying these changes, and in some measure resulting from them, has been a marked
increase in pleasure seeking; the mad rush for money and other material things; the
unwarranted indulgence of personal gratifications; the insidious inroads of tobacco, liquor,
gambling, and many other tendencies in our complex modern civilization. All these have
exerted a pulling power away from the home and have weakened its structure.
</p><p>
There seems to be a tendency for many married people to become soft and to seek a life filled
with ease and the pleasures of the moment They invite the pleasure of conjugality but often
refuse to shoulder the responsibility of parenthood. Reliable reports indicate that
approximately forty percent of the married women have no children whatever or only one
child.
</p><p>
DIVORCE RECORD
</p><p>
The divorce record continues upward at an alarming rate. Fifty years ago there was a ratio of
one divorce to every sixteen marriages; by 1946, one to every three. In some American cities
divorces nearly equal marriages. Reports show that two-thirds of those seeking divorces have
no children.
</p><p>
Frequently in homes where no formal divorce has occurred, there is unhappiness due to
infidelity and lack of harmony and filial affection. It is largely from such broken, bad, and
neglected homes that our youthful delinquents come. According to J. Edgar Hoover, director
of the F.B.I., "The actions of the majority of them were&mdash;and are&mdash;directly related to
the conduct of their parents." Yes, crime begins at home.
</p><p>
In view of these and other well-known but distressing facts, what should be done? Can we
safeguard the home and stabilize family life? Can the deterioration in home life be checked
and corrected? If not, what is our future? 
</p><p>
No nation can rise above its homes. The church, the school, and even the nation, stand
helpless before a weakened and degraded home, in building character. The good home is the
rock foundation&mdash;the cornerstone of civilization. If this, our nation, is to endure, the home
must be safeguarded, strengthened, and restored to its rightful importance.
</p><p>
UNCHASTITY
</p><p>
To do so, we must start with youth&mdash;our boys and girls. They must know that the foundation
of a happy home is laid during pre-marital days. Their relationships should be on a happy but
high plane. There is grave danger in loose and promiscuous relations of young people. The
harmful effects of unseemly familiarities are carried over into married life and tend to weaken
the structure of the home. Unchastity is the most damning of all evils, while moral purity is
one of the greatest bulwarks of successful homemaking. Happy and successful homes cannot
be built on immorality.
</p><p>
May I, as a member of a large family of children and a grateful father of six, say to the
young men and women of America, keep the fountains of life pure. Guard your virtue as you
would your lives. Reserve for the marriage relationship the sweet and soul-satisfying
intimacies of life. The God of heaven, who instituted the marriage covenant, so intended. He
has commanded purity of life and a single standard for men and women. If you fail as young
people properly to restrain yourselves, you will pay the penalty in heartache, disappointment,
and loss of self-respect. Do not reach out too eagerly for the excitements and thrills of life or
they will turn to ashes in your hands. They will come in their own due time in the sacred
bonds of marriage. Youthful sweethearts, be true to God's holy laws. Remember, they cannot
be broken with impunity. If you would be happy and successful in your early association,
courtship, and homebuilding, conform your lives to the eternal laws of heaven. There is no
other way.
</p><p>
IMPORTANCE OF EXAMPLE
</p><p>
As parents, what is our attitude regarding the sacred obligations of parenthood? One of the
two major purposes of marriage is children. "Multiply and replenish the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>)
was among the earliest commandments given of the Lord. Nations which refuse to accept this
God-given obligation, sink into oblivion. Will our sons and daughters want children because
of our attitude and example?
</p><p>
Marriage, designed to be an eternal covenant, is the most glorious and most exalting principle
of the gospel of Jesus Christ. No ordinance is of more importance and none more sacred and
more necessary to the eternal joy of man. Faithfulness to the marriage covenant brings the
fullest joy here and glorious rewards hereafter. The abuse of this sacred ordinance despoils the
lives of individuals, wrecks the basic institution of the home, and causes the downfall of
nations.
</p><p>
The future homes of America will be fortified as parents uphold the Christian virtues before
their children. If parents love and respect each other, and if in their sacred partnership there
are full support and unquestioned fidelity, these essentials will be translated into the homes of
tomorrow. Conversely, if there are bickering, quarreling, and lack of harmony at home, and
participation in the dangerous practice of flirtations with others when away, then the homes of
tomorrow will be weakened thereby.
</p><p>
Parenthood carries with it peculiar responsibilities. If these are accepted without quibbling,
while enthroning motherhood as the highest calling of women, our children&mdash;the parents of
tomorrow&mdash;will be properly impressed and encouraged in the establishment of like homes.
</p><p>
FAMILY PRAYER
</p><p>
The homes of America need also the blessings which come from daily communion with God.
Devotion in the home, which has been such an anchor to youth and parents alike, has all but
vanished. A few generations ago it was a common practice. Then families knelt together in
prayer; the scriptures were read aloud; and households joined in the singing of church hymns.
This practice, if revived, would contribute much to the strength of the home and the nation.
The differences and irritations of the day melt away as families approach the throne of heaven
together. Unity increases. The ties of love and affection are re-enforced and the peace of
heaven enters.
</p><p>
In such homes secret prayers are said night and morning by members of the household.
Individual and family problems are approached with confidence after invoking the favor of
heaven. Young people participating in such a family devotional have hearts freed from evil
intent as they leave for an evening of entertainment. These will be the restraining influence in
the group when gilded temptations arise. Parents who surround their children with the refining
influence of daily devotion are making their contribution to the safeguarding of the American
home.
</p><p>
MUTUAL UNDERSTANDING
</p><p>
America's homes need, also, the stabilizing influence of a closer relationship between parents
and children. Every boy and girl needs the safeguard which an intimate association with
mother or father will provide. The failure of parents and children to understand each other
weakens the framework of the home. This relationship must be built upon love and mutual
confidence. Then when the problems of life arise, father and mother will be the first sought
for counsel. Herein is safety.
</p><p>
Such an atmosphere can be created as parents plan for recreation and diversion together with
their children. An evening at home in wholesome activity; a picnic in the mountains or nearby
park; or a project for fathers and sons and mothers and daughters&mdash;these will all tend to
increase filial affection and love in the home, and strengthen parent-children relations. Time
thus spent yields big dividends. Love at home and obedience to parents increase as the bonds
of home are made secure.
</p><p>
Parents in this close association have no difficulty teaching virtue, honesty, industry, the
principles basic to our American way of life and the dangers of foreign philosophies and
ideologies. Effective parental guidance&mdash;the greatest need of the home&mdash;is here
provided to the profit of the individual, the home, the community, and the nation.
</p><p>
PRESERVATION OF HOMES
</p><p>
Herein, then, lies our path of safety. Our homes must become bulwarks of strength through
enthroning righteousness and bringing into them the peace, unity, and unselfishness
engendered by personal purity, unquestioned fidelity, and simple family devotion. Parents
must accept marriage as a divine institution, and honor parenthood. Children must be inspired
by precept and example in preparation for marriage, to guard against unchastity as against a
loathsome disease, and to practice the other fundamental Christian virtues. Love and mutual
confidence must be safeguarded to strengthen parent-children relationships. Home must
become the abiding place of the Spirit of God because the pure in heart dwell therein.
</p><p>
Yes, America's homes, if this great nation is to endure, must be fortified and preserved. They
must be morally and spiritually sound. There can be no satisfactory substitute for the home.
Its foundation is as ancient as the world. Its mission has been God-ordained.
</p><p>
May God grant that the builders of American homes may have the courage and wisdom to
fulfil faithfully their divine obligations, to inspire young people with a conviction of the
importance of these God-ordained institutions of marriage, the home, and family, that the
marriages of our boys and girls may be consummated under a spiritual influence in the
presence of friends and loved ones, thereby laying a safe foundation for their homes of
tomorrow.
</p><p>
And so today, in this the greatest of all nations, in this land choice above all others, we pay
humble tribute to the home, for a modern prophet declares,
</p><p>
. . . that someday the divinely ordained home is to be the very foundation of the kingdom of
God.
</p><p>
May a kind Providence bless the homes of America, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
