<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Nicholas G. Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Nicholas G. Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1945, pp. 61-64</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, as I look into your faces I endeavor to place you. I have visited half of the
stakes of Zion, up to the present time, and should know half of this congregation, but I have
only been able to pick out about two dozen faces. As I walk amongst you, if you will just
punch me one in the ribs I shall know I have been in your town.
</p><p>
AN INCIDENT ABOUT JUDGE ELIAS A. SMITH
</p><p>
As Brother Joseph Fielding spoke yesterday of the sanctity of work, I could not help thinking
of Judge Elias A. Smith who celebrated his eighty-eighth birthday just about two weeks ago.
Thinking, of course, that a man eighty-eight years of age would be resting in his home, I
went over to his place, only to discover that he was at work, about two o'clock in the
afternoon. So I wended my way down to his office, but he was so busy that he was unable to
stop to have anyone congratulate him on his eighty-eighth birthday. The following day I met
him on the street and said, "Judge, I went to your home and your office yesterday to wish you
many happy returns." "Well," he said, "I am a busy man."
</p><p>
"Yes, I noted that. I couldn't get to see you in the office. I thought you would be home. I
didn't know you were working." "Why," he said, "working, earning my own way. I am so
much happier doing that than I could possibly be in any other way." I wish a lot of folks
could follow Judge Elias A. Smith's way of life, and the way of life which our President has
followed. Day before yesterday morning, down in back of the Church Office Building in his
car, sick and afflicted, our worthy President sat and signed the letters that he had dictated to
go out to different parts of the Church. He isn't too old to work, nor too
sick, nor feeble to work. God bless him.
</p><p>
THE KEEPING OF THE SABBATH
</p><p>
Brother Mark Petersen brought to my mind the words of our Savior:
</p><p>
Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness' sake: for theirs is the kingdom of
heaven. Blessed are ye, when men shall revile you, and persecute you, and shall say all
manner of evil against you falsely, for my sake. Rejoice, and be exceeding glad; for great is
your reward in heaven: for so persecuted they the prophets which were before you
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/10-12#10">Matt. 5:10-12</a>).
</p><p>
And then our President's message, speaking of the many commandments and reminding us of
our responsibility as leaders, to keep the commandments of our Heavenly Father, made me
think of one commandment especially. As I have traveled about attending your conferences,
of necessity I have had to travel on Sundays throughout the intermountain states, and I have
seen men in the fields plowing, and hauling their hay, and putting their grain into the stacks. I
have seen lined up on this sacred Sabbath day many people in front of the moving picture
theatres waiting to purchase their tickets. I have noted crowds lined up at sporting events,
buying their tickets that they might go in and participate in that recreation upon this holy day.
It may surprise you when I say that my grandfather, George A. Smith, was one of the first
men to break the Sabbath day here in Utah. Being rather a practical sort of man, he felt that it
was just as necessary that hunger should be appeased as that we should lift the sheep out of
the pit upon the Sabbath day (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/11#11">Matt. 12:11</a>),
and according to his journal, on July 24th,
1847, you remember, the Saints came down into the valley. Grandfather's diary records that:
</p><p>
. . . it was cloudy but quite warm. Potatoes were planted. I planted the first. At about two
o'clock President Brigham Young and his company came up all better. Water was let on the
ground on the twenty-fourth. Toward evening there was a slight shower. Sunday, July 25th, it
was clear and warm. Meetings commenced at half past ten. In the morning, I, in company
with some others, planted some corn, beans and peas. Meeting again at two p.m. That
afternoon Brigham Young chastised me, directing that the brethren must not work on Sunday.
He said they would lose five times as much as they would gain by it. None were to hunt that
day, and there should not any man dwell among us who would not observe these rules. They
might go and dwell wherever they pleased but they should not dwell amongst us.
</p><p>
Grandfather must have taken that lesson to heart after he had been plowing and planting seeds
upon that Sunday morning, for he got into the soul of my father the great ideal that Sunday
was the Lord's day, the day that we should observe and rest and refrain from all types of
work.
</p><p>
While we had horses and our whitetop, we couldn't use them on the Sabbath
day. I remember on one occasion when my brother, Winslow, and I went to our father and
asked him if we might have the whitetop, he said, "Boys, we must follow so-and-so's
example, and you can't take the horses and the wagon out." That afternoon we saw
so-and-so's boys out in their whitetop, so the following Sunday we came to father and said,
"Father, may we take the whitetop out today?" "What did I tell you last Sunday, boys?" 
"Well, you said to follow so-and-so's example, and last Sunday we saw them out in their
whitetop." Father said, "Well, we won't follow anybody's example. We will set one of our
own. You can't have the whitetop."
</p><p>
ADVICE FROM CHURCH LEADERS
</p><p>
Some years later, after Brigham Young had spoken about the Sabbath day he was again called
upon to speak of it. Apparently they hadn't moved away, those who desired to break the
Sabbath, for he said, "Now remember, my brethren, those who go skating, buggy riding, or on
excursions on the Sabbath day&mdash;and there is a great deal of this practice&mdash;are weak in the faith.
Gradually, little by little, the spirit of their religion leaks out of their hearts, their affections
and in time they begin to see faults in their brethren, faults in the doctrines of the Church,
faults in the organization, and at last they leave the kingdom of God and go to destruction."
</p><p>
He felt very seriously about this subject, as have all of the men who have presided over this
Church. All of them have stressed this important matter. I think that perhaps the greatest and
finest expression was by President Grant when he said, "The Lord's day is a holy day and not
a holiday. It has been set apart as a day of rest and worship, and we accept the Lord's day as
the first day of the week in accordance with the instructions given by the Prophet Joseph
Smith. A sacred Sabbath begets reverence for God." And how essential that is. "It is not
pleasing in his sight that the day be given over to pleasure-seeking in places of amusement or
elsewhere. Sunday Schools and meetings have been so arranged that they meet the
convenience of the people and leave a considerable portion of the Sabbath day without
Church appointments. We earnestly appeal to the people to keep their appointments faithfully
and to utilize that part of Sunday not appointed, for meetings in promoting family association
in the home, with the purpose of stimulating and establishing greater home fealty, a closer
companionship among parents and children; and more intimate relations among all kindred.
We believe it is unnecessary for families to go beyond their homes or those of their kindred
for the relaxation and associations which are proper for the Sabbath day, and we therefore
discourage more traveling than is necessary for this purpose and attendance upon appointed
meetings. Let all unnecessary labor be suspended, and let no encouragement be given by
members of the Church at places of amusement and recreation on the
Sabbath day. If Sunday is spent in our meetings and in our homes, great blessings will come
to our families and to our communities."
</p><p>
So I would appeal, my brethren, to you who are the presiding officers in the Church, that in
your actions nothing can be laid at your door that would cause anyone to start on that path of
desecrating the Sabbath day, and I would bring to your minds that message which was written
by the finger of God upon tablets of stone:
</p><p>
Remember the sabbath day, to keep it holy. Six days shalt thou labour, and do all thy work:
But the seventh day is the sabbath of the Lord thy God: in it thou shalt not do any work,
thou, nor thy son, nor thy daughter, thy manservant, nor thy maidservant, nor thy cattle, nor
thy stranger that is within thy gates: For in six days the Lord made heaven and earth, the sea,
and all that in them is, and rested the seventh day: wherefore the Lord blessed the sabbath
day, and hallowed it (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8-11#8">Ex. 20:8-11</a>).
</p><p>
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
