<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Expanded Indian Program</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1956, pp. 52-58</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brothers and sisters, I should like to speak to you today about our Lamanite
brothers. I quote from Nephite prophets: 
</p><p>
. . . thus saith our God: I will afflict thy seed by the hand of the Gentiles;
nevertheless, I will soften the hearts of the Gentiles, that they shall be like unto a
father to them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/18#18">2 Ne. 10:18</a>).
</p><p>
And again: 
</p><p>
. . . the Lord God will raise up a mighty nation among the Gentiles, yea, even upon
the face of this land; and by them shall our seed be scattered.<br />
And after our seed is scattered the Lord God will proceed to do a marvelous work
among the Gentiles, which shall be of great worth unto our seed; wherefore, it is
likened unto their being nourished by the Gentiles and being carried in their arms and
on their shoulders (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/22/7-8#7">1 Ne. 22:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
Relatively little progress had been made since Columbus discovered America, until recent
years. Hundreds of thousands of Indians were killed by the invading Gentiles from Europe,
128,000 in New England alone, according to historians. The rest were pushed back, scattered,
and finally placed on reservations. The battle of America continued for hundreds of years, the
red people fighting for their families, their homes, their hunting grounds, and their very
existence.
</p><p>
Finally the scriptures are being fulfilled. "Nursing fathers and mothers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/49/23#23">Isa. 49:23</a>) are being raised up to
bring the blessings of freedom and education and health to the sons of Lehi. We can
remember when the majority of Navajo children were without schools, and other tribes were
considerably limited. It is said that "The darkest hour is just before the dawn." But their day
is dawning. There has perhaps been more constructive consideration given to the Indian
people in the last decade than in the entire century before.
</p><p>
In 1947 the cry was raised: "The Navajos are freezing and starving." You remember, I am
sure. Truckloads of clothing and food were gathered here in Utah and taken from our Church
welfare storehouses for these distressed Indians. Simultaneously, the press took up the cry and
the warmhearted people of the nation, and particularly of the West, answered the call with
bedding, food, clothing, and money. The echoes resounded from ocean to ocean and a
sleeping nation roused itself.
</p><p>
Pictures and stories of want and starvation were printed in newspapers and magazines;
pressures were brought to bear upon officials; and the important prophecies began to be
fulfilled and the arms of the Gentile nation which had scattered the Lamanites now opened to
enfold them, and the shoulders which once were used to push them into reservations, now
squared away to carry these deprived ones to their destiny. Even within the past two or three
years, great strides have been made. Education, the common denominator and leveler, is
coming to the red man. The clinic and hospital are available to him. Indian children are being
born in hospitals; sanitation is being taught; and the sun is rising on the Indian world with the
government, churches, and many agencies becoming nursing parents" to them.
</p><p>
Yesterday tribal people resisted education; today they grasp it eagerly. Not long ago nearly all
Indians were illiterate and unschooled; today in 1956 nearly every Indian child in America
may have some training. Yesterday Indian children were kidnapped from their parents and
forced to school. Today parents beg for schools, and children eagerly attend.
</p><p>
     Indian life is swiftly changing<br />
     Like the sand in wind-swept dunes,<br />
     Ever changing 'stablished patterns,<br />
     New strong forces, healing wounds.<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;          (Spencer W. Kimball.)
</p><p>
Mr. Paul Jones, chairman of the Navajo Council, recalls his childhood in his inaugural speech
of April 4, 1955: 
</p><p>
The salvation and hope of our Navajo people lies in education . . . at one time we
made our living on livestock and a little cornpatch. When we returned from Fort
Sumner there were 9,000 of us. There are now 76,000 . . . We must be educated in
order to be absorbed with the rest of the people of these United States . . . those of
you who have been educated must tell your people of the benefits of education . . . It
is the greatest hope that we have for our Navajo people . . . When they returned (from
Ft. Sumner) they were reluctant to send their children to school. The Federal
Government had to send police out to gather the children for school . . . I remember
myself distinctly. I was of school age at that time. My father and mother used to hide
me under sheepskins and blankets when they saw a person coming who represented the
schools. I was the only boy in the family. They used to hide me when they saw the
school people or policemen coming. However, one bright day, they made a mistake.
My parents were not on the lookout, and someone saw me, even though I was hiding
behind the hogan. That person said: "That boy must go to school." So away I went to
school. But our eyes are now open to the advantages that school has for us . . .
</p><p>
Today, Mr. Jones is the educated and cultured chief leader of the Navajo tribe.
</p><p>
The Treaty of 1868 with the Navajos stated that the government would provide a school and a
teacher for every thirty children between the ages of six and sixteen&mdash;"who can be induced or
compelled to attend school." Compulsion has now been replaced with an obsession for school
in many families. It is a far cry from today back to 1744 when the Virginia commissioners
made an offer to the chiefs of the Six Nations to educate six of their Indian boys.
</p><p>
It is of interest to note that in a feeble way the government has been trying for two hundred
years to educate the Indians, and from a few at the inception of the nation, today we approach
universal education for them.
</p><p>
The Virginia Commissioners received this reply from the Indian chiefs: 
</p><p>
Several of our young people were formerly brought up at the colleges of the Northern
Provinces; they were instructed in all your sciences; but when they came back to us,
they were bad runners; ignorant of every means of living in the woods; unable to bear
either cold or hunger; knew neither how to build a cabin, take a deer, or kill an
enemy; spoke our language imperfectly; were therefore neither fit for hunters,
warriors, or counselors; they were totally good for nothing. We are however not the
less obliged by your kind offer, though we decline accepting it. And to show our
grateful sense of it, if the Gentlemen of Virginia will send us a dozen of their sons, we
will take great care of their education, instruct them in all we know, and make <i>men</i> of
them.
</p><p>
That comes from the old records, and Dr. Ernest Wilkinson quoted it in the Indian Congress
here last week.
</p><p>
Now may I tell you of our most perfect program and unselfish adventure in human
relationships. The "outing" program had been attempted by others at times, but I think never
on this basis. As we began to bring into the Church many faithful Indians, almost their first
desire was that their children should have the schooling and church training which the
non-Indian children enjoyed. Indian families working among us here in our beet, cotton, or
potato fields saw the luxury enjoyed by white children who were well-fed and well-dressed, in
comfortable homes, going to excellent schools daily. They saw their own little deprived
fellows who must follow the family to the faraway fields so parents could earn money to feed
them. Their dreams and yearnings finally forced the affectionate parents to become bold
enough to approach a white employer: "Would you let our little girl stay with you and go to
school after we have gone back to the reservation? She will be a good girl and cause you no
trouble."
</p><p>
With the earnestness in their eyes and the pleading in their voices, who could resist? The
experiment began. A few children were left in homes. They were happy and grateful. The
foster parents were pleased, and neighbors wished also to participate. On the reservation,
natural parents told their neighbors, who also wrote pleading letters for their own children.
The number increased to twenty, sixty, eighty, and then last year to 253. It grew like Topsy.
Arrangements at first were between natural parents on the reservation and willing foster
parents in Utah; but when the Church determined to give it support, the plan was given legal
status and brought under the Utah State Department of Public Welfare, children's service,
through the state license of the Relief Society. Inasmuch as it is illegal for anyone without a
state license to engage in any way in the placing or receiving of children, it is urged that
neither missionaries nor members engage in the independent placement of children.
</p><p>
Here is how the plan works: 
</p><p>
In August more than 250 Indian children move northward. The Begay family is typical. The
Begays have a team and spring wagon and ride slowly across the hills and valleys and barren
stretches to the gathering place. In the miles and miles of travel, Father and Mother Begay
have time to discuss with Ruth and Billie the great adventure ahead: "Here is your
opportunity," Father Begay is saying. "Our Church is taking you to a good Mormon home in
Utah where you will be kindly treated and may go to school. You must be grateful and study
hard and learn."
</p><p>
And now Mother Begay, in colorful velveteen, and her hair in a bob, is adding: "These
Church members are doing this in the goodness of their hearts. They are not paid for the food
and clothes and shelter and training that they are giving you. They will treat you like one of
their own. You must do your part like the children of the family."
</p><p>
At last they reach the Gap in northern Arizona. Other Indian families are arriving also in
wagons and pickups. The kindly driver loads their belongings into the chartered busses. Our
friendly Church chaperone meets the family and the children. Farewells are said, and tears are
shed as affectionate parents and children part for the school term. Though already homesick
and lonely at heart, neither parents nor children would change their minds, so grateful are
they for the opportunities just opening. The Begays and the Chees and the Biligodys hitch up
their horses, and with a tearful happiness, drive to their homes on the reservation, while the
busses, filled with eager, excited children, drive northward.
</p><p>
One observer wrote this of the parting: 
</p><p>
There were a few tears&mdash;tears of premature homesickness from youngsters leaving the
reservation for the first time and suddenly reluctant and fearful of the future. Tears
from little brothers and sisters, too young or otherwise unqualified for the great
adventure. And there were a few furtive tears from parents, realizing at this moment of
parting how long and lonely the months stretched out before spring vacation.
</p><p>
Just a few hours and the busses are in Richfield, Utah. The kindly chaperone has kept the
children happy and looked after their every need. It is very early in the morning at the
reception center, but it is already a hive of industry, and keen expectancy is in the air. Sevier
Stake becomes the host, and the stake presidency, members of the priesthood, and the Relief
Society sisters are waiting. There is the smell of bacon in the air, and the young redskins,
some of whom have been here before, file out of the busses and into the Church dining room
for bacon, eggs, milk, fruit, and cereal, prepared by the Relief Society sisters.
</p><p>
Soon breakfast is over. The processing is begun. Kind sisters take the girls in one building
and understanding priesthood brethren the boys in another where they are bathed and
shampooed and made ready for the clinic. The food, soap, shampoo, and other things are
furnished free by the Church. All who assist are volunteer workers, doing this like all other of
their Church work, without remuneration. Six hundred towels are furnished free by a generous
linen company, typical of many other favors. The children line up for the clinic where several
physicians, furnished by the United States Health Service, senior medical students,
technicians, and several nurses, on loan from the Utah State Health Department, all go to
work. The little folk's chests are x-rayed; their hearts, eyes, skin, ears, teeth, and temperatures
are checked, and a complete record made. Their fears are quieted by sweet, sympathetic
women when tears of unhappiness follow the needle-jabbing of immunization and the blood
test. They know this is for their good. Lunchtime comes, and another appetizing meal is
enjoyed from welfare supplies. There is some rest, and there is supervised play and a movie.
</p><p>
Then come the foster families, hundreds of them, from all over Utah: unpaid families whose
only desire is to provide unselfishly for the child and to "mother" and "father" him and train
and guide him. They are driving in from Kanab and Salt Lake City; from Moroni and
Escalante; from St. George and the Uintah Basin-unselfish families anticipating the new
arrival to their family. There are stake presidents, bishops, mayors, editors, doctors,
farmers&mdash;the finest people in the communities of Utah and of the world&mdash;each family to receive for the
school term an Indian child, accepted by them to become a real part of the family. The white
children present excitedly speculate as to which of the Indian youngsters, so hungrily eating
luncheon, is to be their new brother or sister. In the stake tabernacle films are shown on
Indian culture, and a talk is given on the part each is to play in this glorious human drama.
Four days of this processing follow.
</p><p>
Now, for the school term, the Indian child is on a par with his new brothers and sisters. He
rides horses, feasts at picnics, does chores, goes swimming, takes music lessons. He goes to
school and enters into every Church, civic, and community activity on an equal basis. Before
the meal, the new family member takes his turn in family prayers and blessing the food. He
goes to Sunday School and priesthood meeting. The little ones go to Primary and the larger
ones to MIA, and all the family go together to Sacrament meeting. The child attends seminary
and is advanced in priesthood and auxiliary activities. Many do baptism work in the temples.
In school he fits into the regular classes, and if his language is faulty, likely the teacher will
gladly give up her noon hour to tutor him. Foster parents write to natural parents, sending
pictures. Case workers visit every child and family monthly and visit schoolteachers and
principals often and assure themselves that harmony and understanding prevail.
</p><p>
The Indian children have proved themselves to be alert, brilliant, and responsive. They often
take the lead in their classes, being elected to school offices, and they graduate from many
high schools in Utah. They are going out into employment and are making good. The
employer of one of our Indian girls in office work said: 
</p><p>
"She is one of our best workers. I wish we had many more like her."
</p><p>
Four months and Christmas comes. The children remain in Utah where they share the
Christmas gifts, parties, and other kindnesses equal to and the same as the white children.
Latter-day Saints have a keen interest in the Indians and are willing to share with and
sacrifice for them.
</p><p>
Five more eventful months pass and 250 Indian children are on their way back to the
reservation. Though some might like to remain in Utah, all are sent home to keep welded the
natural family ties. Again farewells are said, and tears are shed, and they reluctantly leave
their Utah homes and the tearful family whose home and hearts they have been sharing, and
they fill the chartered busses again. The selected bus driver is exceptionally kind; the
chaperone is most solicitous. No baggage is mixed; no children are lost; and a happy group
turns homeward. Home! Family! Hours of pleasant travel, and the distribution center is
reached. The missionaries are here to greet them, and the Indian families to enfold them
gratefully to their hearts. For three happy months they will cement family ties on the
reservation, and then, off for another year of school.
</p><p>
Much planning and prayer and fasting have gone into our program. In the summer the social
workers travel through the reservation. They visit each home or hogan and get acquainted
with the children and the parents, catching the spirit of the family, its background, the training
of the children, and their individual needs. With our missionaries, who nurture them
constantly, these special workers urge the parents to have the children examined and treated
for dental and medical needs. Proper legal contracts are secured, and arrangements are made
whereby missionaries will pilot them the coming August to the proper place for embarkation.
Careful studies are made for efficient and understanding placement for the coming year.
</p><p>
Now the workers return to the Utah communities and visit the white families who have
previously signified their willingness to cooperate. The home and its facilities are studied to
be sure the child and family will be comfortable and happy. The family is interviewed and,
through a visit to the bishop of the ward, is evaluated and their worthiness determined. No
child of trusting Indian Church members is placed in a broken home or one which is not an
exemplary one. No child goes into a home where liquor is used or where there is friction or
delinquent children. He goes into a well-ordered home where there is the rare combination of
kindness and discipline, firmness and affection; into a praying family, a religious, devoted
family of character, faith, and love. Here is opportunity at its best for the Indian to get away
from his worst enemies: idleness, liquor, and immorality.
</p><p>
It is heartwarming to see the friendly cooperation of government, state, and local and school
officials and teachers. Our Church classes have absorbed the little fellows into their groups,
and timid, shrinking children have become happy, normal playmates and workmates and
family members. One young Indian, after five consecutive years with a delightful,
cooperative family, graduated from a Utah high school where he was student-body president,
and with a $350.00 Standard Oil scholarship, attended Brigham Young University; he is now
in the Northern States Mission on a full, regular mission. Two other Indian boys are filling
regular missions in the Southwest Indian Mission, where Oneida Indian girls have also filled
missions. This is the beginning. The future is most promising.
</p><p>
We expect our graduating youth will continue from these high schools into Brigham Young
University. At first there were a few, and some of them discontinued, but last year with
thirty-four representing eighteen tribes from east to west, and this year with even more, they
are already taking hold and stabilizing themselves. From now on we expect that Indians in
ever-increasing numbers will be numbered in the graduating classes of Brigham Young
University.
</p><p>
The Church has generously provided for an intermediate program whereby Indian students
who have come a little short of collegiate requirements may have special tutorial service from
skilled teachers. Scholarships are provided to assist worthy students in the university, but
many of our Indian children are already paying their entire way.
</p><p>
Hundreds of our Indian youth are receiving character-building and religious training wherever
they go in government schools in Kansas, Oklahoma, Oregon, California, Nevada, Arizona,
New Mexico, and in the great Intermountain Indian School at Brigham City, Utah, where we
have a branch of the Church comprised of Indians. Here, President David O. McKay last
winter dedicated the commodious chapel near the school wherein our youth are taught correct
principles, all the virtues and the doctrines of the gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Our program is appreciated by the Indian people. When some opposition threatened the
program last summer in one area, a petition was sent to us signed by many Indian parents
pleading for the continuance of the program, and reservation officials were also approached.
The petition read: 
</p><p>
We parents feel that your organization has done wonders for our children, and we wish
you would try every effort to place our children this year.
</p><p>
One prominent non-member observer wrote us: 
</p><p>
You have the most perfect program for Navajo children that has ever been initiated to
this time. We are all grateful for its outstanding success.
</p><p>
Another said: 
</p><p>
I have never enjoyed a more wonderful experience in wholehearted cooperation and
complete harmony of effort than I enjoyed at Richfield.
</p><p>
A tribal leader wrote us: 
</p><p>
. . . This is very gratifying to our Navajo people in that your organization has taken
such interest in our Navajo children . . . We deeply appreciate your service to our
Navajo people . . . There have been several notifications reporting the foster homes
for educational purposes by your child placing agency as a very important and
noteworthy help . . .
</p><p>
Two missionaries wrote, when the children had returned home for the summer: 
</p><p>
Yesterday in our testimony meeting, a mother of one of the girls who went to Utah
this year got up and told how grateful she was to our Father in heaven that her girl
had been able to go up to Utah where she could learn to pray, speak English better,
cook, sew, and gain the schooling that she wanted her child to have that she herself
didn't get.
</p><p>
One sister wrote of the first Sacrament meeting after the return of the children from Utah,
how without embarrassment they had taken part in the services, giving talks, songs, and how
some had borne testimony with such poise and impressiveness that the parents were amazed,
as were Indian children who had been away to other schools.
</p><p>
In our great country times are changing. Schools are provided for practically every Indian
child, and tribal funds are made available for determined but impecunious students. True
religion and faith in the Eternal God are replacing superstition; the physician is taking the
place of the medicine man; and administration by the priesthood is replacing the sand patterns
and the signs for the Latter-day Saint members. Young couples are obtaining licenses from
court clerks and being married by ministers and bishops. Bodies are being buried much the
same as the white dead. The Indians who still place on the grave meats and fruits and other
foods cannot understand why the dead of the white man can smell the flowers any more than
the Indian dead can enjoy the food. The destructive custom of burning the home and its
contents when death occurs therein is giving way. One of our sweet Apache sisters wrote this
at the death of her husband: 
</p><p>
I live in my house. I do not burn it like other Indians. I believe what the missionaries
tell me. I think they are my brother.
</p><p>
This is our adventure in good citizenship and righteous living, our experiment in human
relationships carried on by this, the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. Knowing the
origin and destiny of the red men and believing the promises of God as recorded in the Book
of Mormon, our people are willing to sacrifice for the progress and development of these
whose deprivations pyramided mountain high but whose curse is now being lifted. Hundreds
more sacrificing Latter-day Saints may yet have the opportunity of providing temporary
homes for Lehi's children to get an education and to learn the gospel and to become Church
leaders.
</p><p>
This is not a proselyting program, for we bring from the reservations those Indian children
who are already members of the Church and whose families generally are members. The
program will make good young people, stalwart adults. It will fortify them against the evils of
the world; it will train them to become self-sufficient; it will develop them into leaders
prepared to return to their own people and bring to them the benefits which can come from
education.
</p><p>
This program has many advantages: It has at once the multiple advantages of the boarding
school, the day school, the home, the refining and cultural influences of an improved
community.
</p><p>
The children are taught in superior schools, fully accredited, and among the best in the nation.
They have sufficient companionship of their own race to retain their pride in and love for
their own people, for in the same community and school are other Indian young people. They
have the environment of the best communities where are found the least in the world's vices
and the most of its culture and refinement. They retain their family ties with natural parents
by correspondence, pictures, relayed reports, and also letters through the case workers, and
they return to their homes for the summer months to keep bound their home and family loves
and loyalties. They grow naturally into the culture of America at its best, attending with a
minority of their own group and a majority of the non-Indian children, activities in school,
community, church, and family. They are not institutionalized but individualized and become
recognized members of the family where they are integrated and "counted in" for every family
pleasure, adventure, or sacred experience.
</p><p>
Our program is unique. Here is no family of marginal income who must take in a boarder to
supplement the family living. Here is no mercenary care. But here non-Indian families in a
very real and lovable way absorb the Indian children as new members of the family. These
families, give, give, and give as only dedicated people will give. There is no remuneration for
them; but their total compensation for the food, clothes, shelter, care, and love they give is the
satisfaction which comes in giving opportunity for an enriched life to one who could not
otherwise have it.
</p><p>
We rejoice in the greatly accelerated schooling of Indian children by the government, the
states, and other churches and agencies, but we present this program of training in home and
school and community as the finest program conceived of man for the rapid and permanent
advancement and progress of the Indian child so long deprived. Let them have one generation
of this sustained program, and see a new Indian world of prosperity, culture, and happiness.
</p><p>
In conclusion we say: God bless these selfless hundreds of families who have become and are
yet to become "nursing fathers and mothers"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/49/23#23">Isa. 49:23</a>)
who will continue to carry the chosen children of
the ancient prophet Lehi "in their arms and upon their shoulders"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/22/8#8">1 Ne. 22:8</a>), I pray, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
