<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Thomas E. McKay</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thomas E. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1946, pp. 149-154</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President Smith and counselors and my brethren and sisters: I love music. I should like to
take this opportunity to congratulate the music committee or whoever it is that has been
responsible in arranging for the inspiring music that we have had during this conference. The
very beautiful, appropriate music furnished by the Singing Mothers on Friday brought us all
closer to our Heavenly Father, and then we were thrilled yesterday by those more than a
hundred young voices from the Manti district of the South Sanpete Stake. I attended a
conference a few weeks ago in that stake, and was so impressed with the singing of that
young lady soloist that I asked the stake president about her. I was informed that she is one of
a family of thirteen, in fact she is the <i>thirteenth</i>, a very lucky number in her case, I should
say. And then the inspiration that we receive from this great Tabernacle choir and the organ
and our one and only Brother Evans whom we love so well. No one can estimate the good
that this great organization is doing. I join with Brother Kirkham in suggesting that we make
more in our organizations and our wards and stakes of our music. There should be a choir in
every ward, choruses, Aaronic Priesthood choruses, girls' choruses, and others. I know in the
mission field what a great value our choirs are. Scores of families are in the Church today
because of our choirs. Our friends who love music and can sing are invited to join the choir,
and after singing the songs of Zion for a while, and associating with the missionaries and
members, they begin studying the gospel, and then, quite often, apply for baptism. These
contacts change their lives. As one young man expressed in a testimony meeting, where he
was confirmed a member of the Church, his getting acquainted with the missionaries and the
members, and especially the singing of the songs of Zion, had entirely changed his outlook on
life. He said, "It is really like coming from the darkness into the light."
</p><p>
The Savior declared:
</p><p>
I am the light of the world: he that followeth me shall not walk in darkness, but shall have
the light of life (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/12#12">John 8:12</a>).
</p><p>
RELEASED AS ACTING PRESIDENT OF THE EUROPEAN MISSION
</p><p>
With the appointment of Elder Ezra Taft Benson as president of the European Mission, I was
given a very kind complimentary letter, signed by the First Presidency, releasing me from my
very interesting service in looking after the European Mission. Because of the war my work
has had to be carried on largely by correspondence.
</p><p>
I wish to take this opportunity to express publicly my sincere thanks and appreciation for the
wonderful opportunity that this appointment, and also, and especially, my other missions in
Europe, have afforded me. These missions, spaced as they have been, have given me an
exceptionally fine opportunity to observe the practical working of the gospel-to see what a
blessing it really is to all those who accept and obey its teachings, to see them come into the
light after walking in darkness.
</p><p>
LABORS IN EUROPEAN MISSIONS
</p><p>
My first mission was from 1900 to 1903. I was home six years and then was again honored
by another call, this time as president of the Swiss-German Mission, which comprised at that
time&mdash;1909 to 1912&mdash;Switzerland, Germany, Austria-Hungary, and France. I found that an
absence of six years had made quite a difference; many of the children who were, for
example, Sunday School pupils, were now Sunday School officers and teachers. I saw the
development of these young people as well as all other members who had accepted and were
living the gospel. The acceptance of the gospel had given these people also an entirely
different outlook on life.
</p><p>
Twenty-five years after this second mission I again had the privilege of returning to Europe,
with my headquarters again in beautiful Switzerland. The children who were pupils in the
Sunday School in 1900, and Sunday School officers and teachers in 1909 were now, many of
them at least, married and had children of their own; some were or had been missionaries;
some had emigrated. As I say, these three missions, spaced as they were, gave me a most
wonderful opportunity to see what obedience to the gospel of Jesus Christ will really do for
people. It had touched every phase of their lives. Their supervised recreation had influenced
them socially; the courses of study and outlines for the priesthood quorums and the auxiliary
organizations, especially the Sunday School of the Church, had afforded them splendid
educational opportunities. They had been affected financially through the great tithing system
and fast offerings. Some who had previously spent their money for tobacco, beer
and wine and liquor were now using that money to purchase better clothes,
more conveniences for the home, better entertainment, and there was as a result more love in
the home. The gospel affected them also and especially morally and spiritually. Oh, of course,
some were not strong enough to change their way of life and overcome their life-long habits;
these as stated, for reasons best known to themselves, had found the requirements too much.
We find that true here at home, even more so I think than in the mission field. It is so easy,
for example, to find other things to do on Sunday than attend meetings. This seems to have
always been true; at least I find the following admonition in one of President Brigham
Young's sermons on the subject of the Sabbath day:
</p><p>
Now, remember, my brethren, those who go skating, riding, or on excursions on the Sabbath
day&mdash;and there is a great deal of this practiced&mdash;are weak in the faith. Gradually, little by little,
little by little, the spirit of their religion leaks out of their hearts and their affections, and by
and by they begin to see faults in their brethren, faults in the doctrines of the Church, faults
in the organization, and at last they leave the Kingdom of God and go to destruction.
(<i>Discourses</i>, p. 225, first edition; p. 165, 1943 edition.)
</p><p>
When I read this sentence: "Gradually, little by little, little by little, the spirit of their religion
leaks out of their hearts and their affections," I thought of a statement which I recently read
which says:
</p><p>
We never lose our religion by a blowout, usually it is just a slow leak.
</p><p>
And also this:
</p><p>
Many treat their religion as a spare tire, they never use it except in times of emergency.
</p><p>
COMMANDMENTS GIVEN FOR OUR DEVELOPMENT
</p><p>
What President Young states with reference to keeping the Sabbath day holy is equally true
with reference to the breaking of the Word of Wisdom, remaining away from sacrament and
priesthood meetings, taking the name of the Lord in vain, the nonpayment of tithes and
offerings. Tithing for many is one of the most difficult of spiritual exercises we are asked to
take. And do you know why? Because it strikes at one of the most effective weapons used by
Satan for the destruction of mankind, namely, the love of money. A person or a nation that
will pay an honest tithing will never worship gold instead of God. The love of money, we are
told, is the root of all evil. At any rate we all know that it is the love of money, of power, of
dominion of the sea as well as of the land and the people themselves that has caused many of
our wars&mdash;yes, the principle of tithing properly understood and lived would go a long way to
doing away with wars. This commandment and all others given by our Father in heaven are
for our spiritual development, for our happiness and joy in this life. They are to keep us alive
and growing spiritually, our guideposts. They are reflectors along life's
highway to keep us from becoming lost, or, to quote a famous radio voice:
</p><p>
We are much like travelers driving along a highway by night. There faithfully placed are
reflector signs to warn of hazardous curves and dangerous crossroads. The light of our cars
picks up the signs, and they reflect to us their warning or direction&mdash;<i>if we have the light!</i> But
if our light is dark the signs are dark. They have no meaning for the unlighted lamps.
</p><p>
These commandments I have referred to, and others, are given us as means of keeping the
light burning, keeping alive spiritually. One of Dr. Karl G. Maeser's sentence sermons says:
</p><p>
One who has lost the spirit of the Lord is spiritually dead.
</p><p>
THE GOSPEL APPRECIATED IN WAR-TORN COUNTRIES
</p><p>
The gospel has certainly been a light shining in the darkness for our members in the war-torn
countries, and also and especially for our servicemen and women during the terrible war years
just ended&mdash;at least we hope they are ended. Scores of letters have been received testifying of
the comfort and blessings of the gospel. I will take time to refer to only one or two. Here is a
paragraph written by one of our Mormon chaplains, addressed to the servicemen's committee:
</p><p>
Not many days ago I had a deeply spiritual experience that gave me added proof of the power
of the gospel to make men brothers spiritually By chance I read in one of the theater news
sheets the reports of a Christmas program conducted by Protestant and Catholic German
P.O.W. chaplains stationed at the 99th Field Hospital near Pisa. The news item stated that the
special music was presented by the P.O.W. orchestra and a "Mormon" vocal soloist. The
following day I went in search of this "Mormon" P.O.W., and with the help of an American
chaplain I found him, a former Dresden District missionary, who served for a year and a half
under President Rees in the East German Mission&mdash;Elder Hans Karl Schade, 25 Sebnitzer
Street, Dresden, Germany. A few days previous to our meeting, the theater chaplain, Colonel
Frank Brown, had met Elder Schade at a worship service and when he found Elder Schade
was a Latter-day Saint, he gave him my name. And so when I first saw Elder Schade in the
eye clinic where he now works, he extended his right hand and said, as he walked towards
me, "Brother Braithwaite, thank God for this meeting." I shall never forget that
expression&mdash;nor Elder Schade. In the presence of another chaplain and my interpreter, we
spoke with complete freedom and with an understanding that destroys distrust, vengeance, or
hate. We met on common ground, and thanked God for our fellowship in the Gospel. It was
the time when I asked him to sing for me and our men, and to attend our L.D.S. services in
Leghorn, that he reminded me he was a prisoner of war. However, even the restrictions
involved caused no seeming barriers in our relationship. An understanding commanding
officer gave permission for him to sing for us, and for us to go to his office to visit him.
</p><p>
The work of the army occupation tests the moral fiber of our men as perhaps it was not tested
in war. Temptations are great and many. It demands a clear understanding of why we are
here, patience, self-discipline, and self-control. Our job is important, and by and large, the
L.D.S. men are meeting the demands it makes on them.
</p><p>
LETTER ATTESTS FAITH OF EUROPEAN SAINTS
</p><p>
The following is quoted from a letter dated March 14, 1946, at Basel, Switzerland, from Elder
Ezra Taft Benson, president of the European Mission: I hope you will pardon me for reading
this first paragraph; it is quite personal but I do appreciate it so much:
</p><p>
Dear President McKay:
</p><p>
As you will note, I am here at the spot which you loved so much, with the people who love
you so dearly. Everywhere we have been we have found many people who know you and
love you and have asked about you and shown disappointment in your not being here.
</p><p>
As you probably know, we have already made a trip into France, Belgium, Holland, Norway,
Sweden, and Denmark, and now we are here in Switzerland preparatory to making a complete
tour of the Occupied Areas. We have already attended district conference at Karlsruhe last
Sunday. During the next two and a half weeks we will be in the military zones and in
Czechoslovakia. From there we will return to Basel, and then continue on to Paris, Belgium,
and Holland again before returning to London.
</p><p>
I will not comment on conditions which we found except to say that the deep faith of the
Saints in these missions has been a source of joy and satisfaction. The willing service and
clean, exemplary lives of the many Latter-day Saint servicemen who have been among the
people of Europe have left a splendid impression over here.
</p><p>
Yes, the gospel is a light shining in this war-torn world, and it will also show the way to a
permanent peace if our "Father's children," as President Smith so kindly and tolerantly refers
to his fellow men, would but do the will of the Father. He loves us; he is our Father-we are
all his children; and he has given us the gospel for our happiness and joy in this life. We
could have a heaven on earth if we would but keep the commandments of God.
</p><p>
. . . men are, that they might have joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/25#25">2 Ne. 2:25</a>).
</p><p>
The Savior says:
</p><p>
If any man will do his will, he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I
speak of myself (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>).
</p><p>
TESTIMONY COMES THROUGH SPIRIT OF GOD
</p><p>
I cannot give you a testimony of the divinity of the work&mdash;you cannot give me one&mdash;it must
come through the Spirit of God. There are laws governing these spiritual matters as well as
the physical and mental. President Grant used to quote so often:
</p><p>
There is a law, irrevocably decreed in heaven before the foundations of this world, upon
which all blessings are predicated&mdash;And when we obtain any blessing from God, it is by
obedience to that law upon which it is predicated
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/20-21#20">D&amp;C 130:20-21</a>).
</p><p>
And a testimony of the divinity of the Church is received only by obedience to the spiritual
law&mdash;"If any man will do his will, he shall know"&mdash;that means study, work, pray, keep the
commandments, and our Heavenly Father will reveal to each of us, as he did
to Peter, the divinity of his Son. When Jesus asked Peter, "But whom say ye that I am?" Peter
answered, "Thou art the Christ, the son of the Living God." Notice what Jesus answered: "For
flesh and blood"&mdash;the Christ was flesh and blood&mdash;"for flesh and blood hath not revealed it
unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/15-17#15">Matt. 16:15-17</a>).
</p><p>
I feel very humble and extremely grateful that I am able to bear you a similar testimony. I too
know that God lives, that Jesus is the Christ, that this is his Church, the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints, not the church of Joseph Smith. He was the Servant however, the
prophet called of God to establish the Church in this dispensation, with the same organization
that existed at the time of the Savior, and it is here for the last time, never again to be taken
away or given to another people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/44#44">Dan. 2:44</a>),
until the Savior shall come to rule and reign in person. May
we keep oil in our lamps&mdash;keep the light burning, that others seeing our good works, our
example, may glorify our Father in heaven
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/16#16">Matt. 5:16</a>),
I pray, in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
