<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Not Yet, Dear Lord, Not Yet"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1959, pp. 95-98</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Clark President Moyle, President Smith, my beloved brothers and
sisters, and the radio and television audience; I am very grateful for the prayer this morning
of a wonderful man, former mission president, Brother Theodore Jacobsen. I know that the
Lord will answer that prayer, and I shall be grateful to you for your prayers this morning
because I confess to you that I feel very humble and very weak.
</p><p>
As I have listened to these inspired messages today and yesterday and the day before, I have
thought of the words of Riddle: "Those who know books know much, but those who know
nature know more, and those who know God have reached the goal of human wisdom."
</p><p>
This great choir, I am sure, has uplifted us this morning along with thousands and perhaps
millions who have heard them. They are a great credit to the Church and to the city, to the
state and the nation. These choir leaders, the choir members, and the officers, are not just
good musicians: They are good Latter-day Saints, and they are wonderful
missionaries. They are devoted. I have a very choice brother singing in the choir, and I know
how deeply devoted and what great love he has for this organization. May God bless every
single one of them.
</p><p>
I know we have been deeply touched this morning by the inspiring address of President Henry
D. Moyle. May I be pardoned if I tell you this morning that I thought his humble and yet
beautiful address was just like the prayer he offered a few days ago in an upper room of the
temple when the General Authorities met there preparatory to this great conference. As he
spoke to you this morning, he had a prayer in his heart for you, the membership of the
Church, and for our friends not of the Church; and as he offered that prayer in the temple, in
the true order of prayer, I felt sure our Father in heaven had called him to his present
position. Brother Moyle has no selfish interests. He has lived above selfishness. He will be a
great blessing to the membership of this Church. Those of our friends not in the Church, as
well as all of us, will sustain him and pray for him in the great load that he has to carry. The
mantle of Presidency has fallen on his shoulders. Last night the priesthood assembled was
deeply blessed as a result of his marvelous address. President Moyle will be a great comfort
and blessing and assistance to President McKay and President Clark, whom he dearly loves.
</p><p>
A year ago it was the privilege of my wife and myself to visit many countries of Europe, and
only by coincidence we came into countries, missions, branches, and districts where Brother
and Sister Moyle had recently visited. I have never heard anyone speak so beautifully as the
humble Saints of Europe spoke about President and Sister Moyle. I think we will never know
the amount of good and the help that he rendered to so many of our humble Saints in far-off
countries of Europe. In many places he spoke to them in their native tongue. How grateful
they were for his presence. Sister Moyle likewise spoke to them. They are dearly loved in the
far-off countries of Europe.
</p><p>
Faith promotes faith, and testimony inspires testimony.
</p><p>
Today, if I may, I would like to take just one sentence from President McKay's beautiful
dedicatory prayer offered at the London Temple, and may I quote from that one sentence.
Speaking to the Lord, he said: "May we express overwhelming gratitude just to be alive."
</p><p>
I have a personal reason this morning for repeating this sentence from President McKay's
dedicatory prayer, because today I am truly grateful just to be alive. A few months ago I
became critically ill, and I learned then, as I have never learned before, that the line between
life and mortality and death and immortality is very thin indeed. It only takes a few seconds
yes, a very few seconds&mdash;to change from life and mortality to death and immortality, and I
saw how close one can get to the pale of death. I thought I was passing from this life to the
other, and I am truly grateful to the Lord that he permitted me to live. I fully realized then
that I was not prepared or ready for that passing, and it brought to my mind a few words that
I have read in a poem that goes something like this: 
</p><p>
"There is no time that we could set for parting.<br />
Ever our prayer would be," (as mine was)<br />
"Not yet, dear Lord, not yet, just another day."
</p><p>
I realized then more than ever before how dependent we are upon God, our Eternal Father,
even for the preservation of our lives. When one faces such a change, and we are all going to
face it, when we come close to it, many things come to our minds. I wonder if you are ready
for that change. I wonder if you are prepared to change from life to death. I believe that we
can become prepared and ready, and I concluded then that if the Lord would permit me to
live longer, I intended to live better so that I could die better.
</p><p>
Even though one may not be completely conscious or aware of what is going on about him, I
shall always be truly, humbly grateful, I hope, more grateful than ever before in my life for
the blessings and the prayers of my friends and family and my Brethren.
</p><p>
I am more grateful now because I realize the power of the Holy Priesthood of God that we
have heard so much about in this conference, often referred to as the greatest
power on the face of the earth. Some of the Brethren, who are prophets and servants of God,
came to my room in the hospital and laid their hands upon my head and anointed me with
holy consecrated oil, and then said unto me, "By the power of the Holy Priesthood, (Brother
Moyle just told us about that power) and in the name of Jesus Christ, we bless you that you
shall be well."
</p><p>
Do you know of any such power as that in the world? I bear testimony to you that the power
of the priesthood is here in the Church. I testify to you that one knows and one feels that
influence and that power, and is mindful of the blessings of the Lord received through the
administration of his servants holding that Holy Priesthood.
</p><p>
I am grateful to be alive, and I promised the Lord that I would bear testimony of that power
and that healing influence whenever I could have the strength to do so. I thank God, and I
hope that you thank God just to be alive. If you feel that you are not quite prepared or ready
for that change from life to death, let me urge you now&mdash;today&mdash;to change your life.
Remember it only takes a few seconds to change from life unto death. Let me urge you to
make the necessary adjustments in your life. Yes, make new resolutions. Turn back, if you
have reason to believe that you are on the wrong road, turn back now. It isn't too late.
</p><p>
May I quote from Amulek's testimony in the book of Alma, wherein he states: "For behold,
this life is the time for men to prepare to meet God; yea, behold the day of this life is the day
for men to perform their labors . . . for that same spirit which doth possess your bodies at the
time that ye go out of this life, that same spirit will have power to possess your body in that
eternal world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/32,34#32">Alma 34:32,34</a>).
</p><p>
Repent! Forsake those things that are wrong so that when the time comes for you to make
that change you can say as Paul said to Timothy: "I have fought a good fight, I have finished
my course, I have kept the faith: 
</p><p>
"Henceforth there is laid up for me crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous
judge, shall give me at that day: and not to me only, but unto all them also that love his
appearing" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/7-8#7">2 Tim. 4:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
And as quoted in the last verse of the hymn, "Come, Let Us Anew": 
</p><p>
"O that each in the day of his coming may say,<br />
'I have fought my way thro'&mdash;<br />
I have finished the work thou did'st give me to do.'<br />
O that each from his Lord may receive the glad word:<br /> 
'Well and faithfully done,<br />
Enter into my joy and sit down on my throne.'"
</p><p>
That reminds me of a prayer that I read recently, and may I quote: "Your day is almost done.
When the night and the morning meet, it will be an unalterable memory. So let no unkind
word, no careless doubting thought, no guilty secret, no neglected duty, no wisp of jealous
fog becloud its passing."
</p><p>
May God grant us the ability to change our lives where they need to be changed. I wonder if
we are absolutely satisfied with the life we are leading, with the thoughts we are thinking, and
with the deeds that we are doing. Every one of us can thank God, our Heavenly Father, for
our very life, and may we let God be our confidant&mdash;every one of us&mdash;that "thy Father
which seeth in secret himself shall reward thee openly"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/4#4">Matt. 6:4</a>).
</p><p>
As we pass from day to day, each day bringing us closer to the time when we will change
from life unto death may we ask: "Heavenly Father, for what purpose hast Thou given me this
day? To what end do its hours point? Help me not lightly to dismiss this question. Let me not
be carried unthinkingly with the drift of the times. Give me grace to reflect seriously upon the
course of my life, for days are numbered and precious."
</p><p>
May this group here today, and those who listen on the radio and television, resolve to live
better hereafter so that we can die better. May God bless every single one of you, that you
may live as long as you want to live and as long as you ought to live. Remember, each day of
life is so precious we must not let it carelessly slip away.
</p><p>
I bear testimony to you humbly that God lives, that he is our Father, that
Jesus Christ is our beloved Savior and our Elder Brother. Oh, how grateful we should be for
the power and the blessings of the Holy Priesthood of God that are constantly in our midst
today. Oh how important it is to have the faith and ability to recognize, not only our
blessings, but the source of those blessings.
</p><p>
God bless every one of you, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
