<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Be Yourself</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Henry D. Moyle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Henry D. Moyle, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1952, pp. 71-73</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
O that I were an angel, and could have the wish of mine heart, that I might go forth
and speak with the trump of God, with a voice to shake the earth, and cry repentance
unto every people! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/1#1">Alma 29:1</a>),
</p><p>
was the statement of the Prophet of old.
</p><p>
I am sure today in our lives many of us wish that we were something other than we are,
thinking likely that their lot is preferable to our own. But Alma said further: 
</p><p>
Yea, I would declare unto every soul, as with the voice of thunder, repentance and the
plan of redemption, that they should repent and come unto our God that there might
not be more sorrow upon all the face of the earth.
</p><p>
But behold, I am a man, and do sin in my wish, for I ought to be content with the
things which the Lord hath allotted unto me
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/2-3#2">Alma 29:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
I believe that we, as fellow workers in the priesthood, might well take to heart the admonition
of Alma and be content with that which God hath allotted us. We might well be assured that
we had something to do with our "allotment" in our pre-existent state. This would be an
additional reason for us to accept our present condition and make the best of it. It is what we
agreed to do.
</p><p>
We are told in the Doctrine and Covenants that:
</p><p>
He that keepeth his commandments receiveth truth and light, until he is glorified in
truth and knoweth all things.
</p><p>
Man was also in the beginning with God. Intelligence, or the light of truth, was not
created or made, neither indeed can be.
</p><p>
Then the Lord says: 
</p><p>
All truth is independent in that sphere in which God has placed it, to act for itself, as
all intelligence also; otherwise there is no existence
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/28-30#28">D&amp;C 93:28-30</a>).
</p><p>
For that to be true, we had our own free agency in our pre-mortal existence and whatever we
are today is likely the result of that which we willed to be heretofore. We unquestionably
knew before we elected to come to this earth the conditions under which we would here exist,
and live, and work. So little wonder it is that Alma of old said that we sin in the thought, or
in the desire or in the wish that we were someone other than ourselves. He said further: 
</p><p>
Now, seeing that I know these things, why should I desire more than to perform the
work to which I have been called?
</p><p>
Why should I desire that I were an angel, that I could speak unto all the ends of the
earth?
</p><p>
For behold, the Lord doth grant unto all nations, of their own nation and tongue to
teach his word, yea, in wisdom, all that he seeth fit that they should have; therefore we
see that the Lord doth counsel in wisdom, according to that which is just and true.
</p><p>
I know that which the Lord hath commanded me, and I glory in it. I do not glory of
myself, but I glory in that which the Lord hath commanded me; yea, and this is my
glory, that perhaps I may be an instrument in the hands of God to bring some soul to
repentance; and this is my joy
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/6-9#6">Alma 29:6-9</a>).
</p><p>
I have a conviction deep down in my heart that we are exactly what we should be, each one
of us, except as we may have altered that pattern by deviating from the laws of God here in
mortality. I have convinced myself that we all have those peculiar attributes, characteristics,
and abilities which are essential for us to possess in order that we may fulfil the full purpose
of our creation here upon this earth.
</p><p>
Once again, that allotment which has come to us from God is a sacred allotment. It is
something of which we should be proud, each one of us in our own right, and not wish that
we had somebody else's allotment. Our greatest success comes from being ourselves.
</p><p>
I think that we can console ourselves best by believing that whatever is our allotment in life,
whatever is our call in the priesthood, the Lord has been wise and just, and I might add,
merciful, in giving to us that which we need to accomplish the particular purpose of our call.
</p><p>
Furthermore, when we are in the full exercise of our faculties, and live in obedience to the
laws and commandments of God, that which we do in fulfillment of our call as holders of the
priesthood or officers in the Church is all that the people who are thus affected deserve.
Otherwise, God could not be just, and we know he is.
</p><p>
If we apply that principle to our lives, practically, does it not mean that when the bishop or
the stake president, or the President of the Church, calls upon us to fill an office or to render
a service to our fellow men, we should accept that call with an assurance that we possess the
essential qualifications given to us of our Heavenly Father in order to properly fulfil that
mission?
</p><p>
I think this is peculiarly true of those of us who may be called upon missions to go into the
world and preach the gospel of Jesus Christ, the highest calling that can come to man, that
call which the Savior of mankind gave to his disciples last of all, preceding his ascension to
heaven, to go into the world and preach the gospel to every nation, kindred, tongue, and
people.
</p><p>
I wish we could take to heart the admonition of President Joseph Fielding Smith today and
utilize those faculties which God gave us that have been religiously and sacredly allotted to us
for our use in the fulfillment of life's mission, that we might be fully qualified through our
own efforts, as well as through that endowment which we inherited and received from our
Father in heaven, to go into the world and preach his gospel to his children, who wait in
darkness to have truth and light brought to them by men who have been qualified by
endowment, and by perseverance, and by their own work, thus to accomplish this purpose.
</p><p>
We cannot be satisfied with the fact that we are Latter-day Saints and that we have received
the priesthood, and that various calls have come to us. If we have the true perspective of life
and of our mission, we would qualify ourselves from youth to meet any and every
responsibility that might come to us. That is peculiarly necessary for a people to believe and
to practice when they profess to the world that the men who preside over them in the Church
and in the priesthood of God have been called of God by those who are in authority to preach
the gospel and administer in the ordinances thereof.
</p><p>
If we truly believe the Fifth Article of Faith
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/5#5">A of F 1:5</a>), if we truly believe that we have such a mission
upon this earth to fulfil, then indeed will we be diligent in preparing ourselves to meet the
responsibilities of life. We shall feel qualified to go anywhere and to listen to any doctrine,
whether it be of man or of the devil, and be sure before we go that we will come back firm
in the knowledge of the eternal truths that God has revealed in these latter days through his
prophets.
</p><p>
We need not fear the philosophies of the world. We will not need any enlightenment or any
instruction or any assistance from anyone but the Comforter. For I bear witness to you today
that if we accept of the Lord the allotment which he has given to us as our
birthright, as our inheritance, and we build upon it as we should, that we will enjoy all
through our lives that Comforter which the Savior promised his disciples.
</p><p>
The Comforter, which is the Holy Ghost whom the Father will send in my name, he
shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have
said unto you (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/14/26#26">John 14:26</a>).
</p><p>
I hope and pray, my brethren and sisters, that we will be diligent in understanding and
appreciating the eternal truths of the gospel of Jesus Christ, that we will live and not merely
exist. There can come into our lives no greater thrill than to be conscious of the fact that we
have taken those faculties that God has given us and utilized them as our Father in heaven
intended that we should.
</p><p>
I was thrilled beyond measure the other day. I have a little grandson three years of age. I
found him and myself in front of a show window. He said: "Granno, buy me something." I
looked hastily over the articles, and I thought every article in the window was intended for a
little girl, dolls, etc.
</p><p>
I said, "There is nothing there for a boy," but almost in an instant he looked up at me with his
big eyes, and he said, "Why, Granno, there is a truck there. Men drive trucks."
</p><p>
I was thrilled to think in that mind three years of age that that power to utilize the intellect, to
think and to reason existed there so early in life, and brought to that young man, at the
moment at least, the desired results.
</p><p>
Now I hope and pray, my brethren and sisters, that we will all place ourselves in the position
where we can utilize these faculties just as that child did, in every circumstance of life, and
have come before us, through our obedience, and through the guidance and direction of the
Holy Ghost the right answer to all our problems.
</p><p>
May God so bless us I humbly pray in the name of the Lord, Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
