<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 13-14</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We have several notes here should be considered by presiding officers in stakes and wards, in
addition to those already mentioned in the message given by the Bishopric and by the
counselors in the Presidency.
</p><p>
One of these I will mention.  The others we can carry over.  Will the presidencies of stakes at
your quarterly conference please present to the visiting General Authorities any problems
which you have that are current, or might he current within a few days or weeks.  Let the
Brethren who are on the ground consider these problems with you.  It may be the
reorganization of a bishopric, the appointment of high councilmen, or the reorganization of a
high council. Not infrequently we find before us correspondence from stakes in which
quarterly conference was held just the week before our Thursday meeting, problems which
should have been taken up with the visiting Brethren.
</p><p>
If you will follow that little suggestion it will expedite matters in the Presidency's office,
which are accumulating.
</p><p>
As I contemplate the vast audience of Priesthood tonight, assembled in the various places
named at the opening of the meeting, and realize the potency and power of this great body of
men, I am overwhelmed.  As I sat in the audience and listened to the message given so
impressively by the Bishopric, and so successfully by the men and women who produced that
film, I felt my feelings swell within my breast as to the possibility of the good that will be
done, and can be done, by these fifteen or twenty or twenty-five thousand
men of the Priesthood who are worshipping tonight.
</p><p>
"There's surely somewhere a lowly place<br />
      In earth's harvest fields so wide,<br />
      Where I may labor thro' life's short day<br />
      For Jesus, the Crucified; <br />
      So trusting my all to Thy tender care,<br />
      And knowing Thou lovest me,<br />
      I'll do Thy will with a heart sincere,<br />
      I'll be what you want me to be."
</p><p>
I hope everybody who sang that verse applied it to himself, and in a way made a sacred vow
to do better in the future than in the past, and there came to my mind five fundamental
virtues which should be associated with that will.  I will just name them.
</p><p>
First is faith&mdash;faith in God the Father, in His Son, faith in our fellow men.
</p><p>
The second is honesty, a childish sincerity, honest in dealing with our fellow men.  It is the
foundation of all character.  If you offer prayer at night and you have dealt dishonestly with
your fellows during the day, I rather think that as the king in Hamlet, your words fly up but
your thoughts remain below; but if you have dealt honestly, the Lord will hear and answer
your true feelings.
</p><p>
The third is loyalty.  It is a wonderful principle.  A true friend is loyal. Many acquaintances
are not, and may not be.  Be loyal to the Priesthood.  Be loyal to your wives and to your
families, loyal to your friends.
</p><p>
I cannot think that the Spirit of God will strive with a man who in any way helps to break up
another man's family. I care not what seeming attraction may be between him and the wife of
the other man.  God will withdraw his Spirit from such a one.
</p><p>
Do you know that five or six letters that have come just this week from broken-hearted wives
of some men who are disillusioned with the Church have their origin in dishonest dealings
with men, or fancied dishonest dealings of brethren, and three of them from broken-hearted
wives who are pleading for something to be said to have their husbands brought to recall what
it means to be loyal to covenants made in the House of the Lord.
</p><p>
Fourth, there springs from that chastity. All these 25,000 men, clean. That means something
in this old world.
</p><p>
Fifth, in the heart of each one a willingness, indeed, a desire, to serve their fellow men.
</p><p>
I will say no more, but I feel impressed to ask you, and all other listening in to repeat with
me the First Article of Faith, and the Thirteenth Article of Faith, and let us say it slowly, and
think of each word as we say it.
</p><p>
You recall the first: "We believe in God, he Eternal Father, and in His Son, Jesus Christ, and
in the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
The Thirteenth: "We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing
good to all men; indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all
things, we hope all things, we have endured man things, and hope to be able to endure all
things.  If there is anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after
these things" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
Will you brethren?  The first, (The brethren repeated the First Article of Faith.)
</p><p>
Thirteenth.  (The brethren then repeated the Thirteenth Article of Faith.)
</p><p>
May inspiration from on high and the constant guidance of the Holy Spirit enable each of us
to accentuate that belief by radiating in our daily lives the ideals and principles of the Gospel
of Jesus Christ, I earnestly pray in the name of our Lord and Savior, Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
