<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Teaching</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder A. Theodore Tuttle</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">A. Theodore Tuttle, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 84-85</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Once upon a time, so the fable goes, there was a wise monarch who wanted to teach his
subjects an important and vital lesson. He said: "Make me a man." They acquired the finest
artist in the kingdom who painted the picture of a man on canvas. They took it to the king,
but he was displeased and repeated: "Make me a man." They tried other media, sculpture in
wood and stone, but to each the king said: "Make me a man." Finally they caught the vision
of the king's instructions. They found a man, tattered, degraded. They bathed him, shaved
him, dressed him, taught him, and presented him to the king. The king was pleased that they
had learned this lesson and said these words: "Next to the God who creates is the individual
who saves another."
</p><p>
Brothers and sisters, you and I are engaged in and dedicated to the work of saving men's
souls. In view of what President McKay has said about youth fitness, I would like to address
my remarks to that vast corps of teachers in the Church who are saving men's souls in the
hope that instruction might improve in the Church. For if one teacher increases the level of
his competence and ability, that class will improve; and if many teachers improve, all classes
in the ward will. And if each of us improves the instruction, the whole Church will grow in
strength and power and will be blessed. Remember that no class can rise higher than its
teacher.
</p><p>
The second reason is, that I would like to lead all of us to the source of unfailing inspiration,
the Lord Jesus Christ. In the Savior's teachings, we find the finest methods used that are
known today. We see his objective of changing man's behavior clearly set forth. We find the
Savior being acclaimed an authority, because he knew his subject, and likewise we find a
knowledge of students put to use in a beautiful way.
</p><p>
Teachers, if you would improve your teaching, use and adapt illustrations and examples to fit
the present knowledge and experience of your students. May I illustrate: 
</p><p>
We find in the teachings of the Savior such words as camels, sheep, salt, light, candles, fish,
leaven, hens and chickens, lilies, sparrows, things that people knew about and had experience
with. He likened the abstract ideas of his teaching to these concrete things that people knew
about. His new ideas were related to known facts.
</p><p>
Secondly, if you would become a better teacher, learn to answer questions the way the Savior
did. He gave direct answers, but equally as often he would ask another question of his
hearers. You recall this instance:
</p><p>
"Tell us therefore, What thinkest thou? . . .<br />
"But Jesus perceived their wickedness, and said, Why tempt ye me, ye hypocrites?<br />
"Shew me the tribute money. And they brought unto him a penny.<br />
"And he saith unto them, Whose is this image and superscription?<br />
"They say unto him, Caesar's. Then saith he unto them, Render therefore unto Caesar the
things which are Caesar's, and unto God the things that are God's"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/17-21#17">Matt. 22:17-21</a>).
</p><p>
I would like to give another example which shows many things about teaching. You recall
this instance:
</p><p>
"And behold, a certain lawyer stood up, and tempted him, saying, Master, what
shall I do to inherit eternal life?<br />
"He said unto him, [note the technique] What is written in the law? how readest thou?<br />
"And he answering said, Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy
soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind; and thy neighbour as thyself.<br />
"And he said unto him, Thou hast answered right: this do, and thou shalt live.<br />
"But he, willing to justify himself, said unto Jesus, And who is my neighbour?<br />
"And Jesus answering said: A certain man went down from Jerusalem to Jericho and fell
among thieves . . ." and then related the story of the Good Samaritan
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/25-37#25">Luke 10:25-37</a>).
</p><p>
Now, notice the teaching technique. Teachers, you who make up this vast corps of 231,000,
and others, for we are all teachers regardless of our position whether it be president or other
officer&mdash;notice what the Savior said.
</p><p>
". . . love thy neighbour as <i>thyself</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/39#39">Matt. 22:39</a>, italics added).
</p><p>
He might just as well have said, "Love thy neighbor as thy wife or husband or son or
daughter or uncle or aunt," but he gave it <i>universal</i> application, when he said "thyself," for
each man loves himself. Each man, however, does not have a wife, a son or a daughter, and
thus would not have been included in the Master's teaching.
</p><p>
Here we find in the teachings of the Master, a blending of all of the techniques, methods,
ideas, that will help us to be effective in teaching the gospel and in achieving the lofty ideals
that President McKay has outlined for us to achieve.
</p><p>
Thirdly, if you would be a better teacher, teach by the Spirit. You recall that in the Doctrine
and Covenants, the Savior said: 
</p><p>
"And ye are to be taught from on high. Sanctify yourselves and ye shall be endowed with
power, that ye may give even as I have spoken"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/16#16">D&amp;C 43:16</a>).
</p><p>
That is the thing that gives strength and power, meaning and life, to our otherwise weak
efforts.
</p><p>
The fourth thing, (and I will mention it only briefly, because President McKay dealt with this)
is to live your teachings. William E. Berrett, who is vice-president of Brigham Young
University, once remarked that many years ago there was a Danish immigrant who taught his
class. Though he spoke in broken English his life was such that you could warm your hands
by the flame of his testimony.
</p><p>
Remember, teachers, you cannot give away that which you do not possess.
</p><p>
Study the life of the Master. You do not have to have a college degree to be an efficient
teacher. But you do have to become acquainted with the life and teachings of the Master to be
an effective teacher in the Church.
</p><p>
Teachers of the Church, there is an eternal extension of the power and influence of a good
teacher. May we live so that we may teach by the Spirit, so that the youth of the Church
might pattern their lives after the life of the Master.
</p><p>
I am grateful for his life and mission. He lives. He directs the brethren who direct this
Church. This is my humble witness, and I bear it in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
