<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Samuel O. Bennion</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Samuel O. Bennion, <i>Conference Report</i>, pp. 53-54</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren, I am very happy to be in your midst tonight, and during the day, and to partake
of the spirit of the Lord that I find so abundantly among us.
</p><p>
I hope none of us overlooked the fine testimony that we heard from President Grant this
morning, one of the most wonderful that I have listened to in some time.
</p><p>
I haven't thought of anything to say, except this, brethren: I trust that when we return to our
homes again, that we will remember our Father's work, that we will be about our Father's
business (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/49#49">Luke 2:49</a>),
that we will encourage the leadership of the quorums of the Priesthood to meet
together and to appoint members of the quorums to visit the inactive of the members of the
Priesthood who do not attend to their Church obligations. They are good men, and if only we
can just get them to become active in their work we would be doing a fine and good service.
Those men are in our midst and many are fine characters and are at work in some position or
another. Many hold positions of trust that are worth while, so far as our civic and business
life are concerned. If we could just get these men to participate with us I think it would be a
marvelous thing.
</p><p>
I am happy to bear my testimony that I know, without a doubt, that this is the work of God;
that we are engaged in the building up of the Church and kingdom of God on earth; that the
people in this Church are the ones who hold the confirmed gift and power of the Holy Ghost,
and that you men, as leaders, all of us here, have the rights and gifts of the Holy Priesthood
which cannot be found elsewhere in this world, only in the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints. I am happy and thankful to be numbered among you.
</p><p>
I pray the Lord to bless us, in the name of Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
