<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Eternal Life of Man</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder William J. Critchlow, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">William J. Critchlow, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1967, pp. 85-89</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
      "All the world's a stage,<br />
      And all the men and women merely players: <br />
      They have their exits and their entrances; <br />
      And one man in his time plays many parts,<br />
      His acts being seven ages."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;      (William Shakespeare, <i>As You Like It</i>, Act 1, scene 7.)
</p><p>
Yes, the world is truly a huge stage, and upon it the greatest drama ever conceived and
produced is still coursing 6,000 years after the curtains were opened to unveil a beautiful
scene in Act 1 called the Garden of Eden.
</p><p>
<b>Purposes of Divine Providence</b>
</p><p>
In a single sentence the author of this great drama set forth concisely a purpose, a motive, and
an objective for his marvelous work.  He said: 
</p><p>
"For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life
of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
In that simple sentence, I find a fitting title: "The Eternal Life of Man." You who like brevity
may shorten it to Eternal Life.  I like it either way. I hope the author will approve.
</p><p>
Later in my remarks I shall comment on the author's purpose.
</p><p>
Members of the drama's cast respectfully address the author as God. Frequently we dispense
with formality and affectionately call him "Our Father which art in heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/9#9">Matt. 6:9</a>). His
real name is Elohim. (James E. Talmage, <i>Articles of Faith</i>, pp. 465-473.) May he pardon me
for calling him the author.  This I do reverently to avoid too frequent use of the sacred title,
God.
</p><p>
<b>Free agency&mdash;the drama theme</b>
</p><p>
The theme of the great drama is <i>free agency</i>, meaning man's agency or freedom to choose. 
The script is divided into seven acts, each 1,000 years in length.  The play has advanced far
into the sixth act.  Soon the curtain will rise for the seventh or millennial act.
</p><p>
<b>Contest for leadership</b>
</p><p>
To stage and direct the drama, the author needed a director.  Bidding for it, a talented and
ambitious character known as Lucifer, frequently called Satan, offended and insulted the
author.  His bid offended because he proposed to alter the author's script in a way that
nullified the author's theme concept&mdash;free agency; it insulted because the bidder sought as
his price the author's honor and power: ". . . wherefore give me thine honor," and give unto
me thine "own power" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1-4#1">Moses 4:1-4</a>). His bid rejected, he rebelled and cried out in anger, ". .
. I will ascend into heaven; I will exalt my throne above the stars of God . . . I will be like
the most High" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/14/13-14#13">Isa. 14:13-14</a>).
</p><p>
The author awarded the directing Job to his son Jehovah, who agreed to "go down" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/24#24">Abr. 3:24</a>) and
prepare the world stage and to direct the play according to the author's script.
</p><p>
<b>Rebellion</b>
</p><p>
Lucifer's rebellion escalated into a war in heaven.  It spread to earth, a fierce struggle
between Lucifer and Jehovah.  Battles are still raging on the stage here in the sixth act. 
Approximately one third of the cast selected for the great drama defected and sided with
Lucifer (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/36#36">D&amp;C 29:36</a>).  For so doing, they were dropped from the cast and thus denied physical appearances
on the stage. This infuriated them. They vowed to make the play flop, and to that end they
have used freedom&mdash;the very agency they at first protested&mdash;to destroy "free agency."
</p><p>
Lucifer's strategy is to induce the cast to use their individual agency in a way that will
produce chaos on the stage. By exposing the cast to as much evil as possible, he hopes to gain
numerical strength so that he might shout when the curtain rolls down at the
end of the play, "I have the majority of the heavenly host on my side; numerical strength is
my power.  Now I can claim 'thine honor'; now 'I will ascend into heaven'; now 'I will exalt
my throne above the stars of God'" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/14/12-20#12">Isa. 14:12-20</a>).
</p><p>
One thing we are forced to admit: Despite the fact that Lucifer's spirit followers were
eliminated from the cast and thus deprived of physical appearances on the stage, their power
to tempt and adversely influence the cast has been tremendous.
</p><p>
God in his infinite wisdom undoubtedly appointed his son Jehovah to be the drama director
because of the Son's vast experience in building stages or worlds. ". . . worlds without
number have I created . . . and by the Son I created them," he said (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/33#33">Moses 1:33</a>).
</p><p>
By the time the stage was readied, the cast was ready, the leading roles filled by a process or
doctrine called <i>foreordination</i> (<i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i>, pp. 365 and 158. See
also <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/23#23">Abr. 3:23</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The First Act</b>
</p><p>
". . . the morning stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/38/7#7">Job 38:7</a>), and
the heavens resounded with praise when a strong angel proclaiming with a loud voice"
announced curtain time for the first act (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/2#2">Rev. 5:2</a>).
</p><p>
John the Revelator likens the curtains throughout the play to seals (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/1-2#1">Rev. 5:1-2</a>). "We are to
understand that the first seal contains [reveals] the things of the first thousand years [Act 1],
and the second also of the second thousand years [Act 2], and so on until the seventh [Act
7]" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/7#7">D&amp;C 77:7</a>).
</p><p>
The first seal or curtain revealed a beautiful scene called the Garden of Eden.  The first man
to appear on the stage was one Michael, an assistant to Jehovah in the stage-building project.
(<i>Journal of Discourses</i>, Vol. 1, p. 51.) His stage name is Adam.  He was given a wife in a
marriage that will last forever.  Her name is Eve. Free agency, with some help from Lucifer,
got this couple into trouble just as Lucifer had predicted, and they were "cast out from the
Garden of Eden because of his transgression" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/41#41">D&amp;C 29:41</a>).
</p><p>
Cain, a son of the couple, exercising his free agency unrighteously, slew his brother Abel. 
For this he was cursed with "a mark upon [him] lest any finding him should kill him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/15#15">Gen. 4:15</a>).
Thousands upon thousands in the huge drama cast have had problems by exercising
their agency unrighteously; other thousands have soared to great heights by exercising their
agency righteously.
</p><p>
Wickedness reigned upon the stage as Act 1 came to a close, save in the little city of Zion,
where under the leadership of one Enoch the people prospered in righteousness.  Adam lived
930 years.  Shortly before his death he called his righteous posterity together at a place now
known as Adam-ondi-Ahman and previewed for them the six remaining acts of the drama,
predicting "whatsoever should befall his posterity unto the last generation," the end of the
play (see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/53-56#53">D&amp;C 107:53-56</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Second Act</b>
</p><p>
In Act 2 the greatest catastrophe of the drama up to this present time was enacted.  Flooding
waters swept over the stage, engulfing and destroying "every living thing" save eight people
and certain "beasts" and "fowls" and "creeping things" which these people had stored with
them in an ark (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/6/19-20#19">Gen. 6:19-20</a>). Noah was the hero personality in this act. Before the waters poured onto the
stage, the drama director rewarded the righteous people of Enoch, lifting them "up into heaven,
into his own bosom," by a process or doctrine called <i>translation</i>, to save them from the flood
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/23,69#23">Moses 7:23,69</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Third Act</b>
</p><p>
In Act 3, Abraham, "Father of the Faithful" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/41#41">D&amp;C 138:41</a>), played a leading role. Isaac, Jacob, Joseph, and
Moses made appearances.  Moses delivered the children of Israel from their captivity in
Egypt. Great physical changes in the earth's appearances were made in the
days of Peleg (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/10/25#25">Gen. 10:25</a>); and, when the director confused the tongues of the people, a small group under
the leadership of one Jared made an epochal voyage across great waters to found a colony on
this western hemisphere.  In this act, Israel possessed its promised land and divided it among
11 tribes, leaving Levi without a portion.  In one of the final scenes, the great prophet Samuel
anointed Saul first king of Israel; and later, behind Saul's back, he secretly anointed the lad
David to be Saul's successor.
</p><p>
<b>Fourth Act</b>
</p><p>
Act 4 opened with King David on the throne.  Solomon succeeded him and built a great
temple.  Enemies overrunning Israel destroyed it, and friendly enemies subsequently helped
restore it.  Ten of the twelve tribes went into the north countries and were lost.  A prophet
Lehi built ships that came, under the power of God, to this western hemisphere, where his
people became a great nation.
</p><p>
<b>Fifth Act</b>
</p><p>
When the curtain or veil was drawn for the fifth act, it revealed the drama director in person
on the stage.  His name was Jesus.  Because he said he was the Son of God, certain members
of the cast nailed him to a cross.  In brief appearances in Palestine and on the western
hemisphere, he reestablished his gospel, organized a kingdom, and ordained 24 apostles to
direct it&mdash;12 in Palestine and 12 on the western hemisphere.  For associating with Jesus, the
apostles in Palestine were martyred, save one John who was exiled to Patmos, where in vision
he saw the script of the author's great drama&mdash;"Eternal Life."
</p><p>
<b>Sixth Act&mdash;Resurrection Scene</b>
</p><p>
No scene in the entire drama can match the resurrection scene in the sixth act, unless it be a
scene programmed in the seventh act when Jesus will come in glory to rule and reign in
person for a thousand years. Then "every knee should bow . . . and . . . every tongue confess
that Jesus Christ is Lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/10-11#10">Philip. 2:10-11</a>). Then Satan will be bound, "that he should deceive
the nations no more" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/20/1-3#1">Rev. 20:1-3</a>); then "the wolf also shall dwell with the lamb, and the
leopard shall lie down with the kid . . . and the cow and the bear shall feed" together
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/11/6-7#6">Isa. 11:6-7</a>); then "they shall beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into
pruninghooks: nation shall not lift up sword against nation, neither shall they learn war any
more" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/4#4">Isa. 2:4</a>). Temples then will dot the land, so kin may do work for kindred dead. (<i>JD</i>,
Vol. 25, p. 185.) "Eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither have entered into the heart of
man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/9#9">1 Cor. 2:9</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Seventh&mdash;Millennial Act</b>
</p><p>
Before these blissful scenes are enacted in the seventh or millennial act, Act 6, running its full
course, will crowd the intervening time space with spectacular events, some too tragic and
distressing to give comfort to our souls. Already in this act: 
</p><p>
&mdash;the author, accompanied by his director son, has made a brief behind-the-scenes
appearance; 
</p><p>
&mdash;the gospel of Jesus Christ has been restored; 
</p><p>
&mdash;the kingdom of God has been established to stand forever and forever; 
</p><p>
&mdash;the great latter-day Prophet Joseph Smith has come and gone, forfeiting his life in the
restoration cause.
</p><p>
The apostle John forecast a great earthquake in this sixth act. He wrote: 
</p><p>
"And I beheld when he had opened the sixth seal, and, lo, there was a great earthquake; and
the sun became black as sackcloth of hair, and the moon became as blood; 
</p><p>
"And the stars of heaven fell unto the earth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/6/12-13#12">Rev. 6:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
Employing earthquakes and fire, war and lightning, famine and plague, and a desolating,
overflowing scourge (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/31-33#31">D&amp;C 45:31-33</a>), the author will yet cleanse and prepare the stage for the
peaceful millennial act. "Behold," he said, "the day has come, when the cup of the wrath of
mine indignation is full" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/26#26">D&amp;C 43:26</a>).
</p><p>
The stage was cleared and cleansed in Noah's day (Act 2) with a flood of water.  ". . . as it
was in the days of Noe, so shall it be also in the days of the Son of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/17/26#26">Luke 17:26</a>), but
the cleansing coming up soon will involve a flood of the other destructive agents I've just
listed, atomic bombing not ruled out.
</p><p>
At this very moment Lucifer may be gloating at the confusion on the stage. To his
confederates he might right now be repeating, "I told you so.  Free agency doomed the play
before it started." Well, he may think so, but not seriously.  Certain lines in the author's script
must worry him.  On the other band, those lines give hope and comfort to a distressed and
confused cast.  I delight in quoting them: 
</p><p>
"Hearken, O ye people of my church . . . Hearken ye people from afar . . . listen together.
</p><p>
". . . I am no respecter of persons, and will that all men shall know that the day speedily
cometh; the hour is not yet, but is nigh at hand, when peace shall be taken from the earth, and
the devil shall have power over his own dominion.
</p><p>
"And also the Lord shall have power over his saints, and shall reign in their midst, and shall
come down in judgment upon Idumea, or the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/1,35-36#1">D&amp;C 1:1,35-36</a>).
</p><p>
If man's reckoning of time is accurate, the curtain at the end of Act 6 may fall in less than
two score years from now.  My children&mdash;surely some of my grandchildren&mdash;will be
involved in this act's closing scenes.  I call upon them and all of you to "put on the whole
armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/11#11">Eph. 6:11</a>).
</p><p>
Some of my grandchildren may witness the return of the lost ten tribes; some of them may be
around when ancient Enoch and his people return; one might even be bidden to
Adam-ondi-Ahman to sit with Adam in another great council.  Do I hope for more than I
deserve, to hope that I myself might be caught up with the righteous dead to meet the great
director when he comes in glory to rule and reign upon the stage?  One other hope I'd like to
tuck in&mdash;I hope I haven't offended by calling this world a stage.
</p><p>
God never intended his great work to be accepted as a play.  Life is not simulated.  It is real;
the scenes are real; the characters are real; the acting is "for keeps." The drama analogy is
mine.  I like it.  I like the title, "Eternal Life." I like the worthy purpose it serves.
</p><p>
It is our Father's way of providing his billions of spirit children with mortal, flesh and bone
bodies.
</p><p>
It is a course designed to give his children a fullness of joy, like unto our Heavenly Father.
</p><p>
It provides his children with powers of procreation for the first time.
</p><p>
It provides a period of probationary testing.
</p><p>
It is designed to condition his children forever against rebellion and sedition.
</p><p>
It prepares his children for citizenship in a theocratic kingdom, the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
I like the author's objective: ". . . this is my work, and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the
immortality and eternal life of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
When the drama runs its 7,000-year course, what, at its close, happens to the cast?  Will the
players be unemployed?  How were they employed before the play began?
</p><p>
<b>This world drama</b>
</p><p>
My answer must be brief.  This world drama is but a small part, a very brief act, in a great,
grandiose drama that has been coursing through time and will continue to course through time
for millions of years, without end.  It is a drama within a drama, both by the same author.
May he pardon me for the liberty I take in calling it Act 2&mdash;the <i>mortal act</i>&mdash;involving the
cast in their mortal, flesh and bone, state.  Act 1 I would call the <i>pre-mortal act</i>, involving the
cast in their spirit state.  The future, Act 3, will later involve the cast in their
immortal state. I must call it the <i>post-mortal</i> or <i>immortal act</i>.
</p><p>
In these several acts God's grandiose drama courses on and on and on, everlastingly,
eternally.
</p><p>
Life is eternal. Faithful members of the cast, after their resurrection, may attain a state of
exaltation in God's kingdom in a glory called <i>celestial</i>. That glory holds a promise of
<i>eternal life</i>, the power of eternal increase, a continuation of the seeds.
</p><p>
"Life is real! Life is earnest!<br />
      And the grave is not its goal; <br />
      Dust thou art, to dust returnest,<br />
      Was not spoken of the soul."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;      (Longfellow, "A Psalm of Life.")
</p><p>
God, the great Author, lives.  He is in his heaven dispatching his spirit children to this mortal
stage.  Jesus Christ is the director, the very Son of God. Joseph Smith was a prophet. He
played an important role in the great drama, "Eternal Life." David O. McKay is another
prophet, our prophet, in another important role in that great drama.  To this I bear my humble
witness, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
