<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"I Have Witnessed Miracles"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Gordon B. Hinckley</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Gordon B. Hinckley, <i>Conference Report</i> October 1960, pp. 66-67</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
If I had the wish of my heart I would ask for the privilege of sitting down and having this
wonderful choir sing again that hymn which they sang so beautifully this morning:
</p><p>
"I stand all amazed at the love Jesus offers me,<br />
 Confused at the grace that so fully he proffers me."
</p><p>
I seek the inspiration of the Lord. I had prepared a talk, but I think I shall discuss something
else. Brother Dyer has been speaking of the work in Europe, and I rejoice at the marvelous
things that are being accomplished there. I wish to say that I feel that the same spirit, the
power of the Lord upon the people of the earth, is being made manifest all over the world
where the gospel is being taught.
</p><p>
I have recently had the experience, under the direction of the First Presidency, of going
through the missions of the Orient. I cannot deny the miracles of God, and I think many of
the things I have seen are truly miracles.
</p><p>
Not long ago, I sat in an old high school gymnasium in the city of Seoul, Korea. Just a short
time earlier the blood of the young people of Korea had been running in the streets of that
strife-ridden city. In our meeting that evening there were over 500 young Koreans. I was told
that we have only two married couples who are members of the Church in all of the Seoul
District. Our members there are young, forward-looking people. Conducting that gathering
was a sandy-haired, Utah farm boy. He conducted with dignity and spoke with ease the
language of those people, and after the meeting, as they came up and put their arms around
him, and he put his arms around them, I marveled at the power of the gospel of Jesus Christ
to change men's hearts.
</p><p>
We then went down to the sad city of Pusan on the southern tip of Korea. We held a street
meeting in the park overlooking the harbor. Within a few feet of a great anti-aircraft gun
emplacement we opened our meeting, and about
</p><p>
150 curious, intelligent-looking people gathered. A boy from Florida, a missionary of this
Church, began to speak. I then wandered down into the crowd with an army sergeant&mdash;one of
our boys who was taking us around. A Korean who spoke some English said in substance to
the sergeant, "How long that young man been here? Two years," was the reply. "No&mdash;he here
longer. Americans here fifteen years and not speak our language. Americans not speak Korean
like that." I thought of the words of the Savior as recorded by Mark: "... they shall speak with
new tongues" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/17#17">Mark 16:17</a>).
</p><p>
I remember sitting in this tabernacle while I was a university student and hearing one of the
brethren say that peace can come to the world only through acknowledgment of the Lord
Jesus Christ. I was at a critical age, and I doubted the possibility of that ever occurring. I
think recently I have glimpsed the vision of how it might happen.
</p><p>
Not long ago we were in Hiroshima, Japan. We stood in the park and green grows the grass
at the site where on the sixth of August 1945, just fifteen years ago, 80,000 lives were taken
with the blinding flash of the first atomic bomb. Another 80,000 have since died from the
effects of it. It is a sobering experience to stand in that place.
</p><p>
There is a simple monument about the size of this pulpit, and it has inscribed on its face in
Japanese characters, words which say in translation: "Rest in peace. May this tragedy never
again come to the world."
</p><p>
There were three of us, the mission president, a man from Hiroshima, and myself. The man
from Hiroshima was a Japanese businessman, an elder of the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, a man who had served in the Japanese Imperial Army for nine years. I was
an elder of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints from the land which had dropped
the bomb. With emotion and sincerity he said, through an interpreter, "Thank God for the
missionaries. Last night my wife and I were on our knees, as we are
each night, to express gratitude for the coming of these two young men who have literally
saved our lives. We had nothing to live for, no hope here or hereafter, and we were drinking
ourselves to death. They came. They taught us. They brought purpose into our lives. The
change in me has been so noticeable that my partner became curious. I have been teaching
him the gospel, and I am now going to baptize him."
</p><p>
That is the way peace will come to the world. This thing shall spread from soul to soul, and
men in all lands shall come to acknowledge Jesus Christ as the Son of God, the Savior of
mankind, our Elder Brother, the Prince of Peace.
</p><p>
We sat in a testimony meeting one day a few months ago. A boy stood up with a letter in his
hand. He said, "I think I am happier than I have ever been in my life. I have had many
wonderful experiences here, and they have made me happy, but it is this letter that has really
warmed my heart. My father, once active, began drinking, and oh, the sorrow my mother has
suffered because of this. After my farewell my father said, 'My son, I am going to try to live
worthy of you.' Now," the missionary said, "I have a letter from my father, received
yesterday, which says that last week he was ordained a high priest and set apart as counselor
in the bishopric of our ward, and he has just made a down payment on a home for the first
time in his life."
</p><p>
These are some of the miracles I have seen in my associations with our missionaries. I am
grateful, I am more grateful than I can say for this great program of the Church that I have
been blessed to be associated with. I know it is one of the marks of the divinity of this work.
No other organization in this world has anything quite like it.
</p><p>
It touches for good the lives of all who are affected by it.
</p><p>
The work is going forward on the other side of the earth. I recall sitting here as a boy and
hearing President Grant tell of his difficulties in Japan and of his praying to the Lord to give
him another assignment because of his discouragement. Do you know that the missionaries of
the Northern Far East Mission have baptized an average of about six converts per missionary
so far this year? Many of these were not Christian people. Our missionaries in this part of the
world have taken to people who are of the Oriental religions the testimony of Jesus and have
converted them to this cause. God bless them for their devotion and their faithfulness. The
Lord bless us at home to sustain his work throughout the world by the virtues of our lives, I
pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
