<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Cultivate the Spirit of Service</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 118-120</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We are now nearing the close of a very remarkable conference, unusual in many respects.
This conference has been directed primarily to an unseen audience, particularly yesterday
morning and this Sunday morning.
</p><p>
Usually we speak mainly to those who are assembled in this great Tabernacle, but each
speaker yesterday and today has been conscious of a listening audience that goes beyond this
Tabernacle and this city, this Church, this country, into Europe, the South Seas, South
Africa&mdash;and all this has been possible through the kindness of our television and radio
officials&mdash;Brother Arch Madsen and his associates here at KSL, and through assistants and
associates with him, and other leading officials, who are co-operating in efforts to bring this
gospel to the people of the world.
</p><p>
I wish to express appreciation to Brother James O. Conkling, who has just been appointed
President of the International Educational Broadcasting Corporation. We asked him to take
charge of a group of leading, influential men to bring into operation short-wave facilities by
which conferences and other programs, with the assistance of our own Tabernacle Choir,
originating here in Salt Lake City, could be transmitted across the waters. We wish to
acknowledge in your presence today the inspiration of the Lord upon these leading men in the
Church, and many of whom are not in the Church, who are giving their time and means
towards the accomplishment of this great possibility of carrying the message of the restored
gospel to every nation, kindred, tongue, and people.
</p><p>
This has been one of the greatest conferences, I suppose, that we have ever held in the
Church. The music today, as you know, has been furnished by the Tabernacle Choir. We have
been inspired by their singing at both sessions today and Saturday morning when their singing
was heard by millions. Many radio and television stations have been opened to us because of
the singing of this great organization. Their contribution to our missionary work is
inestimable.
</p><p>
In July of this year, they participated in the first formal world-wide television
program by way of Telstar satellite, held at Mount Rushmore in the Black Hills of South
Dakota. At this time, the choir was seen and heard on television by millions across the ocean
in Europe and England in addition to the millions in this country.
</p><p>
In August they made a tour of the Northwest, giving two concerts on August 15th and 16th at
the Seattle World's Fair. People from all over the world attended these concerts, and it was
reported that the concert hall was so crowded on both nights that many were turned away.
</p><p>
We appreciate all who have furnished the singing throughout this conference. First, the
singing for the Friday morning and afternoon sessions by the Relief Society Singing Mothers
from the Central Idaho and Bannock welfare regions. We accept their efforts and are inspired
by their singing, but very few of us ever stop to think of what those sisters
did and the valuable services rendered by Sister Florence Jepperson Madsen in training them
in such an excellent way.
</p><p>
Then we had the music furnished on Saturday afternoon by the Combined Choirs of Brigham
Young University, assisted by the Brass Choir. The Male Chorus and the combined male
sections of Brigham Young University furnished the music for the general priesthood meeting
Saturday evening.
</p><p>
For you, I express appreciation and gratitude to all who have in any way contributed to the
success and inspiration of this great conference: First, to the General Authorities, we express
deep appreciation for their inspired messages; to the public press&mdash;the reporters for their fair
and accurate reports throughout the sessions of the conference; for the co-operation of city
officials&mdash;the city traffic officers who handled carefully and ably the increased traffic; the
fire department and the Red Cross, who have been on hand to render assistance and service
whenever and wherever such became necessary; the Tabernacle ushers, who have rendered
service quietly, courteously, and efficiently in seating the great audiences of these conference
sessions.
</p><p>
I wish that you brethren could leave this closing session of our semiannual general conference
with your hearts renewed with a firm desire to render service to your fellow men and to act in
efficiency and prayerfulness in rendering service to those over whom you preside directly.
</p><p>
It has been said that "the race of mankind would perish if they ceased to aid one another."
One man, from whom I quote, says that "from the time that the mother binds the child's head
until the moment that some kind assistant wipes the death-damp from the brow of the dying,
we cannot exist without mutual help. All, therefore, that need aid have a right to ask it from
their fellow mortals; no one who holds the power of granting can refuse it without guilt."
</p><p>
The Church, with all its quorums and organizations, is God's plan for rendering mutual aid.
The Melchizedek Priesthood is power and authority vested in the Godhead and delegated to
man for the progress, happiness, salvation, and exaltation of the human family. It is a principle
of power by which The Church of Jesus Christ is organized and by which men to whom it is
given may legitimately act in the name of the Lord.
</p><p>
There are two conditions which should always be considered when the priesthood is to be
given to anyone. The first of these is the individual's worthiness to receive it. The second is
the service which he can render to the Church and to his fellow men.
</p><p>
Men who are vessels of the Holy Priesthood, who are charged with words of eternal life to
the world should strive continually in their words and actions and daily deportment to do
honor to the great dignity of their calling and office as ministers and representatives of the
Most High.
</p><p>
Whenever the priesthood is delegated to man, it is conferred upon him, not as a personal
honor, although it becomes such as he honors it, but as authority to represent Deity, and an
obligation to assist the Lord in bringing to pass the immortality and eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
If priesthood meant only personal distinction or individual elevation, there would be no need
of groups or quorums. The very existence of such groups, established by divine authorization,
proclaims our dependence upon one another, the indispensable need of mutual help and
assistance. We are social beings.
</p><p>
"There is a destiny which makes us brothers,<br />
     None lives to himself alone; <br />
     All that we give into the lives of others,<br />
     Comes back into our own."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                        (Edward Markham)
</p><p>
This element of service and mutual help is emphasized by the Lord as follows: 
</p><p>
"Wherefore, be faithful; stand in the office which I have appointed unto you; succor the weak,
lift up the hands which hang down, and strengthen the feeble knees"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/81/5#5">D&amp;C 81:5</a>). So says the Lord in the
Doctrine and Covenants, section eighty-one, verse five.
</p><p>
And again: 
</p><p>
"And if any man among you be strong in the Spirit, let him take with him
him that is weak, that he may be edified in all meekness, that he may become strong also"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/106#106">D&amp;C 84:106</a>).
</p><p>
It is an honor to labor with you, brethren and sisters, throughout the entire Church. God bless
you that you may realize the blessings that are yours through the revelation and restoration in
this day and age of the world of the priesthood of God, which gives you authority to represent
him in proclaiming the reality of the existence of the Father and his Beloved Son Jesus Christ,
and the restoration in this day of the gospel as given through Christ the Lord as the plan of
salvation to all mankind, through obedience to which peace shall be established on earth, and
the will of God carried forth to the salvation and exaltation of his children.
</p><p>
With all the power the Lord has given his servants, I bless you, and pray that you will go
forth with the spirit of service, honoring his name now and forever, in the name of Jesus
Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
