<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">A Divine Plan for Finding Security and Peace of Mind</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1966, pp. 4-8</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We are grateful for the blessings of the Lord to his Church in all the world and for the
assurance of his divine guidance and inspiration. With deep gratitude we acknowledge his
nearness and his goodness. It is a source of real encouragement to contemplate the loyalty and
energetic efforts of the members of the Church who are contributing of their time and their
means to building up the kingdom of God on earth. There is a general response, as the figures
and reports of the Church indicate, on the part of the people of the Church everywhere. The
responsibilities they carry, the undertakings that they adopt and employ to raise their share of
the cost of our houses of worship are most remarkable.
</p><p>
<b>I love life</b>
</p><p>
I love life! I think it is a joy to live in this age. Every morning, as I view from my window
the mountains to the east and greet the sun as it ushers in these unexcelled autumn days, I feel
the joy and privilege of life and appreciate God's goodness. I appreciate and realize the
accomplishments, to a certain degree, of this wonderful atomic age in which we are living.
Scientific discoveries of today stagger the imagination. Nearly every day we read of almost
unbelievable accomplishments. The age of the atom has only begun, and no one knows what
exciting developments may yet unfold when the atomic research now in progress is
completed. Its potential for good far outweighs its potential for destruction. The discoveries
and inventions of this age are unequaled by any previous period in the world's history,
discoveries latent with such potent power, either for the blessing or the destruction of human
beings, as to make man's responsibility in controlling them the most gigantic ever placed in
human hands.
</p><p>
<b>Perils and possibilities</b>
</p><p>
Yes, it is a glorious age in which we live, but no thinking man will doubt that this age is
fraught with limitless perils, as well as untold possibilities. There are causes for real
apprehension over world conditions. As we study and learn of the increase in crime and
disrespect for law and order that exist right here in our own country, we become alarmed.
</p><p>
Just the other day, I read an editorial in the <i>Deseret News</i> giving the information that an
estimated six million Americans suffer from alcoholism. The Public Health Service ranks
alcoholism as the fourth major public health problem in the United States. At the moment
Utah, fortunately, contributes less than its share to this problem. Contrary to what many
people think, Utah ranks forty-sixth from the top among the 50 states in the number of
alcoholics it has in proportion to the total population. Furthermore, it is the only state in
which per capita consumption of alcohol, as well as the alcoholism rate, has consistently
decreased for several years. Let us hope that Utah will not adopt the proposed legislation for
"liquor by the drink" and thereby entice more people to drink in more places more of the
time. As the editorial points out, our state, with our traditions and standards, should be doing
just the opposite. Liquor by the drink, as a recent study of the experience in Iowa shows, only
increases drinking and the attendant evils of alcoholism. The impaired morals, ruined health,
broken homes, and increased traffic deaths that result from drinking are well known by all of
us.
</p><p>
It is because of these threatening dangers that the world should become anchored in the
eternal truths of Jesus Christ and realize that there are eternal verities in this changing world.
</p><p>
Dr. Charles Foster Kent, commenting upon the "chaotic state" of our civilized world, says: 
</p><p>
"Political organizations and ideals that have both fortified and handicapped us have been
thrown into the discard. Long accepted social theories have suddenly been rejected, and new
ones are being adopted. Many of the moral standards of our Fathers are being set aside in
theory as well as in practice. The rising generation has no fear and little respect for Elders . . .
Religious dogmas, long regarded as the corner stones of religion and the Church, are being
disproved, or supplanted."
</p><p>
<b>Free agency threatened</b>
</p><p>
Efforts are being made to deprive man of his free agency, to steal from the individual his
liberty; and we must never forget that next to life itself, free agency is the greatest gift of God
man.
</p><p>
The two most important documents affecting the destiny of America are the Declaration of
Independence and the Constitution of the United States. Both of these inspired, immortal
papers relate primarily to the freedom of the individual. Founded upon that principle of free
enterprise fostered by these documents, the United States of America, in less than two
centuries, has achieved a greatness that far exceeds that of any other country in the world.
The deep concern of every loyal citizen regarding the threatened loss of our freedom has been
well expressed by Fred G. Clark, who is chairman of the American Economic Foundation,
New York City. In a speech given over a decade ago, he expressed the fear that the "code of
the people" is replacing the "code of God." His words so impressed me that I quoted them in
an address delivered in 1952. He declared that "something is wrong with America.
</p><p>
<b>America imperiled</b>
</p><p>
"At this moment of history when the task of world leadership has been thrust upon us, we
stand confused, reluctant, and hesitant . . .
</p><p>
"We are no longer certain what we stand for, and this, I believe, is because have forgotten the
circumstances surrounding the birth of our nation . . .
</p><p>
"For decades it has been popular in America for the cynical intellectuals to sneer and scoff at
what we call the traditions of Americanism.
</p><p>
"The instruments of this sabotage were words and thoughts&mdash;plausible half-truths, sly appeals
to that spark of larceny that lurks in every human  was heart, subtle suggestions of an
atheistic obvious that the nature, and the careful nurturing of a patronizing attitude toward
anything America has held to be fine and sacred.
</p><p>
"The people who planted these words and thoughts may have been either stupid or vicious,
fools or foreign agents, smart-alecs or smart organizers.
</p><p>
"What they were does not now matter. The thing that does matter is to counteract what they
have done.
</p><p>
"Everybody in every position of leadership has to get into this act because the damage has
affected every phase of our life.
</p><p>
"The places in which this sabotage occurred were the schools, the churches, the
Communist-dominated labor halls, the lecture platforms, the motion pictures, the stage, the
pages of our newspapers and magazines, and the radio. Every means of communication has
been utilized against us . . .
</p><p>
"The man (or nation), who has a plan&mdash;a way of life&mdash;in which he believes, has mental
security.
</p><p>
"To destroy this security, one must destroy that man's faith in his plan . . .
</p><p>
"[It is a] reliance on a code of life which, if held in common with one's fellow men, brings
peace of mind, develops the abilities of the group . . .
</p><p>
"The degree to which the American code of life has been weakened can best be demonstrated
by simply calling attention to the degree to which the foundation of that code has been
weakened . . .
</p><p>
"That foundation (and of this there cannot be the slightest shadow of a doubt) is made up of
the Ten Commandments and the Golden Rule.
</p><p>
"Within this moral code, we have a complete way of life.
</p><p>
"Acceptance of these precepts takes care of every phase of human life&mdash;spiritual, political,
social, and economic . . .
</p><p>
"America was a nation of people who had faith in their political and economic systems
because they had faith in God, and had built those systems around the teachings of God.
</p><p>
"Every collectivist from Karl Marx to [the present leader] has agreed that faith in God must
be destroyed before socialism can take over.
</p><p>
"Therefore, it was obvious that the problem of sabotaging America's faith in America was the
problem of transferring the people's faith in God to faith in the State.
</p><p>
"That thing called morality in politics, business, and private contracts, had to be broken down.
</p><p>
"To an increasing extent the people have come to look upon morality as an old-fashioned
superstition.
</p><p>
"Religion has for many church members become a safe way of <i>dying</i> rather than
<i>a good way of living</i>." (From "The Code of the People Is Replacing the Code of God," by Fred G. Clark.)
</p><p>
We all know that these threatening upsets in national standards have increased since that
speech was given. We know, also, that there has been an alarming increase in the abandoning
of the ideals that constitute the foundation of the Constitution of the United States and of the
American home, and you will agree with me that ears from the truth, and shall be there is real
cause for apprehension.
</p><p>
At this very moment while we are here worshipping, war is raging and blasting out the lives
of young men, old men, women, and children in Viet Nam. The standards of the home, even
the criteria for the rearing of children, have broken down.
</p><p>
<b>Evidences of danger</b>
</p><p>
J. William Hudson, formerly professor of philosophy at the University of Missouri, states:
"The leisure occupations of youth, always symptomatic in any age, are not only unguidedly
and frankly hedonistic, but have gone across the borders of what was once considered
decorous, not because of a new and liberalizing moral standard, as we sometimes pretended,
but because of the lack of any. The popularity of certain recent dances, formerly forbidden
even in the 'red-light' districts, is typical. So is much of our periodical reading matter, and
any number of 'movie' plays, over the edge of the decadently erotic, with a censorship that
does not censor because of moral and financial doubt."
</p><p>
He also mentions the fact that "dishonesty is permeating public and private life alike, tainting
the administration of justice, tainting our legislative halls, tainting the conduct of private
business, polluting at times even the church itself."
</p><p>
He goes on to assert that "if there is to be social and political regeneration in out Republic
and in the rest of the world, it must be by tremendous regeneration of moral ideals."
</p><p>
<b>"What shall we do?"</b>
</p><p>
What shall we do about all this?
</p><p>
When Paul was a prisoner in Rome, he sent a letter to Timothy, saying in substance: 
</p><p>
"Preach the word; be instant in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort with all
long-suffering and doctrine.
</p><p>
"For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts
shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears; 
</p><p>
"And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/2-4#2">2 Tim. 4:2-4</a>).
</p><p>
It is just as important today as when Paul wrote that farewell message to Timothy that officers
and teachers and members and everywhere "preach the word; be instant [that is, to be
<i>eager, earnest</i>] in season, [and] out of season."
</p><p>
Today, in the midst of the world's perplexity, there should be no question in the mind of any
true Latter-day Saint as to what we shall preach. The answer is as clear as the noonday sun in
a cloudless sky.
</p><p>
In the year 1830, there was given to the people of this land and the world a divine plan
whereby individuals can find security and peace of mind and live in harmonious accord with
their fellow beings. In all man's theories and experiments since history began, human
intelligence has never devised a system which, when applied to the needs of humanity, can
even approach this plan in effectiveness.
</p><p>
<b>Offer the Gospel plan of Salvation</b>
</p><p>
In simple words, then, this is the word that we should preach&mdash;the <i>gospel plan of salvation</i>.
</p><p>
The founders of this great republic had faith in the economic and political welfare of this
country because they had faith in God. Today it is not uncommon to note an apologetic
attitude on the part of men when they refer to the need of God's governing in the affairs of
men. Indeed, as has already been pointed out, success of Communism depends largely upon
the substitution of belief in God by belief in the supremacy of the state.
</p><p>
But I say to you, preach in season and out of season
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/4/2#2">2 Tim. 4:2</a>)
belief in God the Eternal Father, in his
Son Jesus Christ, and in the Holy Ghost
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The sacredness of the individual</b>
</p><p>
Proclaim that fundamental in the gospel plan is the sacredness of the individual; that God's
work and glory is "to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Under this concept, it is a great imposition, if indeed not a crime, for any government, any
labor union, or any other organization to deny a man the right to speak, to worship, and to
work.
</p><p>
The least child was sacred to Jesus. ". . . it is not the will of your Father which is in heaven,
that one of these little ones should perish"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/14#14">Matt. 18:14</a>).
What would that simple truth mean
in this world? "Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye
have done it unto me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/40#40">Matt. 25:40</a>).
And in this modern day, he said, "Remember the worth
of souls is great" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/10#10">D&amp;C 18:10</a>).
</p><p>
A proper conception of this divine principle would change the attitude of the world to the
benefit and happiness of all human beings. It would bring into active operation the Golden
Rule: "Do unto others as you would have others do unto you" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/12#12">Matt. 7:12</a>). What a
different world this would be if men would accumulate wealth, for example, not as an end, but
as a means of blessing human beings and improving human relations.
</p><p>
Declare the truth that man has the inherent power to do right or to do wrong. In this he has
his free agency to choose the right and obtain salvation, or he may choose to do evil and
commit abominations.
</p><p>
<b>Respect for governments divinely established</b>
</p><p>
Preach that the plan of salvation involves the belief that governments were instituted of God
for the benefit of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/1#1">D&amp;C 134:1</a>).
Man was not born for the benefit of the state. Preach that no
government can exist in peace, and I quote from the Doctrine and Covenants, "except such
laws are framed and held inviolate as will secure to each individual the free exercise of
conscience, the right and control of property, and the protection of life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/2#2">D&amp;C 134:2</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Necessity for honesty and loyalty</b>
</p><p>
Proclaim the necessity of honesty and loyalty, doing an honest day's work for an honest day's
pay. Preach that honesty in government is essential to the perpetuation and stability of our
government as it is necessary to the stability of character in the individual. "We believe in
being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men . . . If there is
anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report, or praiseworthy, we seek after these things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
</p><p>
Proclaim that God lives, and that his Beloved Son is the Redeemer and Savior of mankind;
that he stands at the head of his Church that bears his name; that he guides and inspires those
who are authorized to represent him here on earth, authorized by the priesthood when
heavenly messengers bestowed upon the Prophet Joseph Smith and others associated with him
divine authority.
</p><p>
<b>Responsibility of everyone</b>
</p><p>
Preach that the responsibility of declaring this plan of life, this way of life, this plan of
salvation, rests upon the entire membership of the Church, but most particularly upon those
who have been ordained to the priesthood and who have been called as leaders and servants
of the people.
</p><p>
<b>Verities promulgated by the Son of God</b>
</p><p>
These eternal verities are as applicable in the year 1966 as they were when Jesus first
promulgated them and they will remain fundamental and essential in man's progress and
happiness as long as life and being last.
</p><p>
In the questioning days of early boyhood, I first felt a kinship with Christ, our Lord and
Savior. I know his love and his divine guidance. He is the sinless Son of man. "He is the first
and the last . . . and [is] alive for evermore" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/18#18">Rev. 1:18</a>). Only by obedience to his
teachings can man find happiness and peace. Our Father is a kind and loving Heavenly Father
who is as ready and eager today as ever to bless and to guide all his children who will
sincerely seek him, and I bear you witness to that truth.
</p><p>
God help us all to walk in the light as he is in the light
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/1/7#7">1 Jn. 1:7</a>),
thereby avoiding the unhappiness,
sinfulness, and misery of a misguided world, and find joy and peace and beauteous life here
in this probation and in the life to come, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
