<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Not a Prophet&mdash;but a Listening Ear</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President J. Reuben Clark, Jr.</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">First Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">J. Reuben Clark, Jr., <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1948, pp. 77-82</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters, I humbly pray that the spirit which thus far has guided this
conference, of which we have all partaken, may continue while I shall speak to you.
</p><p>
One gets so much in one of these general conferences not only from the direct instructions
and observations which come, but also from the thought which these instructions and
directions invoke, that it is a little difficult sometimes to collect one's thoughts along a
particular line.
</p><p>
THE TREASURES OF LIFE
</p><p>
As we grow and enter the upper brackets of years, we reflect a great deal upon the things
which are of lasting importance and we come clearly to see that many of the things which we
thought were of value in our earlier lives are merely the dross and that the gold, the treasures
of life, we may have overlooked.
</p><p>
I am grateful that while I still live and have opportunity to serve that I have come more or
less to appreciate, I try fully so to do, the things that are worth while. I try to shear away the
unimportant, and, when I do so, I find that worldly things have pretty largely disappeared,
that the objects which ordinarily are the matters of ambition among men have gone, and life
settles down to the problem of the future. I cease to look at time and get over as near as may
be into eternity. I am grateful for the knowledge which the Lord has enabled me to get, which
means he has given to me of the things of the spirit. I am grateful for the knowledge of the
gospel, imperfect as is the knowledge which I have. I am grateful for my testimony which
strengthens with the days and the years, and I am grateful that the blessings which I thus
recount to myself are the blessings which belong and are enjoyed by all of you. I come to see
that the things which men give in the way of honor and respect and office and position are
really of little worth. They are not worth what sometimes we feel we have to give in order to
obtain them. I come to know that worldly goods are of no consequence whatever, save I have
enough to eat, and to drink and reasonably to wear, and that to attempt to leave wealth to my
children will not only be a futile effort but that it may prove a curse.
</p><p>
I do not mean by this that we should cease to exert our efforts to become influential for good
in our communities. I do not mean that we should forget that we are living here and have our
lives to live. I do not forget that a reasonable provision for those who come after us is a wise
thing. I am only saying that none of these things is worth the sacrifice of a principle. They
are not worth the sacrifice of our integrity, of our honor, of our righteous living.
</p><p>
WORLD IN A MESS
</p><p>
It is a trite thing to say the world is in a mess. That we know, and out of a life of
seventy-seven years I can say that so far as I can see, it has never been in the mess that it is
in today. There have never before, in my life, been the powers of evil in such strength. Satan
seems to have taken us over very largely, and we are more or less his tools. This is not the
first time in our national history that we have been in trouble, and when I say "we," I mean
the people. I am not talking of administrations. I am talking of us, we the people of the
United States.
</p><p>
PROCLAMATION OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN
</p><p>
I have always been impressed with a great proclamation that was issued by Abraham Lincoln.
He issued it in one of the darkest hours of the Civil War, just before Vicksburg, the surrender
of which opened up the Mississippi River, and just before Gettysburg, which stopped the
threatened invasion of the North. The Senate had passed a resolution calling attention to the
needs of the country and asked him to set apart a day for national prayer and humiliation. The
nation was considered almost bankrupt from debt. The people were tax-ridden, almost beyond
endurance; the army was unpaid, some of it for a period of six months, and it was daily
dwindling by desertion. The president issued a proclamation, and I want to read two or three
paragraphs therefrom.
</p><p>
"We," by which he meant the people,
</p><p>
. . . have been the recipients of the choicest bounties of heaven; we have been preserved these
many years in peace and prosperity; we have
grown in number, wealth, and power as no other nation has ever grown. But we have
forgotten God. We have forgotten the gracious hand which preserved us in peace and
multiplied and enriched and strengthened us, and we have vainly imagined, in the
deceitfulness of our hearts, that all these blessings were produced by some superior wisdom
and virtue of our own. Intoxicated with unbroken success we have become too self-sufficient
to feel the necessity of redeeming and preserving grace, too proud to pray to the God who
made us.
</p><p>
It behooves us, then, to humble ourselves before the offended power, to confess our national
sins, and to pray for clemency and forgiveness. Now, therefore in compliance with the request
and fully concurring in the views of the Senate, I do by this my proclamation designate and
set apart Thursday the 30th day of April, 1863, as a day of national humiliation, to abstain on
that day from their ordinary secular pursuits, and to unite in their several places of public
worship and be devoted to the humble discharge of the religious duties proper to that solemn
occasion.
</p><p>
All this being done in sincerity and truth, let us then rest humbly in the hope authorized by
the divine teachings that the united cry of the nation will be heard on high and answered with
blessings no less than the pardon of our national sins and the restoration of our now divided
and suffering country to its former happy condition of unity and peace.
</p><p>
WE HAVING HAD PROPHETS
</p><p>
In some respects, too many, we stand in that same place today. Some time ago a pamphlet
came across my desk which unfortunately I threw away. On the outside page it was stated,
"We need a prophet," and as I read it then, and as I think of it now, I think how blind the
world is. We have had a prophet, an American prophet, one who spoke our language, one
who was imbued with Christian ideals, and that prophet gave us the great righteous principles,
of which we know and of which the world partly knows; he gave them in our own language
over a hundred years ago. These may all be read; we have been teaching them for a century.
The trouble with the world is they do not want a prophet teaching righteousness. They want a
prophet that will tell them that what they are doing is right, no matter how wrong it may be.
</p><p>
There is nothing new in this. Going back to the beginning, Noah taught the people. He was a
prophet, and he told them what to do. He finally convinced his own family, and they were
saved. So of Moses&mdash;while the children of Israel were in Egypt and he was promising them
deliverance, they followed him, they did what he told them, but once out of Egypt and away
from the bondman's lash they forgot, and he had rebellion after rebellion upon his hands from
then until he died. The later prophets in Israel&mdash;Elijah vindicated by a miracle, that he was a
prophet of God; yet Jezebel hunted him like a wild beast and would have killed him had not
the Lord taken him by a miracle; and Isaiah and Jeremiah, these prophets spoke not only
about righteous living and what Israel should do in their family life and in their religious
worship, but those prophets spoke also of the relationship of nations and how Israel should
bear herself toward those nations, but their warnings and prophecies went unheeded, and the
calamities which they predicted came.
</p><p>
Now our Prophet, Joseph Smith, and the prophets since his time&mdash;and there has always been a
prophet in this Church, and prophets, and you sustain the brethren here, conference after
conference, as prophets, seers, and revelators the Prophet himself through the Lord by
revelation, gave certain great principles that would save the world if the world would but
listen. We do not lack a prophet; what we lack is a listening ear by the people and a
determination to live as God has commanded. That is all we need.
</p><p>
The way has been made perfectly clear.
</p><p>
REVELATIONS GIVEN TO JOSEPH SMITH
</p><p>
In the earliest days of the Church the Prophet, through revelation, gave a plan we call it the
United Order&mdash;which if lived, would have preserved individual initiative, what we have come
to call the American way of life, and at the same time have cared for all who needed to be
cared for. When we could not live that, the Lord then gave us, through a series of revelations,
step by step for he always leads us gradually, we cannot always be led clear through to the
end all at once he gave us revelations out of which we have developed the plan for caring for
the poor, through the giving by those who have to those who have not. We now know it as
the great welfare plan. There is nothing new in the welfare plan except a little machinery that
we have added to carry it out.
</p><p>
The Lord gave us a great dietary law more than one hundred years ago. He called it a Word
of Wisdom. If this law were lived, it would regenerate the human race, so far as their physical
bodies are concerned; and because of the intimate relationship between our physical bodies
and our spiritual welfare, we would, if we had lived it, by this time be well on our way
spiritually toward that peace for which men today so earnestly and devoutly work and pray.
</p><p>
He taught us also the relationship between father and son, child and parent, a great principle,
one of the saving principles of society, given first on Mount Sinai
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/12#12">Ex. 20:12</a>) and repeated by the Savior
to the questioning Pharisees (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/15/4#4">Matt. 15:4</a>).
We have forgotten that. The prophecy is here. There is no
difficulty about that. It is our ears that are at fault.
</p><p>
He gave us the true principle for righteous ruling in that great revelation which tells us how
the priesthood' should rule, as already referred to by Brother Romney, I believe, who quoted
some teachings from the Book of Mormon.
</p><p>
He gave us a great law of war telling us that we his people, should not go to war unless
commanded by him and then telling what those who were attacked should do, how many
times they should forgive (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/39-48#39">D&amp;C 98:39-48</a>),
following along the lines of those quotations made by Brother
Romney.
</p><p>
He declared also, this prophet of ours, that this was a promised land and should so remain so
long as we worshiped the God of this land, Jesus Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/12#12">Ether 2:12</a>); but he warned us that when and if
we became ripe in iniquity, he would destroy us, just as he had destroyed others before us
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/2/8-10#8">Ether 2:8-10</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet gave a great revelation involving fundamental principles of government, the
relationship between the civil officers and the people, the relationship between the people and
the laws commanded obedience to righteous laws
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/1-12#1">D&amp;C 134:1-12</a>)&mdash;all sufficient in general principles to take
us out of our present morass of pride, lawlessness, and crime.
</p><p>
He told us that the Constitution, under which we live, was an inspired document
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/80#80">D&amp;C 101:80</a>), that its
principles were elemental to free human government and declared we should adhere to the
Constitution and to the principles thereof. In that Constitution is the great Bill of Rights,
guaranteeing to us freedom of the press, freedom of speech, freedom of conscience, freedom
to assemble, and so on.
</p><p>
AMERICA NEEDS A LISTENING EAR
</p><p>
All this is in our gospel. It is all part of the work of our great prophet Joseph Smith, and
those who have followed him. It is in the books and has been in print for a century. The
American Prophet has spoken; American prophets are speaking. The great principles I have
named, and almost countless others, have been proclaimed for a hundred years. No, America
does not need a prophet; America needs a listening ear. And more than all, we who are here,
members of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, we need a listening ear.
</p><p>
May God give us that ear. May he give us a disposition to read what he has told us. May he
give us a spirit, his spirit, to take into our souls the principles of the gospel which he has
given to us. May he give us the will and power to live them, having taken them into our
souls; and the blessings and the joy and the happiness of life that will come to us if we so
live are beyond any powers of expression or suggestion that I possess.
</p><p>
May God give us, again I say, a listening ear to all that he has told us, in order that we may
live as he would have us live and give us the spirit to which I have referred, and the power to
live as he would have us live, and to us men the will and power to honor our priesthood, and
give to all of us every blessing that would be for our good. I humbly pray in the name of
Jesus. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
