<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">How Fortunate Can We Be?</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1965, pp. 90-93</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I suppose I could not possibly fail to tell you now what happened to me in Twin Falls some
years ago in the home of the stake president's counselor, when two little girls engaged in
conversation about the visitor to the stake conference the coming weekend. The smallest had
been influenced by the full-time missionaries, who had impressed her greatly. She could
hardly wait to grow up to be a missionary; she wanted to be an elder. Her older sister assured
her that she couldn't possibly be an elder, that only men could be elders, and she said, "Oh,
no. Daddy told me that Marion D. Hanks is coming to our conference, and <i>she's</i> an elder."
</p><p>
There are some things we live with gratefully, if sometimes patiently.
</p><p>
There is a poem which I believe was written for President McKay, though I am not sure the
author knew he wrote it for him, and I would like to take this chance to quote it. It is short
and impressive. Will you get the words&mdash;it says,
</p><p>
"'Tis human fortune's happiest height to be<br />
     A spirit melodious, lucid, poised, and whole; <br />
     Second in order of felicity<br />
     To walk with such a soul."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;     (Quoted in O. C. Tanner, <i>Christ's Ideals for Living</i>, p. v.)
</p><p>
I am sure I express your gratitude for the privilege of the walk with such a soul.
</p><p>
To me one of the most impressive sights in this world is the group at which I now look and
what it represents. Interspersed among you men are many choice youngsters. I had a chance
to shake hands with some a few minutes ago. And though I don't intend to talk only to them
or especially to them in the few minutes I stand here, I would like to be able to feel that they
understand what I am saying, and I am going to try to do that. If they do, I think the rest of
us will.
</p><p>
<b>"How Lucky Can You Be!"</b>
</p><p>
Brother Hinckley gave us a wonderful sermon this afternoon. I'm hopeful that all will have a
chance to read it. It revolved around an experience with mature, successful, effective,
intelligent men in varying degrees of involvement or noninvolvement with tobacco. As he
spoke the words of them, which he applied to himself, I applied them to myself; and you who
are here were doing likewise, I feel sure: "How lucky can you be."
</p><p>
I thought of an experience that occurred on these grounds a few years ago when an
internationally known nutritionist and research scientist, who had flown here from Stockholm
for the express purpose of looking at us and getting something of our story, sat across the
desk with a copy of the Doctrine and Covenants opened to section 89, of which and from
which we have been speaking tonight. I had asked him a question, and I was very much
interested in his answer. He had been a bit combative, or at least defensive along the route. I
said to him, "Dr. Waerland, what would you think of a young man, 27 years of age, who
wrote that document more than 120 years ago?"
</p><p>
He said, "I would say that he was 120 years ahead of his time." He then talked of some of the
nutritional, affirmative aspects of the Word of Wisdom. He talked of the discoveries of
science and of his own researches, and said that every suggestion of the Word of Wisdom was
affirmative and valid.
</p><p>
I said again, "What would you think of a prophet who knew all that long ago, without any
special preparation or training in the sense you have had it?"
</p><p>
And he said again, "I am not a religious man, and I know little of prophets, but whoever
wrote that document was 120 years ahead of his time."
</p><p>
<b>Investment in Health</b>
</p><p>
How fortunate can we be? Many of us are not acquainted with the facts, though many of us
are, that in this world there are many choice forces seeking the same ends we are when we
teach this great principle of health. One who represented an interesting viewpoint was Thomas
A. Edison, thought by many to be the greatest creative genius this world has known. In his
diary he wrote these words, and I would hope that every young Latter-day Saint who
sometimes feels uneasy in the peculiarities or uniqueness of his own health viewpoints would
remember them or have access to them. Edison is talking about ways of living and thinking
and working. He says, "The useful man never leads the easy, sheltered, knockless, unshocked
life. At 36 he ought to be prepared to deal with realities, and after about that period in his
life, until he is 60, he should be able to handle them with a steadily increasing efficiency.
Subsequently, if he has not injured his body by excess indulgence in any of the narcotics (and
by this term I mean liquor, tobacco, tea, and coffee), and if he has not eaten to excess, he
very likely may continue to be achievingly efficient up to his 80th birthday, and in
exceptional cases until 90."
</p><p>
<b>The Nature of Alcohol</b>
</p><p>
Now, I interpolated no words, all of those are his. He identifies narcotics specifically and
interestingly as substances with which we as a Church have been at odds since God spoke to a
boy-prophet a long time ago.
</p><p>
I cannot forget an occasion when Dr. John A. Widtsoe, whom you will remember as a great
scientist as well as a great Latter-day Saint leader, was one of a group of panelists at a
university. Two others, also representing religious points of view, preceded him. One
attempted to make an accommodation to work out an acceptable approach to moderation in
drink. The next was a fine young minister of the gospel, and he with measured but very
emphatic phrases objected to all that his predecessor had said, and added, "As a people, and
particularly as a group of young leaders in my church, we believe alcohol to be a tool of the
devil, and we are against it." Dr. Widtsoe stood and very quietly and graciously said, "We
link arms with this choice young man and those who walk with him because his view I accept
and believe to be our own." And then, he said, "Because I have a little time allotted and
because my background happens to be chemistry and its research, let me talk to you of the
nature of alcohol." I understood that he was linking arms with other good people of honest
intent who were seeking to teach the truth about substances that are not good for the human
body.
</p><p>
<b>The Cleanness and Integrity of the Human Body</b>
</p><p>
Now, the Lord has given us a great program of health, but not infrequently I expect some of
us don't tell our young people and maybe fail to recall ourselves that this program is based on
marvelous fundamental eternal principles. You will remember that in the Doctrine and
Covenants in a great section received in 1832, a great revelation, the Lord says, ". . . the spirit
and the body are the soul of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/15#15">D&amp;C 88:15</a>).
A little later he revealed again the truth that
the elements&mdash;that is, the elements that make up our body&mdash;[p. 92.] and the spirit in us,
when they are combined, permit us to have a fulness of joy. These are eternally important
principles. They go hand in hand with the great truth that God lives, that he is the Father of
the spirits of all mankind, that mortal life has a great meaning in the eternal journey man
makes, and that one of the great purposes of mortal life is to take upon ourselves a mortal
body (the elements), because in our eternal experience there will come a time of reunion of
body and spirit. You see, young men, when we die, as surely we do, the body goes to the
tomb. The spirit persists, it goes on it lives. You will be you, and I will be I, each will be
himself. Yes, there is a break in the eternal journey, but the break is only for the body. The
spirit goes on, and then one day in God's wisdom and through his power the body will be
reconstituted (in a way I do not know, and the detail is of no great consequence to me),
resurrected, and the body and the spirit will recombine: ". . . the spirit and the body are the
soul of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/15#15">D&amp;C 88:15</a>).
A little later he revealed again the truth that the elements&mdash;that
is the elements that make up your body&mdash;and the spirit in us, when they are combined, permit
us to have a fulness of joy. These are eternally important principles. They go hand in hand
with the great truth that God lives, that He is the father of the spirits of all mankind, that
mortal life has a great meaning in the eternal journey man makes, and that one of the great
purposes of mortal life is to take upon ourselves a mortal body (the elements), because in our
eternal experience there will come a time of reunion of body and spirit. You see, young men,
when we die, as surely we do, the body goes to the tomb. The spirit persists, it goes on, it
lives. You will be you, and I will be I, each will be himself. Yes, there is a break in the
eternal journey, but the break is only for the body. The spirit goes on, and then one day in
God's wisdom and through his power the body will be reconstituted (in a way I do not know,
and the detail of which is of no great consequence to me), resurrected, and the body and the
spirit will recombine:  ". . . the spirit and the body are the soul of man"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/15#15">D&amp;C 88:15</a>). That's
one big reason why it is very important that we understand the fundamental principles upon
which this great program rests. It is vital that we do everything we can to preserve in honor
and cleanliness and integrity this mortal body. It is part of our eternal soul.
</p><p>
I remember reading a statement by a great person who said that this is one of the paradoxes
of modern Christianity. It makes the body a very useless, negative, evil thing, and yet teaches,
theoretically at least, the reality of a resurrection in which this body is part of an eternal soul.
There is no such difficulty in the philosophy God has permitted us to understand. The body is
a non-evil component of the eternal soul. That's one big reason why we ought to be anxious
to keep it clean, anxious to be interested to keep from it the substances that would harm it&mdash;and
not alone it, but the rest of us. Have you ever heard these words of Goethe, the great
German: "The  whole purpose of the world seems to be to provide a physical basis for the
growth of the spirit."
</p><p>
<b>The Temple in which the Spirit Dwells</b>
</p><p>
Now, in effect, and perhaps with some limitations of understanding, Goethe was talking about
what Paul said. Paul said that this is a temple, this body in which the Spirit of God dwells
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/3/16#16">1 Cor. 3:16</a>)&mdash;a spirit child of God. And Paul thus expressed his understanding that it is
our obligation to keep it clean and pure and, so far as we are able, free from the intrusions of
that which would harm it.
</p><p>
<b>"A principle with a promise"</b>
</p><p>
Now let me say, as I conclude, one other thing. This is a principle with a promise. For years,
young and some older people have been coming to me asking me to define substances or list
them which were not to be used. And I have tried to reply with the words of the Lord: This is
a principle with a promise (see (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/3#3">D&amp;C 89:3</a>).
What is the principle? As I understand it, the
principle is that everything that God has provided for us that is good we should use with
thanksgiving, with judgment, with prudence, and not in excess. Everything that isn't good for
us we should let alone. I understand that to be the heart of the principle. And the promise?
The promise is that if we will obey the principle through obedience we will get better health,
greater knowledge and wisdom, and wonderful spiritual blessings. There are so many
examples of these great truths that I would like to tell you about, but let me mention one. As
I walked to this building this very afternoon, I heard a man say to his companion (and I
didn't recognize either, nor do I think they were part of the conference group and I know
nothing of the genesis of the statement or its circumstances, but I report accurately what he
said): "When he gets a few drinks in him, he is really ugly and mean."
</p><p>
I'm not sure anybody can improve upon that description of one who makes the mistake of
getting involved in a substance that dulls his judgment, that inhibits his natural anxiety to
control himself, that imposes upon his will.
</p><p>
God bless us to have the courage of conviction to live the principle and therefore inherit the
promise, and to be courageous enough as we mingle with those who do not understand the
principle, to appreciate their value and their worth, and share with them, as they will permit,
the important reasons why we should be concerned to be obedient to this law of God, in the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
