<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Unforgettable Holy Land</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Spencer W. Kimball</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Spencer W. Kimball, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 77-81</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
When I was a little boy in Primary and Sunday School there was one song we sang almost
more than any other. One verse and chorus go like this: 
</p><p>
"O Galilee! sweet Galilee!<br />
Where Jesus loved so much to be; <br />
Oh Galilee! blue Galilee!<br />
Come, sing thy songs again to me.
</p><p>
     "And when I read the thrilling lore<br />
     Of him who walked upon the sea<br />
     I long, oh, how I long once more<br />
     To follow him in Galilee."
</p><p>
And at last after many years, that longing was fulfilled, and I saw his beloved Galilee. Would
you like to make a little hurried trip with us to the land of milk and honey
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/3/8#8">Ex. 3:8</a>), the land our
fathers loved?
</p><p>
We stand on the steepened hill rising north from the blue, blue sea of Galilee. We are
hundreds of feet below sea level. It is winter, and the air is crisp, and our top coats are little
enough. Our guide points out locations, at least some of which are authentic. Here, he says,
sat the multitude while the Master expounded the never-dying "Sermon on the Mount." Below
us lies the sea he loved. It is smaller than we expected. We can see the whole of it in one
glance. It is not unlike a great heart in shape or function for its fluid has been the life blood
of millions of people through many ages.
</p><p>
This is the sea of miracles. We see it calm and placid, and again, rough and boisterous.
Countless fish from it have fed countless peoples. It was crossed numerous times by the
Savior in little boats, in larger ships; and in its cool waters, tired feet were cooled. Its wild
waves were calmed by his single command: "Peace, be still!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/4/39#39">Mark 4:39</a>). He walked on its surface; he
preached from its shores. Not far to our left gathered the thousands whose hunger was
satisfied on the miracled increase of loaves and fishes.
</p><p>
And we can almost see the disciples gathering up twelve baskets of residue after 5,000 had
fed on five loaves and two fishes (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/20-21#20">Matt. 14:20-21</a>).
We seem to see the four special fishermen with their nets
and boats. Here Peter grappled with a fish which had in its mouth a coin for taxes
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/27#27">Matt. 17:27</a>). Down
there he walked on the water (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/14/25-31#25">Matt. 14:25-31</a>);
and when his faith waned, it was supplemented by that of the
Lord. With our Testament open we read of the ministry of Christ, for this was the scene of
much of it. We ask for the cities in which he lived and performed so many miracles, for we
remember that in this area of but a few miles much of his work was done, much of his
ministry was accomplished. We would like to walk through the triplet cities
so often visited: Bethsaida, Chorazin and Capernaum. We see no spires nor towers, nor walls.
We ask our guide: "Where is Chorazin?" He shakes his head. There is no Chorazin. We
conclude it must have been on those hills above where now are sprouting grain and vegetables
and dry weeds.
</p><p>
"Then where is Bethsaida?" we ask. "Where is that noted city where so many sick were
healed and the lame were made to walk; where deaf could hear and lepers lost their curse?
Where is his favorite place he often lodged, the home of Andrew, Peter, and Philip, his dearest
friends? Where is old Bethsaida, the house of fishers, the place of miracles, the seat of gospel
teachings, where fishermen became apostles?" In these very few miles much of interest
happened. "Where is Bethsaida?" Our guide shakes his head again. There is no Bethsaida.
"Capernaum, then?" we ask, "Where is that important place, the port where fish were loaded,
traded, marketed?" He shakes his head again, then smiles as he thinks it through and changes
the accent, and "Oh, you mean Capernaum." He shows us the ruins of a large synagogue.
</p><p>
If this was of the Messianic period, it is the sole survivor. A back wall, great stones tumbled in
disarray, some olive presses are mute reminders of long ago. But that can't be Capernaum, his
own city, the great Capernaum, the haughty, wicked, rebellious, Capernaum!
</p><p>
Now we realize that we should not have expected to see these cities, for were they not
doomed 1,900 years ago? Have we forgotten the prophetic curse of the Master? In their
unrepentant attitudes toward the Savior of the world and his exalting message, Christ warned:
"Woe unto thee, Chorazin! Woe unto thee, Bethsaida! for if the mighty works, which were
done in you, had been in Tyre and Sidon, they would have repented long ago in sackcloth and
ashes.
</p><p>
"But I say unto you, It shall be more tolerable for Tyre and Sidon at the day of judgment,
than for you." We found that Tyre and Sidon still exist on the Mediterranean coast.
</p><p>
"And thou, Capernaum, which art exalted unto heaven, shalt be brought down to hell: for if
the mighty works, which have been done in thee, had been done in Sodom, it would have
remained until this day. But I say unto you, That it shall be more tolerable for the land of
Sodom in the day of judgment, than for thee"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/21-24#21">Matt. 11:21-24</a>).
</p><p>
And then we remember that only prophets and angels had visited Sodom to call that people to
repentance, but for these tri-cities the Creator, the Lord, the Christ had come in person and
for nearly three years had dwelt among them and performed the miracles and taught the
gospel. They had ignored and rejected him. (We cannot remember ever reading about any
Church branches in these cities.) Sodom and Gomorrah went up in smoke "as the smoke of a
furnace" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/19/28#28">Gen. 19:28</a>).
If these cities were more rebellious than Tyre and Sidon, more corrupt than Sodom,
and more wicked than Gomorrah, we think we understand.
</p><p>
We bathe our tired feet in the rippling waters of the shoreline. We look for remains of former
cities. A few stones lapped by the water are rounded or squared. Could they have been a part
of a synagogue, the home of Peter, the remains of a stone harbor, the walls of the centurion's
place?
</p><p>
We move to the Jordan, the deepest ditch in the world, the liquid backbone of Palestine. "The
river that goes down" is an appropriate name, for it descends in many streams from
snow-covered Mt. Hermon in thousands of leaps and falls and gurgles to saunter through the
valley of Hula and take a kind hospitable rest in the blue of Galilee. It tears and twists ever
more swiftly downward in an almost incredibly sinuous manner from the sweet waters of the
fountains and melting snow to the bitter dead waters of the salt sea, 2,500 feet lower.
</p><p>
This Jordan is not so unlike our own Jordan in this Salt Lake Valley. Squirming, twisting,
burrowing madly, reversing, side to side, turning, writhing like a serpent, meandering like a
lazy tidewater stream but in places pushing, hurrying swiftly down its circuitous way. It loops
in quarter, half, and three quarter turns and travels two hundred miles of river in a sixty mile
distance, covered three to ten feet deep and ninety to one hundred feet wide.
It flows swiftly, some of the way through its whirlpools, cascades, and winding through the
jungle growth. And we are on its banks not many miles from where it spreads gently into the
sea, where it also dies.
</p><p>
The Jordan&mdash;the famous Jordan! (We open our Bibles and read.) Across and beyond, not
many miles is Mt. Pisgah. We fancy we see an old bearded man whose "eye was not dim nor
his natural force abated" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/34/7#7">Deut. 34:7</a>).
He climbs the heights as commanded: 
</p><p>
"Get thee up into the top of Pisgah," said the Lord, "and lift up thine eyes westward, and
northward, and southward, and eastward, and behold it with thine eyes: for thou shalt not go
over this Jordan" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/3/27#27">Deut. 3:27</a>).
It is a little land. Moses could see Mt. Hermon to the far
north, the Mediterranean to the west, south and east to the deserts and the country in between.
Miles are short unless one travels on foot or by donkey as did the Savior. From Dan to
Beersheba he can see almost the whole of Palestine spread out before him like a huge
elephant hide, wrinkled in hills and valleys and thicker and heavier on top and thinning at the
edges where are the Jordan and the Mediterranean.
</p><p>
We fancy we can see the hordes of Israelites coming from the south, four decades earlier
released from Egypt's thralldom. They come with their families and burdens to this river, too
deep to ford. Moses has been left behind, but Joshua commands, and the Jordan dries as did
the Red Sea before them (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/3/7-17#7">Josh. 3:7-17</a>).
And Israel with their bundles, animals, burdens, flocks, and families
crossed this winding muddy river to the promised land on which we stand. We turn westward.
About three miles are Gilgal ruins, the first camp of Israel on the west. And a little farther is
Jericho, the old and the new. The ancient one is in ruins and its tumbling walls, buried for
ages, are now excavated. These crumbling walls fell when the ram horns of the people of
Joshua rent the air and when the tramping of hordes of feet seemed to shake them
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/josh/6/1-27#1">Josh. 6:1-27</a>). Beyond is
the precipitous mountain between here and Jerusalem where, tradition claims, is the Mount of
Temptation, where the divine voice commanded, "Get thee behind me, Satan"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/8#8">Luke 4:8</a>).
</p><p>
We are back on the banks of the Jordan where it is narrower and swifter. We fancy we see
Elijah and Elisha cross the miraculously drained river bed. From here we see the towers of
Jerusalem on the crest of the high western hills. The river still intrigues us. Abraham, Lot,
and Jacob waded it; Joshua and Israel crossed it; its fords were fought over; it was a barrier
against enemies and a hiding place for fugitives; in it the Syrian captain left his leprosy; here
Elijah crossed dry shod, and here Elisha received Elijah's mantle. Here John preached, and
here was the Lord baptized to fulfil all righteousness. We tread lightly, for this is sacred
ground. We reabsorb the story as we read. We fancy we see in the muddy water two people
and one is immersed. A holy voice speaks, and we hear impressive words, "This is my
Beloved Son in whom I am well pleased"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/17#17">Matt. 3:17</a>).
</p><p>
We climb the sharp hills to the west, reluctantly leaving the sacred spots made holy by the
presence and works of the Master. Perhaps these very hills may be the ones in which he
sought solitude so often as he climbed the mount apart.
</p><p>
Through grain fields, over hilly areas, and through the great valley of Jezreel, with a distance
less than from Salt Lake City to Ogden, we come to Megiddo. Let us stand on this abrupt
eminence for from here we can see much of Galilee. This steep hill goes back near the
beginning. History grew up here. Many civilizations have come and gone, and the debris tells
scientists that the ruins of the 20th civilization is the one on which we tread. This is Megiddo
or Armageddon&mdash;Megiddo, the ancient&mdash;Megiddo, the scene of mighty conflicts&mdash;"Battle
Mountain," it could be called. This hill has witnessed the caravans of traders for many
centuries&mdash;caravans laden with treasures for trade around the fertile crescent and the East.
This hill has seen armies of great nations, training, camping, fighting, bleeding&mdash;Egyptians,
Assyrians, Canaanites, Israelites, Persians, Greeks, Romans, Saracens, Crusaders, the Turks,
and the British.
</p><p>
Soil here was fertilized with human bodies&mdash;soil here was drenched with human blood.
</p><p>
We climb the ramp walk on the farther side and pick gorgeous scarlet poppies as we climb.
Did not the Savior say something about Solomon in all his glory not being arrayed like one of
these (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/29#29">Matt. 6:29</a>)?
</p><p>
Here Solomon stabled his horses and stored his chariots. Here are the excavated silo pits in
which their barley and other feed was stored; here certainly were some of Solomon's "forty
thousand stalls for horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/4/26#26">1 Kgs. 4:26</a>).
Below us is the fertile, watered valley of Esdraelon, where grew the barley and the straw
stored in the silos for the king's horses and dromedaries. His horses were prized ones, costing
in Egypt 150 shekels of silver, and a chariot, four times the amount
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/10/29#29">1 Kgs. 10:29</a>). They must have the best
food and lodging. Below in the checkered valley grew the barley, the vegetables, the fruits,
the grapes.
</p><p>
Beneath us is the brook Kishon (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/18/40#40">1 Kgs. 18:40</a>).
To our left is the Carmel range, and here was Elijah in his
memorable contest with the priests of Baal. Mt. Carmel stones made the altar, Mt. Carmel
wood was the fuel. Mt. Carmel saw the defeat and route of 400 idolatrous priests of Baal and
the great triumph of the prophet of the God of Israel.
</p><p>
Across the little valley in a clump of green is Endor. Just those few miles away. Disguised
King Saul and the witch of Endor were here. What consternation must have enveloped the
perturbed Saul as he was told his army would be captured; he and his sons would be killed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_sam/28/7-19#7">1 Sam. 28:7-19</a>).
The Lord could have walked here many times. It is near Nazareth.
</p><p>
A little to the right is Nain. We fancy we see the large crowd of people with the Master at the
head walking into the little village. A funeral procession is en route to the cemetery, and they
meet at the city's gate. A few minutes pass, and the mourners turn around and return to their
homes. A miracle has happened&mdash;a dead man is now a living soul. The widow is overjoyed.
The restored lad is speaking (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/7/11-15#11">Luke 7:11-15</a>).
The Nazarene may have been acquainted with and sympathetic
with this widow, for Nain is but a few miles from Nazareth. Across to the left is the rounded
Mt. Tabor. It looks like a gigantic basketball with its lower seventy percent buried. It is
wooded. We read our New Testament again. Here is reputed to be the Mount of
Transfiguration. If that be true then up these steepening slopes walked the Lord with Peter,
James, and John. There they would meet in conference with Moses and Elias, and three
humble fishermen apostles would hear from the overshadowing cloud the voice of the Eternal
Father in heaven introducing his Son Jesus Christ as his Beloved Son in whom he was well
pleased; and here would Peter say: ". . . let us make here three tabernacles; one for thee, and
one for Moses, and one for Elias" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/4#4">Matt. 17:4</a>),
and here would unspeakable things be told and authority be given.
</p><p>
Beyond Tabor, not very far is Cana, the place of the miracle of the wedding feast. Jesus and
his family might have been well acquainted in nearby Cana.
</p><p>
To the left of Tabor and across the valley of Jezreel, in the cup in the cluster of hills, is the
boyhood home of the Savior. That is Nazareth toward the top of the long canyon draw, the
city of gnarled olive trees and threshing floors. There are the old stone houses of the ages
past. There are the caves in which he played, the hills he climbed, the places where he
worked.
</p><p>
And this is Galilee, and in a glance we can see the haunts of Jesus' growing-up years and his
ministry. He likely knew every hill and vale, every creek and valley. He surely knew many of
the people, for distances were not great and people not too numerous. Here and in the plains
below he must have learned the many lessons of his parables. Birds of the air, the foxes in
their holes, the lilies of the valley, the olive press, the plow, the waving grain, the wine press,
the watchmen towers. It would be from one of these sharp hills that his townspeople would
have thrown him to death (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/29#29">Luke 4:29</a>)&mdash;perhaps
the only inhabitant which would ever be prominent
enough to be remembered by history. Perhaps in those very caves or tombs was he
able to escape from their fury to leave forever the city of his growing up.
</p><p>
We stand upon Mt. Olivet the mile-long mountain above Jerusalem. It is a long, rugged way
to its top, but the Lord must have climbed it numerous times. Behind the mount but a few
short miles is Bethany where he visited his loved friends Mary and Martha and Lazarus whom
he brought out of the tomb when four days dead by the single authoritative command,
"Lazarus come forth" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/43#43">John 11:43</a>).
</p><p>
Below us is the Kidron Valley, deepening sharply down to the Pool of Siloam where the
fountain water comes forth from the mountain on which the city stands. Here the blind man
came to see, when he washed the clay and spittle from his eyelids in response to the
command, "Go, wash in the pool of Siloam"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/7#7">John 9:7</a>).
</p><p>
Above are the high up, irregular city walls and within them the narrow streets, the cave-like
shops, the dark passages, the wailing wall. Nearest us are the temple precincts, where the
courts and towers were so important in those centuries when history was being made. Beyond
is Golgotha, the place of the skull, the hill of crucifixion. There he suffered and bled and
died. Not far from the mount is the garden tomb thought to be the sacred one where the
lifeless body of the Redeemer lay, and immediately outside of it the garden into which he
emerged from the tomb where he said to Mary, "Touch me not; for I am not yet ascended to
my father" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/17#17">John 20:17</a>).
</p><p>
At the foot of this mount is Gethsemane where his sufferings were beyond all mortal
comprehension. We climb this lofty Mount of Olives to its rounded top and stand on sacred
ground. Here Christ's earthly ministry was completed; here the apostles gathered about him,
saw the overshadowing cloud receive him out of their sight, and breathless, stood in awe and
wonder as the angels said, "Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven? this
same Jesus, which is taken up from you into heaven, shall so come in like manner as ye have
seen him go into heaven" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/1/11#11">Acts 1:11</a>).
</p><p>
To visit the places where such momentous happenings affected the eternities of us all was
most interesting and intriguing and added color to our picture, but we did not need to walk
through the Holy Land to know eternal truth.
</p><p>
We realized it is not so important to know whether Mt. Hermon or Mt. Tabor was the
transfiguration place but to know that on the summit of a high mountain was held a great
conference of mortal and immortal beings where unspeakable things were said and
authoritative keys were delivered and approval was given of the life and works of his only
Begotten Son when the voice of the Father in the overshadowing cloud said: "This is my
Beloved Son in whom I am well pleased"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/17/5#5">Matt. 17:5</a>).
</p><p>
Not so important to know upon which great stone the Master leaned in agonizing
decision-prayers in the Garden of Gethsemane, as to know that he did in that area conclude to
accept voluntarily crucifixion for our sakes. Not so needful to know on which hill his cross
was planted nor in what tomb his body lay nor in which garden he met Mary, but that he did
hang in voluntary physical and mental agony; that his lifeless, bloodless body did lie in the
tomb into the third day as prophesied, and above all that he did emerge a resurrected
perfected one&mdash;the first fruits of all men (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/20#20">1 Cor. 15:20</a>)
in resurrection and the author of the gospel which
could give eternal life to obedient man.
</p><p>
Not so important to know where he was born and died and resurrected but to know for a
certainty that the Eternal, Living Father came to approve his Son in his baptism and later in
his ministry, that the Son of God broke the bands of death and established the exaltation, the
way of life, and that we may grow like him in knowledge and perfected eternal life. And this
I know, and give my solemn witness, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
