<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Concept of the Christlike Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Harold B. Lee</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Harold B. Lee, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1954, pp. 69-73</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I would be indeed ungrateful this morning were I not to acknowledge the blessings of my
Heavenly Father to me and mine, and I do that most humbly.
</p><p>
I seek for the uplift of the spirit of this great conference and your faith and prayers in these
next few minutes.
</p><p>
I could wish for no better background for the few thoughts I would like to express than the
buoyancy of the wonderful youth representing our great Brigham Young University who have
sung to us so inspiringly at this session of our conference.
</p><p>
The text that I would like to consider for a few moments is in the nature of a question from a
young Latter-day Saint youth at Fort Lewis military training camp, a son of a prominent
Latter-day Saint family.  His question was: "What is your concept of a Christlike life? Please
explain in detail the qualifications necessary for one to gain an exaltation in the kingdom of
heaven."
</p><p>
I was intrigued by that question, and if the Spirit of the Lord is willing, I should like to make
an answer to that young man within the time limitations this morning; and if the congregation
here will pardon me, I will talk directly to that young man who may
possibly be in attendance because I believe that his question is the question that is being asked
by every serious-minded Latter-day Saint youth today.
</p><p>
Young man, your question is not unique.  It is not different.  It is the same question that has
been asked by the honest-hearted ever since the world began.  It is the question that was in
the mind of Nicodemus, the master in Israel, when he came to the Savior by night, and the
Master discerning the purpose of his coming, explained to aim what was necessary in order
for him to enter or even to see the kingdom of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/3-5#3">John 3:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
It was the same question asked by the zealous Saul of Tarsus on that memorable occasion
while on his way to Damascus when he was blinded by the light; he heard a voice speak out
of heaven; humbled as only one can be humbled in the presence of a great spiritual
experience.  In answer to the Lord's rebuke, the humble Saul asked, "Lord, what wilt thou
have me to do?" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/6#6">Acts 9:6</a>).
</p><p>
It was the cry of the sinful David who, amidst his pleadings
and his sufferings, granted the knowledge of the course which he must pursue, in order that
his soul would not be left in hell
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/16/10#10">Ps. 16:10</a>).
It was the same thing the Jews asked on the day of
Pentecost: "What must we do to be saved?" (see
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/37#37">Acts 2:37</a>).
</p><p>
To answer your question fully, and that of these others to which I have made reference would
require a full explanation of the plan of salvation given in the gospel of Jesus Christ.  While
yet in your youth, you have done well to ask that question, young man, to seek counsel as to
your course in life, for every soul who lives has the possibility, as you have, of an exaltation
in the celestial kingdom.
</p><p>
I wish you could have been here to the general priesthood meeting on Saturday night, but
maybe you were.  I wish you could have repeated under President McKay's direction the First
Article of Faith, "We believe in God, the Eternal Father, and in His Son, Jesus Christ, and in
the Holy Ghost" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1#1">A of F 1:1</a>), and then listened intently to every word as you repeated with President
McKay the Thirteenth Article of Faith: "We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent,
virtuous, and in doing good to all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>).
But I would have you this morning think of
another of the Articles of Faith in connection therewith because it has a particular significance
in the answer to your question: "We believe that through the Atonement of Christ, all
mankind may be saved, by obedience to the laws and ordinances of the Gospel"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/3#3">A of F 1:3</a>).
</p><p>
A great philosopher has said the same thing in other words when he declared: "Every one of
us, with of God and within the limitations of human capability, himself makes his own
disposition, his character, and his permanent condition." (Emil Souvestre.)
</p><p>
May I give you in answer to your question the example of three youths who, faced with the
stern temptations of life, met those tests and came through nobly and victoriously, despite the
odds against them. I say I give you these examples in order that you may learn and recognize three of
the great dangers which confront youth today.
</p><p>
The first, an example of a young girl, whom I met when I was asked address a group of
young girls a few years ago over at the Lion House where they were being shepherded under
the direction of the great Young Women's Mutual Improvement Association.  At the close of
our meeting this lovely girl took me aside, and from her purse she unfolded a picture of a
handsome young soldier.  Underneath the picture was something about love, and his name
signed.  I asked, "Well, what does this mean?" Tears were swimming in her eyes.  She
replied, "I met that young man here in an army camp.  He was not a member of the Church. 
He was clean and fine, and he had the ideals I had longed for in a companion, all except one
thing, he was not a member of the Church.  And when he proposed marriage
to me, I said, 'Only will I be married when I can be married in the house of the Lord because
love means something more than just a thing that pertains to this life.  It is an eternal thing,
and I want to be married in the temple.'"
</p><p>
Well, he reasoned with her, he pleaded with her, he scolded, and then came angry; and finally
after repeated efforts to break down her religious objection to a marriage out of the temple, he
finally left her.  It was now time to go overseas, and she cried her heart out the night he left
thinking that maybe she had made a mistake because her heart had gone out to this fine
young man.
</p><p>
During a long ocean voyage over to Australia where he was to be stationed and from where
he was to go into combat, he began to think about this young woman.  He began to think that
he had been a little hasty in his judgment about her religious convictions.  Perhaps it was her
religion that had made her the fine girl that she was.  With that on his mind, he began to seek
companionship with our Latter-day Saint men. He finally met a Latter-day Saint chaplain
there and became associated with the Latter-day Saint boys of the camp and began to study
the gospel. On her birthday he had sent her this picture attached, and behind the picture was a
slip of paper which proved to be a certificate evidencing the fact that he had been baptized a
member of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints.  In the letter which accompanied
the picture, he had said, "I am preparing now to live worthy so that when I come home, I can
be ordained an elder and together we can be married in the house of the Lord."
</p><p>
There, young man, is the first thing that you must think of, if you would have an exaltation in
the celestial kingdom.  Marriage is eternal, and there was a youth who realized the foundation
on which she must build if she were to have a fullness of eternal happiness. The second
example is that of an impetuous young man.  One morning he was confronted by his mother
with rather a startling statement.  His mother said to him, "Son, last night I had a
premonition.  I had a feeling that you are going to be faced with a grave temptation by a
certain woman who is setting her cap for you.  I warn you to be on guard." And this youth
brushed it aside in his characteristic way, "Oh, Mother, you are silly; nothing is farther from
the fact.  She is a fine woman." And the mother replied, "Well, be careful, my son." Within
thirty days from the time of his mother's warning, that youth stood face to face with the
temptation about which his mother had been warned.
</p><p>
Youth, if you want to be guided by wisdom, stay close to your parents.  Listen to the counsel
of your father and your mother and lean heavily upon the experience of their lives because
they are entitled to inspiration in the rearing of their family.  Young man, may I plead with
you to keep yourself morally clean?  Revere womanhood.  May I remind you of what you
repeated some years ago as a slogan in the MIA.  It was a quotation from a portion of a
message of the First Presidency particularly to servicemen in military service during some of
these strenuous, difficult times through which you and others like you have lived.  This is
what the First Presidency wrote: "How glorious and near to the angels is youth that is clean.
This youth has joy unspeakable here and eternal happiness hereafter.  Sexual purity is youth's
most precious possession.  It is the foundation of all righteousness.  Better dead clean, than
alive unclean."
</p><p>
Honor your name, young man.  You come of an illustrious family. Not to maintain the high
standards which the Presidency have suggested would not only be a blight upon you, but a
blight upon that great family name you bear, and a blight upon the Church for which your
forefathers and ancestors sacrificed their lives to establish.
</p><p>
In the prayer at the dedication of the Idaho Falls Temple the First
Presidency said something of  great  importance to the girls about the purity of life.  This is what
the Presidency wrote in that inspired prayer: "We pray for the daughters of Zion.  May they
be preserved in virtue, chastity, and purity of life, be blessed with vigorous bodies and minds,
and with great faith. May they develop into true womanhood and receive choice companions
under the new and everlasting covenant for time and for all eternity in thy temples provided
for this priceless privilege and purpose.
</p><p>
Young man, should you find companionship with a beautiful young girl, will you remember
that quotation, and will you take occasion during your courtship to read to her that most vital
message from the prophets of the living God in our day to warn her also against one of the
besetting sins of this world in which we live?
</p><p>
May I now give you the third example to suggest a third danger?  The story of this incident
comes from the testimony of the wife of a mission president who just returned from one of
our Communist-dominated countries. A young girl attending a school in that country one day
was abused by her teacher when he learned of her identity as a Latter-day Saint girl, having
faith in a living God.  As a punishment to her he demanded that she sit down and write fifty
times, there is no God." This little girl, shaken by the punishment imposed by that teacher,
went home and talked it over with mother.  Her mother said, "No, girl, you must never write,
'There is no God.' You go back and tell your teacher you know there is a God and you can't
lie." And the girl went back and faced this teacher, and he said, more angrily than ever, "You
go back and write that and write it a hundred times, 'There is no God,' or I warn you that
something terrible will happen to you."
</p><p>
The mother and daughter prayed nearly all night that night, and then next morning they fasted
and went together to the room of that teacher. They waited for him to come.  The he didn't
show up, and the principal, seeing that they were waiting, came to them and asked, "Are you
waiting for your teacher?" She said, "Yes, we are waiting for him." "Well, I am sorry to tell
you that he suffered a heart attack and died suddenly this morning."
</p><p>
Something terrible did happen, but it wasn't to that young girl.  It happened to a man inspired
with satanic motives.
</p><p>
Young man, I would warn you, along with the others of your age, to be forewarned of the
threats to your faith. I warn you against the man-made philosophies and the doctrines which
would destroy that faith in God basic to exaltation in the celestial kingdom.
</p><p>
If you remember those examples, young man, and live worthy of your name, the marvelous
rewards of our heavenly Father will be yours.  Listen to what the Lord promised: 
</p><p>
Verily, thus saith the Lord: It shall come to pass that every soul that forsaketh his sins and
cometh unto me, and calleth on my name, and obeyeth my voice, and keep my
commandments, shall see my face and shall know that I am
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/1#1">D&amp;C 93:1</a>).
</p><p>
And after you begin to understand that, then, young man, go to the 76th Section of the
Doctrine and Covenants, in some respects, one of the most glorious visions that has ever been
given to mortal man.  Read from the 50th to the 70th verses of that great vision
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/50-70#50">D&amp;C 76:50-70</a>), and you will
have understanding in better words than I can give you today.
</p><p>
My son, go and have your patriarchal blessing, for there under inspiration your patriarch will
give you, as someone has said, "paragraphs from the book of your own possibilities."
</p><p>
And now after this brief conversation with you, my young brother, may I close it by a little
quotation from a great thinker who said this: 
</p><p>
The highest of all arts is the art of living well.  Beyond the beauty of sculpture and painting,
of poetry or music, is the beauty of a well-spent life.  Here all can be artists.  Every man can
be a hero.
</p><p>
Obedience to that divine command, "Be ye therefore perfect, even as your Father which is in
heaven is perfect" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>),
will ally man with God and will make of earth a paradise.
</p><p>
God bless you, my young friend. Keep on thinking the serious thoughts and asking those
serious questions, and in time, as you keep your eyes fixed upon the stars to guide you on and
on and upward, you will reach your objective&mdash;an exaltation in the celestial kingdom of our
Heavenly Father, which I pray for you and all youth of Zion, and all the world if that were
possible, in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
