<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Road to Damascus</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Howard W. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Howard W. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 106-110</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I would like to invite you to turn back the pages of history nearly two thousand years and
walk with me down Damascus Road. This ancient way commences at one of the gates
through the north wall of the city of Jerusalem; winds through the hills of Judea; crosses the
Jordan River, the plains of the Decapolis east of Galilee; and goes over the plateau to the city
of Damascus, the oldest continuously inhabited city in the world. It was on this road, two or
three years after the crucifixion and resurrection of the Savior, that a marvelous event took
place which changed the course of a man's life and in turn has had an effect upon the lives of
millions of persons.
</p><p>
<b>Saul Born a Roman Citizen</b>
</p><p>
In the city of Tarsus, the Hellenistic capital city of Cilicia which was rival to Alexandria and
Athens, was born a Jewish boy who was given the name of Saul
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/3#3">Acts 22:3</a>). By birth he was a Roman
citizen because Cilicia had become a Roman province under the great Roman general and
statesman, Pompey. History has not recorded much of his early childhood, and we have very
little information concerning his father and mother, but it is assumed by most scholars that
they were people of means and position. His father was a Pharisee, one of the two major
religious and political divisions of Judaism. The Pharisees were the leading sect and held most
of the political offices in the state as well as the high priestly offices. They believed in a
resurrection and in a future life where men would be rewarded or punished
according to their deeds in this life. The Sadducees, on the other hand, denied a resurrection.
The Pharisees observed the law of the Sabbath, tithing, and ceremonial purity. They were
known for their comprehensive knowledge of the law and their strict observance of it. Saul
followed in the footsteps of his father and was a devoted Pharisee.
</p><p>
At Tarsus he learned the trade of working with his hands in weaving goat's-hair cloth and in
fabricating it into tents (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/18/1-3#1">Acts 18:1-3</a>).
This is not inconsistent with the assumption that he was a student of
the law because Jewish students were taught a trade so that they might provide for themselves
by their own hands.
</p><p>
<b>Gamaliel's Pupil</b>
</p><p>
While in his youth, Saul went to Jerusalem to be educated as a rabbi at the feet of Gamaliel
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/3#3">Acts 22:3</a>),
who was considered the most outstanding teacher of his time. This great rabbi and doctor of
the law taught the doctrine of strict compliance with the law, which was fundamental with the
Pharisees, yet he was liberal in some respects, and his teachings were tempered with
moderation. As a member of the Sanhedrin, he argued a course of tolerance and took a firm
stand against the prosecution of Peter and the other apostles after the death of the Master.
</p><p>
Under the teaching of Gamaliel, Saul became a zealot for God, a serious and a pious man. He
hungered and thirsted after righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/6#6">Matt. 5:6</a>)
and sought diligently to keep the law in every
respect as a devout Pharisee. In spite of the fact he had been a pupil of Gamaliel who taught
tolerance, Saul became an extreme persecutor of those who did not comply strictly with
Pharisaic Judaism.
</p><p>
<b>Persecuted the Christians</b>
</p><p>
After the crucifixion of Jesus, widespread persecution was soon commenced upon those who
followed his teachings. The activity of Stephen, a Hellenistic Jew, in this new cause brought
him into conflict with the Jews of Jerusalem, who, being angered by his eloquent presentation
of the new faith, brought him to trial before the Sanhedrin on the charge of blasphemy. The
age-old traditions of Judaism and the doctrines of Christianity, the two opposing orders, were
brought into sharp focus.
</p><p>
Stephen's statements before the Sanhedrin concerning his faith in Christ so maddened his
accusers that they dragged him from the tribunal and stoned him to death. Saul was present at
the trial. He stood by and held the garments of the chief witnesses while they killed Stephen
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/54-60#54">Acts 7:54-60</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/20#20">Acts 22:20</a>).
Following this, Saul began to participate actively in the campaign against the Christians. This
is the usual course of a man's life as he turns toward evil. First, he is a silent observer, then
he becomes a consenting spectator, and finally he is an active participant.
</p><p>
To this time there had not been a separation of the Christians from the synagogues of the
Jews, but the hour had come when the gospel of Christ should take the place of the law of
sacrifice, and the rupture with Judaism was imminent.
</p><p>
The persecutions which followed suppressed and dispersed the followers of Christ from
Jerusalem and scattered them throughout Judea and Samaria, thus aiding the spread of
Christianity. Like the tiny mustard seeds which grew into large plants, mentioned by the Lord
in the parable (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/31-32#31">Matt. 13:31-32</a>),
the seeds of Christianity were scattered to the wind and fell upon fertile soil.
As the plants began to grow, Saul was determined to stamp them out. His zeal as a defender
of the faith was unloosed against the followers of Jesus. A Christian man's house was no
longer his castle, for Saul entered into every house and dragged both men and women before
the magistrates, who in turn committed them to prison.
</p><p>
<b>On the Damascus Road</b>
</p><p>
Apparently Saul, one of the main instigators of the persecutions, feared the spread of the
gospel of Christ to more distant places. He went to the high priest in Jerusalem and secured a
commission in writing to the synagogues in Damascus, authorizing him to take into custody
the Jews of that city who had become followers of Jesus and return them to Jerusalem in
chains. This authority was issued, and Saul commenced his journey down Damascus Road
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/4-5#4">Acts 22:4-5</a>).
The record gives no information as to the other persons in the company, the
number of days it took to make the long journey, the conversation that may have taken place,
or any of the happenings along the way, until the day they came near Damascus about noon
". . . and suddenly there shined round about him a light from heaven. And he fell to the earth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/3-4#3">Acts 9:3-4</a>). This Pharisee who had come on an errand of persecution and those who
were with him heard a voice from the midst of the light saying: "Saul, Saul, why persecutest
thou me?" Saul answered: "Who art thou, Lord? And the Lord said, I am Jesus whom thou
persecutest: it is hard for thee to kick against the pricks"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/4-5#4">Acts 9:4-5</a>). This proverbial
expression of kicking against the pricks usually refers to the ox goad which was a piece of
pointed iron stuck in the end of a stick used to urge the ox while drawing the plow.
Sometimes a stubborn ox will kick back against the goad only to receive its sharpness more
severely. It has become a proverb to signify the absurdity of rebelling against lawful
authority.
</p><p>
Saul had been kicking against the goad, and now he was humbled to the dust. "And he
trembling and astonished said, Lord, what wilt thou have me to do? And the Lord said unto
him, Arise, and go into the city, and it shall be told thee what thou must do.
</p><p>
"And the men which journeyed with him stood speechless, hearing a voice, but seeing no
man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/6-7#6">Acts 9:6-7</a>).
</p><p>
Saul stood upright, but he could not see; his eyesight had been taken from him, and he was as
blinded physically as he had been spiritually. Those who were with him led him by the hand
into the city and to the house of Judas in the street called Straight. For three days he neither
ate nor drank but waited for the Lord to reveal to him what he must do as he had been
instructed by the voice (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/8-16#8">Acts 9:8-16</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The Climax</b>
</p><p>
On the third day the Lord appeared in a vision to a Jewish Christian named Ananias and told
him to go to Saul. Ananias demurred, for he had heard of the evil done by this man to the
Saints in Jerusalem and knew of the authority he had received to arrest the believers in Christ
in Damascus, but he did as the Lord instructed. When he came to the house of Judas, he
found Saul and laid his hands on him and administered to him saying, ". . . brother Saul, the
Lord, even Jesus, that appeared unto thee in the way as thou camest, hath sent me, that thou
mightest receive thy sight, and be filled with the Holy Ghost"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/17#17">Acts 9:17</a>). Saul had been
instantly blinded on Damascus Road, and his sight was instantly restored when Ananias laid
his hands on him. To make his conversion complete he was baptized. Paul's life was changed.
It is remarkable that the man who held the garments of Stephen's executioners thereafter
became the chief exponent of the principles for which Stephen died. Soon there was
commenced the great ministry of which the Christian world is so familiar, by the one whose
name became romanized and known as Apostle Paul.
</p><p>
<b>Paul's Purpose and Life Changed</b>
</p><p>
These are the facts from the record of one of the most important encounters in history. There
are those who are skeptics and cannot reconcile the events which might be classified as
supernatural. Appearances of Deity and voices and visions are often looked upon with
suspicion. Some are inclined to explain away the marvelous experience of Paul by saying it
was merely the imaginative culmination of an inner conflict of a man who had taken a strong
position in defense of the law, who had resolved to stamp out the threat to Judaism, but who
had a deep feeling that he was doing wrong. It doesn't seem likely that the whole course of a
man's life upon which he was so urgently set would be changed so suddenly and drastically
by an inner conflict. Men who are as determined as Paul are not quickly changed although
there may have been a spark which had smoldered for a long time before bursting into flame
that day on Damascus Road.
</p><p>
Some have said it was the long journey from Jerusalem to Damascus which gave him time to
think and contemplate during the days of travel upon the recent events of the persecution.
Paul had been present at the stoning of Stephen and had seen him die. He
heard him ask in his last words that those who had dragged him from the Sanhedrin and
stoned him in defiance of the law might be forgiven for their acts
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/59-60#59">Acts 7:59-60</a>). This must have made a
lasting impression on the mind of Paul. He had personally gone from house to house and
brought men and women before the tribunals which condemned them to prison or imposed the
sentence of death (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/8/1,3#1">Acts 8:1,3</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/4-5#4">Acts 22:4-5</a>). Because of him, many had left their homes and fled. Now he had traveled
to Damascus with further threats to inflict persecution upon those who followed Christ
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/9-12#9">Acts 26:9-12</a>). Could
it be that these things commenced to weigh heavily upon his conscience?
</p><p>
<b>Paul Tells of His Conversion</b>
</p><p>
Paul testified on many occasions concerning his conversion, that he had seen Jesus our Lord
and that the vision was a reality. In the book of the Acts of the Apostles there are three
accounts of the conversion. The first is the record of Luke in which the conversation between
the Lord and Paul is set forth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/9/3-6#3">Acts 9:3-6</a>).
In the second account Paul personally relates the facts of the
conversion in his speech to the angry crowd on the steps of the temple in Jerusalem
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/22/6-11#6">Acts 22:6-11</a>), and the
third is his defense before King Agrippa, the nephew of Herod, who had tried the Savior just
a few years before. Standing in the elegant surroundings of the court of the king, Paul spoke
in his own defense, recalling his youth, his beliefs as a Pharisee, his part in the persecutions,
and the marvelous vision on Damascus Road (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/13-18#13">Acts 26:13-18</a>).
After bearing witness of Jesus he said:
"Whereupon, O King Agrippa, I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/19#19">Acts 26:19</a>).
</p><p>
Paul's life had been bisected by Damascus Road. Before, he was an aggressive persecutor of
Christianity, but after Damascus Road he was one of its most fervent propagators.
</p><p>
<b>Others Like Him</b>
</p><p>
There are many men in the world who could be like Paul, men who could be changed in the
twinkling of an eye if willing to change the object of their lives as did Paul. There are some
who see but do not believe. One needs to be only a bystander to see, but to believe, one must
accept wholeheartedly and commit himself to his belief. This requires faith and repentance of
old ways. Paul had been raised in the belief his family had held for generations. He had been
trained in that faith, and it is fair to say that he understood it, but it was not until that day on
Damascus Road when Jesus spoke to him that the object of his life was changed. There are
persons in every church who see, but some do not believe. Because they have been raised in
the beliefs of their fathers, their minds are closed, and they are satisfied to continue. We
wonder why it took Paul so long to see the light and why he so vigorously opposed the
teachings of the Savior. The answer is apparent. He was born into a certain belief and
followed it until it became a habit. He had a preconceived idea of the law which closed his
mind to the truth until that event on Damascus Road.
</p><p>
<b>Need Paul's Experience of Conversion</b>
</p><p>
Nearly two thousand years have passed. Many of the problems and questions of Paul's day
are with us yet because of tradition and preconceived ideas. The prophets of old foretold of
the coming of the Savior and the establishment of his Church. They also foretold that the
gospel would be taken from the earth because of the corruptions of men and again established
before Christ's second coming. The fulfillment of these prophecies has been confirmed by
history. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints declares to the world that the true
gospel of Jesus Christ was taken from the earth and that it has been restored in our day. A
young man who had been pondering and questioning the established faith of his fathers had
the simple faith to seek his Heavenly Father in humble prayer. In response, a glorious vision
burst upon this young man, a Prophet of the Lord, in a manner similar to that given to Paul.
God the Eternal Father and his Son Jesus Christ, two separate and distinct Personages,
appeared to him and instructed him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17-20#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17-20</a>).
By reason of this event and the subsequent events by
which God revealed his mind and will to men, the gospel of Jesus Christ has been restored in
its fulness for the benefit of all mankind.
</p><p>
It is startling to many in the world to learn that there is a prophet of God on the earth at the
present time who speaks to us the will of the Lord, and of this fact I bear witness. There are
hundreds of thousands who also so testify, yet today as in Paul's day there are others who see
but do not believe because of old traditions, closed minds, and preconceived ideas. For this
reason I invited you to walk with me down Damascus Road. If you are willing to do so with
a prayer in your heart for the truth, the Lord will shed his light upon you as he did Paul, and
the truth will be made manifest to you.
</p><p>
I further testify that God does live and that Jesus is the Christ, the Savior of all mankind. He
will bring light to those who honestly seek it. May the Spirit of God be with you, I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
