<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"Ye Have Heard My Voice"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder S. Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 73-74</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
About a year ago I was reading in the Doctrine and Covenants and came upon a verse of one
of the sections. I suppose everybody has an experience of the type I had as I read. I think the
Prophet had such an experience the day he read, "If any man lack wisdom let him ask of
God" (see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>),
for that scripture leaped at him; and so this one leaped at me. For a
year or so I have been reading it off and on, contemplating it. Now I should like to read it to
you, but first I should like to give it its framework.
</p><p>
Back in 1829 the Lord, through the Prophet Joseph Smith, said there would be appointed
twelve disciples, which of course we know as apostles, and he appointed two of the three
witnesses to choose them. And then he did a thing which to me is remarkable. He began to
instruct the Twelve before they were chosen, and after having instructed them he then gave
them this verse. In 1835 the Twelve were chosen, as you know, and on one occasion they
were called together and given their instructions. Oliver Cowdery was the spokesman; and
after having given them some very powerful and heartwarming instruction, so moved was he,
himself, that he had to stop two or three times to weep. He finally read the revelation to
which I refer and this verse.
</p><p>
Brigham Young was so impressed by it that he copied it in his laborious handwriting into his
diary. I am impressed by it likewise. These are the words: 
</p><p>
"These words are not of men nor of man, but of me; wherefore, you shall testify they are of
me and not of man; 
</p><p>
"For it is my voice which speaketh them unto you; (now this is six years later that they are
hearing it) for they are given by my Spirit unto you, and by my power you can read them one
to another; and save it were by my power you could not have them." And this is the
verse&mdash;"Wherefore, you can testify that you have heard my voice, and know my words"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/34-36#34">D&amp;C 18:34-36</a>).
</p><p>
The thing that impresses me about this is, and I have never thought of it before, when I read
a verse in the Doctrine and Covenants I am hearing the voice of the Lord as well as reading
his words, if I hear by the Spirit.
</p><p>
Now I have heard it said many times by men that they have often asked the Lord for a special
testimony and oftentimes haven't had it. They seem to want to hear the voice of the Lord. I
confess I have often wanted to hear the voice of the Lord, without knowing that all these
years I have been hearing it with deaf ears. This woke me up.
</p><p>
I can testify that, having read, I hear the voice of the Lord. I also testify to you that when you
hear the Prophet, here sitting on the stand, speak by the voice of prophecy and by the spirit of
the inspiration which possesses him, you also hear, through him, the voice of the Lord. In the
name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
