<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Joseph Smith, the Prophet</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alma Sonne</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alma Sonne, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1969, pp. 14-15</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
</p><p>
My brethren and sisters: The Latter-day Saints are a chosen people. Their mission is to
teach the restored gospel to the world. They feel that responsibility keenly. Their missionary
endeavor is evidence of their sincerity and determination to make known truth.
</p><p>
<b>Relationship to God</b>
</p><p>
They realize that the souls of men are precious in the sight of God. They know their
relationship to God, and they are rightfully called the children of God. He is their Father and
is vitally concerned about their welfare. He will hear and answer their prayers. He will come
to their rescue in times of need and he will sustain them when they put their trust in him.
</p><p>
<b>Belief in the prophets</b>
</p><p>
The Latter-day Saints believe in the prophets, each one of whom has left a vital
message to the world. Joseph Smith, called the founder of Mormonism, is the prophet of the
last dispensation. Like Moses, the lawgiver of Israel, he spoke with God face to face
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/33/11#11">Ex. 33:11</a>) and
received from him revelations concerning man's destiny and his possibilities. He taught that
God is a person, and that he rules in the affairs of men and nations, and that he is the Father
of his children who live and have lived upon the earth.
</p><p>
<b> Religious foundations</b>
</p><p>
Our country was founded in a religious atmosphere. The original colonists who came
to America laid their foundations in that background. They came with deep religious
convictions. They built churches and schools and worshiped God in their own way. Their
quest was religious freedom, and although unknown to them, they prepared the way for the
restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ, which, according to James, is the perfect law of
liberty (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/25#25">James 1:25</a>).
</p><p>
I have found in most people a deep religious sentiment. Many of them go to church to satisfy
their religious longings. The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints is building churches
and chapels at a rapid rate. Most of them are crowded with worshipers on Sunday, where the
gospel is being taught and righteous living encouraged.
</p><p>
<b>Prophetic calling of Joseph Smith</b>
</p><p>
Joseph Smith, the Prophet, was the man selected to open a new dispensation of the
gospel. He announced to the world a restoration of divine truth. There are many incidents in
his life supported by eyewitnesses who testify of his prophetic calling. These eye-witnesses
responded to his greatness and his leadership in a way to prove their loyalty. Strong men like
Brigham Young, John Taylor, and Wilford Woodruff followed him with a devotion seldom
seen in human affairs. They were men who were not easily deceived or led astray.
</p><p>
Men of renown saw in the Prophet a force to be reckoned with on the pages of history.
</p><p>
A knowledge of Mormonism is necessary to understand this prophet of the latter days. He
cannot be ignored by the conscientious investigator; neither can he be disposed of by the
old-fashioned methods of ridicule and abuse. His name is secure in the history books already
written. Speaking of himself, he said: "You don't know me; you never knew my heart. No
man knows my history" (<i>Documentary History of the Church</i>, Vol. 6, p. 317).
</p><p>
Who, for instance, knows Jesus Christ? No one except those who understand his gospel of
salvation. Joseph Smith came to prepare the world for the reign of Christ. The Church teaches
the second coming of the Savior, at which time he will appear in glory and splendor.
</p><p>
<b>Early history preserved</b>
</p><p>
The Prophet did not write his autobiography, but the history of the early days of the
Church is well preserved. The Prophet, wise and farseeing, kept records. "For the last three
years," he said on one occasion, "I have a record of all my acts and proceedings, for I have
kept several good, faithful, and efficient clerks in constant employ; they have accompanied me
everywhere, and carefully kept my history, and they have written down what I have done,
where I have been, and what I have said . . . and my enemies cannot prove anything against
me" (<i>DHC</i>, Vol. 6, p. 409). The Prophet believed he was a man of destiny, that this work was
an important event in history, and that it should be preserved for future generations. He had
been told by an angel that his "name should be had for good and evil among all nations"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/33#33">JS&mdash;H 1:33</a>).
That prophecy has been fulfilled.
</p><p>
<b>Reliable history kept</b>
</p><p>
We are grateful today for the fragmentary history of the early Christian church, for the
records from which the four gospels were assembled, and for the teachings and testimonies of
its early leaders. They have been a source of inspiration and guidance to the generations that
followed. Without those precious records, darkness would have prevailed. The Church has
kept and is keeping a faithful record and a reliable history of its growth, its development, and
its expansion since it was organized on the sixth day of April 1830; and it will move forward
in the future as it has in the past. I so testify sincerely, in the name of Jesus Christ the Lord.
Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
