<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Training of Youth</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1959, pp. 71-75</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Frequent reference has been made throughout this conference by previous speakers to the
importance of training youth. Several messages have been directed specifically to the young
people of the Church. I should like to say a few words on this important theme.
</p><p>
Our children are our most precious possessions. They are treasures of eternity. None of them
should be lost. Our Father's glory is in their salvation. As a Church we have great opportunity
to reach these young people, and as individuals&mdash;teachers and officers&mdash;we have a great
responsibility in teaching them correct principles.
</p><p>
Emphasizing the opportunities of the Church in this regard, Paul wrote to the branch at
Corinth:
</p><p>
"And he gave some, apostles; and some, prophets; and some, evangelists; and some,
pastors, and teachers;<br />
"For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of the body of
Christ;<br />
"Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a
perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11-13#11">Eph. 4:11-13</a>).
</p><p>
<i>Fitness of American Youth</i>
</p><p>
On November 21, 1957, the President of the United States appointed the Presidents Council
on Youth Fitness, composed of the Secretary of the Interior as Chairman, the Secretary of
Defense, the Secretary of Agriculture, Ezra Taft Benson, who sits here with us this afternoon,
the Secretary of Labor, and the Secretary of Health, Education, and Welfare.
</p><p>
He said it was the duty of this council to promote the efficacy of existing programs and the
launching of additional programs which will enhance the fitness of American youth. He also
established at that time the President's Citizens Advisory Committee on the Fitness of
American Youth. That was in 1957.
</p><p>
On the thirty-first day of January of this year, the President issued another proclamation: 
</p><p>
"Whereas the ongoing strength of our Nation depends upon the health of our young people;
and
</p><p>
"Whereas we must always strive to improve the fitness of our youth by determined and
coordinated efforts; and
</p><p>
"Whereas, in this challenging world, it is essential that our young people recognize their
obligation to themselves, to their families, and to the Nation, to endeavor to keep themselves
mentally, emotionally, spiritually, socially, and physically fit; and
</p><p>
"Whereas the President's Council on Youth Fitness has recommended that a National Youth
Fitness Week be designated: 
</p><p>
"Now, therefore, I, Dwight D. Eisenhower, President of the United States of America, do
hereby proclaim the week beginning May 3, 1959, as National Youth Fitness Week.
</p><p>
"<i>I request officials of the Government, and I urge parents, young people, and interested local</i>
<i>and national organizations, to use all appropriate means during that week to promote programs</i>
<i>and activities demonstrating the importance of youth fitness to the end that we may assure the</i>
<i>continuing strength and well being of our people</i>."
</p><p>
Over a quarter of a century ago another President of the United States made the following
significant reference to the importance of training childhood and youth (I quote from
President Hoover's address to the White House Conference on Child Health and Protection,
November 1, 1931, Washington, D. C.)
</p><p>
"These questions of child health and protection are a complicated problem requiring much
learning and much action. And we need have great concern over this matter. Let no one
believe that these are questions which should not stir a nation; that they are below the dignity
of statesmen or governments. If we could have but one generation of properly born, trained,
educated, and healthy children, a thousand other problems of government would vanish. We
would assure ourselves of healthier minds in more vigorous bodies, to direct the energies of
our Nation to yet greater heights of achievement."
</p><p>
President Eisenhower's council has as its scope not only "muscle making"
and "tendon stretching," as set forth by Shane McCarthy, Executive Director, but also the
mental, moral, emotional, and spiritual development of youth. This youth program is most
timely and fitting. I am glad that two of our General Authorities are connected with it&mdash;Elder
Ezra Taft Benson, of the Council of the Twelve, and Elder Marion D. Hanks of the First
Council of the Seventy.
</p><p>
Recently one of my sons called attention to an address delivered by Major Mayer of the
Brook Army Medical Center, Department of Psychiatry, San Antonio, Texas. It was delivered
to the officers and supervisors of the San Francisco Naval Shipyard, and the Naval
Radiological Defense Laboratory on the fourth of October, 1956. The major pointed out that
the communists have gained control over many people in this world by the well-known
devices of wars, purges, Siberian war camps, mass executions, etc. But he says more
significant is the fact that for every person brought under the Russian banner by violence,
many hundreds have been controlled without violence, and yet such control has been absolute.
</p><p>
Then he gives the result of his study of 4000 returning prisoners of war from Korea, and he
finds a technique which has been termed "brainwashing." Before the communists could put
their plan into effect they had to segregate these prisoners, which they did very simply by
putting them into what was called "reactionary" camps. Note whom they put into these
"reactionary" camps.
</p><p>
<i>First</i>, people who tried to be leaders or who showed what the communists called "poisonous
individualism." If the soldier had the temerity to try to organize anything, off he went to the
"reactionary" camp. He was obviously hopeless.
</p><p>
<i>Second</i>, those "reactionaries" or people with a higher education, who were considered
automatically pretty reactionary unless they volunteered to cooperate, and some of these did.
</p><p>
<i>Third</i>, overtly religious people. The communists felt that they could not do much with them.
</p><p>
Out of these 4000 prisoners, what percent do you think they put in the "reactionary" camp?
Five percent, and after getting rid of those, they began the process of "brainwashing." It is
surprising how many soldiers knew so little about our way of life&mdash;the American way of life.
</p><p>
Once they had the leaders segregated they invoked the techniques which have become
universal throughout the communist world.
</p><p>
<i>Youth's Responsibility</i>
</p><p>
We are living in an age of gadgetry which threatens to produce a future generation of
softness. <i>Flabbiness of character</i> more than <i>flabbiness of muscles</i> lies at the root of most of
the problems facing American youth.
</p><p>
The youth of yesterday are carrying the responsibilities and directing the affairs of the world
today. The youth of today will contribute to the destiny of the world tomorrow.
</p><p>
Never a day passes but gives some reminder of the fleetness of time and the brevity of
life&mdash;childhood&mdash;youth&mdash;maturity&mdash;old age. In childhood there is no past&mdash;no future&mdash;happy
in the present&mdash;heaven lies about him, and it is all for him.
</p><p>
Youth&mdash;beautiful&mdash;sweet&mdash;rash&mdash;inexperienced! In the words of Longfellow: 
</p><p>
"How beautiful is Youth! How bright it gleams<br />
With its illusions, aspirations, dreams!<br />
Book of Beginnings, Story without End,<br />
Each maid a heroine, and each man a friend!"
</p><p>
Then comes manhood with all its responsibilities, duties, failures, successes, each spending his
time and worry on how much he can get, instead of how much he can give to this world and
make it better. Before he knows it old age is upon him. "The easiest thing for our friends to
discover in us, and the hardest thing for us to discover in ourselves is that we are growing
old." But of one thing we are keenly aware&mdash;that
</p><p>
"Years rush by us like the wind<br />
We see not whence the eddy comes,<br />
Nor whitherward it is tending,<br />
And we seem, ourselves, to witness their flight<br />
Without a sense that we are changed.<br />
Yet time is beguiling man of his strength<br />
As the winds rob the trees of their foliage."
</p><p>
(Sir Walter Scott's "Woodstock")
</p><p>
The President's Council on Youth Fitness should be commended in recommending that a
National Youth Fitness Week be designated. By so doing they recognize that in this
challenging world it is essential that our young people be aware of their obligations to
themselves, to their families, and to the nation. In this recognition they endeavor to keep
themselves mentally, emotionally, spiritually, socially, and physically fit.
</p><p>
<i>I. Responsibility of Parents</i>
</p><p>
Parents have a responsibility in this education. Youth needs guidance, direction, and proper
restraint. "Let thy child's first lesson be obedience, and the second will be what thou wilt,"
said Benjamin Franklin. A child learns this lesson early at his mother's knee&mdash;sometimes
across his mother's knee. The child should learn early that the world is not created for him
alone; that he has an obligation to others; that he owes his parents, particularly, a debt
unpayable except in only one way&mdash;in living a life that will honor his name and bring joy to
them in their old age. He should learn that
</p><p>
"He ought to be true for the sake of
     the folks who think he is true.<br />
He should never stoop to a deed that
     his folks think he would not do.<br />
If he is false to himself, be the blemish
     but small,<br />
He has injured his folks, he has been
     false to them all."
</p><p>
(Paraphrased from Edgar A. Guest.)
</p><p>
It was old King Lear who cried in his anguish, "How sharper than a serpent's tooth it is to
have a thankless child." He is recreant, indeed, who for selfish indulgence would bring
disgrace upon his parents, and upon the good name he bears.
</p><p>
Parents, too, have a responsibility in this training not to provoke children to wrath. They
should be considerate not to irritate by vexatious commands or place unreasonable blame.
Whenever possible they should give encouragement rather than remonstrance or reproof.
</p><p>
<i>II. The Obligation of the Church</i>
</p><p>
The obligation of the Church is to spend not just <i>one week</i> this coming month on Youth
Fitness, but <i>fifty-two weeks</i> every year. Quorums and organizations have been set up in the
Church, as our text says, for the "perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the ministry, for the
edifying of the body of Christ; 
</p><p>
"Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a
perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12-13#12">Eph. 4:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
Now, let us just take a glimpse of the completeness of the Church organizations, and we shall
find it discloses the fact that in the auxiliary organizations, quorums, and other groups, there
is an army of officers and teachers ready to guide and direct youth in the proper way.
</p><p>
In the Sunday School for example, there are 82,449 officers and teachers, having under their
charge 664,750 people. Primary: 51,053 officers and teachers, having under their charge
290,789 children. YMMIA: 24,754 officers and teachers, and 178,766 youth under their
direction. YWMIA: 32,988 officers and teachers, and 194,094 girls under them. Aaronic
Priesthood: 28,837 officers and teachers, having 86,176 youth. Foreign missionaries: 5,512,
and stake missionaries, 5,934, or 11,446 missionaries. Or a total of 231,527 <i>officers and teachers</i>
in the Church who first of all should be <i>exemplars</i>. "Children have more need of
models than of critics." No officer or teacher should be continued in office who persists in the
obnoxious use of tobacco. The elder who hesitates to teach the Word of Wisdom is shirking
his duty. He who fails to live it robs himself of strength of body and strength of character to
which he is entitled.
</p><p>
<i>Resisting Temptation</i>
</p><p>
Truth is loyalty to the right as we see it; it is courageous living of our lives in harmony with
our ideals; it is always power. With the ideals of right living before him, no member of the
Church can continually violate the Word of Wisdom with impunity.
</p><p>
In this old world, the easiest way seems to be the indulgent way. If a person
has the least desire or inclination to drink tea and coffee or to smoke cigarettes, temptations to
indulge the appetite are on every hand. At parties, during social calls, at chance introductions
or friendly visits, in restaurants or trains, indulgence in these stimulants and narcotics is not
only encouraged but also too often urged. Under such influence and environment, the easy
way is to yield and become one of the crowd. But not one of these officers, 231,527 of them,
should ever yield to that easy way. One never develops character by yielding to wrong. "To
him that overcometh will I give to eat of the tree of life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/2/7#7">Rev. 2:7</a>). Strength comes by
resisting!
</p><p>
We are living not only in a commercial age, but also in a nicotine age, and viciously the
cigarette habit is fastening itself upon the human race. Government, medical, and other
statistics are constantly warning us of the enormous strides that this insidious enemy to health
and morals is making; but we little realize how active and potent are the forces at work to
foster this and kindred vices, and all for commercial gain.
</p><p>
In "Habits that Handicap," Charles B. Towne, a quarter of a century ago, explains how
"salesmen and demonstrators a few years ago were employed by manufacturers to go
throughout China 'to show the people how to smoke cigarettes.' It is estimated that as a result
of this campaign, one half of the cigarette consumption in the world is in China. It is little
wonder, when we learn that because of cheap labor twenty cigarettes could be sold for a
penny!" The author also makes this remarkable statement: "<i>I consider that cigarette smoking is</i>
<i>the greatest vice devastating humanity today because it is doing more than any other vice to</i>
<i>deteriorate the race</i>."
</p><p>
Think of the effect of an army of officers and teachers, with hundreds of thousands of youth
under their care, not one of whom should ever put a cigarette in his or her mouth! What a
potent example! The voice of the Church will ever be raised against the increasing tendency
among men and women to stain their lives with nicotine. Especially does it deplore this
growing evil among women. Heretofore, virtuous Anglo-Saxon womanhood has been above
this indulgence, and has therefore been a restraining and uplifting influence on men. Now, this
influence is being subjected to the insidious lure of the cigarette; and mothers of men, around
whom center the sweetest, purest, noblest sentiments of our lives, are contaminating their
sweetness and purity by indulgence in one of man's vices. The more woman becomes like
man, the less he will respect her; civilization weakens as man's estimate of woman lessens.
</p><p>
That it is woman's right to indulge in this habit, we do not question, yet, we lose some of
that sweet respect and admiration for women when we see them walk deliberately into mire
holes that have heretofore besmeared only men. It is difficult to conceive that any mother
would arrogate to herself the thought that staining her lips with tobacco would add to her
dignity as mother, or increase the admiration and pride that children hold for true
motherhood.
</p><p>
The mission of the Church is to proclaim the truth of the restored gospel to uplift society that
people may mingle more amicably one with another; to create in our communities a
wholesome environment in which our children may find strength to resist temptation and
encouragement to strive for cultural and spiritual attainment. It is the binding duty of leaders
of youth and particularly mothers, <i>by example</i> to make ineffective the influence of designing
men who would make profit out of their fellows who have fallen so low as to be slaves to
vice and passions.
</p><p>
The restored gospel is a rational philosophy that teaches men how to get happiness in this life
and exaltation in the life to come. The mission of the Church is to establish the kingdom of
God upon the earth, "which is not a mythical but a real kingdom," says a prominent writer not
of the Church. "It is a body of people dominated by ideals of productivity, which is mutual
service. We do not strive for the things which satisfy but for the moment and then leave a bad
taste. We strive for the things which build us up, and enable us and our
children to be strong, to flourish, and to conquer. We strive to make ourselves worthy to
receive the world by fitting ourselves to use the world more productively than others. We
believe that obedience to God means obedience to the laws of nature which are but the
manifestations of his will; and we try by painstaking study to acquire the most complete and
exact knowledge of that will in order that we may conform ourselves to it." (Thomas Nixon
Carver.)
</p><p>
<i>III. Power of Example</i>
</p><p>
To live an upright life, to conform to high ethical standards, is the responsibility and duty of
every teacher of the land. Greater than this is the responsibility of the religious teacher for in
addition to his belief in the efficacy of ethical and moral precepts, the religious teacher
assumes the responsibility of leading the youth into the realm of spirituality.
</p><p>
Example is the best and most effective way of teaching. Let us be exemplary in our speech.
No true leader of the Church will ever profane the name of God or his Beloved Son,
especially in the presence of his sons, or in the presence of any other young people. Profanity
is a vice. We can set a proper example also by speaking well of others. The Lord has
admonished us not to engage in backbiting. Another worthy example is exercising self-control,
controlling our temper by not speaking angrily in the home. Let calmness be characteristic of
our home life.
</p><p>
<i>"Children, obey your parents in the Lord:" said Paul, "for this is right.</i><br />
<i>"Honour thy father and mother which is the first commandment with promise;</i><br />
<i>"That it may be well with thee, and thou mayest live long on the earth.</i><br />
<i>"And, ye fathers, provoke not your children to wrath: but bring them up in the nurture and</i>
<i>admonition of the Lord</i>" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/1-4#1">Eph. 6:1-4</a>,
italics added).
</p><p>
To this admonition of Paul, we add the word of the Lord to the Prophet Joseph as follows: 
</p><p>
"And again, inasmuch as parents have children in Zion, or in any of her stakes which are
organized, that teach them not to understand the doctrine of repentance, faith in Christ the
Son of the living God, and of baptism and the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the
hands, when eight years old, the sin be upon the heads of the parents.<br />
"For this shall be a law unto the inhabitants of Zion, or in any of her stakes which are
organized . . .<br />
"And they shall also teach their children to pray, and to walk uprightly before the Lord"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25-28#25">D&amp;C 68:25-28</a>).
</p><p>
The training of youth is an obligation, first, upon the parents; next, upon teachers in the
Church, in auxiliaries and quorums, in the missionary field proclaiming the gospel wherever
they may be called, and upon all the citizens whether in the Church or out of the Church. It is
one of the obligations to which our attention is now called by the President of the United
States who has placed the responsibility upon his cabinet, who have appointed a citizens'
committee, and asking the entire nation to combine in this great educational campaign.
</p><p>
Fellow workers, may inspiration from on High be given each of us to discharge our
responsibilities throughout this Church in training the youth, not only during Youth Training
Week throughout this land but <i>always</i>, having in mind God's saying found only in this
revealed Church: "For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the
immortality and eternal life of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
God help us to be true instruments in his hands in accomplishing this divine ideal, I pray in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
