<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Hunger in the Midst of Plenty</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John A. Widtsoe</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John A. Widtsoe, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1948, pp. 110-113</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Friends of the Church of the Air:
</p><p>
Our generation of men has secured a tremendous command over surrounding things and
forces. Matter and energy have become man's abject servants. His mastery of the physical
universe has reached heights beyond the dreams of earlier days. Every thinkable material
comfort and help, including the conquest of most diseases, seems within man's reach. Man
has become a conquering giant. The utopias of the past, the dreams of ideal places, were
trivial in material comforts compared with our present luxurious world.
</p><p>
HUNGER IN THE MIDST OF PLENTY
</p><p>
Yet, in the midst of such plenty there is hunger, a worldwide, gripping hunger&mdash;a hunger for
simple happiness, culminating in peace. The nature of man is not satisfied with the
multiplicity of inventions in our mechanical-scientific age. Fear and unhappiness are becoming
the world's masters. The very discoveries that have made possible the world's physical
comforts, have, in distorted use, produced unspeakably horrible instruments of destruction.
Peace has been replaced by war, bloody and beastly; and, daily, war clouds rise in the
horizon. As a result, fear, the chief torturing implement of evil stalks the halls of government,
stands at household doors, and tears at every human heart. Tomorrow is no longer a hope; it
has become a threat. The world is sick.
</p><p>
It requires neither sage nor "elder statesmen" in church or state-craft to tell us why this
condition exists. The marvelous gifts of the day are material only. Such physical bounties do
not produce happiness; they only contribute to our ease. Material gifts, used throughout the
ages in the hope of satisfying man's hunger, have always been found wanting. If true
happiness could be found in material things, humanity's joy should now exceed any ever
known.
</p><p>
THE CURE FOR THE WORLD'S DILEMMA
</p><p>
To cure the world's present distemper, we must turn for help to the larger domain, of which
the material is but a faint reflection. Out of the unseen world comes a body of laws, the
so-called moral laws, among them the Ten Commandments
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/3-17#3">Ex. 20:3-17</a>)
and the Beatitudes (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/3-11#3">Matt. 5:3-11</a>). These laws are
as real and comprehensible as any physical law. If a wire carrying an electric current is placed
above a mariners compass, the needle swings sharply to one side, and remains there. Just so,
obedience to any of the moral laws will determine and hold the actions of the man under that
law. The acceptance or rejection of these moral or spiritual laws, higher laws of God,
determine in fact the behavior and conduct of every human being. They determine the use a
man makes of any gift. It is the misuse of physical laws, in defiance of higher laws, which
has brought into being cannons, bombs, torpedoes, and other devices for the destruction of
human life. The moral laws, if sincerely and properly used, give power to solve life's
problems. Above all else, conformity to them gives men conquest over themselves. They then
dare to do right. In short, conformity to the laws that flow from the unseen world where God
dwells, their acceptance in spirit and in deed, is the cure for the world's dilemma. True, it is
an ancient remedy, but is certain to cure the soul's anxiety.
</p><p>
But, as a nation, and as a world, we are largely ignoring these laws of well-being. We have
wandered away from the practices that form the foundation of the happy life. We must not
shy away from the knowledge of existing conditions.
</p><p>
HAPPINESS BEGINS WITH HEALTH
</p><p>
For example: Happiness begins with the health of the human body, fashioned in the image of
God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/26-27#26">Gen. 1:26-27</a>).
Yet our bodies are held, today, perhaps often ignorantly, in utter disregard. Not only are
the general laws of health in contempt; but at no other time in our country have
nerve-whipping, destructive substances been used by the people so extensively and greatly.
For this surrender to unnatural appetites we are paying a terrible price in illness of body and
mind. It is not conceivable that whiskey and vodka are reasonable preparations for the wise
consideration of matters of state&mdash;so urgently needed today.
</p><p>
A LIST OF OUR SINS
</p><p>
The marriage covenant, the basis of a sound society, is flagrantly forgotten. The mounting
divorce rate has become a national disgrace. Thereby the very foundations of our nation are
undermined. Immorality, with its unspeakable slime of degradation, is reaping its harvest.
</p><p>
The Sabbath day, ordained by God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/20/8#8">Ex. 20:8</a>),
has been the main and full day of pleasure. In the mad
rush for wealth, the nation will not suffer a play-day to be established in the week.
Consequently, not only are the churches empty, but men no longer take time to commune
with God, an essential requirement of the happy life. We are fast growing into a godless
nation.
</p><p>
Likewise, in our greedy love of gold, advantage is taken of our neighbor whenever legally
possible. Our own advantage is our main concern. When we give, it is because it helps us.
That is not the spirit of honesty. We stand on the verge of becoming a dishonest nation.
</p><p>
We have forgotten the practice of family and private prayer. We have become sufficient unto
ourselves, and therefore have loosed the tie that binds us to God. Thereby we are allowing
evil to range freely among men, and in horror. We have lost the divine protection and sweet
peace and satisfactions that come to a family who engage in daily prayer.
</p><p>
The list of our sins is long&mdash;too long for this talk.
</p><p>
RETURN TO THE SPIRITUAL FOLD
</p><p>
We know that to correct these and other evils, to heal our sick world, and to bring happiness
to hungry hearts, mankind must return to the spiritual fold, and become worthy citizens of the
moral kingdom. But how is it to be done? Churches and other organizations that try to win
men to the better way of life have had indifferent success. They have been able to reach only
a few.
</p><p>
Can we not hopefully try an old type of missionary endeavor, one which, unfortunately, has
fallen into disuse in matters of human welfare? We have tried other ways and failed. Why not
try this one?
</p><p>
Let each follower of the moral law, the nation over, accept the duty of being his neighbor's
keeper. Let him assume a personal responsibility in this matter of curing a sick world. Let
him constitute himself a missionary to neighbors and friends, to teach by example and word
of mouth the better way of life, to persuade them that it is the best way.
</p><p>
DETERMINED RIGHTEOUSNESS NEEDED
</p><p>
Under this call to world service, all men of good will&mdash;in business and professions, farmers
and artisans, in and out of organizations&mdash;would set out with courage, emphasis, and steady
faith to talk about and teach the eternal plan for human joy, and the stern necessity of victory
over self, if the world's sickness is to be cured.
</p><p>
This could be made a mass movement of national and international scope. It would flow and
grow from centers, such as the group listening in today. It would be doubly powerful coming
out of the hearts of common men. It would be a help to church and other organizations for
human good. It would be a mighty deterrent to evil, for Satan, an incarnate coward, flees
before determined righteousness. And it would have divine backing.
</p><p>
True, such a campaign would need some sacrifice of time, strength, and money. But the cause
is the greatest on earth. Lesser causes are fiercely vocal. Millions of dollars are spent annually
to advertise a brand of whiskey or cigarettes. Why not shout the way to peace from the
housetops? Publicity and repetition need not be confined to the material aspects of life. Our
spiritual needs, always battling with evil, have greater rights. It could be made the greatest
campaign for human happiness in the last two thousand years. It would beggar any movement
for human good, of any time.
</p><p>
CONSIDERATION OF INDIVIDUAL MAN
</p><p>
Any campaign for righteousness must consider first the individual man. As he is, so the group
is. He is the one who, noting current events, is either hopeful or hopeless, who either
courageously tries to solve for himself the problems of the day, or thinking there is no escape
from impending events, eats, drinks, and is merry. By happy individuals the happy nation is
built, as bricks of a color and shape reveal the architect's dream. Mass conversions are like
heaps of bricks.
</p><p>
Moreover, we must teach these hungry individuals in our Christian country the doctrines of
Christ, as taught by him, and not as conceived and interpreted by men. Christ spoke as man to
man, to common men, and they understood him. It often happens that men lose the spirit of a
doctrine because they cannot agree on the meaning of well-known words. There is no saving
grace in such hair-splitting, no cure of the soul's hunger. It only confuses the ordinary man.
We must speak to one another as we offer Christ's words, his lucid teachings, to solve our
present crisis, in simple, understandable language.
</p><p>
Besides, the individual man asks for specific directions. Generalizations serve little. When we
talk of the moral law, he replies, which one? He asks what in the nation saps our strength?
What shall I do, he asks, to be saved from the world's confusion? In answer to such questions
we can begin with the issues of the day at home, such as those here mentioned. Acceptance of
one law makes it easier to yield to others.
</p><p>
SOLUTION OF WORLDS TROUBLES
</p><p>
There are then two principles of action in solving the world's troubles: Every man must be
his brother's keeper (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/9#9">Gen. 4:9</a>);
and in his labor must consider individual needs first, group needs last.
</p><p>
We live in a land of plenty in material things. We revel in luxury. Meanwhile, the blood of
our children is shed over the earth, for heaven only knows what. We live in a land of spiritual
famine. We are hungry for the bread that feeds the spirit. Because of our waywardness,
contention, warfare, and other evils rob us of the happiness the Lord would have us enjoy.
</p><p>
However, we must not be hopeless of the future. Repentance and forgiveness are eternal
principles. But there is work to do. Each one of us must change his own life. Each one of us
must be a converter of others.
</p><p>
May the Lord of heaven help us so to build that there will no longer be hunger in the
land&mdash;in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
