<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Obedience Brings Blessings to the Church and to Individuals</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President George Albert Smith</p>
<p class="gcbib">George Albert Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1945, pp. 18-25</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I wonder if anyone else here feels as weak and humble as the man who stands before you. I
have been coming to this house since my infancy. I have seen all the Presidents of the Church
since that time sustained by the congregation here, as their names have been presented from
this stand. I have seen the Church continue to grow in numbers, and have realized throughout
all my years that the Church of Jesus Christ is what its name implies. We who are members
of this Church are indeed fortunate to have found the light and to have accepted the truth.
</p><p>
GROWTH OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
In the year 1830, the Church was organized with six members. The adversary of all
righteousness (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/23#23">Alma 34:23</a>)
has from that day to the present sought to impede its progress and destroy it. I
wonder if that great man, Joseph Smith, who gave his life that the Church might be organized
and carried on as the Lord intended, can see the Church as it exists today, with its branches
established in all parts of the world, and realize that each day since he was martyred, since he
laid down his life and sealed his testimony with his blood, the Church has become stronger
than the day before.
</p><p>
From this stand addresses have been delivered by some of the great teachers of the world.
Some of the greatest students of the scriptures have explained the gospel from this stand, and
men and women from everywhere have worshiped here. Yesterday, this house was apparently
as full of the membership of the Women's Relief Society of the Church as it is today with
both men and women together. Through that great organization, the Relief Society, begun by
the Prophet Joseph, was given to womankind the dispensation of representing the Lord in
their way as daughters, as wives, as mothers, and as representatives of their kind in all the
world.
</p><p>
THE RESTORATION OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
We have had sustained here today various of the quorums of the priesthood, each one directed
in its organization by our Heavenly Father. It was not a matter of personal wisdom on the part
of individuals. In each case there was necessity for group organization, and as the Church
grew and multiplied in numbers, the quorums have correspondingly increased until today in
all parts of the world there are men divinely appointed, set apart, and endowed with divine
authority, who state positively that they know whereof they speak when they testify that Jesus
was the Christ, the Son of God, who died that we might all live. The Church that he
organized in his day represented his Father and himself in all the parts of the world where it
was established. In our day, by the direction of Jesus Christ our Lord, this Church was
organized. It wasn't organized from just the imagination of men and women. There came a
necessity that the priesthood of the living God be restored. A youth was selected to begin the
work. When he was less than fifteen years of age, Joseph Smith lived at or near Palmyra,
New York state, on a little farm. He was confused about what he should do, or which church
he should join. The various denominations in that community were holding revival meetings
and one group was saying, &ldquo;This is the way,&rdquo; and another, &ldquo;This is the way,&rdquo; until he, being
of a naturally religious turn of mind, having lived in a home where the Bible, the holy
scripture, was read (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/11-13#11">JS&mdash;H 1:11-13</a>),
found in one passage of James:
</p><p>
&ldquo;If any of you lack wisdom, let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and
upbraideth not; and it shall be given him&rdquo;
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/5#5">James 1:5</a>).
</p><p>
THE COMING FORTH OF THE BOOK OF MORMON
</p><p>
Although a boy fourteen years of age, he went into the woods near his home, into one of
God's first temples, bowed down upon the ground, and asked the Lord in his confusion,
&ldquo;Which of these churches shall I join?&rdquo; I have no doubt he was surprised when the answer
came to him, &ldquo;Join none of them.&rdquo; And then he was told that if he would obey the direction
of our Heavenly Father, an important mission would be given for him to perform under divine
direction (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/18-19#18">JS&mdash;H 1:18-19</a>).
That was not the idea of a man who desired to deceive; it was the humble, simple
faith of a boy. So he continued following the inspiration of the Lord. He continued carrying
out the directions that were given to him by holy beings, the result of which was the
uncovering in the Hill Cumorah of the golden plates from which the Book of Mormon, the
history of the ancestors of the American Indians, was translated and published. Since then that
book has been carried to the ends of the world, having been published in many languages. He
was only a young man when that occurred. When the time came for its publication, he was
ridiculed. People derided him and called him a money digger because he worked for a living
and had to earn that living part of the time digging in the earth. But they didn't look upon
him as a servant of the Lord; neither did the majority of the people in the days of the Savior
accept Jesus Christ of Nazareth as a servant of the Lord. The great majority rejected Christ
and rejected each of his followers who became members of the quorum of the Twelve.
</p><p>
Joseph Smith persisted in his work; and when the Book of Mormon was finally about to come
from the press, after having been translated through the gift and power of God, for it was in a
language unknown to him, the people in the neighborhood of Palmyra agreed that they would
not buy it, thinking that they would thwart the bringing forth of the book. They supposed that
their refusal to purchase it would make impossible the completion of its publication.
</p><p>
There had been written in that book at the time of its compilation the statement that the book
would be received by many people (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/30/3#3">2 Ne. 30:3</a>).
Joseph Smith didn't eliminate that statement when it
came to publication. When the people said, &ldquo;We'll not read it,&rdquo; he did not take it out and say,
&ldquo;Well, I can't fulfill this.&rdquo; If he had been writing the book himself, he probably would have
changed the script, but it was not his script, and so it went to the world. I was present a few
years ago when the Smith farm near the Hill Cumorah was purchased, and as I went through
the neighborhood I found only one copy of the Book of Mormon. That was owned by a man
named Pliny T. Sexton, who was chancellor of the University of New York and the banker at
Palmyra. He had a copy of the first edition of the Book of Mormon as it came from the press.
The leaves had never been cut, and he kept it in the safe in the bank. I asked him, &ldquo;Is there
any place here where I can find another copy of the Book of Mormon?&rdquo; He said, &ldquo;I do not
know.&rdquo; I then began to inquire among the people and found that the people of Palmyra had
kept their word. They had neither bought nor would they read it. At that time Palmyra was a
village and is still a village, but the Book of Mormon that was discredited then has since been
read and accepted by people in all parts of the earth, people from many nations, numbering
hundreds of thousands, and the work is still going forward, fulfilling the prediction that it was
to be made
</p><p>
&ldquo;. . . known to all kindreds, tongues, and people, that the Lamb of God is the Son of the
Eternal Father, and the Savior of the world; and that all men must come unto him, or they
cannot be saved&rdquo; (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/40#40">1 Ne. 13:40</a>).
</p><p>
THE SAINTS MOVED FROM PLACE TO PLACE
</p><p>
Men may conspire to prevent the work of the Lord, as they have done when they are
prompted by the adversary, but his work has continued to grow from that day until the present
time. As the Church grew, the people were compelled to move from their smaller places.
Palmyra became too small, and they moved to Kirtland, Ohio. That became undesirable, so
they moved into Missouri, from which state they were banished by the edict of the governor,
and many of them laid down their lives as martyrs to the cause. The people then passed
across the Mississippi River into the state of Illinois. In fewer than seven years that group of
people, led by the youthful Prophet who had now grown to be a man, erected buildings and a
magnificent temple which was the finest building in its day in the state of Illinois. In less than
seven years Nauvoo became the largest city in the state, regardless of persecution and
everything that was done to prevent the growth of the gospel of Jesus Christ that the
adversary could inspire, including murder and every other wrong that goes with it.
</p><p>
PROPHECY REGARDING SETTLEMENT IN THE ROCKY MOUNTAINS
</p><p>
At that time Springfield was a city of about twelve thousand and Chicago had a population of
about five thousand. The Prophet of the Lord prophesied one day:
</p><p>
&ldquo;. . . the Saints would continue to suffer much affliction and would be driven to the Rocky
Mountains; many would apostatize; others would be put to death by our persecutors, or lose
their lives in consequence of exposure or disease, and some of them would live to go and
assist in making settlements and build cities and see the Saints become a mighty people in the
midst of the Rocky Mountains&rdquo; (<i>History of the Church</i>, Vol. 5, p. 85).
</p><p>
Think of such a prediction at that time. The Saints were then four or five hundred miles east
from where Omaha now is, and Omaha is approximately a thousand miles from the Salt Lake
Valley. For the Prophet of God to say that they would be driven from there and go fifteen
hundred miles into the wilderness, and there become a mighty people was a remarkable
statement indeed. Has that prophecy been fulfilled? Our presence here today attests that it has.
</p><p>
REVELATION ON THE WORD OF WISDOM
</p><p>
I could, if I had time, open to you the D&amp;C containing the prophecies, the revelations of God
to the Prophet Joseph Smith, and show that one by one they have been fulfilled, not by
Joseph Smith's power but by the power of God. In referring to the advice and counsel
contained in the eighty-ninth section of the D&amp;C, the Lord made this promise:
</p><p>
&ldquo;And all saints who remember to keep and do these things, walking in obedience to the
commandments, shall receive health in their navel and marrow to their bones; And shall find
wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures&rdquo;
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-19#18">D&amp;C 89:18-19</a>).
</p><p>
While Joseph Smith might write those words, he couldn't fulfill that promise. I stand here
today as one of the humblest among you, as the result of the observance of the requirements
of that revelation and other commandments that God has given. Observance of that
commandment has placed the membership of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
in the tops of these everlasting mountains in a class by themselves. Not only do we have the
lowest death rate of any people in all the world, but we also have a high birth rate as well.
That was the promise that was given by the Lord in the days of the Prophet Joseph Smith.
The Lord said that the destroying angels should pass by us and not slay us if we kept his
counsel (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/21#21">D&amp;C 89:21</a>). What has been another result? The age of men and women in the Church of Jesus
Christ of Latter-day Saints has increased until the average term of life among us is longer
than among any other people in the world.
</p><p>
Another promise: The Lord said that he would give to those who would keep this word of
wisdom, &ldquo;great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures&rdquo;
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/19#19">D&amp;C 89:19</a>).
I refer you to the February,
1944, number of <i>The Improvement Era</i> wherein was published a graph showing the relative
position of the states of the Union as to the number of scientists born in those states in
proportion to population. Strange as it may seem, if you began at the lower corner of that
graph and followed up state by state, you would come to the state of Massachusetts next to
the highest on the graph, yet you would not have reached the state of Utah. You have to go
twenty percent points higher up the graph to find Utah, the state that has produced more
scientists born within its borders per capita than any other state in the American Union. That
wasn't an accident; it was a fulfilment of the promise of God as a result of observance of the
Lord's commandments. And so I call attention this morning to the fact that when we do
represent our Heavenly Father in the way that he has desired, these blessings follow and are
not an accident. They are the direct fulfilment of God's promises through his Prophet.
</p><p>
A PROMISE MADE AS A REWARD FOR LOYALTY
</p><p>
And so today, my brethren, standing here in humility before you, I would like to express to
you my gratitude that you have seen fit to promise that you will help the humble man who
has been called to preside over this Church as he strives to carry on by the inspiration of the
Almighty. For this promise I am grateful, and I thank you that you have offered to do the
same thing with regard to the two men who stand by my side as counselors, loyal and true
and devoted Latter-day Saints, who have done everything to make my responsibility easier for
me to carry. You voted to sustain the Quorum of the Twelve, the quorum that I belonged to
for so many years that I felt like a stranger, almost, when I walked out of it to occupy the
position as President of the Church.
</p><p>
And so I might go on with all these quorums. You have held up your hands in the presence
of God to sustain this body of men in the leadership of the Church. I assure you that if you
will fulfill your promise, the blessings of our Heavenly Father will abide with you and in your
homes and with your loved ones, and Zion will continue to grow and spread abroad, and the
truth will be carried to every land and clime and the power of the priesthood will be made
manifest among our Father's children in many places where it has never yet even been heard.
You men who are here, or who hold the priesthood, have that responsibility, and as one of the
number, I would like to say, we can't let our own personal affairs stand in the way. If the call
comes for us to divide the gospel of Jesus Christ with our Father's other children, it will be
our privilege as well as our duty to put our own affairs in order, and like Joseph Smith and
the men who began with the Church in the early days, go where we may be called to go. One
of our departed brethren, Melvin J. Ballard, used to sing so beautifully, &ldquo;I'll go where you
want me to go, dear Lord; I'll be what you want me to be.&rdquo; That's the spirit of the gospel of
Jesus Christ. Great is the joy that comes into the hearts of the men and the women who
devote themselves to doing what our Heavenly Father desires them to do.
</p><p>
PRAISE FOR THE WOMEN OF THE CHURCH
</p><p>
I would like to say to this great body of priesthood, you are fortunate men if you have been
blessed with a good wife, a daughter of God, to stand by your side. And I want to say to you
that God loves her just as much as he loves you. If you would have his blessings, you will
treat her with love and kindness and tenderness and helpfulness. She will then be able to carry
on under the responsibilities that come to her to bring children into the world and nurture and
care for them and teach them the plan of life and salvation. And so I plead with you, my
brethren, let your homes be the abiding place of love, and the authority that you bear should
magnify that love in your soul and in the lives of your wives and your children.
</p><p>
Yesterday this house was filled with the daughters of Zion, and I say without hesitation that
you could find no more beautiful picture of womankind in all the world than was here
yesterday afternoon. These faithful wives, these faithful daughters, assume their portion of the
burden and carry it on. They make their homes a heaven when sometimes without them the
homes would be anything but heaven.
</p><p>
So today, my brethren, I feel to say to you, grateful am I for membership in this Church.
Thankful am I that I have lived among this people. I want to express my gratitude to
hundreds of you who are here today for the courtesies and the hospitality that many of you
have extended to me. I realize that it is not because of the man that you have extended these
courtesies, but because he represented the Lord as his humble servant. You have earned your
blessing and will continue to have it for all your kind deeds extended to his servants.
</p><p>
WORK OF EARLY DAY LEADERS
</p><p>
Now, as I stand here I realize that those who gave their lives in the early rise of the Church,
including Joseph Smith and Hyrum, his brother, could have run away from the danger that
threatened them. They knew, however, that that was not the thing their Heavenly Father
desired. So they remained behind, after having finished their work; and under the leadership
and direction of the Prophet, who by the way was the younger of the two brothers, builded a
temple to God on the banks of the mighty Mississippi River in the beautiful city of Nauvoo,
and they built it to completion far enough so that the ordinances of the Holy Priesthood were
administered, and marriage for eternity was consummated therein. And since the erection of
the Nauvoo Temple, the same blessings given there have followed in the other temples to the
number of nine. Think of it, my brethren. Beginning only a comparatively few years ago with
six members, day by day the work of God has gone forward among the children of men. No
longer are the Latter-day Saints despised as they used to be, because the adversary had
misrepresented them, but they are now respected by great and good men everywhere because
of what has been accomplished. We could not have made these achievements except that our
Heavenly Father had made it possible for us to do it. So, we ought to be thankful this day.
</p><p>
I ask that the Lord may take us to our homes when we have finished our labors with this
conference, and that each of us will go back to the roof that shelters us, wherever it may be,
with the renewed determination that God, being our helper
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/54/4#4">Ps. 54:4</a>), we will prove worthy of him in
whose image we have been created. If we will do that, there will radiate from our very
presence, wherever we go, a power of righteousness, and the communities in which we live
will be blessed thereby.
</p><p>
GRATITUDE FOR BLESSINGS
</p><p>
I am grateful to these wonderful organizations, without naming them, that have carried their
part of the responsibility. You voted for the leadership of these here today. I am grateful for
the Tabernacle choir and the other glorious choirs that we have throughout the Church. This
marvelous Tabernacle choir and organ that hold forth every Sabbath day have preached the
gospel to the ends of the earth, because its program has been carried everywhere And then we
have the Singing Mothers of the Relief Society. They not only do what the Lord desires them
to do in their lives, but they sing praises to him and teach others to do the same.
</p><p>
How blessed we are in this house, sanctified to God by the teachings that have been given
here by righteous men and women. Here we are today, not as a conglomerate community, but
as a band of brothers and sisters, worshiping at the same shrine, praying to the same God,
living the same gospel, keeping our homes under the supervision of the same spirit. I don't
know how any one of us can enjoy these blessings without having his feelings exalted and
from the depths of his soul thank him who bestows upon us all our blessings.
</p><p>
I pray that our Heavenly Father may continue his favor; that peace, comfort, and satisfaction
may abide in your homes; that these men who are in the various mission fields of the earth,
may be magnified before the people and exercise the authority that has been conferred upon
them to build, not destroy, but to build a better world that our Heavenly Father will be
delighted to honor and to bless because of its righteousness The Lord bless you in your
missionary fields of labor, and all of you men in your various callings, all you women in your
homes and abiding places, and the organizations with which you are identified. May the Lord
bestow every blessing, and I pray that his spirit may continue with us today, henceforth and
forever; and when the time comes that we shall stand before the Great Judge, where we all
will report some day, that we will find our record of such a character that the Lord will say to
us,
</p><p>
&ldquo;. . . Well done, good and faithful servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will
make thee ruler over many things: Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord&rdquo;
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/23#23">Matt. 25:23</a>).
</p><p>
I pray that this may be our blessing and the blessing of every soul that we can influence by
lives of righteousness and worthy example, all of which I ask in the name of Jesus Christ, our
Lord. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
