<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Aaronic Priesthood, Its Powers and Blessings</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Carl W. Buehner</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Carl W. Buehner, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1958, pp. 53-56</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I esteem it a great honor, my brothers and sisters, to be in your presence and to bear you my
humble testimony of the divinity of this great work.  As I look into the faces of this large
audience of leaders gathered from all parts of the Church, fully aware of the tremendous
activity going on in the Church, I feel to say, "God bless you every one."
</p><p>
Last Wednesday and Thursday, I enjoyed the honor of attending and participating in a number
of sessions of the outstanding Primary conference.  I came to a realization, more than ever
before, of the marvelous influence of these sisters on the lives of our children. I would like
wholeheartedly to commend them for the fine work they are doing and assure them that they
have the love and blessing of each of us.
</p><p>
Among other things, they are teaching the Articles of Faith in language the children can
understand. This after all is the very heart of the gospel. They are also conducting
departments which are providing a great stimulation in preparing the young boys to receive
the Aaronic Priesthood.
</p><p>
I heard a story the other day that could well be the result of the teaching of the Primary
organization. This concerned a family who came to the bishop at tithing settlement time.  In
the group were the father, mother, and a number of children. As they came into the bishop's
office, he greeted each of them, and when they were all seated, the bishop
said, "I assume you have come to talk to me about your tithing and that you would each like
to express your wishes concerning your own tithing account.  Shall we start with little Johnny
on the end of the line? Johnny, would you like to come forward and settle your tithing?" To
this Johnny replied, "Yes," and he reached in his pocket, brought out a little worn purse, and
after fumbling around in it a little while, found a dime, two nickels, and two or three pennies.
He put these on the bishop's desk and said, "Bishop, this is my tithing in full." The bishop
congratulated Johnny, wrote him out a receipt, indicated on it that it was tithing in full, and
gave it to him. Returning to his seat, Johnny very proudly displayed the receipt to his father
and said, "Dad, when you settle yours, I hope you will get one that says on it, 'Paid in full.'"
</p><p>
Faith-promoting stories such as this indicate to me that someone is providing our children
with a desire to keep the principles of the gospel.
</p><p>
I feel honored and very grateful that I have been found worthy to be one of those selected to
preside over the Aaronic Priesthood in this growing Church of ours. I sincerely hope that the
Lord will assist us in our objective of saving every boy who comes under our direction. Some
of the bishops are catching the vision and spirit of this.  Not long ago I sat with one of these
brethren while attending a ward teaching convention. He said to me, "Bishop, we have not
lost one boy of Aaronic Priesthood age in our ward in the past five years." And just recently
in a ward in the West Jordan Stake, a ward Aaronic Priesthood adviser made a similar
statement, "Bishop, we have lost only one boy in six years." Then I recall at Christmas time
being in my own ward and hearing my own bishop say to me, "This morning out of
forty-eight boys holding the Aaronic Priesthood in our ward, forty-four were present at
priesthood meeting, three had good excuses, and out of the forty-eight, only one is a problem
boy." I imagine when all of the big guns are centered on that one boy, he will succumb, too. 
It will be easier for him to come to church than to endure all the pressure that will be put on
him to bring him back into activity.
</p><p>
I have always been a great believer in our young men.  I am happy to be associated with
them, and I appreciate what you are doing to help us keep every one of them active in the
Church.
</p><p>
A charming sister, Janet Frame Mecham, whose husband is the chairman of the Aaronic
Priesthood committee in one of our stakes, observing the activities of her husband as he went
about the work assigned to him, wrote the following lines: 
</p><p>
<i>Let's Accelerate in Fifty-Eight</i>
</p><p>
In fifty-eight let's co-operate<br />
To accomplish what we designate.<br />
Our record we'll accentuate<br />
As each member we will stimulate.<br />
In the plan we want to instigate,<br />
Let's not one of us procrastinate.<br />
But each thing we shall inaugurate,<br />
Let's unanimously corroborate.
</p><p>
There are methods we'll incorporate,<br />
And others we must perpetuate.<br />
But some we cannot tolerate<br />
As we keep our plans right up-to-date.
</p><p>
Let each one our time here dedicate<br />
To each job our leaders delegate,<br />
And our efforts unitedly concentrate<br />
So each priesthood bearer will participate.
</p><p>
Joy and blessings forever compensate<br />
For the work and plans we consummate.<br />
There are stakes we could impersonate,<br />
But each one we should evaluate.
</p><p>
Take the best from each and contemplate<br />
How their methods we'll accelerate<br />
So our record will reverberate<br />
Through the Church in nineteen fifty-eight.
</p><p>
I am sure her husband could not have produced such a masterpiece.
</p><p>
Our problem does not concern us so much with the boys under twenty-one since their records
are improving each year but with those who are over twenty-one who through the years have
slipped into inactivity. These brethren we designate as senior members of the Aaronic
Priesthood.  I do not know when these brethren all got away from us, but I do know that we
now have the greatest program we have ever had to bring them back to an appreciation of this
great power called the priesthood&mdash;Aaronic Priesthood.  Last year some three
hundred and fifty schools for senior members of the Aaronic Priesthood were held in the
Church.  From these schools came a tremendous result for good.  I have heard men bear their
testimonies with tears dripping from their cheeks, grateful for the program of reactivation and
that someone has gone out of his way to put his arm around them and invite them back into
the activities of the priesthood program.
</p><p>
Brethren, we have some eighty thousand men like this. I hope through the united effort of all
of the organizations that can make a contribution that we will have success in bringing back
into activity most of these men who are depriving themselves of the blessings of our
Heavenly Father, because they are now outside and not inside enjoying the blessings which
come from magnifying the priesthood that they bear.
</p><p>
Recently, a sister who is the wife of one of these brethren said among other things while
addressing a session of quarterly conference, "All I want for Christmas is a temple marriage."
Her husband sitting in front of her heard this request.  I would like eighty thousand other
women to challenge their husbands to prepare their lives so that there can be eighty thousand
temple marriages of this same type. We would strengthen the activity in this Church as we
have never seen it before.
</p><p>
Responding to an assignment to give a talk, a senior member of the Aaronic Priesthood in the
Portland Stake quoted a few familiar lines from Benjamin Franklin's <i>Almanac</i>: 
</p><p>
For the want of a nail, the shoe was lost.<br />
For the want of the shoe, the horse was lost.<br />
For the want of the horse, the rider was lost.<br />
For the want of the rider, the battle was lost.<br />
For the loss of the battle, the kingdom was lost,<br />
And all because of a nail.
</p><p>
This senior member paraphrased these few lines, and this is what he said: 
</p><p>
For the want of activity, the love was lost.<br />
For the want of love, the service was lost.<br />
For the want of service, the faith was lost.<br />
For the want of faith, the repentance was lost.<br />
For the want of repentance, the salvation was lost.<br />
For the loss of salvation, a place in God's kingdom was lost.<br />
And all because of the want of activity.
</p><p>
I do not have time to elaborate on this, but I think that man had a great thought.
</p><p>
What is the Aaronic Priesthood?  It is a power that has been delegated to man that has in it
great blessings and great opportunities to serve. The Aaronic Priesthood was named after a
devoted and faithful man, Aaron, the brother of Moses, who was given to Moses as a
spokesman since, as the scriptures record, Moses was slow of speech
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/4/10#10">Ex. 4:10</a>). It was by the power of
the Aaronic Priesthood that John the Baptist came crying in the wilderness and told of one
coming who was greater and mightier than he and who would perform great miracles
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/3,11-12#3">Matt. 3:3,11-12</a>). It was
by the power of this same priesthood that the Savior of the world was baptized in the River
Jordan by John the Baptist (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/13-17#13">Matt. 3:13-17</a>).
It was this same John the Baptist who under the direction of
Peter, James, and John restored the Aaronic Priesthood to Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery. 
After his ascension, Joseph Smith and Oliver Cowdery, by the authority of the Aaronic
Priesthood that had come to them, baptized each other in the Susquehanna River.  It is the
power by which the emblems of the Sacrament are administered each Sunday and given to the
members of the Church in remembrance of the broken body and the spilt blood of the Savior
of the world.
</p><p>
It is the power by which young men are designated as ward teachers to go with their senior
companions into the homes of members of the Church to preach, teach, expound, and the
other things spoken of in the Doctrine and Covenants
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/46#46">D&amp;C 20:46</a>).  It is also the power by which a young
boy twelve years of age comes to your door and offers you a blessing by inviting you to
make a contribution to the fast offering funds of the Church.  It is a great honor to be a
bearer of the Aaronic Priesthood and to magnify that power which has come through being so
honored.
</p><p>
I would like to say to the seventy or eighty thousand other bearers of the Aaronic Priesthood
who are men, now likely heads of families, I wish that to you, too, could
come the blessing that comes to every active bearer of the Aaronic Priesthood. I would like
you to know that you are invited to come into our chapels.  There have been many who have
said, "I have been away so long, I think I am not wanted." You will never know how much
you are wanted, and you will never know how much good it will do you, too.  The Church
needs you, but you also need the Church.  Your family needs you, as a man magnifying the
priesthood, to stand at the head of your home.
</p><p>
     I have heard a few verses of poetry quoted that have a line which goes something like
this, "And I stepped in your footsteps all the way." Would we be proud if our boys stepped in
our footsteps all the way? We would if we were magnifying the priesthood and enjoying the
blessings that come to us through faithful participation.
</p><p>
In conclusion I would like to say that it has been reported that someone said a dirt-road
traveler traveling along the highway saw a sign that read, "You had better pick your rut now
because you are going to be in it for the next twenty miles." There is nothing that says you
are going to be in it for the rest of your life, and while most of us may detour a little&mdash;we
get in trouble, and we may be in a rut for a little while&mdash;it does not mean we cannot get out
of the rut and get on a good, hard highway and make up for the years we were in the rut by
getting on that road that leads us to life eternal.
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony, my brethren of the Aaronic Priesthood, that if you will magnify that
priesthood and work for its great blessings, even greater blessings will come to you, and then
one day will come to pass that which this one sister asked for, "All I want for Christmas is a
temple marriage."
</p><p>
May it come to each of us, and may we find joy in assisting these brethren back into activity
in the Church, I pray humbly in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
