<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Fellowship, Unity and Love</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Joseph Fielding Smith</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Joseph Fielding Smith, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1951, pp. 152-153</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
We have just witnessed, and taken part in a most solemn, wonderful manifestation of
fellowship, unity, and love.
</p><p>
PLEDGE OF SUPPORT
</p><p>
First, I wish to say before this vast congregation of priesthood and members of the Church
that I pledge myself to support my brethren of the First Presidency. They have my full
support, my love, and fellowship, and I pray that the Spirit of the Lord may rest upon them in
great abundance to guide them and direct them in all things pertaining to their high and holy
callings.
</p><p>
I feel humble in standing here, considering myself the weakest of my brethren. I love each
one of them: the First Presidency, the Council of the Twelve, and the other brethren whose
names have been presented and approved here this day. And may the Lord be with us to help
each one of us to magnify his calling.
</p><p>
I realize the position I have been called to fulfil is one of great importance. It makes me
humble. I am grateful for the expressions that I have received from my brethren. They have
expressed their confidence, and already have given me their support.
</p><p>
It is wonderful to see a great body such as we have here today (composed of the leading
brethren of the Church and many others who have not been called to presiding capacity),
raising their hands enthusiastically, feeling in their hearts to give their support, and they do
give their support with all their hearts to the brethren who have been sustained.
</p><p>
I thank the Lord for the gospel of Jesus Christ, for my membership in the Church, for the
opportunity which has come to me to give service. I have only one desire, weak as I am, and
that is to magnify to the best of my ability the calling which is mine.
</p><p>
FAITH AND PRAYERS NEEDED
</p><p>
I need the faith and the prayers of the members of the Church. These brethren of the
Presidency need them, too. We should support them, uphold them, sustain them by our faith
and by our prayers, that they may feel the influence that radiates from this great body of
priesthood and from the membership of the Church.
</p><p>
There is an influence that radiates forth. In fact, every individual radiates some influence. Our
influence should be for good, for the building up of the kingdom of God. We should have no
other purpose, only to bring to pass this great work and see it established in the earth as the
Lord would have it.
</p><p>
ESTABLISHMENT OF ZION
</p><p>
In the early days of the Church the brethren came to the Prophet Joseph Smith asking what
the Lord would have them do. The answer given to them was "to bring forth the cause of
Zion" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/6#6">D&amp;C 6:6</a>).
That is our work, to establish Zion, to build up the kingdom of God, to preach the
gospel to every creature in the world
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15#15">Mark 16:15</a>),
that not one soul may be overlooked where there is the
possibility for us to present unto him the truth.
</p><p>
As we have heard during this conference, we are all going to be judged according to our
works, every soul. I have often thought of my place and responsibility in this Church. What a
dreadful thing it would be to be going forth to teach, to lead men, to guide them into
something that wasn't true. I think the greatest crime in all this world is to lead men and
women, the children of God, away from the true principles. We see in the world today
philosophies of various kinds, tending to destroy faith, faith in God, faith in the principles of
the gospel. What a dreadful thing that is.
</p><p>
The Lord says if we labor all our days and save but one soul, how great will be our joy with
him (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/18/15#15">D&amp;C 18:15</a>);
on the other hand how great will be our sorrow and our condemnation if through our
acts we have led one soul away from this truth.
</p><p>
TESTIMONY
</p><p>
Again I bear my testimony to you. I know that God lives. I know that Jesus Christ is the
Only Begotten Son in the flesh of our Father, the great Elohim whom we worship. I have
perfect faith in the mission of the Prophet Joseph Smith and those who have succeeded him.
</p><p>
I know that we have the truth of the everlasting gospel of Jesus Christ, just as well as I know
that I stand here before you. If I did not know it, I wouldn't want to be here or have anything
to do with this work. But I know it in every fiber of my body. God has revealed it to me.
May the Lord bless us all I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
