<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Substance or Shadow</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Marion D. Hanks</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Marion D. Hanks, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1962, pp. 101-104</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
When the Apostle Paul wrote to the Corinthian Saints, he spoke of a Spirit through which the
things of God may be known (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/10-11#10">1 Cor. 2:10-11</a>).
In a modern time when God revealed his will to his choice
servant Joseph Smith, there was spoken of a Spirit through which they who listen and he who
speaks may find communion and be mutually edified
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/22#22">D&amp;C 50:22</a>). For that Spirit I earnestly pray.
</p><p>
In the great land in which I am privileged to work in the missionary cause with many of your
choice sons and daughters, a clergyman recently issued a statement, urging his people not to
listen to the representatives of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints as they seek to
converse with them. He urged the people not to "surrender the substance for the shadow."
This latter admonition is interesting and should receive the most serious consideration. I have
been thinking all through this conference, as testimony and witness have been borne as to God
and Christ and the relationship of man to them, as to the eternal nature of life, the reality of
the resurrection, the profound importance and absolute validity of the restoration, "Where is
the substance? Where is the shadow?"
</p><p>
This inquiry would be valid and of great interest in every aspect of religious faith and
practice. Comparisons of the revealed word of God and the Church established on the earth
by Christ and his apostles with presently existing churches and their creeds and organizations
and practices would be interesting. I commend to you this experience. For today, let me
center attention on one theme to which the clergyman's suggestion is pertinent.
</p><p>
It has been my blessing for many years to work among the young and among those who work
with the young. Recently it has been my especial privilege to labor with several hundred
choice young men and women, serving as missionaries in a foreign land. I believe I know
better today than I have ever known in my life how substantial and remarkable and marvelous
are the blessings of God to this Church in these days. He has blessed us with substance in a
day when mists of darkness shadow the land. Ours is a family-centered religion, our families
are religion-centered, and the gospel as we understand it affects the total personality and all of
the aspects of the life of the individual child of God. What do the young people need? What
can we offer them of real substance which will help them to avoid the shadows of falsehood
and failure and sin and sorrow?
</p><p>
There are some suggestions I'd like to make, not to the young and not especially or at least
uniquely to their parents, but to all of us, including parents, who deal with and influence or
have great potential to influence and bless the young.
</p><p>
I am sure as I begin, that we are united, you and I and all people of goodwill and honest
intent throughout the world, as to the objectives we may desire for the young. I don't know a
single parent or other honorable human being who does not want for the young a decent,
constructive, contributing, happy life. Many of us would like to help youth, though many give
only lip-service to their need for help. What would we want for them? Oh, I'd like my son to
win an Olympic event. This would delight me, please me greatly, make me proud. I'd like my
little boy to be a fine surgeon or lawyer or salesman, or whatever he chooses to be. But if he
were to succeed at some significant service and fail to be an honest, ethical, moral, spiritually
perceptive man, I would be a failure and a sad father, in my own eyes. What good people
want for youngsters is constructive, happy, participating lives.
</p><p>
It would seem likely that we are united also in our estimate of their value as individual
children of God. They are infinitely valuable. Do you know the poem
</p><p>
"Nobody knows what a boy is worth,<br />
     We'll have to wait and see.<br />
     But every man in a noble place<br />
     A boy once used to be."
</p><p>
Bishop Simpson's allusion to the Second World War brought to my mind a story which
impresses me greatly as to the value of one individual and the impact of one life in the lives
of others.
</p><p>
The first great B-29 strike on those who were then our enemy, flown from a land base, was
led by an airplane named "City of Los Angeles." (There had been previous strikes from
carriers, but this was our first flown from our own airfields recovered from the enemy. It was
meant to inform him that the war was now to be carried to his own homeland, and it was a
very important mission.) Aboard the aircraft were twelve men, eleven regular crewmen and a
colonel flying as squadron commander for the mission. They were to reach a rendezvous point
50 to 75 miles off the mainland of the enemy, then assume regular fighting formation and fly
in on target, which was a complex of high octane gasoline plants feeding the enemy war
potential.
</p><p>
Rendezvous point was reached as scheduled, and Colonel Sprouse ordered the dropping of the
phosphorous bomb which was to mark the point. Sergeant "Red" Irwin skidded the bomb
down the chute as ordered. The act was loaded with death. The flap at the end of the bomb
chute had somehow become stuck. When the bomb struck it, it exploded prematurely and
burst back into the cabin of the airplane and into the face and chest of Sergeant Irwin.
Dropping to the deck it began swiftly to burn its way through the thin metal flooring
separating it from the incendiary bombs stored in the bomb bay below. In moments the "City
of Los Angeles" and its crew would be blown to bits far out over the ocean in enemy
territory.
</p><p>
Sergeant Irwin, tragically wounded, got to his knees, picked up the bomb in his bare hands,
cradled it in his arms, and staggered up the passageway. Crashing into the navigator's table,
he had to stop and unlatch it with fingers that left burn marks in the hardwood. By now the
aircraft was filled with acrid fumes, blinding the pilot, and was wallowing less than 300 feet
above the water. Irwin staggered into the pilot's compartment shouting "Window, window."
He could not see that it was already open, and his fumbling fingers left burn marks on the
metal. He threw the bomb out of the window and collapsed to the deck. Two hours later,
Colonel Sprouse having ordered the "City of Los Angeles" back to base in the slim hope that
Irwin's life might be saved, they reached Iwo Jima. Irwin's flesh was still smoking with
imbedded phosphorous when he was removed from the plane by comrades who had to avert
their faces from his tragic wounds.
</p><p>
Sergeant Irwin lived to receive his nation's highest honor for extreme bravery and to survive
nearly fifty plastic surgery operations which restored him to a somewhat normal life. He lived
to marry and to become a father. And with him, there lived eleven other men who but for his
almost unbelievable courage would be dead. Eleven men, spared to their lives and work and
families through the decision and courageous act of one man! When Sergeant Irwin picked up
that bomb, he knew that it was burning at 1,300 degrees Fahrenheit, 1,088 degrees hotter than
boiling water!
</p><p>
This dramatic story came out of a war, but its implications are applicable to each of us, to our
families, communities, nations. How many young people are there in your home or
neighborhood, choice young children of God, who are wanting for lack of someone who has
the courage and concern to interest himself or herself in their welfare? The prime
responsibility, of course, is in the home, and we are as a Church and people anxiously
interested in strengthening our homes and families. But we are aware that there are literally
millions of youngsters who are not receiving in their homes the care they desperately need.
They are the legitimate concern of all of us.
</p><p>
What can we do for them?
</p><p>
I offer these quick suggestions in headlines only. The rest of the story, each of us may fashion
as we will. I believe them to be the substance of youthful success and joy.
</p><p>
1. Be concerned with their welfare. Recognize their worth and our potential
to bless them and influence them and help them and lift them.
</p><p>
2. Understand that they are different They are not all out of one mold. They are at varying
levels of spiritual and social and intellectual maturity, even though they may be the same age.
They must be accepted and dealt with as individuals, as they are, and in terms of what they
can be, and helped to become the best that they can be.
</p><p>
3. They need to be taught. They need instruction. Someone has said that we habitually
overestimate their experience and underestimate their intelligence. We expect them to act like
little adults, and yet we fail to take time and interest to teach them.
</p><p>
At a meeting in England a few weeks ago a little girl, perhaps younger than four years of age,
walked into a hall where a film and lecture were to be presented. I watched her as she stepped
daintily over a moving picture projector cord. A man standing near the machine to protect it
from accidental damage said to her, "Sweetheart, hurry and sit down. We're going to start."
She <i>sat</i> down, right there in the middle of the aisle, smiling sweetly at those around her. He
picked her up and explained that he had wanted her to sit up in front on a chair and then
escorted her there.
</p><p>
Now, as the father of five children I am not blind to reality. I know that they don't always do
what we tell them, but if we have a proper appreciation of their value and of our ability to
influence them, if we will accept them as they are and teach them in a spirit of love,
wonderful blessings will come to them and to us. Let me add it as a special and significant
point: 
</p><p>
4. We must really love them. We can afford to make the mistakes of the inexpert if we
sincerely love them.
</p><p>
5. They need discipline. They need to realize that there are rules, wise and fair rules, which
apply to them, lack of conformity to which brings a penalty.
</p><p>
You will remember the wonderful counsel given by the Lord to Joseph Smith in response to
his anguished cry from the dungeon at Liberty, Missouri, where he had been cruelly confined
for months, away from his friends and loved ones. The spirit of the priesthood was movingly
explained and direction given as to how it must be used. Included was this remarkable
statement: "Reproving betimes with sharpness, when moved upon by the Holy Ghost; and then
showing forth afterwards an increase of love toward him whom thou hast reproved, lest he
esteem thee to be his enemy" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/43#43">D&amp;C 121:43</a>).
</p><p>
Young people need discipline, administered in love.
</p><p>
In the great state of Vermont a few months ago I faced an unruly crowd of choice teenagers
brought from all regions in the state. They had listened to good music, had heard the mayors
and the governor, and had responded to every effort with contempt and discourtesy. The
person who introduced me was quite apologetic. I think he wished that I would disappear, so
embarrassing had been the behavior of the young people to that moment. I stood up and said
something I hadn't ever said before to a group of teens. I said, "I'm sorry that most of you
didn't hear the great talk that your governor just delivered. It was a wonderful talk, and you
would have profited from hearing it, but you weren't listening. Let me repeat the theme of
what your governor said. He talked about 'Vermont's Chief Asset, Her Teenagers.' I'd like to
tell you the truth. I'd like to tell you that I've been all over America commending your
generation and expressing confidence in you, and tonight you have made me wonder. For the
first time you've really made me wonder. I'd just like to tell you that if your behavior tonight
is typical, if you've been acting as you really are, and if you are Vermont's chief asset, the
Lord help Vermont."
</p><p>
Well, they listened. I spent the next forty-five minutes showing forth an increase of love
toward them, talking to the theme of "Moral Courage." I did my best to recover from what
might be thought a very strange way to approach a group of young people. They didn't move
a muscle. They listened, and their response was wonderful.
</p><p>
When the meeting was over, I walked out of the building and was stopped on the path outside
by a rather grim-looking group of handsome, rugged young men. One of them stepped for-
ward and said, "Mr. Hanks, we were very grateful for your talk on moral
courage. We learned a lot. But we'd like you to know that what you did here tonight was lots
more important than anything you said, and we're never going to forget it."
</p><p>
Young people need to be disciplined in love.
</p><p>
6. They need wholesome participation with others.
</p><p>
7. Young people need to be encouraged to stretch, to develop their creative capacities.
</p><p>
8. They need to be taught and given experience in the great religious truths. Would you bless
youth? Teach them the truth about God and Christ and themselves. Teach them that they have
a special responsibility toward God and all their fellow men, his children. Teach them to be
compassionate and considerate and kind, which they can best be when they know God as their
true Father in whose image and likeness they are created; when they know Christ as their
living Savior; when they recognize themselves as choice, responsible children of God,
brothers to all men. Lead them to religious search and service and reverence. Help them to
learn the truth.
</p><p>
9. Be an example to them of what you'd like them to be.
</p><p>
I testify that God lives, that we are his children, and that we can bless each other and our
choice young brothers and sisters if we will. In the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
