<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Keep the Faith</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop Thorpe B. Isaacson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Second Counselor in the Presiding Bishopric</p>
<p class="gcbib">Thorpe B. Isaacson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1951, pp. 129-133</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, President Richards, President Clark, and my dear brothers and sisters, I feel
very humble this morning.
</p><p>
I think the service that started here in the Tabernacle at eight o'clock this morning has been
heavenly and divine. I sincerely pray that the Lord will sustain me, give me the strength and
the inspiration that I know I need while I stand here. I have prayed humbly, I believe, that the
Lord would purge my soul of everything that is not of him.
</p><p>
SPIRIT OF CONFERENCE
</p><p>
I have rejoiced with you in the spirit of this conference. The Spirit of the Lord has been here
in rich abundance. No one could attend these sessions and not feel the holy influence of our
Father in heaven. No one could come here with the right spirit, with the spirit of peace and
love, and the spirit of worship, and not know that these brethren are inspired of the Lord.
</p><p>
We come here by the thousands. The first conference in this Tabernacle was held eighty-four
years ago now this October conference, and we have assembled semi-annually since that time
with very few exceptions. Many of the men and the brethren who have attended are not here
now.
</p><p>
I am thinking of Bishop Marvin O. Ashton who spoke here five years ago at the Sunday
session of the October conference. As I have gone about the Church, many of you fine
brethren have expressed your great love and affection for Bishop Ashton. Yes, he loved the
people, and the people loved him. He loved the Church, and he loved the Lord.
</p><p>
Many who have come to this block are impressed with the feeling and the spirit they have
while they are here. Many of them tell us that they feel different here than they do anywhere
else. Well, that is right. They do feel different here because this is a sacred block&mdash;this
building, and the temple to the east have all been dedicated to the work of the Lord, and his
influence is here.
</p><p>
INSPIRATION OF TEMPLE SQUARE
</p><p>
I would like to read a paragraph from three of the people who were recently here. One of
them from Arizona sent this paragraph: 
</p><p>
The inspiration which we derived on Temple Square will always be remembered, and
there will always be a fond spot in our hearts for the people of Utah. Those who come
from outside your state can only marvel at the wonderful feeling which we felt there.
It brings a new understanding into our lives to realize that we are all the children of
God, and it has meant much to me to know that life can still be joyous and beautiful.
</p><p>
Here is one from Delaware: 
</p><p>
What golden memories we have from being in Salt Lake City. It seems to me that it
means more because of the setting, and because of the spiritual uplift and devotion to
principles and ideals. As I entered that great Tabernacle, I felt a peace, and that feeling
has remained with me. We went from there filled with the highest admiration for your
people and for the wonderful principles for which you stand.
</p><p>
Then this one came from Ohio: 
</p><p>
The thought keeps going through my mind that God was really in that place. The
unusual way in which all of your people demonstrated the true living of your religion
gave me a real insight into Mormonism which we would have had in no other way. I
am very grateful personally for the opportunity of my enlarged understanding of your
principles.
</p><p>
People that come here in the right attitude feel the holy influence of our Father in heaven. It
is up to you and me to make sure that they do not leave here with an incorrect feeling. Oh,
my brethren and friends and associates, in the Church and out of the Church, who are
somewhat inactive, and who are uninterested, I would plead with you with all the earnestness
of my soul that you repent of your wrongdoings. Let the Spirit of the Lord come into your
hearts, and you will know joy that you have never known before.
</p><p>
REPENTANCE OF WRONGDOINGS
</p><p>
Repent of your wrongdoings, and the Lord will forgive you, because he has told us that if we
would repent and overcome our weaknesses and imperfections and come unto him,
</p><p>
. . . the same shall be clothed in white raiment: and I will not blot out his name out of
the book of life, but I will confess his name before my Father, and before his angels
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/3/5#5">Rev. 3:5</a>).
</p><p>
Let us repent of our wrongdoings, humbly and truly, so the Spirit of the Lord can dwell with
us. To you, my brethren, who may be listening in on the air or who may be watching
television or who may read the proceedings of the conference, I would plead with you that
you not divorce yourselves longer from the activities of the Church because it is impossible
for you to know the happiness that is waiting for you without the blessings of the Lord.
</p><p>
To our young people, stay very close to the Church. You young men in business, you young
professional men and you boys in college, you young married people, don't feel any longer
that you can get along alone. Take the Lord into your confidence with all your hearts. It
ought not to be hard when we recognize and understand that he knows the feelings of our
souls, anyway. Let us put aside that false pride, and you young people don't be too anxious
for success. Don't be in a hurry. Don't want to make all the dollars you can, and while you
are so doing, divorce yourselves from the Church.
</p><p>
IMPORTANCE OF FAITH
</p><p>
Oh, the blessings that await you if you will only come and mingle with the Saints of the
Church! Attend your sacrament meetings. It seems that our people need to be continually
encouraged to attend their sacrament meetings. They should come to sacrament meetings in
large numbers as often as possible. We should partake of the sacrament and renew our
covenants with the Lord, so that during the following week we may be able to withstand
those temptations with which we are confronted.
</p><p>
To you young people, do not lose faith in the Church. Do not lose faith in the government.
There may be things done by men in high places that you do not approve, but do not judge
the government by that. Think of your founding forefathers, of your Constitution, divinely
inspired of the Lord, and you will not lose faith in your land or in your government.
</p><p>
LETTER FROM KOREA
</p><p>
Have faith in the Lord at all times. I have a letter here from a young man in Korea that I
would like to read, and if a young man in Korea can live and write as this young man has
lived and has written, you likewise can go and do the same.
</p><p>
From Korea he wrote: 
</p><p>
Dear Bishop: I wish I could find the words to explain my feelings while I read your
most welcome letter. In a war-stricken world as I am now living in, I couldn't have
received a more warm and appreciative wish than you gave me. A guy's soul gets so
low and tired of seeing the world about one fall in ruins, and taking thousands of
innocent people with it.
</p><p>
It makes a guy like me realize how lucky the American people are, but I wonder if
they appreciate it. I have been here in Korea ever since the war broke out. I am really
getting pretty tired, and I will be so glad when this mess is all over with.
</p><p>
My entire life has changed so much since I came here over two years ago. It seems
more like ten years to me, since I have experienced so much in these last two years.
</p><p>
Before I left home I didn't realize what nice people I was accustomed to, but after
seeing the outside world I now appreciate my family for teaching me the good things
that they taught me. I begin to see the difference between people I was used to living
with and those of the outside world. I have missed decent people who were taught the
ways of the Lord, which he has asked us to live. I have missed friendly neighbors who
always greeted me with a smile. I miss my Sunday School and the association of my
people. All that I have seen here are temptation and sin that I would never have been
able to fight down had it not been for the teachings that I received in my home and in
this Church.
</p><p>
It seemed as if every time sin crossed my path because of loneliness I would then see
my mother's face and my people at home looking at me as though they trusted me and
expected me to be an example of right living until I returned home, to live so that I
would be worthy of a fine girl and have life's happiness and a home and children.
</p><p>
God only knows the torture a guy goes through from being so far from home under
such trying circumstances. I will say with all my heart that I believe in God and
prayer. Otherwise I never would have succeeded and survived. When I felt alone, I
would walk at night so that I could pray to my God. I prayed that he would help me
live a clean life and find satisfaction and happiness in living that way. For that reason,
I have been successful.
</p><p>
I went to school and was graduated, and then I went to Japan. I worked in an office as
a typist. I found a liking for the work, and I worked hard to keep it and earn
promotions. My most trying time in Korea was when the United Nations forces were
so hard pressed. There I lost my best buddy. He was shot down through the head right
before my eyes. I will never forget that as long as I live. That is my deepest regret in
coming to Korea.
</p><p>
I have had several terribly close calls, but I know that God has saved my life and
saved my soul. I trust him completely with it, and my wish is for him to be the judge.
I guess I should have fear, but I don't any more. After seeing my buddy die, I feel I
am no better than he was, so far that reason I want to leave it for God to decide, and I
don't worry about it. We have lost lots of good boys over here, probably many more
than the people of America realize. I know I would be the happiest guy alive if I was
home to attend your meetings, and be part of them, and it is the true work of God that
is striving to keep the world at peace today.
</p><p>
No person could be doing more to make a peaceful world than to live and teach God's
ways of living. My prayer will always be with all of you in your work.
</p><p>
Our hearts and prayers go out to these boys that are there, and the thousands who will yet go.
Oh, is it asking too much that we pray for them daily? Whether they are our own or not, they
are somebody's boys. Let us pray for them. Let us write to them. Think how you would feel
if you were a young man in the service, way over in Korea, and at the end of a hard day if
you came to your bunk at night and found a letter from some of your folk or your friends, to
help buoy you up.
</p><p>
TESTIMONY
</p><p>
Well, I want to bear you my testimony that I know that God lives. I know that he hears
prayers. I know that his Spirit can dwell with men, and I know it can withdraw from them,
and I know it is up to you and me to live close enough to the Lord that we can have the
companionship of his sweet Spirit.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us that we may take to our homes and apply in our lives the messages of
these conferences. Oh, parents, stay close to your children. Love them with all your hearts.
Hold them near and dear to you. They need you today as they have never needed you before.
</p><p>
May God bless the youth that they may stay close to the Church, and that we will be mindful
of them, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
