<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Loyalty to the Church</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President Hugh B. Brown</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Counselor in the First Presidency</p>
<p class="gcbib">Hugh B. Brown, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1961, pp. 84-87</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brethren, I think that in a long lifetime of Church service and appearing before
various sized groups, I have never felt more humble than I do tonight as I stand before this
vast group of men and realize that more than as many as are here are probably listening in
other places. My feeling of inadequacy is emphasized by the fact that you have asked me to
assume some duties and responsibilities for which I am not prepared. I therefore lean heavily
tonight on your sympathy and God's goodness.
</p><p>
I had made some preparation, having been notified that I would be asked to speak, but I am
leaving my notes on the chair and shall attempt extemporaneously, with the help of the Lord,
to emphasize what has been said, though I may not be able to add thereto. Elder Lee and
Elder Evans have given us much to think about. Brother Lee intimated an analogy which I
should like for a moment to enlarge upon.
</p><p>
I do not like to compare the Church to an army, but there are some things that are similar. At
least in both organizations we are dealing with human beings, and human beings are pretty
much the same wherever you find them. I am thinking at the moment of an incident in 1912
when the then highest ranking officer in the British Army, came to western Canada to
promote the organization of what was then known as the militia. He called all the young
officers who were in training into a meeting. Among other things, he said to us, and I can
only paraphrase: 
</p><p>
"Gentlemen, a war is coming. In my opinion it cannot be delayed more than two years. It is
going to be the worst war in history thus far, and I am here, to do what I can to prepare the
nation for what is ahead."
</p><p>
His prediction, of course, as to the time of the outbreak of the war was accurate, because the
war started for Britain in 1914. Subsequent to that time, and on a number of occasions, it was
my duty to talk to officers in the army. Always, under instruction from commanding officers,
my purpose was, first to acquaint the officers, so far as I could, with the strength and position
of the enemy; and secondly, to remind the men of their duty and to encourage undeviating
loyalty; and then to warn them against the methods employed by the enemy
by subtle infiltration and attempted alienation.
</p><p>
We said to these officers, "Your units will not be stronger than their leaders. You can pretty
well judge the strength of any military unit by the quality of its leaders." We remind them
also that the lives of their men depended upon their efficiency and loyalty.
</p><p>
Tonight we are speaking to perhaps 50,000 men, and every man is a volunteer and qualified
officer. Upon each one of you there is great responsibility regardless of where you are
working or the size of the group you preside over. Here, as in the army, our strength is going
to depend in large measure upon the quality of our officers, and our purpose tonight is to
warn you priesthood holders, and through you the men and women of your various groups, of
the existence, strength, location, and tactics of the enemy, and to remind you that we rely on
your absolute loyalty and that preparedness is indispensable.
</p><p>
In the army too frequently we refer to fitness as only physical fitness. Tonight we are calling
upon all of you officers of the Church to be fit and ready, physically, mentally, morally, and
spiritually, for the war that lies ahead because the enemy is determined to destroy all that we
hold dear. He is thoroughly organized; he is cunning and ruthless; he is led by men well
trained in his type of warfare; and the devil is his commanding officer. Not only must we
meet a head-on assault from the enemy, but the more dangerous and subtle attack will be by
infiltration, when human termites undertake to undermine our forces. I believe, my brethren,
the time has come when every man who holds the priesthood should figuratively stand
himself up against the wall and look himself over, ask himself some questions and be honest
with his answers. I may say here, you may as well be honest when you are talking to yourself
because the man you are talking to knows who you are and what you are. There are at least
two places when a man will be honest, and that is when he is talking to himself and when he
is in his closet talking with God Here at least the truth will be distilled.
</p><p>
Let us then examine ourselves and ask what kind of men we are. We might make a pretty
good showing in public, be fairly successful in business or in politics; but let each man ask
himself what kind of man are you in the home, in your business, in your private life. If you
do not like what you see as you look at yourself, then do something about it because God will
not hold any man guiltless who simply confesses his sin and doesn't abandon it, or, who
admits his weakness and doesn't work for strength.
</p><p>
May I pause here to remind all of us that it matters little what position we hold, but it matters
much what we do in the position we hold. Brother Lee referred to Paul's reminder that there
is need for all the parts of the body. I am thinking of the Church as the body. No one of us
should say or think at any time, "If I were in some other place, I could display my superior
ability and faith, but just where I am I do not get a chance to show what I can do. If I were a
bishop or stake president or high councilmen or one of the General Authorities, of course, I
could be something great, but down here where I am it doesn't amount to much."
</p><p>
Brethren, when we stand before the Judgment Bar of God&mdash;and I am saying tonight as the
British officer said in 1912, a judgment day is ahead&mdash;when we stand there, I think we will
not be asked what position we held in the Church. I think the only question, if any questions
are necessary, will be, "What did you do with the job assigned to you?" And if a counselor in
an elders' quorum, or a counselor in the bishopric, or a man in any other position anywhere
in the Church can honestly say, "I did the best I could to fill the position assigned to me," if
he can say that honestly, and if one of the General Authorities cannot say it honestly, I would
rather be the counselor in the elders' quorum, etc., because I think the Lord is not going to
pay much attention to any label one may have on his chest. I don't think the Lord is much
interested in labels. He knows as we do that labels do not always tell the truth.
</p><p>
My thought tonight, then, is: Brethren, in connection with this program that
has been presented to us tonight, let not any of us say, "Now they are giving us something
more to do, more organizations, more committees. Let's join some other church."
</p><p>
Personally, I thank God for the opportunity to work. I am grateful, among other things, that
this, the Church of Jesus Christ, gives opportunity to every man and woman and children as
well, incidentally, to participate in the work of the Lord. May I add, there is no position in
this Church that is not bigger than the man that holds it as there is room for growth in every
position or calling. Every man should be apprised of that and realize that in any position in
the Church there is opportunity for any man to employ all the ability with which the Lord has
blessed him.
</p><p>
We come to you tonight to challenge you, to warn you that there is a war now being waged,
the most dangerous and devastating&mdash;I am not only speaking of a war with arms&mdash;I am
speaking of an ideological war, a spiritual war, a war in which the enemy is endeavoring to
enslave the bodies and minds and souls of men, and for this we must be prepared.
</p><p>
Let us be loyal to the stakes and wards, missions and branches to which we have the honor to
belong. Let us be true to ourselves and true to our leaders. Again a quick analogy. I saw
instances where junior officers criticized senior officers because they stayed far behind the
lines and did not know what was going on in the trenches. I am speaking of World War I,
which definitely dates me, but I am willing to take that. Very often the junior officers were
critical of the senior officers because they did not know there was a rat hole in a dugout,
forgetful of the fact that the man back there upon whom rested the total responsibility of the
entire operation had something other to do than to look at a rat hole. He must leave that to
the man who happens to be in that dugout.
</p><p>
At the head of our force, we have a prophet of God, who is working directly under Jesus the
Christ, who joined issue with Beelzebub when the foundation of this world was laid, and
Beelzebub, the devil, Lucifer, declared then that he would never rest until he enslaved the
souls of men (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1-4#1">Moses 4:1-4</a>),
and Christ declared he would never rest until all were free to "choose their lives
and what they'd be."
</p><p>
We, then, are enlisted in an army with Christ at the head and a living prophet through whom
he directs his work. Let us be loyal to them, true to ourselves, and let each of us do the job
assigned to him in the place where he is asked to work to the best of his ability.
</p><p>
I want to assure you that I know what it means to be asked to do a job a thousand times too
big for me, and yet I know too that God can take any one of us and do anything he wants to
do through us. Let us not spend time asking the Lord to do something for us when he is
waiting and anxious to do something through us. Let us not forget that the priesthood we bear
is not in us as individuals, but the power of it comes through us. Let us keep ourselves in
such condition that that power can be transmitted. Let us go forward as President McKay
admonished us at the beginning of this conference and be unafraid. May we have courage and
fortitude and faith and go forward with the knowledge that though we will undoubtedly have
to meet many difficult things. With God's help we need not fear.
</p><p>
I like one verse of the "Battle Hymn of the Republic."
</p><p>
"He has sounded forth the trumpet that shall never call retreat; <br />
     He is sifting out the hearts of men before His judgment-seat: <br />
     O, be swift, my soul, to answer Him! Be jubilant, my feet!<br />
     Our God is marching on."<br /><br />
&nbsp; &nbsp;                              (Julia Ward Howe.)
</p><p>
God bless you, my brethren I thank you for your support. I want to tell you from intimate
association that we have at the head of the Church today one of the greatest leaders of the
Dispensation of the Fulness of Times. God has honored him, and we who sit next to him day
by day see the work of the Church being outlined, organized, and going
forward under the inspiration of heaven. I testify to you that he is the prophet of God, and
that these men who are associated here with us are true and loyal to him.
</p><p>
I leave you my testimony of the restoration of the gospel, and I want you to know that the
President and all of us have confidence in you, that you will not let us down nor be untrue to
yourselves nor become traitors to the cause. Furthermore, you may be sure that ultimately
righteousness will triumph. Truth will prevail. The Church has been organized and set up. It
is the kingdom of God, and it will never be thrown down.
</p><p>
God bless us to do our part. To this end I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
