<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">"We Believe in Being Honest"</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Alvin R. Dyer</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Alvin R. Dyer, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 49-52</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
It is always a great spiritual uplift to attend the conference of The Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints, and I am grateful with you, my brethren and sisters, once again to have this
privilege.
</p><p>
President McKay's great message yesterday, which went straight to the heart of the individual,
gives encouragement to the remarks that I thought to make about honesty. The great need of
the world is for spiritual quality in men, for depth and altitude of soul, for wealth of inward
life, out of which good deeds shall come like a stream from the mountains, with power. But
this nobility of character is not arrived at in a day. Its source lies far back in the days of
youth, in the practice of restraint and the acquisition of honest thoughts and good habits.
</p><p>
We believe in being honest!
</p><p>
Through the efforts of the American Bar Association and Presidential Proclamation, we now
have a new day in America. It comes every first of May and is referred to as "Law Day."
Efforts are being made to popularize this day by many national organizations of which the
following are but a few: The American Heritage Foundation, The United States Conference of
Mayors, and The General Federation. The need for such a day to be brought to the attention
of America stems from the apparent complacency with regard to the rule of law, devotion to
morality, and moral honesty.
</p><p>
In recent weeks, as reported in our newspapers, J. Edgar Hoover, the director of the Federal
Bureau of Investigation, based upon statistics compiled by this bureau, stated among other
things "that since 1950 the crime rate in America has increased four times as fast as our
population. For every dollar our churches cost us, our crime is costing us 12 dollars. Bank
robberies and fraud have increased with leaps and bounds." In viewing this appalling situation
there are those who say, "Such crimes are committed by the professional criminal, and we
will always have them." But, truly, are such deviations into crime and dishonesty expanding
only in the so-called ranks of the professional criminal?
</p><p>
In an article appearing in the <i>Reader's Digest</i> not long ago, we learn of the
reported inroads of dishonesty made into the ranks of the average person.
</p><p>
A fisherman or a hunter is generally regarded as a "sportsman" with a sense of fairness and of
playing the game according to the rules; yet in one month in one of our states, 350
"sportsmen" were fined for violation of the game laws. An officer reported that there would
have been many more had there been sufficient wardens to check the infractions.
</p><p>
Access to the daily press releases of the Federal Trade Commission reveals the mendacity of
our sellers of goods&mdash;lies about origins, lies about qualities, lies about reduced prices!
</p><p>
Recently, a New York newspaper printed many columns about unscrupulous persons on relief
who had dishonestly requested and received more money than the law permits.
</p><p>
The revealed facts of employee and customer dishonesty are most startling. Chiseling a big
impersonal company is not stealing at all, say some. A report of this was made in <i>Look</i>
Magazine published the last week of September. A reputable citizen recently told proudly of
returning a five dollar bill to a drugstore clerk who had given him too much change; but
when he completed a long distance call from a pay booth and the operator returned his five
quarters by mistake, he kept the money without any qualms. "The phone company is so big
they won't miss it," he said.
</p><p>
The New Jersey Bell Telephone Company not long ago made a big fuss over a ten-year-old
girl who had returned several dollars which she had found in the return slot of a public
telephone. The company tried upon this occasion to impress the fact by having her picture
placed in the paper that when a person faces a machine with a moral question, his answer
should be the same as when he faces a human being.
</p><p>
During the first ten months at New York's new Americana Hotel, the well-meaning average
guests stole among other things 38,000 demitasse spoons, 18,000 towels, 355 silver coffee
pots, 1,500 silver finger bowls, and, believe it or not, 100 Bibles.
</p><p>
Supermarkets are especially vulnerable to the "amateur" thieves, eighty percent of whom are
women. One example, 500,000 supermarket shopping carts disappeared last year, at an
average cost of $30.00 each, this comes to $15,000,000.00. One expert estimates that fifteen
percent of your food bill goes to cover what customers and employees take, salving their
conscience with the thought that big companies can afford it. The question is: Can you afford
it?
</p><p>
It is estimated that supermarket employees steal the equivalent of $300,000.00 every day.
Across the country, employee thefts of money and merchandise are estimated to total two
billion dollars a year. Three years ago this was estimated at one billion. Such pilferage has
destroyed many companies. An organization has been formed in New York City not to
investigate criminal rings, but to suggest methods to big business concerns on how to control
employee dishonesty. Much of this is in such innocent quantities that it hardly appears evil at
all. Secretaries go home with pencils and carbon paper. Employees use the telephone for
personal calls that add up to big money. One executive in a big company said, "If you asked a
girl to put down a dime for a phone call, she would think you were crazy."
</p><p>
The fact that moral dishonesty has settled like an evil blanket upon the peoples of all lands is
told in an interesting story by Russell Kirk reporting in the <i>National Review</i>, having written
the story from a country house in Fife, Scotland. "Once upon a time," he wrote, "a strict
Calvinism, whatever its defects, did install a high degree of honesty in the typical Scot. But
this week, at the raspberry picking here, the gardener remarked to me, that of the thirty or
forty people who came to pick on shares, probably everyone would steal a basket or two of
berries if he saw the chance."
</p><p>
These examples of moral dishonesty are not those of the hardened criminal, but rather the
average everyday citizen we see go to and from work on the streets of our cities. Civilizations
may not fall because of cheating raspberry pickers or dishonest supermarket
employees, yet great states do come to an end of their tether when religious sanctions no
longer govern the soul of the average citizen.
</p><p>
Well might we ask ourselves this question at this crucial time, "What is it that produces moral
and physical dishonesty in the lives of people?" The facts that have been reported here refer
to overt acts of moral dishonesty, in a supposedly noncriminal cross section of the people.
Can we possibly believe that any act of such dishonesty is born as of that minute when the act
is committed? This cannot be true, for it goes back even to childhood where little traits of
dishonesty go undetected. I once heard a father jokingly tell of how his little son was always
able to find loose change around the house. Perhaps the urge to take something that does not
belong to an employee can be traced back to the lack of respect which adolescents have for
the property of others, even members of their own families.
</p><p>
That child or adult who is unaccountable for his actions, disregarding repentance and
restitution, weaves into his character the trait of dishonor. Here we see the need of
righteousness and kind discipline in the home.
</p><p>
The lack of realism on the part of parents in failing to detect and correct innocent acts of
dishonesty in their children can lead to disaster later. The passing over of small amounts of
money taken by children, the failure to correct stories told by children which are completely
false, can lead to acts of a graver nature later. There are many ways in which the unsuspected
seeds of moral dishonesty are planted and which will blossom forth in due time.
</p><p>
Generally speaking, moral dishonesty tends towards <i>insincerity</i> and <i>hypocrisy</i>. These three are
evil companions and can destroy the majesty of the will, nullifying the power of agency.
Nothing displeases the Master more than hypocrisy. His frequent denunciations of the
Pharisees because of this trait are a matter of biblical record. Of those who are not what they
profess to be, the Apostle James has said, "A double minded man is unstable in all his ways"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/8#8">James 1:8</a>).
Following this declaration with another: "But be ye doers of the word, and not
hearers only, deceiving your own selves"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/22#22">James 1:22</a>).
</p><p>
An insincere person lives a strenuous life, says Anne Lindbergh. There must ever be restraints
against "putting on" or assuming a superficial front to sway an impression or a credit in our
direction. That leader or teacher who is not honest in heart lacks sincerity. Such a one does
not live by what he teaches. The very word itself when traced to its origin means to be honest
in our relations with others; a negative message will ever emit from an insincere and morally
dishonest person. From my own experience in serving with thousands of missionaries, I have
come to know that sincerity is the most necessary of all qualifications. Without it a
missionary can't hope to succeed.
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith, while being held without cause in Liberty Jail, was inspired to say
concerning those whose insincerity of purpose had led to dishonest membership:
</p><p>
"How much more dignified and noble are the thoughts of God than the vain, (insincere)
imaginations of the human heart! None but fools will trifle with the souls of men." (<i>DHC</i>
3:295.)
</p><p>
The Apostle Paul urged the Ephesians to serve God with sincerity of purpose honest intent.
Said he:
</p><p>
". . . Be obedient . . . with fear and trembling, in singleness of your heart, as unto Christ;
</p><p>
"Not with eyeservice, as men-pleasers; but as the servants of Christ,
<i>doing the will of God from the heart;</i>
</p><p>
"With good will doing service, as to the Lord, <i>and</i> not to <i>men</i>:
</p><p>
"Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to stand against the wiles of the devil.
</p><p>
". . . in the evil day, and having done all, <i>to stand</i>"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/6/5-7,11,13#5">Eph. 6:5-7,11,13</a>), italics added).
</p><p>
Someone has written a paraphrasing of this of those who take much from life but give little:
</p><p>
"He stands having his loins girt about with religiosity and having on the
breastplate of respectability. His feet are shod with ostentatious philanthropy, his head is
encased in the helmet of spread-eagle patriotism. Holding in his left hand the buckler of
worldly power and in his right hand the sword of influence, and thus shall he stand in the evil
day."
</p><p>
In conclusion, I quote the Thirteenth Article of Faith of our Church:
</p><p>
"<i>We believe in being honest</i>, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men;
indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all things, we hope all
things, we have endured many things, and hope to endure all things. If there is anything
virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/13#13">A of F 1:13</a>, italics
added).
</p><p>
I have spoken of but one phase of this article:
</p><p>
"<i>We believe in being honest!</i>"
</p><p>
I bear testimony to the need of this attribute in our daily lives that we may not be deceived
by the force of evil in hidden and unsuspecting ways. I bear testimony also of the vitality and
truth of the message of the restoration of the gospel of Jesus Christ, which we have for the
world. In the words of Joseph Smith the Prophet:
</p><p>
"We say that God is true; that the Constitution of the United States is true; that the Bible is
true; that the Book of Mormon is true . . . that Christ is true; that the ministering angels sent
forth from God are true, and that we know that we have an house not made with hands,
eternal in the heavens (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/5/1#1">2 Cor. 5:1</a>),
whose builder and maker is God (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/10#10">Heb. 11:10</a>)"
(<i>DHC</i> 3:304).
</p><p>
I testify of this in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
