<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Restored Gospel&mdash;An Ensign to the Nations</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1963, pp. 96-99</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
"And even so I have sent mine everlasting covenant into the world, to be a light to the world,
and to be a standard for my people . . . and to be a messenger before my face to prepare the
way before me" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/9#9">D&amp;C 45:9</a>).
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints was scarcely one year old when that
declaration was made. Joseph Smith, to whom the inspiration came, was but twenty-five years
of age. It is a marvelous declaration, great in its pretention, comprehensive in its scope&mdash;"Mine
everlasting covenant [the gospel] is sent into the world, to be a light unto the world."
</p><p>
On Bedloe Island, at the entrance of New York Harbor, there stands a Statue of Liberty, a
light to the nations. What it has meant to thousands and hundreds of thousands of the
downtrodden of Europe has been most graphically expressed by Israel Zangwill in that
impressive production <i>The Melting Pot</i>, from which I quote (David, the immigrant Jew, is
speaking): 
</p><p>
"When I look at our Statue of Liberty, I just seem to hear the voice of America: 'Come unto
me all ye who are weary and heavy-laden, and I will give you rest&mdash;rest.'"
</p><p>
What that Statue of Liberty has symbolized to the oppressed and downtrodden of Europe, the
gospel of Jesus Christ is to the world.
</p><p>
The restored gospel, the Church, has reared an ensign to the nations, and with words as
comprehensive as those I have read in the revelation, invites the world to peace, to rest, to
contentment.
</p><p>
And what does that ensign offer to the nations?
</p><p>
Forty-three years ago, Elder Stephen L Richards, speaking from this pulpit, answered that
question as follows: "There are provided within the Church agencies and facilities which meet
every requirement of social life. Our wards, to my thinking, constitute the most advantageous
social units that have ever been devised or suggested in the history of society. There are
presented within the organizations of the wards opportunities for every person to receive
legitimate training in society, proper social intercourse, and the cultivation of all the desirable
traits of character that go to make up good men and good women." (<i>Annual Conference</i>, April
6, 1920.)
</p><p>
Sitting in the audience on that occasion was a statesman who had won national and
international eminence, not only as a great leader in the political world, but also as a speaker
and writer on religious topics. He was William Jennings Bryan, who only a few months
before had written an article for a current magazine entitled "In the World, of the World, and
for the World," wherein he outlined a number of ways in which he thought the church could
make the world a better place in which to live. "My suggestion, therefore," I read from his
article, "is that an effort should be made to set up a Christian standard for Christian
communities, and to create an environment that will be helpful to the Church and the spiritual
things for which the Church stands."
</p><p>
Such an organization is the restored Church of Jesus Christ, functioning effectually, as the
Apostle Paul says, "For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the
edifying of the body of Christ: 
</p><p>
"Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a
perfect man, [even] unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12-13#12">Eph. 4:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
I invite you today to have in mind the various organizations of the Church: <i>first</i>, the
<i>priesthood quorums; second,</i> the <i>auxiliaries; third, educational opportunities; fourth, judicial</i>
<i>phases of the Church;</i> and <i>fifth, the ecclesiastical groups.</i> To elaborate on each one would
occupy more time than I can give, but we can just glimpse it.
</p><p>
Consider the priesthood of the Church. Picture therein the men and boys organized in working
sections or groups, from the father ninety years old, down to the boy twelve years of age. In
these groups you find exemplified all that human society seeks in social groups and in
societies. There is opportunity in these quorum groups for fellowship, brotherhood, and
organized service. No man who is worthy of that fellowship can be kept out from it&mdash;not
one!
</p><p>
Those who are active are working in an organized way for the betterment of one another, for
the personal welfare of the membership and for the good of society as a whole. If we
considered no further than the quorums, is not that a sublime picture, where men and boys
may congregate, associate, affiliate in service for humanity, in which every man considers
everyone a brother? In that quorum the doctor sits by the side of a carpenter, each interested
in the most ennobling of aspirations&mdash;worship of God and helpful service to humanity! There
is the essence of priesthood work in the Church, and, in the achievement of the purpose,
every act and influence should be performed or wielded only "by persuasion, by
long-suffering, by gentleness and meekness, and by love unfeigned." The words of the
Prophet! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/41#41">D&amp;C 121:41</a>).
</p><p>
In addition to quorums, there are Young Men's and Young Women's Mutual Improvement
Associations, having charge of the recreation for the young, guiding the leisure hours of the
youth as emphasized by Mr. William Jennings Bryan&mdash;one of the great
problems facing civilization today! In these groups you have an organization of young men
and young women, directing in music, in art, in debating, in drama, as well as in other
uplifting activities of community life.
</p><p>
All quorums and groups are in themselves educational factors. It is surprising how many
officers and teachers are engaged in the teaching and directing of youth just in quorums and
auxiliary organizations.
</p><p>
Let us take one stake for example: I refer now to notes taken on a visit made in 1950 here in
Salt Lake City. Among the groups in the Melchizedek Priesthood of that stake were 804 men
serving without one penny of compensation for the betterment of society every week, and
some of them every day.
</p><p>
If the high council and members of the bishoprics in that stake who are working with young
boys between the ages of twelve and twenty-one be included, there were a total of 1,022 men.
</p><p>
The number of officers and teachers in the auxiliaries in the twelve wards of that stake was
1,950, so adding this number to the 1,022, we have a total of 2,972, or approximately 3,000
men and women teachers.
</p><p>
In addition, there were missionaries laboring under the direction of the stake presidency. In
this one stake, they had held 2,715 meetings in homes in this city. They had baptized, since
the first of the year, 106 converts and ten children who had gone beyond the age of eight
years.
</p><p>
The Church progresses only as fast as these groups work in perfect harmony.
</p><p>
In the Doctrine and Covenants, we read: "It is the duty of the [priesthood] to watch over the
Church always, to be with and strengthen them"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>). This is a laymen's
Church.
</p><p>
And what a message the Church has for this distracted world! "Its appeal," as Kent says of
true Christianity, "is universal&mdash;to the rich and the poor, the strong and the weak, the learned
and the unlearned. It proclaims God to be not only the one Supreme Ruler of the Universe,
but the Father of each individual, a God of justice, yet a God of love, constantly watching
over and guiding even the humblest of His children."
</p><p>
The Church, with its complete organization, offers service and inspiration to all. It is
"pre-eminently a social religion." In quorums and auxiliaries it "aims by training the
individual conscience and will to establish a closely knit, worldwide fraternity." It is in no
sense ascetic. Instead of taking men out of the world. it seeks to develop perfect, Godlike men
in the midst of society, and through them to solve the problems of society.
</p><p>
There is not a principle which is taught by the Savior of men but is applicable to the growth,
development, and happiness of mankind. Every one of his teachings seems to touch the true
philosophy of living. I accept them wholeheartedly. I like to study them. I like to teach them.
It is a job to try to live them. Even phase of the restored Church is applicable to the welfare
of the human family.
</p><p>
Twelve thousand missionaries and more, each paying individually or with the aid of parents
his or her own expenses. are declaring to a troubled world that the message heralded at the
birth of Jesus, "Peace on earth, good will toward men," (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/14#14">Luke 2:14</a>) may become a reality
by compliance to the principles of the gospel.
</p><p>
As the Savior said to the eleven disciples, and to all whom they appointed, so he says to his
authorized servants today: "Go ye therefore and make disciples of all nations, teaching them
to observe all things whatsoever I have commanded" (see
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19-20#19">Matt. 28:19-20</a>).
</p><p>
Where, however, each missionary of old could speak only to one person, the representatives
of Christ today can speak to millions. A sentence uttered in an ordinary tone of voice can
encircle the globe in less than a minute. Daily, nations are becoming more closely united. The
interest and destiny of each one becomes more closely the interest and destiny of all.
</p><p>
In the ecclesiastical groupings, there is opportunity for social welfare such as cannot be found
in any other organization in the world. Thus does the Savior and his Church
become my inspiration, my ideal in life. I think it is the one great thing for which man should
strive. It presents the most efficient methods for human service, social uplift, and progressive
steps toward universal peace and brotherhood; and in its idea of salvation it comprehends the
whole of the human family.
</p><p>
May he bless the priesthood throughout the Church, the auxiliary associations, and all men
and women who seek to instill into the hearts of men the redemptive power of Jesus Christ,
the Son of the Living God. May all utilizing the organization of the Church continue more
zealously "For the perfecting of the saints, for the work of the ministry, for the edifying of
the body of Christ: 
</p><p>
"Till we all come in the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a
perfect man, [even] unto the measure of the stature of the fulness of Christ"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/12-13#12">Eph. 4:12-13</a>).
</p><p>
God bless and prosper the Church as it bears witness to the reality of the personality of Deity
and to the fact that God has again revealed himself to man and established a means whereby
spirituality, brotherhood, and universal peace may be fostered among the children of men.
</p><p>
The Lord help us to be able to prove to the world that the restored gospel is just what the
world today is longing for; and when they see it, may they know, as you know and as I
know, that the everlasting gospel is a light to the world. May it ever be a light to the nations,
a guiding solution of all the world problems, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
