<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The First Vision</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder S. Dilworth Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">S. Dilworth Young, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 118-120</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I cannot remember the time when I have not heard the story, quoted by Brother Bennion,
concerning the coming of the Father and the Son to the Prophet Joseph Smith. I am convinced
as I grow older and become proportionately wiser that if boys and girls in our Church could
keep that story uppermost in their hearts, believing it, having a testimony of it, much of the
ills of our youth which President Richards so graphically portrayed this morning would not
be.
</p><p>
I am concerned however with one item which has recently been
called to my attention on this matter. There appears to be going about our communities some
writing to the effect that the Prophet Joseph Smith evolved his doctrine from what might have
been a vision, in which he is supposed to have said that he saw an angel, instead of the Father
and Son. According to this theory, by the time he was inspired to write the occurrence in
1838, he had come to the conclusion that there were two Beings.
</p><p>
This rather shocked me. I can see no reason why the Prophet, with his brilliant mind, would
have failed to remember in sharp relief every detail of that eventful day. I can remember quite
vividly that in 1915 I had a mere dream, and while the dream was prophetic in its nature, it
was not startling. It has been long since fulfilled, but I can remember every detail of it as
sharply and clearly as though it had happened yesterday. How then could any man conceive
that the Prophet, receiving such a vision as he received, would not remember it and would fail
to write it clearly, distinctly, and accurately?
</p><p>
It seems to me, too, that had he evolved such a thing, his enemies would have used it against
him. In 1838 there was a crisis in the Church. Men were falling away. It was at that time that
Oliver Cowdery became disaffected. If any man in this Church had ever heard that story of
the first vision, Oliver Cowdery must have heard it. Yet his reasons for disaffection were
never given as an evolution of the first vision. Other men of that time did not use it as their
excuse. In 1844, when the final conspiracy was concocted to murder Joseph Smith, the
reasons given by those men were not discrepancies in his story of the first vision, but rather
other matters far removed from it.
</p><p>
When Joseph wrote the story in 1838, men and women who had known him ever since he had
started this work took the story in their stride; that is, it was common enough knowledge from
the beginning that no one took an exception to it. Everybody knew it; everybody had heard it;
not exactly in the words in which he wrote it&mdash;I believe no man will speak extemporaneously
in the same manner that he will write something&mdash;but essentially the same, and when the
Saints read it, it merely confirmed what they had heard over and over again.
</p><p>
His mother should have known something about it. You will remember, he walked into her
house that morning and told her that the church to which she had given allegiance was not
true. To my way of thinking, he must have told her all about the vision. When she chose to
write the story of her son's experience, she did not put it in her own words. I suspect that she
must have felt that so nearly was what he had written the way he had described it to her, that
she quoted his written statement.
</p><p>
All of these things seem to me to add up to irrefutable evidence, although not said exactly,
that Joseph Smith, in 1838, told the correct story of his vision of 1820.
</p><p>
Recently I made some slight investigation, although not enough, trying to find the testimonies
of some of those who had heard Joseph say these things before 1838. I did not find much&mdash;I
did not have time to look far&mdash;but I have one, which I should like to give you.
</p><p>
Edward Stevenson told how in 1834 the Prophet came to Pontiac, Michigan, Stevenson's
home town, and there held a series of meetings, attended by Brother Stevenson. Brother
Stevenson wrote that the following was the Prophet's testimony on that occasion:
</p><p>
"I am witness that there is a God, for I saw him in open day, while praying in a silent grove
in the spring of 1820." Then Brother Stevenson wrote: "He further testified that God the
Eternal Father, pointing to a separate Personage in the likeness of himself, said, 'This is my
beloved Son. Hear Him'" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/17#17">JS&mdash;H 1:17</a>).
</p><p>
I submit this excerpt as enough like the story that the Prophet wrote to bear witness that he
wrote it accurately and correctly.
</p><p>
I am of the fifth generation. I can remember the second generation. My grandchildren are of
the seventh generation. Likely in their day, they will remember not only my generation, but
will see also, before they die, the tenth or the eleventh generation. It is just possible that some
of them may be interested enough to want to know what their
grandfather thought about these things, and they will investigate the conference reports. I
should like them to have in my words what I believe about this great event.
</p><p>
So will you indulge me while I talk a moment to my grandchildren and to my
great-great-grandchildren, to Loraine, to Parkie, to Charlotte, to Annette, and Wendy, and any
that may come hereafter. (I hope there will be many of them.) I want you to know that I
know that Joseph Smith walked into a grove in 1820, inspired of the Lord to do so, knelt
down, as he said, among the silent trees, offered up a prayer, and there he was given a vision
in which he saw God the Eternal Father, who in his turn introduced to Joseph his beloved
Son. The Son told Joseph many things which would transpire but of which he was not
allowed to speak. Beginning with that vision, which gave us our first knowledge since the
time of the Savior of the true relationship of our Father and his Son to us, has grown this
Church. That is my solemn and humble testimony to those of my house who in the future will
want to know what I thought and believed.
</p><p>
In order that they will have no doubt, and that no carping critic may read into my words
things that are not there, I should like to repeat for their benefit what the Prophet said when
he wrote his vision:
</p><p>
. . . I saw a pillar of light exactly over my head, above the brightness of the sun,
which descended gradually until it fell upon me.<br />
. . . when the light rested upon me I saw two Personages, whose brightness and glory
defy all description, standing above me in the air. One of them spake unto me,
calling me by name and said, pointing to the other&mdash;This is My Beloved Son.
Hear Him! (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/16-17#16">JS&mdash;H 1:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
I will stand on that witness and add mine that I know by the Spirit of the Holy Ghost that it
is true, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
