<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Gospel Imperatives</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Howard W. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Howard W. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1967, pp. 115-118</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
The greatest search of our time is the search for personal identity and for human dignity. Each
of us wants life to be worthwhile and to have real meaning&mdash;a personal meaning&mdash;in the
living we do from day to day. There is a search being made by people everywhere, a search
as important as life itself for self-respect, for self-fulfillment, and for emotional maturity.
Much of our character and nature, as individuals, depends upon how and to what ends we
conduct this search. Too many of us turn the direction of our lives to tragic goals and
distorted purposes. The friends we choose, the choices we make, and what we do about these
choices are the determining guide lines that form and mold our lives; but choices alone are
not enough. The best goals, the best of friends, and the best of opportunities are all
meaningless unless they are translated into reality through our daily actions.
</p><p>
<b>Gospel of imperatives</b>
</p><p>
Belief must be realized in personal achievement. Real Christians must understand that the
gospel of Jesus Christ is not just a gospel of belief; it is a plan of action. His gospel is a
gospel of imperatives, and the very nature of its substance is a call to action. He did not say
"observe" my gospel; he said "live" it! He did not say, "Note its beautiful structure and
imagery", he said, "Go, do, see, feel, give, believe!" The gospel of Jesus Christ is full of
imperatives, words that call for personal commitment and action&mdash;obligatory, binding,
compulsory.
</p><p>
There is never achievement in any field of endeavor unless it is preceded by a strong sense of
purpose. There must be reasons for action and guides for action in the form of real goals and
objectives. That is why we are given a plan of salvation and progression. Because the gospel
is a long-range even an eternal&mdash;goal, it must be broken up into short-range, immediate
objectives that can be achieved today and tomorrow and the next day. The gospel imperatives
constitute an immediate challenge to action in our lives right now, today, as well as a plan for
action eternally.
</p><p>
Notice the forceful expression Jesus gave to his teachings; he said: "Ask, and it will be given
you; seek, and ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you: 
</p><p>
"For every one that asketh receiveth; and he that seeketh findeth, and to him that knocketh it
shall be opened" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/7-8#7">Matt. 7:7-8</a>).
</p><p>
". . . Love your enemies, bless them that curse you, do good to them that hate you and pray
for them that despitefully use you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/44#44">Matt. 5:44</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Gospel of action</b>
</p><p>
I believe he would have endorsed the modern addition to an ancient scripture: "And with all
thy getting (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/4/7#7">Prov. 4:7</a>), get going!" His principles are briefly paraphrased. "Do unto others as you would
have them do unto you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/12#12">Matt. 7:12</a>). "Go the second mile"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/41#41">Matt. 5:41</a>). "If you want to know whether what I say is
true (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/17#17">John 7:17</a>), try it out!" This is what we mean by gospel imperatives. They are words that challenge
to action&mdash;"Go, do, pray, repent, love, find, give, consider, provide," and a host of others.
</p><p>
One of the most dynamic challenges in the scriptures comes at the end of King Benjamin's
address to his people as he concludes his ministry and turns the reigns of government over to
his son, Mosiah. Standing on the tower he built to address the people, he guides them through
the fundamentals of the gospel and commits them to the wisdom, power, and purposes of
God, making this most important challenge: ". . . and now, if you believe all these things see
that ye do them" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/10#10">Mosiah 4:10</a>). The sincerity of their belief must be demonstrated in the
verity in their actions.
</p><p>
Action is one of the chief foundations of personal testimony. The surest witness is that which
comes firsthand out of personal experience. When the Jews challenged the doctrine
Jesus taught in the temple, he answered, ". . . my doctrine is not mine, but
his that sent me." Then he added the key to personal testimony, "If any man will do his will,
he shall know of the doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speak of myself"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/16-17#16">John 7:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
Do we hear the imperative in this declaration of the Savior? "If any man will <i>do</i> . . . he will
<i>know!</i>" John caught the significance of this imperative and emphasized its meaning in his
gospel. He said, "He that saith he abideth in him ought himself also so to walk, even as he
walked" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/2/6#6">1 Jn. 2:6</a>).
</p><p>
Merely saying, accepting, believing are not enough. They are incomplete until that which they
imply is translated into the dynamic action of daily living. This, then, is the finest source of
personal testimony. One knows because he has experienced. He does not have to say, "Brother
Jones says it is true, and I believe him." He can say, "I have lived this principle in my own
life, and I know through personal experience that it works. I have felt its influence, tested its
practical usefulness, and know that it is good. I can testify of my own knowledge that it is a
true principle."
</p><p>
Many people carry such a testimony in their own lives and do not recognize its worth.
Recently a young lady said, "I do not have a testimony of the gospel. I wish I did. I accept its
teachings. I know they work in my life. I see them working in the lives of others. If only the
Lord would answer my prayers and give me a testimony, I would be one of the happiest
persons alive!" What this young lady wanted was a miraculous intervention; yet she had
already seen the miracle of the gospel enlarging and uplifting her own life. The Lord <i>had</i>
answered her prayers. She <i>did</i> have a testimony, but she did not recognize it for what it was.
Of such, Jesus said, ". . . they seeing see not; and hearing they hear not, neither do they
understand.
</p><p>
"And in them is fulfilled the prophecy of Esaias, which saith, By hearing ye shall hear, and
shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and shall not perceive" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/13-14#13">Matt. 13:13-14</a>). The
gospel is the way of life. It is practical, plain, and simple. It is a gospel of action, even to the
tiny day-to-day actions that make up the art of living.
</p><p>
Elder Adam S. Bennion, when he was with us, used to say, "Important as knowing is, there is
a more important field, and that is the field of doing. Life is always bigger than learning. It is
a wonderful thing to know, but it is better to do." This, of course, is the meaning of the
biblical injunction, "Be ye doers of the word, and not hearers only" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/22#22">James 1:22</a>), which is
another gospel imperative.
</p><p>
This gospel imperative expresses the very nature of Church education. The doctrine of making
hearers into doers of the word extends to the point at which we believe that what we know
and do in the gospel needs to become ingrained into the very nature of our being. Nels L.
Nelson expresses this gospel imperative in one of his books defining the Mormon concept of
education in these words: "The only kind of education which squares with the ideals of
Mormonism is that which trains a man to do. If it be asked, to do what, the answer is,
<i>to do the things that need to be done</i> . . .
</p><p>
"True education is therefore training a man to do his part in the social world . . .
</p><p>
". . . knowledge is only half of intelligence. To stop here is to be falsely educated. If,
however, the truth perceived becomes a dynamic fact in a man's character; if it is
incorporated into his mental attitude, and reacts immediately upon his life; if, in short, it
ceases to be something <i>in</i> a man and becomes the man himself changing the very . . .
[character of his soul, then knowledge has passed over into power&mdash;or character&mdash;or
wisdom&mdash;or, to adopt the term used by Joseph Smith, has passed over into intelligence, and
it is such a process alone that represents true education." (Nels L. Nelson,
<i>Scientific Aspects of Mormonism</i> [New York and London: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1904], pp. 151-52.)
</p><p>
<b>Factors of action</b>
</p><p>
If the gospel of Jesus Christ is truly to become a part of ourselves, then there are several
things we must keep in mind in putting the gospel imperatives into action.
</p><p>
First, it is essential to remember that it is more important to be able to <i>think</i> and hence to <i>act</i>
in terms of gospel principles and teachings than it is to merely memorize gospel facts.
Remember the injunction from Proverbs: "Wisdom is the principle thing; therefore get
wisdom: and with all thy getting get understanding" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/4/7#7">Prov. 4:7</a>). Solomon's great blessing
was "an understanding heart" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/3/12#12">1 Kgs. 3:12</a>). We should study gospel principles with the purpose of
understanding how they apply and may be used in our life today, not just to be able to
remember them.
</p><p>
Second, don't be afraid to put them into action. Courage&mdash;and this is as true of spiritual
courage as it is of physical courage&mdash;is not acting in the absence of fear. Courage is acting
in spite of fear. If we stood tall in the gospel, we would soon find that it is easier to act than
it is to remain idle or to cower in a corner.
</p><p>
Third, remember that our attitudes are most important tools to success. Knowledge is power
only when it is used constructively. We should extend a positive belief in the gospel into a
positive belief in our own ability to live the gospel as an effective factor in our lives and in
the lives of those about us. Businessmen have proven that the difference between the
successful and the unsuccessful usually reduces down to a difference in attitudes. This is just
as true of gospel living. "As [a man] thinketh in his heart, so is he" ought to be a prime tenet
in every gospel lesson (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/23/7#7">Prov. 23:7</a>).
</p><p>
Fourth, be assured that one kind of ability we must have is "stick-ability." No matter how
good the beginning, success comes only to those who "endure to the end."
</p><p>
Fifth, whenever we tackle a gospel imperative, immediate goals will help us master it. Our
decision to read scripture becomes quite practical when we decide to read a chapter at night
before we go to sleep. We should set up long-range and eternal goals, to be sure&mdash;they will
be the guides and inspiration of a lifetime; but we should not forget the countless little
immediate objectives to be won tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow. To win and pass
these objectives marks our progress toward the greater goals and insures happiness and the
feelings of success along the way.
</p><p>
Gospel imperatives are action words challenging every Latter-day Saint to gospel living. They
are the active pathway to personal participation in the laws of the gospel, and every one leads
to rewards and blessings. An example of this may be found in the blessing attached to one of
these gospel imperatives. It reads, "And all saints who remember to keep and do these
sayings, walking in obedience to the commandments, shall receive health in their navel and
marrow to their bones
</p><p>
"And shall find wisdom and great treasures of knowledge, even hidden treasures"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/18-19#18">D&amp;C 89:18-19</a>).
Such are the blessings promised, and there are many more, each to its own gospel
imperative. They are imperatives because they call to action, and every positive action in the
gospel plan makes better and happier men and women.
</p><p>
I never think of gospel imperatives without remembering the story of Mary Fielding Smith,
that indomitable pioneer mother who was the wife and widow of the Patriarch Hyrum Smith
brother of the Prophet. I am sure you are all familiar with the story of her struggles to bring
her little family to the valley of the Great Salt Lake. Well, one of the highlights in that story
for me is also the signature of gospel imperatives. One spring as they opened the potato pits
she had her boys get a load of the best potatoes, which she took to the tithing office.
</p><p>
She was met at the steps of the office by one of the clerks, who remonstrated as the boys
began to unload the potatoes. "Widow Smith," he said, remembering no doubt her trials and
sacrifices, "it's a shame that you should have to pay tithing." He added a number of other
things her son did not care to repeat, chided her for paying her tithing, and called her
anything but wise and prudent; he said that there were others able to work who were
supported from the tithing office. The little widow drew herself up to her
full height and said, "William, you ought to be ashamed of yourself. Would you deny me a
blessing? If I did not pay my tithing, I should expect the Lord to withhold his blessings from
me. I pay my tithing, not only because it is a law of God but because I expect a blessing by
doing it. By keeping this and other laws, I expect to prosper and to be able to provide for my
family." (<i>Life of Joseph F. Smith</i>, pp. 158-59.)
</p><p>
This is the goal of gospel imperatives, "to be able to prosper and provide for our families."
The abundance of the good and worthwhile things of life comes from following them. I bear
you my testimony that in them lies the wisdom of eternity. It is my witness that God lives,
that Jesus is the Christ, the Savior of the world. My appeal is to each of us, and the hundreds
of thousands of persons who joined with us by viewing this conference today, to catch the
vision of and follow the admonition contained in the key to all imperatives: "For every one
that asketh, receiveth and he that seeketh, findeth; and to him that knocketh, it shall be
opened" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/14/8#8">3 Ne. 14:8</a>). This is my humble prayer, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
