<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Immortality and Eternal Life</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Milton R. Hunter</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Milton R. Hunter, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1953, pp. 76-80</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Today the hearts of millions of people throughout the world are turned in adoration to the
Master of life and salvation. We, the members of the true Church of Jesus Christ, in this great
conference assembled, bow our heads in reverence and from the depths of our hearts thank
God for the mission of Jesus Christ and the marvelous atonement which he so gloriously
brought about. Already in this meeting we have listened to some wonderful testimonies given
by the various speakers regarding the resurrection of the Son of God. Especially is that true in
the case of the testimony which was so beautifully presented by President J. Reuben Clark. I
also want to voice my testimony here on this glorious Easter morning, because I also know
that my Redeemer liveth, and my heart is filled with gratitude for that knowledge.
</p><p>
I have never read a statement in any of the holy scriptures dealing with the work of God
which is as important as the one found in the Pearl of Great Price. It is as follows: 
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life
of man (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
That marvelous statement contains two distinctive features. The one is the immortality of
man; and the other, the eternal life. Each of these items means something entirely different,
distinctively different, from the other. Immortality means the resurrection from the grave.
Eternal life means the type of life that will be lived in celestial glory by those who showed
their love for God by keeping his commandments while living in mortality.
</p><p>
When the Eternal Father appointed his Only Begotten Son to be the Savior of the world, he
gave unto him two major assignments. One of these assignments was to break the bands of
death and thereby bring about the resurrection of all of God's sons and daughters. In other
words, Jesus was to give immortality universally to the human family. The other assignment
was to proclaim a gospel plan of salvation to the inhabitants of the earth, granting all men
their free agency and promising that all those who would obey that gospel
plan, which contained the words of eternal life, eventually would be brought back into the
presence of the Father and the Son and receive eternal life.
</p><p>
In the meridian of time, Jesus Christ came into the world; and in three short years' time of
public ministry he marked out the pathway which leadeth unto eternal life. In other words, by
the life he lived and through the teachings he gave, he proclaimed to the human family the
gospel plan of salvation, assuring exaltation to everyone who proved faithful in doing "all
things whatsoever the Lord their God shall command them"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/25#25">Abr. 3:25</a>). And then,
having been rejected by his own, he was crucified, dying as a ransom for the sins of the
world.
</p><p>
As was so beautifully explained by President Clark in his address a few moments ago, early
on that first Easter morning, Mary Magdalene and others of the women from Galilee who
loved Jesus very much went to the tomb for the purpose of giving the Master's body a more
proper burial. As has been pointed out, upon finding the tomb empty all the women returned
to Jerusalem except Mary Magdalene. She lingered near the doorway of the tomb weeping,
and then she looked inside. There she saw two angels dressed in white and heard one of them
declare: 
</p><p>
I know that ye seek Jesus, which was crucified.
</p><p>
He is not here: for he is risen . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/5-6#5">Matt. 28:5-6</a>).
</p><p>
Thus, as had been predicted by the holy prophets even from the very beginning, Jesus Christ,
the Savior of the world, had broken the bands of death. He had now overcome the tomb and
the grave and thereby had given assurance to the human family that as he had risen from the
grave, each of us also shall rise from the grave and take upon ourselves immortality.
</p><p>
The holy prophets had proclaimed that Jesus Christ was the Lamb of God slain from the
foundation of the world (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/8#8">Rev. 13:8</a>);
that he would die and rise again; and that every man, woman, and
child&mdash;bond and free, rich and poor, righteous and wicked&mdash;would receive immortality as a
result of his atoning sacrifice.
</p><p>
Regarding this vital subject, the Lord revealed the fact to the Prophet Joseph Smith that
through the redemption of the Only Begotten Son the human family would be raised from
death
</p><p>
. . . in immortality unto eternal life, even as many as would believe; 
</p><p>
And they that believe not unto eternal damnation . . .
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/43-44#43">D&amp;C 29:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
Amulek declared that resurrection or immortality would come to
</p><p>
. . . all, both old and young, both bond and free, both male and female, both the wicked and
the righteous...
</p><p>
[And at the resurrection or the receiving of immortality]
</p><p>
. . . the wicked remain as though there had been no redemption made, except it be the loosing
of the bands of death
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/44,41#44">Alma 11:44,41</a>).
</p><p>
The other part of that great scripture, previously quoted, is: 
</p><p>
For behold, this is my work and my glory&mdash;to bring to pass . . . the eternal life of man
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Eternal life is very, very important. A careful study of the scriptures reveals the fact that it is
the most desirable and important thing of all that exists.
</p><p>
In modern revelation we read: "Behold, he that hath eternal life is rich"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/7#7">D&amp;C 6:7</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/11/7#7">D&amp;C 11:7</a>).
The Doctrine and Covenants also states that ". . . eternal life . . . is the greatest of all the
gifts of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>).
Therefore, eternal life is the blessing that comes to the individual
who keeps the commandments in their fullness.
</p><p>
Since eternal life is the greatest of all of God's gifts to man, it should be of more importance
and much more worthwhile to you and me to put forth every effort to attain eternal life than
it would be to accumulate a million dollars, or even a million, million dollars, or to rise to
any position of leadership in this world, or to gratify any or all of our
mortal desires.
</p><p>
A careful study of the statements on this subject found in the scriptures, especially those
found in the Doctrine and Covenants reveals the fact that eternal life is the gift received by
husband and wife who are married for eternity, and has reference to their power of eternal
increase or a continuation of the seeds forever and ever. Also exaltation may include less than
a continuation of the seeds and Godhood may convey a slightly different shade of meaning. In
many of the quotations in the scriptures, "eternal life" and "life eternal" are also used with
meanings closely akin with those other words or phrases. Therefore, all of those terms,
although possessing slightly different shades in meaning, seem to lead to a similar final goal.
In order to come to a more thorough understanding regarding the meaning of those terms, we
shall refer directly to latter day revelation. In Section 131 of the Doctrine and Covenants, it is
written: 
</p><p>
In the celestial glory there are three heavens or degrees; 
</p><p>
And in order to obtain the highest, a man must enter into this order of the priesthood
[meaning the new and everlasting covenant of marriage]; 
</p><p>
And if he does not, he cannot obtain it.
</p><p>
He may enter into the other, but that is the end of his kingdom, he cannot have an increase
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/1-4#1">D&amp;C 131:1-4</a>).
</p><p>
Section 132, that marvelous revelation on celestial marriage, explains and clarifies the
quotation I have just given, and also tells definitely what is meant by eternal life, exaltation,
etc. In that revelation the Lord has informed us that if a man and a woman, members of the
Church of Jesus Christ, refuse to enter into God's holy order of marriage, but accept instead a
man-made order, and if this man and woman live all of the other principles of the gospel
sufficiently well to go to the celestial glory, they will not attain exaltation. To quote the
words of the Lord as received by the Prophet Joseph Smith: 
</p><p>
. . . they . . . are appointed angels in heaven; which angels are ministering servants, to
minister for those who are worthy of a far more, and an exceeding, and an eternal weight of
glory.
</p><p>
For these angels did not abide my law; therefore, they cannot be enlarged, but remain
separately and singly, without exaltation, in their saved condition, to all eternity and from
henceforth are not gods, but are angels of God forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/16-17#16">D&amp;C 132:16-17</a>).
</p><p>
We also read in the same revelation that if a man and a woman enter into the holy covenant
of marriage, according to God's law, and are sealed by the Holy Spirit of promise, living in
accordance with the covenants made therein, rendering obedience to all of his commandments
and enduring faithful to the end, they shall rise in the resurrection and be assigned to dwell
with the Lord in the celestial glory. And then the revelation states: 
</p><p>
. . . they shall pass by the angels, and the gods, which are set there, to their exaltation and
glory in all things, as hath been sealed upon their heads, which glory shall be a fullness and a
continuation of the seeds forever and ever
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/19#19">D&amp;C 132:19</a>).
</p><p>
The Prophet Joseph Smith points out that this "continuation of seeds forever and ever," means
to have children in the celestial glory.
</p><p>
To continue the revelation: 
</p><p>
Then shall they be gods, because they have no end . . .
</p><p>
Verily, verily, I say unto you, except ye abide my law ye cannot attain to this glory.
</p><p>
For strait is the gate, and narrow the way that leadeth unto the exaltation and continuation of
the lives, and few there be that find it, because ye receive me not in the world neither do ye
know me (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/20-22#20">D&amp;C 132:20-22</a>).
</p><p>
And then the Lord explained the meaning of eternal lives. He said: 
</p><p>
This is eternal lives&mdash;to know the only wise and true God, and Jesus Christ, whom he hath
sent... (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/24#24">D&amp;C 132:24</a>).
</p><p>
Now how can we come to know God fully, and completely? Such a
knowledge or status cannot be obtained completely in this world. A full knowledge of God can be
attained only in the celestial degree of glory by those who ultimately become as he is. When
one thinks as he thinks, acts as he acts, attains power comparable to that enjoyed by him, then
that individual has attained exaltation or eternal life. To such a person, Jesus has promised:
". . . all that my Father hath shall be given unto him"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/38#38">D&amp;C 84:38</a>).
</p><p>
The question of importance which lies deeply imbedded in the hearts of each of us is: How
may we gain eternal life?
</p><p>
Jesus Christ, our Lord and Master, came to the earth and pointed out the path which leadeth
to eternal life; and he commanded us, saying: 
</p><p>
And I now give unto you a commandment to beware concerning yourselves, to give diligent
heed to the words of eternal life.
</p><p>
For you shall live by every word that proceedeth forth from the mouth of God
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/43-44#43">D&amp;C 84:43-44</a>).
</p><p>
A summary of Jesus of Nazareth's teachings regarding the pathway that leadeth to eternal life
is as follows: 
</p><p>
First, we must have faith, faith in Jesus Christ and in the gospel plan which he promulgated; 
</p><p>
Second, we must repent of all our sins;
</p><p>
Third, we must be baptized by one having proper authority; 
</p><p>
Fourth, we must be confirmed members of the Church of Jesus Christ and receive the Holy
Ghost; 
</p><p>
(Then, according to Nephi, we have entered through the gateway into the kingdom of God
and are now on the ". . . straight and narrow path which leads to eternal life"
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/17-18#17">2 Ne. 31:17-18</a>).
</p><p>
Fifth, we must receive the Holy Melchizedek Priesthood and honor and magnify that
priesthood; 
</p><p>
Sixth, we must enter into the law of celestial marriage and keep all of the covenants made
therein; 
</p><p>
Seventh, we must demonstrate to the Lord through the lives we live and by rendering
obedience to his commandments that we are willing to consecrate all we possess&mdash;our
talents, our time, our means, and our very lives if need be&mdash;to the upbuilding of the Church
and kingdom of God here upon the earth and also to the salvation of his sons and daughters; 
</p><p>
Eighth, we must continue to press forward with unshaken faith in the words of Jesus Christ,
whether spoken by himself or through the mouths of his prophets, proving faithful in keeping
all of the commandments, pressing "forward with a steadfastness in Christ, having a perfect
brightness of hope, and a love of God and of all men," and enduring faithful to the end, then,
according to the promise of the Eternal Father, we ". . . shall have eternal life"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/20#20">2 Ne. 31:20</a>).
</p><p>
Thus, if we prove faithful in walking along the pathway enumerated in those eight points,
". . . feasting upon the word of Christ . . . [for] there is none other way nor name given under
heaven whereby man can be saved in the kingdom of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/20-21#20">2 Ne. 31:20-21</a>), then our election
shall be made sure, with the glory of eternal lives as our reward; and then, as the revelation
previously quoted states, those faithful ones ". . . shall pass by the angels, and the gods,
which are set there, to their exaltation and glory in all things, as hath been sealed upon their
heads" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/19#19">D&amp;C 132:19</a>).
</p><p>
I would like to bear my testimony, which testimony has been given to me through the power
of the Holy Ghost. I know that Jesus is the Christ, the Only Begotten Son of God. I know as
I know that I live that he died for you and me, and on the third day he was resurrected,
thereby breaking the bands of death and giving immortality to the human family. I have a
strong conviction that some of God's children will rise through immortality to eternal life and
others will rise through immortality to eternal condemnation. It is also my testimony that
through the blood that Jesus shed and the sacrifice that he made, he atoned for the sins
of those who receive him and keep his commandments; but, on the other
hand, as Jesus of Nazareth declared, those who will not receive him and repent and keep his
commandments will be required to suffer even as he, the greatest of all, suffered; and his
suffering was so intense that it caused him "to tremble because of pain, and to bleed at every
pore, and to suffer both body and spirit"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/17-18#17">D&amp;C 19:17-18</a>; see also
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/44#44">Luke 22:44</a>,
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/7#7">Mosiah 3:7</a>).
</p><p>
I know also that if we will render obedience to all the commandments given us by our Lord
and Savior, Jesus Christ, and also those given through his holy prophets, someday we will
come back into the presence of God and hear the voice of the Lamb, saying: "Well done, my
beloved servants, enter ye into your exaltation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/21#21">Matt. 25:21</a>);
and as King Benjamin has said, through the
covenants we have made and by taking upon ourselves his name, we become sons and
daughters of Jesus Christ and shall dwell with him eternally in the celestial degree of glory
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/5/6-10#6">Mosiah 5:6-10</a>).
This blessing and glory will be ours if we press forward "with an eye single
to the glory of God" and endure faithful to the end
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/4/5#5">D&amp;C 4:5</a>;
<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/19#19">D&amp;C 82:19</a>).
</p><p>
May our Eternal Father bless us as Latter-day Saints, who are now on the pathway which
leadeth to eternal life that we will be diligent and faithful in all things and eventually receive
that great blessing which is "the greatest of all the gifts of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/14/7#7">D&amp;C 14:7</a>), namely, eternal life, I
humbly pray, in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
