<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Need for Moral Courage</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder ElRay L. Christiansen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">ElRay L. Christiansen, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1963, pp. 115-117</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My beloved brethren and sisters, I have not forgotten the statement made in one of the recent
general conferences by Elder Richard L. Evans, who reminded us that to know is not enough.
As we draw near to the close of this great and uplifting conference, it seems to me that the
thing that remains is for us to go to our homes and conform our lives to the teachings of the
Lord Jesus Christ as they have been expounded here, lacking not in determination and in
moral courage to do it, for "to know is not enough."
</p><p>
One of the greatest demonstrations of moral courage ever shown in this day was when in the
dead of winter, 1846, the first of the Saints, living in the city of Nauvoo, rolled their loaded
wagons onto flatboats to be ferried across the broad, icy Mississippi River. That marked the
beginning of the exodus of modern Israel. Later in the month, according to the historians, long
caravans crossed the river on a solid floor of ice.
</p><p>
These people had been living in substantial and comfortable homes. They had fanned their
fertile lands; they had completed the construction of the sacred Nauvoo Temple and had
developed an attractive city, which they proudly referred to as "Nauvoo the Beautiful." All
these they left behind to move their families, with what household goods and provisions that
they could take with them, to make an almost superhuman trek thirteen hundred miles into an
almost unknown western land.
</p><p>
With a background of culture and refinement, they were not accustomed to the hardships of
improvised shelters erected against the wintry blasts of February winds; yet, because of their
faith and their courage, they resolutely met the challenge, and turning their backs upon their
beautiful homes and their faces toward the west, they met whatever was to come. These
exiled people, with implicit trust in their leaders, chose to ". . . seek ye first the kingdom of
God, and his righteousness" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/33#33">Matt. 6:33</a>).
Their physical courage was equaled only by their moral courage.
</p><p>
In our day there is a crying need for this same quality in each of us, especially the moral
courage to resist the ever-increasing pressures and insidious influences that are constantly at
work, distorting the truth, tearing down the good and the decent, and attempting to substitute
therefore the vain and shallow philosophies and practices of a carnal world. There is need for
the moral courage to uphold correct principles in our personal lives and to defend right and
truth and decency and honor, and above all, to have faith in and honor God our Father.
</p><p>
It seems to me that moral courage is made of a firm desire, coupled with determination to
accept and to do what is right and to shun the wrong. It is the outgrowth of moral conviction.
Moral courage may not be dramatically displayed. Seldom does it receive public acclaim,
nevertheless, it is an indispensable attribute of noble character. It must be exercised if
worthwhile principles and institutions are to be preserved and perpetuated.
</p><p>
He who stands steadfastly for that which is right must take the risk of becoming at times
disapproved and unpopular, or even shunned by others&mdash;sometimes by his closest friends.
Indeed, some have become martyrs. Knowing what is right and true and honorable, they have
had the courage to do, not what is <i>easy</i> but what is right; not what is <i>expedient</i> but what is
best.
</p><p>
I think of a young boy with whom I am acquainted, who, rather than join his companions one
night in an escapade that was not in harmony with the training he had received in his home
and in the Church, chose to walk more than six miles to his home while his companions in
the car proceeded to carry out their plans. I imagine that boy, for more reasons than one, slept
well when he finally arrived at home. And no doubt his parents were proud
of him. Truly, "A wise son maketh a glad father"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/10/1#1">Prov. 10:1</a>).
</p><p>
It requires no moral courage to drift with the multitude or to run with the "pack," so to speak.
The real test is in choosing and pursuing the right, even though it appears that in so doing,
one is alone.
</p><p>
Jesus, the personification of this quality, disagreed with the powerful and influential Jewish
governing body&mdash;the Sanhedrin. He referred to certain unrighteous Pharisees as ". . .
hypocrites! for ye are like unto whited sepulchres, which indeed appear beautiful outward, but
are within full of dead men's bones"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/27#27">Matt. 23:27</a>).
</p><p>
And Matthew records him saying plainly, ". . . for ye devour widows' houses, and for a
pretence make long prayer: therefore ye shall receive the greater damnation"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/14#14">Matt. 23:14</a>).
</p><p>
With righteous fervor he drove out the money changers, because he could not bear to see
them desecrate the temple. He was fearless in defense of correct principles, and although he
was falsely and maliciously accused&mdash;even though he was subjected to railings and mockery
of the worst kind&mdash;he stood majestically and composed before Pilate and again before Herod,
while the howling mob cried, "Crucify him, crucify him!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/21#21">Luke 23:21</a>).
</p><p>
He was not concerned with his own security nor with the indignities he suffered at the hands
of foul men. His great desire has to do the will of the Father, even though it meant his
crucifixion.
</p><p>
While we in our day may or may not be called upon to suffer unduly or to test our moral
courage in the great issues of the world, there is, nevertheless, always need for each of us to
exercise self-discipline and moral courage in our everyday living.
</p><p>
It was Lincoln that reminded us that, and I quote: "We must return to idealism&mdash;the idealism
of character and truth; of integrity in private and public (affairs) . . . no people can ever
become greater by lowering their standards, no society was ever improved by adopting a
looser morality."
</p><p>
Someone has said our physical fitness program is wonderful and is needed, but we have also a
need in our lives for a moral fitness program. It takes moral courage, for instance, to
apologize, to put aside pride and say, "I was wrong," or to explain a misunderstanding which,
if ignored, would hurt another person; or to defend a person when slighting remarks are made
against his character. It takes courage to stand up and be counted when you may not agree
with the crowd; for example, to plan, and to live, and to qualify to go to the house of the
Lord when the time comes to be married even though some of our associates may do
otherwise.
</p><p>
It requires moral courage to tell the truth regardless of the situation or the consequences, but
it pays great dividends in peace of mind.
</p><p>
It takes courage to resist envy and hate and anger, the destroyers of happiness. The Bible
says: "He that is slow to anger is better than the mighty; and he that ruleth his spirit than he
that taketh a city" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/16/32#32">Prov. 16:32</a>).
</p><p>
Have we the moral courage to forgive or to ask forgiveness? Never is the human soul more
noble and so courageous than when it forgives and then forgets. Jesus said in a revelation to
Joseph Smith: "Wherefore, I say unto you, that ye ought to forgive one another; for he that
forgiveth not his brother his trespasses, standeth condemned before the Lord; for there
remaineth in him the greater sin.
</p><p>
"I, the Lord, will forgive whom I will forgive, but of you it is required to forgive all men"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/9-10#9">D&amp;C 64:9-10</a>).
</p><p>
And Matthew records: "For if ye forgive men their trespasses your heavenly Father will also
forgive you" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/14#14">Matt. 6:14</a>).
</p><p>
The religious life of a Latter-day Saint should be based not upon obligation and duty alone,
but upon a genuine desire to be honorable, to do good, to do what is right, to love God, and
to love one another.
</p><p>
We ought to think right and do right simply because it is right. If there is to be any moral
perfection for us in this life, it will come because we consistently and automatically do what
is right.
</p><p>
I bear solemn testimony to the fact that Jesus is the Christ, that God our
Father lives, that Joseph Smith was indeed the Prophet of this dispensation through whom the
gospel, the divine pattern for living, was restored, and that President David O. McKay is
presently the prophet, seer, and revelator of the Lord Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
Let us go from here with the determination and the moral courage to say as Job said, ". . .
while my breath is in me . . .
</p><p>
"My lips shall not speak wickedness, nor my tongue utter deceit.
</p><p>
". . . till I die I will not remove . . . integrity from me"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/27/3-5#3">Job 27:3-5</a>).
</p><p>
I pray for this in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
