<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Untitled</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">President David O. McKay</p>
<p class="gcbib">David O. McKay, <i>Conference Report</i> April 1957,  pp. 92-94</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Thank you brethren who have so ably discharged your duty in ascertaining the attendance this
night in 97 houses of worship, including this Tabernacle. It is complete.
</p><p>
<i>General Priesthood Conference, April 6, 1957</i>
</p><p>
Salt Lake Tabernacle                           7,291<br />
Assembly Hall, Barratt Hall, and Grounds       3,294<br />
94 Groups reporting in                        26,595<br />
Total tonight                                 37,180<br />
</p><p>
That is the largest attendance in the history of the Church!
</p><p>
We do not favor taking photographs in our meetings, but I do wish that we could get a
picture of this assembly tonight. All who can see it as we from the rostrum will never forget
it. If anybody have his flashlight camera, he may take a picture, so we may have it enlarged.
</p><p>
I think this is wonderful, it is glorious! What a power assembled tonight in 97 groups, men of
the Priesthood&mdash;men of God! We just feel in our hearts to say, "O Father," as Christ pleaded
with Him, "keep us one as thou, Father, and thy Son are one"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/22#22">John 17:22</a>).
Nothing can stay the progress
of the kingdom of God as long as this mighty army of Priesthood will keep united.
</p><p>
We heard tonight from two released missionaries&mdash;presidents from missions. They represented
all mission presidents tonight, first, in their ready response to the call that came to them&mdash;one
a prominent businessman, another a professional man, and their wives with them. So have all
other mission presidents. I happen to know some of the sacrifices that their sweet wives have
made in the missions represented. So the other mission presidents' wives make these
sacrifices. Do they complain? No. They rejoice in the opportunity. Other mission presidents
could tell us of interesting items just as Brother Romney and Brother Coombs gave us
tonight.
</p><p>
The world does not realize what this missionary work in the Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints entails, and what a mighty contribution the members of the Priesthood are
making to make it a success. I, too, wish that all had heard that program last evening. One
thing they realized was that one of the influential factors in missionary work is personal
contact, that is one of the most potent, most effective.
</p><p>
And so it is in the field of activity to which I wish to refer in a few words&mdash;our ward
teaching.
</p><p>
Especially during the last year, I have been impressed with the realization that we are not
reaching those whom the Lord would like us to reach. Now, the ward teachers are doing an
excellent work. They visit homes regularly. They have their lessons prepared. And they make
their report.
</p><p>
Statistics show that the ward teaching is in good shape. So what I say is not reflecting upon
the effort that is made by this group of Priesthood. But tell me, fellow workers, are we doing
all that is implied by the Lord's statement that it is the ward teacher's duty to watch over the
Church always?
</p><p>
A man who knows about the ills that befall our Government because of criminals wrote
recently&mdash;I refer to F.B.I. Director J. Edgar Hoover&mdash;about the responsibility of parents. He
said:
</p><p>
"Criminals are not born with a stamp of criminality affixed to them. They are created by the
forces and influences surrounding them. Certainly parental influence is a vital element in
determining the direction in which a child will go. The parent who fails his duty by
neglecting to provide moral training and essential consistent discipline in the home should be
accountable for the delinquencies which emanate from that neglect. I firmly believe that the
tide of juvenile crime could be stemmed if neglectful parents were made to face legal and
financial responsibility for the criminal acts of their children.
</p><p>
"I am convinced that parental incompetency, parental indifference are at the root of the vast
majority of youthful behavior problems.
</p><p>
"Back of the majority of cases of juvenile delinquency lies, in some form
or another, the abdication of parental responsibility; broken homes; lack of parental
supervision; over-protective parents, drunken parents; over-indulgent mother; overly strict
father; parent works nights; poor home conditions; parental neglect; lack of religious training;
no discipline; depraved home environment. Nothing is sadder, in my opinion, than those cases
in which children lack nothing in material things, and yet parental irresponsibility destroys
their potential development as good citizens." (Published in "The Rotarian," October, 1956.)
</p><p>
One cause of delinquency he names is broken homes. I appreciate the statistics sent me every
month by the Salt Lake County Sheriff and his associates. I brought two here tonight
regarding broken homes.
</p><p>
In November, 1956, 96 criminals were fingerprinted; 4 women among them; 23 repeaters. In
December, 1956, there were 95 fingerprinted; 6 women; 22 repeaters. In November, among
those 96, 60 were from broken homes; 24, in which the father was dead; 12, the mother was
dead; 22, both dead; and 2 were divorced. Among the 95 in December, 1956, 56 broken
homes. Note, it is over half of the people, half of the criminals. Father was dead in 16 of the
homes; mother was dead in 10; and in 25, both were dead.
</p><p>
Well there are other statistics, but I do not have time to refer to them.
</p><p>
Now, it is the duty of the ward teacher to watch over the Church always, to be with and to
strengthen (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>).
</p><p>
I wish we could see tonight how many of those 60 who came from broken homes were on the
list of the ward teacher; how many of those 56 offenders last December from broken homes
were listed by the ward teacher. Do not go away with the idea that they are not members of
the Church. The Sheriff's report gives the number of deacons, the number of teachers, the
number of priests, and the number of elders among those who were fingerprinted. As it is the
duty of the teacher to "watch over the Church always" every one of the children from these
broken homes (members of the Church) should be on the ward teachers' list.
</p><p>
I have a case in mind that will illustrate:
</p><p>
A mother died and left a large family, none of whom were married, and a little baby boy. The
father was quite indifferent. He had been born in the Church. We all felt sorry when his wife
died and left him with a large family. The oldest girl took care of that family wonderfully
well. They are all in the Church. But the young boy grew up and did not attend his school
until winter came, and then he left it as soon as spring opened up. He liked to ride horses and
he could ride the bucking horse. He learned to shoot. Early in his teens he went out to herd
sheep, and he made money. But when he came back, he did not go to Sunday School, he did
not go to M.I.A. His interest was in activity&mdash;a life of activity.
</p><p>
Well, I will not go through the whole story. He was skillful in herding, riding, shooting, and
the outdoor life.
</p><p>
I have referred several times to that rhyme given by the Presiding Bishopric to the Aaronic
Quorums about the boy who stood alone . . .
</p><p>
The boy stood at the crossroads all alone,<br />
The sunlight in his face.<br />
He had no thought for the world unknown,<br />
He was set for a manly race.<br />
But the roads stretched east and the roads stretched west,<br />
And the lad knew not which road was best.<br />
So he chose the road that led him down,<br />
And he lost the race and the victor's crown.<br />
He was caught at last in an angry snare,<br />
Because no one stood at the crossroads there<br />
To show him the better road.
</p><p>
That is just what this boy did. While still in his teens, he entered a grocery store, bought
something, paid with a bill, $10 or $20, and a dispute arose about the change. The
merchantman attempted to throw him out. The young boy had his sixshooter and was caught
"at last in an angry snare."
</p><p>
Personally, I made inquiry, when that boy went to the penitentiary, as to
whether the Sunday School teacher had ever visited him. No. Nor had the Mutual
worker nor the ward teacher. I do not know that they could have won him. I think they could
have. Personal contact would have won that boy.
</p><p>
It is the teacher's duty to watch over the Church always
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/53#53">D&amp;C 20:53</a>).
That boy's name should have been on some teacher's list.
</p><p>
So it is with these 60 people&mdash;let us say there are only 30&mdash;half of these who were
fingerprinted belong to us&mdash;thirty last November, were from broken homes.
</p><p>
Ward teachers, when you go home tonight, make a complete list of all those in your district,
every boy, every girl. You may not go to a broken home, you may not find them there. Find
out where they are and reach them. God bless you, and bless us all as we watch over the
Church always.
</p><p>
For first, Priesthood means service; it is not given just as an honor. I congratulate you and
commend you that you are worthy to receive it, but it is given to you for service, and you act
as an authorized representative of our Lord Jesus Christ in whatever position you may be
assigned.
</p><p>
God bless you that you may serve worthily, I pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
