<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Power of Example</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Bishop LeGrand Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Presiding Bishop of the Church</p>
<p class="gcbib">LeGrand Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1942, pp. 30-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
With all my heart, brethren, I appreciate the opportunity of being here today, feasting on the
spiritual food that we have been receiving from our leaders and associates. I thank the Lord
that there never has been a time in my life that a shadow of a doubt has crossed my mind as
to the divinity of this work and the divine calling of the Prophet Joseph Smith and those who
have succeeded him in the Presidency of this Church. I thrilled today with President Grant's
testimony, as it was read to us by President McKay, and I was delighted with the message of
the First Presidency delivered to us this morning by President Clark. Of all the leadership in
the world today, surely there is none comparable to that which we have in the Church. How
safe and secure we should feel in following their precepts and their example.
</p><p>
A few days ago I received a letter from a man in the East with whom I have had some,
correspondence&mdash;a prominent business man, but not a member of our Church. I forwarded him
some of our literature. He and his wife have read the Book of Mormon three times. He has
just read the Articles of Faith and writes a beautiful appreciation for the truths contained
therein. But I would like to read from his letter his comment after having read the message of
the First Presidency delivered at the April conference. He says: "The message of the First
Presidency was read with intense interest. It portrays the mind of a soul deeply interested in
the welfare of a higher civilization, with a clear understanding of 'mercy and justice.'" It is
good to know that thinking men, though not of us, recognize the power of leadership of those
whom the Lord has placed to guide His people in these days.
</p><p>
We have a great responsibility, those of us who are here today. For we represent the
leadership of this Church &mdash;the General Authorities and those who preside in the stakes, the
wards, and the Priesthood quorums of the Church. We have problems and responsibilities and
opportunities probably such as we have never had before, particularly in these defense areas. I
hope we will realize that there will be more expected of us&mdash;that our arms will be just a little
longer, and our love a little deeper, and our faith a little more sincere, and that our confidence
and trust in God and the ultimate triumph of His work in the earth may never falter.
</p><p>
I hope the bishops will realize that they are in very deed fathers of the people, all who live
within the confines of their wards whether their names be on their records or not. Many have
come from outside places and they need care and attention. I hope the bishops will also sense
their great responsibility as presidents of the Aaronic Priesthood in their wards&mdash;that the ward
teachers will realize that their responsibility is greater than ever before, that the presidencies
of Priesthood quorums and all charged with responsibility in this Church will respond thereto
as never before. And I wouldn't like to overlook the seventies, for I feel with Brother
Kirkham the great importance of missionary work, for the Lord has decreed that the gospel
shall be preached in all the world for a witness to all nations
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>), even to every creature
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15#15">Mark 16:15</a>). I feel
that there are added opportunities within our reach today, and I hope that we will meet these
responsibilities in such a way that whoever comes into our communities need never go away
and say that he was not given an opportunity to hear the gospel of the Lord Jesus Christ from
the elders of this Church.
</p><p>
I would like to leave one other thought with you before closing. It has been said that those
who live in glass houses should not throw stones. Probably it was because Paul never had any
children of his own that he wasn't afraid to tell the bishops and deacons that they should be
able to rule well their own houses, for said he: "If a man know not how to rule his own
house, how shall he take care of the church of God"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/3/5#5">1 Tim. 3:5</a>).
Some of us may not have dared say
such a thing, but I believe that under present conditions we should give more thought to this,
each one of us individually, than we have ever done before.
</p><p>
We listened to President Clawson a few minutes ago reading the words of Alma. It has
always occurred to me that that great mission of Alma, the son, was the result of the faith and
the prayers of Alma, his father, who pleaded with the Lord until the Lord saw fit to call him
back from the error of his ways (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/27/14#14">Mosiah 27:14</a>).
I wonder if we are doing that for our boys and girls. I
wonder if we are holding council meetings as husbands and wives, and fathers and mothers,
to try to meet the new conditions and temptations that are in our midst. I wonder if we know
each one of our children well enough to know that they are making their contribution to the
building up of the kingdom of God in the earth. Are our children setting an example because
of our power as leaders and priests in our own homes?
</p><p>
A few days ago, I received a letter from one of our boys in the service, and I commend the
counsel given in this conference, that we write them. He said he had just been ordained an
elder in the Church, and he thanked the Lord for that more than for any other thing. While he
has been in the service he has changed his way of living so that he is setting an example in
upholding the standards of this Church.
</p><p>
But how did he get started in the way of righteousness? His grandmother in one of our stakes
was concerned about him, because his mother was dead. She wrote a letter and asked if we
would write to this boy. We finally located him, and the first letter we received told how he
was in California and heard two missionaries speaking on the street corner and lady
missionaries singing; and he said he wouldn't have gone and spoken to them for anything in
the world. He was afraid. He drew a diagram showing how he went down to the corner and
back again, and then down to the corner and back again, and finally he found himself
standing talking to the missionaries. In his letter he asked: "Do you think the Lord had
anything to do with this?" As far as I am concerned I think the prayers of that grandmother
and the importunities probably of his mother who had gone beyond, were the means of
bringing that boy back into line of duty and righteousness.
</p><p>
God help us to labor with our children, to pray with them, to see that our own are setting an
example in the Church. It will do more than all the preaching we can do. God help us to do
it, I pray in Jesus' name. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
