<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Our Temptations Upward</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Sterling W. Sill</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Sterling W. Sill, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1970, pp. 28-30</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
In Charles Dickens' great book <i>The Tale of Two Cities</i>, he talks about the French revolutionary
period of 200 years ago, almost as though he were describing our own day. In establishing the
setting for his story, he said: 
"It was the best of times, it was the worst of times, it was the age of wisdom, it was the age of
foolishness, it was the epoch of belief, it was the epoch of incredulity, it was the season of Light,
it was the season of Darkness, it was the spring of hope, it was the winter of despair, we had
everything before us, we had nothing before us, we were all going direct to Heaven, we were all
going direct the other way."
</p><p>
<b>A world of contrasts</b>
</p><p>
In our world of contrasts, the hazards frequently become greater as the benefits are increased,
and it seems that difficulty is one of the prices that we pay for our blessings. The 12 months
lying immediately before us will probably be the greatest period that our world has ever seen. In
this coming year more babies will be born than in any other comparable period. More new
inventions will be made than ever before. We will learn more new things and have greater
material comforts. In the next 12 months more people will go to college, and more people will
join the Church of Christ than in any other year. On the other hand, there will probably be more
people die than ever before. We may have more troubles, commit more crimes, use more dope,
drink more liquor, indulge in more sins, foster more soul-destroying violence, and send a greater
number of ourselves to hell, than ever before.
</p><p>
<b>Dispensation of fulness of times</b>
</p><p>
The apostle Paul spotlighted the greatness of our day when he referred to it as the dispensation
of the fulness of times, when God would gather together in one all things in Christ, both which
are in heaven and which are upon the earth. (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10#10">Eph. 1:10</a>) The ancient prophets eagerly
looked forward to our time, and many of them almost lived in our day. They knew about our
great knowledge explosion and the unheard-of miracles, wonders, and wealth that it would
produce. Jesus himself looked beyond the black night of the dark ages, caused by the apostasy
from God in the meridian of time, and he saw our day, when the gospel would be restored in a
fulness never before known in the world. And as one of the signs preceding his own glorious
second coming to the earth, he said, "And this gospel of the kingdom shall be preached in all the
world for a witness unto all nations; and then shall the end come." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14#14">Matt. 24:14</a>)
</p><p>
<b>Preparation for millennium</b>
</p><p>
Our generation is living on the approaches of the final cleansing that will prepare the earth for its
great millennium of peace, when Christ shall reign personally upon the earth for a thousand
years. The prophet Malachi describes this part of our future when all corruptible things will he
consumed. He says, ". . . and the Lord, whom ye seek, shall suddenly come to his temple . . . But
who may abide the day of his coming? and who shall stand when he appeareth? for he is like a
refiner's fire, and like fullers' soap." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/1-2#1">Mal. 3:1-2</a>)
</p><p>
The apostle Paul fills in some of the details by saying, "For the Lord himself shall descend from
heaven with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in
Christ shall rise first: 
</p><p>
"Then we which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to
meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we ever be with the Lord." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_thes/4/16-17#16">1 Thes. 4:16-17</a>)
</p><p>
These great latter-day events are now well on their way toward fulfillment. The gospel is already
going forth under divine command. We are now in the midst of the greatest and the last of all of
the dispensations. From many points of view we are presently living in the very best of times.
The priesthood is again upon the earth. God has given us three great volumes of new scripture,
outlining in every detail the simple principles of the gospel of Christ. The pathway to exaltation
is now perfectly marked and brilliantly lighted, so that no one need get off that straight and
narrow way except by his own choice. For every point of Christian doctrine, there is now an
authoritative statement saying, "Thus saith the Lord." The stone that Daniel envisioned being cut
out of the mountain without hands is now rolling toward its divine destiny of filling the whole
earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/34-35,44-45#34">Dan. 2:34-35,44-45</a>).
</p><p>
<b>The best and worst of times</b>
</p><p>
But the best of times is also the worst of times. As Jesus looked forward to our day and
contemplated our doings, he made a very uncomplimentary comparison to us by saying, ". . . as
the days of Noe were, so shall also the coming of the Son of man be." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/37#37">Matt. 24:37</a>) By their
wickedness the antediluvians brought about their own destruction, and many evidences indicate
that we are now trembling upon the very brink of a comparable disaster. And yet our day of
wonders and enlightenment offers us so much more than any other period since creation. We
now have our greatest opportunity to make Christian converts. Now is the best time ever known
to make money. And no people have ever had a greater chance to be faithful to God or loyal to
the government, nor has anyone ever had a better opportunity to uphold law and order than we
now have.
</p><p>
<b>Increased intensity of temptations</b>
</p><p>
However, simultaneously with these advantages, we are now making our greatest indulgences in
idleness, disloyalty, confusion, uncleanness, irresponsibility, and indifference to God. The new
morality gives us more freedom to indulge our sins, and it also makes our atheism seem more
respectable to us.
</p><p>
Our age is noted for the increased number variety, and intensity of our temptations. Almost
everything that we read, hear, or think is likely to have some lurking temptation to draw us
downward. But the dictionary says that to tempt is to arouse a desire for, and a desire can go in
either direction. However, we frequently forget the temptations upward, while we overindulge
ourselves in the temptations or evil. The temptations downward are the temptations of
ignorance, the temptations of crime, the temptations of misery, the temptations of eternal
damnation. We are filling our minds with delusions. We picture to ourselves how attractive evil
is and how difficult it is to live the religion of being honest, fair, decent, and obedient to God.
But no temptation is a temptation, unless we are entertaining it.
</p><p>
<b>Temptations imply desires</b>
</p><p>
In denying our own responsibility, we frequently blame Satan for much of the misery that we are
bringing upon ourselves. Satan has no power over us except as we give it to him. And
temptations without imply desires within; and rather than say, "How powerfully the devil
tempts," we might say, "How strongly I am inclined." God never forces us to do right, and Satan
has no power to force us to do wrong. As someone has said, "God always votes for us and Satan
always votes against us, and then we are asked to vote to break the tie." It is how we vote that
gives our lives their significance.
</p><p>
Someone has said: 
</p><p>
"All the water in the world,<br />
     However hard it tried,<br />
     Could never sink the smallest ship<br />
     Unless it got inside.<br /><br />
     And all the evil in the world, <br />
     The blackest kind of sin, <br />
     Can never hurt you the least bit <br />
     Unless you let it in."
</p><p>
The Pacific Ocean may contain more water than the Atlantic Ocean, but it can't sink any ship a
bit more easily. And our tremendously increased present-day evils have no more power over us
than the ancient temptations had over our fathers, except as we provide them with a more
enticing entertainment.
</p><p>
<b>Our temptations upward</b>
</p><p>
Actually, the greatest of all our opportunities is provided by our exciting present-day temptations
upward. And inasmuch as we seem to be temptation prone, we might give more thought to the
thrilling temptations to culture, the temptations to happiness, the temptations to honor, the
temptations to be like God. The temptations up are far more pleasant and much more profitable
than the temptations down. We need to take greater advantage of those challenging temptations
to be friends with God.
</p><p>
Because of God's new revelations, it is now no longer necessary to repeat the dark ages' mistakes
in Christian doctrines. And in living by every one of God's commandments, we may now more
effectively help to bring about our own eternal life. The beast goes down on all fours and thus
his vision is cast upon the ground, but man stands upright in the image of his Maker that he may
look up to God our Eternal Father.
And among the greatest of all our human concepts are the immortality of the human personality
and the eternal glory of the human soul. Each of us is a child of God, created in his image and
endowed with his attributes and potentialities.
</p><p>
<b>Our inheritance</b>
</p><p>
Each of us should cling to our inheritance. There is everything in knowing our inheritance and
constantly reaffirming it in our lives. And certainly we should not claim to be children of God
and then go about the world acting as though we are orphans or weaklings or cowards or sinners.
By an abundance of our good works, we can have our own finest year this year and make for our
world the very best of times. We can also help to usher in the age of belief in God, the age of
light, the age of reason, and the age of righteousness, as well as to help bring about a millennium
of peace on earth and goodwill toward men. And may God grant that it may be so, I humbly pray
in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
