<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Three Threatening Dangers</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1964, pp. 56-60</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Some years ago President Joseph F. Smith, a prophet of the Lord, warned that "There are at
least three dangers that threaten the Church within" (<i>Gospel Doctrine</i>, p. 312). He also
counseled the Authorities of the Church to warn the people unceasingly against them.
</p><p>
These dangers are:
</p><p>
Flattery of prominent men in the world,<br />
False educational ideas,<br />
Sexual impurity.
</p><p>
I should like to comment briefly on these three dangers.
</p><p>
<b>Flattery</b>
</p><p>
First, <i>the flattery of prominent men in the world:</i>
</p><p>
The Master warned, "Woe unto you when all men shall speak well of you!"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/6/26#26">Luke 6:26</a>).
</p><p>
As Latter-day Saints we have been driven, mobbed, misunderstood, and maligned. We have
been a peculiar people. Now we are faced with world applause. It has been a welcome
change, but can we stand acceptance? Can we meet the danger of applause? In the hour of a
man's success applause can be his greatest danger.
</p><p>
There is, of course, nothing wrong with being honored by men, if one is being honored for a
good thing, if one comes to these honors through righteous living, and if, while holding these
honors, one lives honorably. One should strive to have wide influence for good.
</p><p>
However, virtue is not the only basis for being singled out and promoted. As the world gets
more wicked, a possible way to attain worldly success may be to join the wicked. The time is
fast approaching when it will require great courage for Latter-day Saints to stand up for their
peculiar standards and doctrine&mdash;all of their doctrine, including the more weighty principles
such as the principle of freedom. Opposition to this weighty principle of freedom caused
many of our brothers and sisters in the pre-existence to lose their first estate in the war in
heaven.
</p><p>
We are far removed from the days of our forefathers who were persecuted for their peculiar
beliefs. Some of us seem to want to share their reward but are ofttimes afraid to stand up for
principles that are controversial in our generation. We need not solicit persecution, but neither
should we remain silent in the presence of overwhelming evils, for this makes cowards of
men. We should not go out of the path of duty to pick up a cross there is no need to bear, but
neither should we sidestep a cross that clearly lies within the path of duty.
</p><p>
We are in the world, and I fear some of us are getting too much like the world. Rather than
continue a peculiar people, some are priding themselves on how much they are like everybody
else, when the world is getting more wicked. The Lord, as he prayed for his Apostles, said, ".
. . the world hath hated them, because they are not of the world, even as I am not of the
world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/14#14">John 17:14</a>).
As Latter-day Saints, we too have been called out of the world.
</p><p>
Some things are changeless&mdash;priceless. We must anchor ourselves to the eternal verities of
life, for life is eternal. The honors of men more often than not are fleeting. Anxious to run
after the honors of office or succumb to the pressures of public glamour and worldly acclaim,
some of us are no longer willing to stand up for all the principles of the
gospel. We seek to justify our unrighteousness by claiming that if only we can get title or
position, then think of the good we can do. Hence we lose our salvation en route to those
honors. We sometimes look among our numbers to find one to whom we can point who
agrees with us, so we can have company to justify our apostasy. We rationalize by saying that
some day the church doctrine will catch up with our way of thinking.
</p><p>
Seeking the applause of the world, we like to be honored by the men the world honors. But
therein lies real danger, for ofttimes, in order to receive those honors, we must join forces
with and follow those same devilish influences and policies which brought some of those men
to positions of prominence.
</p><p>
More and more the honors of this world are being promoted by the wicked for the wicked.
We see this in publicity and awards that are given to movies, literature, art, journalism, etc.
We see in our own newspapers widely read columnists carried who advocate one world
socialism who have been consistently caught in falsehoods, and who continually parrot the
communist line. Less and less we see the virtuous rewarded by the world, and when they are,
ofttimes it almost seems to be done insidiously in order to get us to swallow the many evils
for which the wicked are even more profusely honored.
</p><p>
Yes, President Joseph F. Smith was right. Today we are being plagued within by the flattery
of prominent men in the world.
</p><p>
<b>False Educational Ideas</b>
</p><p>
Second, <i>false educational ideas:</i>
</p><p>
During the past several years many of our institutions of learning have been turning out an
increasing number of students schooled in amorality, relativity, and atheism&mdash;students
divested of a belief in God, without fixed moral principles or an understanding of our
constitutional republic and our capitalistic, free enterprise economic system. This follows a
pattern which was established years ago at some of our key colleges that produced many of
the teachers and leaders in the educational field across the country today.
</p><p>
The fruits of this kind of teaching have been tragic, not only to the souls of the individuals
involved but also to the parents and even to our country. We saw these tragic fruits with some
of our boys in Korea.
</p><p>
When a survey was recently made among students asking which they would prefer, nuclear
war or surrender to the communists, those campuses scored highest for surrender who had
been most permeated by these cowardly teachings of false economic principles, atheism, and
amorality. On one very liberal college campus over 90 percent favored surrender. Other
surveys on moral standards are equally alarming. More disturbing is the fact that the more
college courses the students take on these campuses, the worse their thinking seems to
become. Freshmen who have just left home or work do not seem as fully permeated with the
brainwashing as the seniors.
</p><p>
Some alumni of various schools have expressed concern. One alumnus from Yale wrote a
book a few years ago entitled <i>God and Man at Yale</i>. Another group (which includes Teddy
Roosevelt's hero son Archibald) from Harvard University established the Veritas Foundation
and wrote a book, <i>Keynes at Harvard</i>, explaining the degree to which the destructive Fabian
economic philosophy has permeated educational institutions and government. Concerned
educators have begun to write books. Professor E. Merrill Root authored <i>Collectivism on the Campus</i>
and <i>Brainwashing in the High Schools</i>. Dr. Max Rafferty, now state superintendent
of schools in California, wrote <i>Suffer Little Children</i> and <i>What They Are Doing to Your Children.</i>
</p><p>
In the school history textbooks of recent years, some of the greatest phrases in American
history have been dropped. <i>This Week Magazine</i> recently surveyed history books issued
before 1920 and since 1920. Patrick Henry's famous words, "Give me liberty or give me
death," appeared in twelve out of the fourteen earlier texts, but in only two out of the
forty-five recent texts. Perhaps this might help explain the percentage of students who are
willing to surrender to communism.
</p><p>
The whole process can be quite insidious. Young people know that the best
jobs are available to college graduates. They want to do well at school. When exam time
comes, they must give back to the teacher what the teacher wants. Now under the guise of
academic freedom&mdash;which some apparently feel is freedom to destroy freedom&mdash;some
teachers reserve to themselves the privilege of teaching error, destroying faith in God,
debunking morality, and depreciating our free economic system. If questions reflecting the
teacher's false teachings appear on the exam, how will the student answer who believes in
God and morality and our Constitution? One student put on his exam paper what he knew the
professor wanted to see, but then the student added a little p.s. which said, "Dear Professor So
and So: I just want you to know I don't believe one word of what I just wrote above."
</p><p>
These kinds of professors are not concerned about the truth or even giving both sides of a
question that only has one right answer. They weight the scales on the side of falsehood. If
they can see there is another side, it usually gets but passing and belittling reference. To give
the impression that they are objective, these professors often invite someone to present a
different point of view in one lecture, while the professor spends the whole semester pointing
out the other side.
</p><p>
Now truth, if given as much time and emphasis as error, will invariably prove itself. And if
our young students could have as much time studying the truth as they and some of their
professors have had time studying error, then there would be no question of the outcome. The
problem arises when under the pressure of a heavy course of study and the necessity of
parroting back what certain professors have said, the student does not have the time or take
the time to learn the truth. If he does not learn the truth, some day he will suffer the
consequences. Many an honest student, after graduation, has had to do some unlearning and
then fresh learning of basic principles which never change and which he should have been
taught initially.
</p><p>
Now these false educational ideas are prevalent in the world, and we have not entirely
escaped them among teachers in our own system. There are a few teachers within the Church
who while courting apostasy still want to remain members in the Church, for being members
makes them more effective in misleading the Saints. But their day of judgment is coming, and
when it does come, for some of them it would have been better, as the Savior said, that a
millstone had been put around their necks and they had drowned in the depths of the sea
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/6#6">Matt. 18:6</a>), than
to have led away any of the youth of the Church.
</p><p>
The Lord has stated that his Church will never again be taken from the earth because of
apostasy. But he has also stated that some members of his Church will fall away. There has
been individual apostasy in the past, it is going on now, and there will be an even increasing
amount in the future. While we cannot save all the flock from being deceived, we should,
without compromising our doctrine, strive to save as many as we can. For as President Clark
said, "We are in the midst of the greatest exhibition of propaganda that the world has ever
seen."
</p><p>
Parents, stay close to your children; you cannot delegate your responsibility to the educators
no matter how competent they may be. Parents have a duty to train their children, to talk over
their problems with them, to discuss what they are learning at school. And it is neither wise
nor safe, as President Stephen L Richards stated, to leave the determination of our
educational system and policies exclusively to the professional educators.
</p><p>
Students, study the writings of the prophets. Fortunately, the consistent position taken over the
years by the prophets of the Church on vital issues facing this nation have recently been
compiled in an excellent book entitled <i>Prophets, Principles and National Survival</i> [by Jerreld
L. Newquist].
</p><p>
Students, pray for inspiration and knowledge. Counsel with your parents. Let Sunday be the
day to fill up your spiritual batteries for the week by reading good church books, particularly
the Book of Mormon. Take time to meditate. Don't let the philosophies and falsehoods of
men throw you. Hold on to the iron rod. Learn to sift. Learn to discern error through the
promptings of the Spirit and your study of the truth.
</p><p>
Yes, false educational ideas are a serious threat today.
</p><p>
<b>Immorality</b>
</p><p>
Third, <i>sexual immorality:</i>
</p><p>
Sexual immorality is a viper that is striking not only in the world, but in the Church today.
Not to admit it is to be dangerously complacent or is like putting one's head in the sand. In
the category of crimes, only murder and denying the Holy Ghost come ahead of illicit sexual
relations (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/39/5#5">Alma 39:5</a>),
which we call fornication when it involves an unmarried person, or the graver sin of
adultery when it involves one who is married. I know the laws of the land do not consider
unchastity as serious as God does, nor punish as severely as God does, but that does not
change its abominableness. In the eyes of God there is but one moral standard for men and
women. In the eyes of God chastity will never be out of date.
</p><p>
The natural desire for men and women to be together is from God. But such association is
bounded by his laws. Those things properly reserved for marriage, when taken within the
bonds of marriage, are right and pleasing before God and fulfil the commandment to multiply
and replenish the earth (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/1/28#28">Gen. 1:28</a>).
But those same things when taken outside the bonds of marriage are a
curse.
</p><p>
No sin is causing the loss of the Spirit of the Lord among our people more today than sexual
promiscuity. It is causing our people to stumble, damning their growth, darkening their
spiritual powers, and making them subject to other sins.
</p><p>
Recently, a young man commented that if he quit reading books, watching TV, seeing
movies, reading newspapers and magazines, and going to school, there was a chance he might
live a clean life. And this explains, in large part, the extent to which this insidious evil has
spread, for the world treats this sin flippantly. These evil forces build up your lust and then
fail to tell of the tragic consequences. In so many movies the hero is permitted to get away
with crime so long as he can joke about it, or explain he was powerless to do anything, or
else at the close of the movie show forth one minimal virtue that is supposed to cover over
the grossest of sin. Many of our prominent national magazines pander to the baser side, but
then try to cover for themselves by including other articles, too.
</p><p>
So garbled in values have our morals become that some youth would not dare touch a
cigarette but freely engage in petting. Both are wrong, but one is infinitely more serious than
the other.
</p><p>
Parents should give their children specific instructions on chastity at an early age, both for
their physical and moral protection. Years ago President David O. McKay, God bless him,
read a statement written by Mrs. Wesley to her famous son John. I commend it to you as a
basis for judgment pertaining to the matter of chastity. "Would you judge of the lawfulness or
unlawfulness of pleasure? Take this rule: Now note, whatever weakens your reason, impairs
the tenderness of your conscience, obscures your sense of God, takes off your relish for
spiritual things, whatever increases the authority of the body over the mind, that thing is sin
to you, however innocent it may seem in itself."
</p><p>
<b>Avoid Pitfalls of Immorality</b>
</p><p>
May I suggest some steps to avoid the pitfalls of immorality:
</p><p>
(1) Avoid late hours and weariness. The Lord said retire to your bed early
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/124#124">D&amp;C 88:124</a>), and
there are good reasons for that. Some of the worst sins are committed after midnight by tired
heads. Officers in the wards and stakes, branches and missions should not keep our people,
especially our youth, up late at night even for wholesome recreation.
</p><p>
(2) Keep your dress modest. Short skirts are not pleasing to the Lord, but modesty is. Girls,
do not be an enticement for your downfall because of your immodest and tight-fitting clothes.
</p><p>
(3) Have good associates or don't associate at all. Be careful in the selection of your friends.
If in the presence of certain persons you are lifted to nobler heights, you are in good
company. But if your friends or associates encourage base thoughts, then you had best leave
them.
</p><p>
(4) Avoid necking and petting like a plague, for necking and petting is the concession which
precedes the complete loss of virtue.
</p><p>
(5) Have a good physical outlet of some sport or exercise. Overcome evil with good. You can
overcome many evil inclinations through good physical exertion and healthful activities. A
healthy soul, free of the body-and-spirit-dulling influences of alcohol and tobacco, is in better
condition to overthrow the devil.
</p><p>
(6) Think clean thoughts. Those who think clean thoughts do not do dirty deeds. You are not
only responsible before God for your acts but also for controlling your thoughts. So live that
you would not blush with shame if your thoughts and acts could be flashed on a screen in
your church. The old adage is still true that you sow thoughts and you reap acts, you sow acts
and you reap habits, you sow habits and you reap a character, and your character determines
your eternal destiny. "As a man thinketh, so is he"
(see <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/23/7#7">Prov. 23:7</a>).
</p><p>
(7) Pray. There is no temptation placed before you which you cannot shun. Do not allow
yourself to get in positions where it is easy to fall. Listen to the promptings of the Spirit. If
you are engaged in things where you do not feel you can pray and ask the Lord's blessings on
what you are doing, then you are engaged in the wrong kind of activity.
</p><p>
Yes&mdash;avoid late hours; dress modestly; seek good associates; avoid necking and petting; have
a good physical outlet; think good thoughts; pray.
</p><p>
May the Lord bless us as a people. We have taken upon us sacred covenants. We must be
faithful. We are in the world, it is true, but we must not partake of the evils of the world. Let
us be ever on guard against the flattery of prominent men in the world, false educational
ideas, and sexual impurity, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
