<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Our Need for Better Parents</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Mark E. Petersen</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Mark E. Petersen, <i>Conference Report</i>, April 1961, pp. 134-136</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
I wish to talk with you today about our youth, our homes,
and our future.
</p><p>
May I first remind you that students of youthful trends and
activities emphasize the fact that our juvenile problem is
now more than ever an adult problem, and that the only way
to solve it is to provide our youth with better parents.
There can be no doubt that children learn most of their
moral behavior within the family and that behavior patterns
are fixed at an early age. To change them later in life is
such a slow and difficult task that many consider it almost
impossible. Hence, the only way to build good adults for the
future is to provide children with better parents now.
</p><p>
In a recent address Mr. J. Edgar Hoover, the head of the
F.B.I., expressed this thought: "Given discipline, young
people will learn self-discipline; given training, they will
learn to live useful lives. In almost every case, the
failure to develop character is directly attributable to a
lack of proper influence and guidance in the home."
</p><p>
Surveys and studies made in various parts of the United
States indicate that 80 per cent of our delinquent children
say that they had no real family life, and that their
parents were too busy with other things to give them any
guidance. Nearly all of these delinquents said that there
was no religion in their homes, and that their parents set
them a bad example.
</p><p>
<b>Lack of Religion</b>
</p><p>
Lack of religion is characteristic of delinquent families.
It is interesting to note that a police report from one
large American city showed that 84 per cent of the juvenile
criminals in that city did not attend any church. A juvenile
court judge in Michigan reports that last year, 91 per cent
of the youngsters appearing in his court had no religious
training.
</p><p>
Lack of faith among children generally reflects the
attitude of their parents.
If the parents have no religion, they can hardly teach it to
their children. And yet, religion is our best deterrent to
juvenile crime.
</p><p>
Mr. Hoover analyzes the problem in this way: "The basic
cause of the present (juvenile delinquency) situation is
that so many of our young people have no real sense of moral
responsibility which comes from an intimate knowledge of
God's teachings. The tragic void of God and Prayer in their
lives weakens our homes and our Nation's welfare."
</p><p>
America seems to have forgotten that true religion is the
very source of its freedom and strength, because nearly half
the parents of this land appear to withhold religion from
their children.
</p><p>
Does it shock you to learn that almost 50 per cent of our
population belongs to no church at all?
</p><p>
Do you know the price which the irreligious have to pay for
their rejection of God?
</p><p>
<b>Antidote to Communism</b>
</p><p>
It is a well-known fact that Communism is rooted in the
irreligious. It is anti-religion and anti-Christ. Do we want
Communism in America? When nearly half of our population is
irreligious are you not frightened by the fact that
Communism is based upon a rejection of religion? Living the
Gospel of Christ is our strongest antidote to Communism.
</p><p>
Crime, which is increasing at an alarming rate in America,
also is rooted in the irreligious. It too is anti-Christ,
violates the Golden Rule which deals with our treatment of
our fellowman, and which Christ taught during his earthly
ministry (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/7/12#12">Matt. 7:12</a>).
</p><p>
Crime is selfish, brutal, and deceitful. Do we want
criminals and gangsters to run our country? Is it within the
range of possibility since so many of our people have
practically banished all forms of religion from their lives,
setting aside the very basis of character-building, honesty,
and integrity?
</p><p>
Mr. Hoover has said that either faith in God must triumph in
the United States, or we will be dominated by criminals and
Communists.
</p><p>
Is being irreligious worth the price we must pay for it? Are
ease, pleasure, and irresponsibility worth the price we must
pay for an abandonment of good character?
</p><p>
Is there any real joy in wickedness, weakness, or
carelessness? Is ignoring God the way to enduring happiness?
</p><p>
America may well remember that it is in Godless countries
where people are slaves. It is in Godless countries where
dictators reign, and where iron curtains shut out all
freedom and opportunity for the average individual. In such
countries worship of God is punished in many subtle ways
because dictators know from past history that there is
power and strength in religion, while it is their plan to
keep their people weak and subdued.
</p><p>
In homes where parents are irreligious, the children grow up
without God, without faith, or prayer, or the spiritual
strength which builds good character.
</p><p>
<b>Parents As Examples</b>
</p><p>
In our love of pleasure and money-making, we too often
neglect to set our children examples in good living, in
dealing fairly and honestly with their fellows, in telling
the truth, in doing unto others as they would be done by, in
learning to respect law and order, in reading good books and
seeing to it that their homes contain many of them; in
looking on honest work as a duty and a privilege.
</p><p>
Many children now-a-days know but little about work, except
that it is for the other fellow, and yet it is one of the
first laws God ever gave to man.
</p><p>
Not one among us, if we gave it any thought, would purposely
and with design nurture in the hearts of our children the
seeds of failure and crime. Yet these seeds grow in a lack
of faith in God, a rejection of church activity, a neglect
of the simple habits which make parents and children a
family, and which make a house a home.
</p><p>
We must learn to become better parents. We must build
better homes. We can do this by showing our children the
attention they deserve. We can provide them with the
companionship they
need, and set before them good examples in our own lives.
</p><p>
We can do many things together as a family. We can plan
family recreation, and family work and responsibility from
earliest childhood. Each child should have his own definite
duties assigned to him, whether it be to help mother with
the housework, or wash the car, or lend a hand with the yard
work. Regularity of work responsibilities is vital to the
development of children.
</p><p>
Truth and honesty should be held before them constantly.
There can be no success without integrity. We rob our loved
ones of their opportunities if we fail to prepare them for
the advancement which can be made only upon the principles
of good character.
</p><p>
Above all we can teach our children the Gospel of the Lord
Jesus Christ. It is the foundation of good character. It is
the way to success.
</p><p>
<b>Live the Gospel</b>
</p><p>
We can study the Gospel ourselves and live it. We can
worship God in our homes. We can become active in our church
and teach our children to do likewise.
</p><p>
Do you think that the children will resent it? Statistics
show that 85 per cent of the young people of America hope
their parents will give them leadership in religious and
character-building matters. Delinquent children admit that
there was no such training in their homes.
</p><p>
Then as parents, let us acknowledge that lack of leadership
on our part in giving our children spiritual and
character-building instruction may result in serious
difficulty for them.
</p><p>
Let us be willing to face the fact that we really are the
custodians and the guardians of our little ones, and that
if we neglect that guardianship we do them irreparable harm.
</p><p>
We must not surrender our guardianship. Both the law of the
land and the law of God make us the heads of our homes. Let
us take the leadership there, assert our position and lead
our children in love and kindness, but with firm and
intelligent discipline, into the paths of right.
</p><p>
For the love of our children, for the sake of their future
development, for their happiness and well being, let us
restore family life and the true worship of God to our
homes. Let us keep faith with our families. Their destiny is
in our hands.
</div>
</div>
