<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Talents: A Blessing and Responsibility</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Franklin D. Richards</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve</p>
<p class="gcbib">Franklin D. Richards, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 111-114</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
President McKay, my beloved brothers and sisters: I stand before you with a humble heart
and seek divine guidance in the things I say.
</p><p>
<b>A divine spark</b>
</p><p>
It is not unusual to hear a religious leader, a philosopher, or a poet refer to man as having a
divine spark within him. Such characterizations infer that man possesses great abilities and
potentials. We are frequently admonished to develop our capabilities, reach out, and set high
goals for ourselves.
</p><p>
What does it mean to have a divine spark within you? Presumably that man has a certain
relationship with God.
</p><p>
From time to time throughout the history of the world God has made known to man what this
relationship is.
</p><p>
The scriptures teach that God is a personal being in whose image man was created, and that
God the Father is the literal Father of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ and the Father of the
spirits of all men. Because of this, we inherit divine attributes. This was beautifully stated
when Job of old explained that "there is a spirit in man: and the inspiration of the Almighty
giveth them understanding" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/32/8#8">Job 32:8</a>).
</p><p>
This simple doctrine as taught by Christ gave way to the theories and dogmas of men through
the hundreds of years of apostasy.
</p><p>
<b>The gospel restored</b>
</p><p>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints proclaims to the world that the gospel of
Jesus Christ in its fullness and simplicity has been restored through the instrumentality of the
Prophet Joseph Smith.
</p><p>
We assert that God the Father and his Son Jesus Christ appeared to the Prophet Joseph Smith,
and that Christ's Church has been reestablished on the earth.
</p><p>
Thus, through modern revelation, God's relationship to man has again been clarified. I ask
you to seriously consider the fact that the life of your earthly body is your spirit and that God
the Eternal Father is the Father of your spirit.
</p><p>
<b>The light of Christ</b>
</p><p>
The apostle John testified that Jesus "was the true Light, which lighteth every man that
cometh into the world" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/9#9">John 1:9</a>).
</p><p>
And in this dispensation President Joseph F. Smith bore witness to this same truth, that the
light of Christ, the Spirit of Truth, lighteth every man who is born into the world. (Joseph F.
Smith, <i>Gospel Doctrine</i>, p. 61.)
</p><p>
What a tremendous effect this has in the lives of those who accept this doctrine. Our Father in
heaven loves each and every one of us and is interested in our welfare and growth and
development. In fact, it is his work and glory "to bring to pass the immortality and eternal life
of man" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/39#39">Moses 1:39</a>).
</p><p>
Again, let me say we know that not only do we have a spark of divinity within us, but that
we are actually spirit children of our Heavenly Father and that "every man is given a gift by
the Spirit of God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/11#11">D&amp;C 46:11</a>).
</p><p>
With this relationship, we are thus blessed with many talents and possess great possibilities.
The Savior set our greatest goal for us when he said, "Be ye therefore perfect, even as your
Father which is in heaven is perfect" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>).
</p><p>
To become perfect requires growth and development, and as we contemplate perfection we
recognize that growth is the greatest phenomenon of this existence.
</p><p>
This Church teaches the value and necessity of eternal progression. We progressed in the
preexistence, and it is our responsibility and opportunity to progress in this estate and
throughout all eternity.
</p><p>
<b>Parables on developing talents</b>
</p><p>
During his earthly ministry the Savior gave two parables dealing with the requirement that we
develop the talents with which we are endowed. These parables are the parable of the
entrusted talents (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/14-30#14">Matt. 25:14-30</a>) and the parable of the pounds.
</p><p>
The talent was an ancient weight and money unit. The dictionary defines talent as "the
abilities, powers and gifts bestowed upon a man; natural endowments; thought of as a divine
trust. A natural capacity or gift."
</p><p>
The parable of the entrusted talents was given to his apostles, and in it the Savior told of a
man who was about to leave on a long trip and who therefore called his servants together and
gave them his goods. To one he gave five talents, to another two, and to another one. To each
man he gave according to his ability.
</p><p>
While the master was away, the one that received five talents put them to use and made five
more talents. The one that received two talents put them to use and made two more talents,
but the one that received the one talent hid it in the ground.
</p><p>
After a period the master returned and asked for an accounting.
</p><p>
Unto the servants that had doubled their talents the master said, "Well done, good and faithful
servant; thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things:
enter thou into the joy of thy lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/23#23">Matt. 25:23</a>).
</p><p>
The master called the servant that hid his talent and did not multiply it a slothful servant and
said that he would take the one talent from him and give it to the servant that had ten talents.
</p><p>
Whereas the parable of the entrusted talents was given to his apostles, the parable of the
pounds (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/19/11-27#11">Luke 19:11-27</a>) was given to a mixed multitude on the Savior's last journey from Jericho to
Jerusalem; and although there are some differences in the two parables, in essence they teach
the same truths and principles.
</p><p>
From the men endowed with many talents, more was expected than from the men with lesser
talents, yet all were expected to multiply such talents as they were given. However, in each
parable, although relatively little was expected of the men given one talent, each failed to use
his talent. Good use of the talent on the part of the men given one talent was just as important
and necessary as on the part of the men given two and five talents.
</p><p>
<b>The Lord's charge today</b>
</p><p>
In this dispensation the Lord has been equally direct in his charge to his children. He has told
us that he has given us many things "for the benefit of the church of the living God, that
every man may improve upon his talent, that every man may gain other talents, yea, even an
hundred fold." (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/18#18">D&amp;C 82:18</a>).
</p><p>
He has admonished us that "of him unto whom much is given much is required."
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/3#3">D&amp;C 82:3</a>).
</p><p>
He also says, "But with some I am not well pleased, for they will not open their mouths, but
they hide the talent which I have given unto them, because of the fear of man. Wo unto such,
for mine anger is kindled against them.
</p><p>
"And it shall come to pass, if they are not more faithful unto me, it shall be taken away, even
that which they have" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/60/2-3#2">D&amp;C 60:2-3</a>).
</p><p>
And then we are charged: "Thou shalt not idle away thy time, neither shalt thou bury thy
talent that it may not be known" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/60/13#13">D&amp;C 60:13</a>).
</p><p>
The Savior evidenced little regard for the slothful servant. He expects us to work and use our
initiative.
</p><p>
<b>Obligation to develop talents</b>
</p><p>
These scriptures clearly emphasize our obligations to use and  develop the gifts and talents we
have been blessed with&mdash;shall we say, develop the spark of divinity within us. Human
experience confirms the soundness of this doctrine.
</p><p>
All of us then should be concerned about how to best develop our gifts and talents. First, we
should recognize our talents and make up our minds to pay the price necessary to develop
them. The price to be paid in developing talents includes, among other things, faith, study,
and persistence.
</p><p>
In developing faith, we must never overlook the fact that we are spirit children of God the
Eternal Father, and that our Father in heaven will assist us in developing our talents as we do
our part.
</p><p>
<b>The fear of men</b>
</p><p>
One way in which he will assist us is to open up opportunities for us to use our talents. Some
recognize their talents, but we are told they do not use them because of the fear of men.
</p><p>
Fear destroys faith and deprives us of many blessings. This is clearly brought out in a
revelation when the Lord said, "Ye endeavored to believe that ye should receive the blessing
which was offered unto you; but behold, verily I say unto you there were fears in your hearts,
and verily this is the reason that ye did not receive" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/67/3#3">D&amp;C 67:3</a>).
</p><p>
We must, therefore, overcome fear. The Lord has told us that if we are prepared, we "shall
not fear" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/30#30">D&amp;C 38:30</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Progress involves study</b>
</p><p>
Preparation involves study, and we are also counseled to "seek learning, even by study and
also by faith" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/118#118">D&amp;C 88:118</a>).
</p><p>
Eternal progress involves continual study. Increased learning gives us confidence, and
confidence engenders faith, and faith banishes fear. I therefore encourage you to never cease
to study, this being an important part of developing your talents.
</p><p>
Likewise, persistence plays a vital part. President Heber J. Grant used to frequently quote
from Emerson: "That which we persist in doing becomes easy to do, not that the nature of the
thing has changed but that our power to do has increased." President Grant exemplified this
throughout his entire life, and his persistence no doubt played a great part in many of his
accomplishments.
</p><p>
<b>Talents developed by use</b>
</p><p>
We should appreciate that talents are developed by use and they will not grow and multiply
unless they are used. This principle was clearly taught in the Savior's parables.
</p><p>
As we develop our talents, we should develop the spirit of sharing or giving, not only with
those who are closest to us, but with all of God's children. Remember the words of King
Benjamin: ". . . when ye are in the service of your fellow beings ye are only in the service of
your God" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/17#17">Mosiah 2:17</a>).
</p><p>
The Lord wants us to enjoy our talents, but he also expects us to use them for the enjoyment
and benefit of others and to build the kingdom of God.
</p><p>
<b>The need for challenges</b>
</p><p>
Today we hear much about the need of challenges for the youth as well as for our senior
citizens. Despite the fact that we are living in a troublesome period, we are living in the
dispensation of the fullness of times, a most wonderful period in the history of the world.
Yes, in a new era of growth and development. Opportunities today, for young and old, exceed
those of any other age.
</p><p>
We should be grateful to live at this particular time, when the spirit of the Lord is being
poured out upon the people of the earth so abundantly.
</p><p>
One of the important and distinguishing features of The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day
Saints is that its affairs are administered by the lay members of the Church rather than by
paid clergy.
</p><p>
I have been told by some of my non-member friends that the thing that has impressed them
most about the Church is that it gives every person a chance to serve, regardless of his age.
How true this is.
</p><p>
<b>A vehicle for growth</b>
</p><p>
The Church in reality is a vehicle for the growth and development of God's children. The
priesthood quorums, Primary, Mutuals, Sunday School, Relief Society, and other Church
organizations, in their various activities and programs, all contribute to the development of
their members' talents and provide opportunities for them to be shared with others.
</p><p>
Thus, as stated, exciting and challenging leadership opportunities are afforded men, women,
and children of all ages to become involved in interesting and worthwhile projects. This is not
only a great opportunity but likewise a responsibility for Church members, because the future
growth of the Church is dependent upon the development of leaders&mdash;leaders for the general
Church administration as well as missions, stakes, wards, priesthood quorums, auxiliaries, and
other Church organizations and activities.
</p><p>
<b>Talents developed in many areas</b>
</p><p>
Talents may be developed in many areas of teaching, speaking, missionary work, music,
drama, dancing, athletics of many kinds, Scout work, genealogical and temple work, welfare
programs, compassionate service, and many other fields that might be mentioned; all
contribute to the development of talents and leadership.
</p><p>
Sometimes we may think that we have too many opportunities to serve and develop our
talents, and feel it requires too much of a sacrifice. Let me suggest, however, that we not
consider it as a sacrifice but as a great blessing.
</p><p>
Never forget the Savior's great challenge to each of us to become perfect, even as our Father
which is in heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48#48">Matt. 5:48</a>).
</p><p>
Each activity that we participate in provides experiences wherein we may improve our talents,
thus contributing to our goal of perfection.
</p><p>
As we develop the spirit of giving and sharing, we find great peace, happiness, joy, and
contentment, as well as growth and development.
</p><p>
<b>Accept every opportunity</b>
</p><p>
May I encourage you, therefore, to accept every opportunity presented to you to serve with
enthusiasm, not as a burden but as a great blessing. Organize your time by putting first things
first, and perform each assignment well. By so doing, the divine spark within you will be
magnified and your talents will be increased, "yea, even an hundred fold" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/18#18">D&amp;C 82:18</a>).
</p><p>
As you follow this admonition I can hear, "Well done, god and faithful servant; thou hast
been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over many things: enter thou into the
joy of thy lord" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/25/21#21">Matt. 25:21</a>).
</p><p>
I bear you my testimony that God lives and that Jesus is the Christ; that the gospel of Jesus
Christ in its fullness has been restored in this latter day through the Prophet Joseph Smith,
and that there is a prophet of God with us today, our beloved President David O. McKay.
May the Lord bless and sustain him. I bear this witness in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
