<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Proper Role of Government</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Ezra Taft Benson</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">Ezra Taft Benson, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1968, pp. 17-22</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My brethren and sisters: Humbly and gratefully I stand before you.
</p><p>
I am truly thankful that the Church is led by a prophet of God, who, as chief watchman on
the towers of Zion, has the courage and inspiration to speak out against current evils as he has
done again today. Thank God for David O. McKay, our Prophet-leader!
</p><p>
<b>Gratitude for Founding Fathers</b>
</p><p>
I am humbly grateful to God for the blessings we all enjoy as citizens of these great United
States of America. I am grateful for our Founding Fathers who were raised up with the
courage to give their lives, with the unselfishness to give their fortunes and the vision to
pledge their sacred honor in order to establish a new kind of government of their own
choosing where men might be free. I am additionally grateful that these Founding Fathers had
the faith and humility to accept the divine inspiration so necessary in setting forth the
Constitution as the foundation for their new republic. The Lord said he raised up these
founders and called them "wise men" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/80#80">D&amp;C 101:80</a>).
</p><p>
<b>Political opportunists</b>
</p><p>
Men are often asked to express an opinion on a myriad of government proposals and projects.
All too often, answers seem to be based not upon solid principle, but upon the popularity of
the specific government program in question. Seldom are men willing to oppose a popular
program if they themselves wish to be popular&mdash;especially if they seek public office.
</p><p>
Such an approach to vital political questions of the day can only lead to public confusion and
legislative chaos. Decisions of this nature should be based upon and measured against certain
basic principles regarding the proper role of government. If principles are correct, then they
can be applied to any specific proposal with confidence.
</p><p>
Unlike the political opportunist, the true statesman values principle above popularity and
works to create popularity for those political principles which are wise and just.
</p><p>
<b>Origin of human rights</b>
</p><p>
It is generally agreed that the most important single function of government is to secure the
rights and freedoms of individual citizens. But, what are those rights? And what is their
source? Until these questions are answered, there is little likelihood that we can correctly
determine how government can best secure them.
</p><p>
Let us first consider the origin of those freedoms we have come to know as human rights.
Rights are either God-given as part of the divine plan or they are granted by government as
part of the political plan. Reason, necessity, tradition, and religious convictions all lead me to
accept the divine origin of these rights. If we accept the premise that human rights are granted
by government, then we must be willing to accept the corollary that they can be denied by
government.
</p><p>
I support the doctrine of separation of church and state as traditionally interpreted to prohibit
the establishment of an official national religion. But this does not mean that we should
divorce government from any formal recognition of God. To do so strikes a potentially fatal
blow at the concept of the divine origin of our rights and unlocks the door for an easy entry
of future tyranny. If Americans should ever come to believe that their rights and freedoms are
instituted among men by politicians and bureaucrats, then they will no longer carry the proud
inheritance of their forefathers, but will grovel before their masters seeking favors and
dispensations, a throwback to the feudal system of the Dark Ages.
</p><p>
<b>Man superior to government</b>
</p><p>
Since God created man with certain inalienable rights, and man, in turn, created government
to help secure and safeguard those rights, it follows that man is superior to the creature which
he created. Man is superior to government and should remain master over it, not the other
way around. Even the nonbeliever can appreciate the logic of this relationship.
</p><p>
A government is nothing more or less than a relatively small group of citizens who have been
hired, in a sense, by the rest of us to perform certain functions and discharge certain
responsibilities which have been authorized. The government itself has no innate power or
privilege to do anything. Its only source of authority and power is from the people who
created it.
</p><p>
<b>Delegation of powers</b>
</p><p>
Keep in mind that the people who have created their government can give to that government
only such powers as they themselves have. They cannot give that which they do not possess.
</p><p>
In a primitive state, there is no doubt that each man would be justified in using force, if
necessary, to defend himself against physical harm, against theft of the fruits of his labor, and
against enslavement by another.
</p><p>
Indeed, the early pioneers found that a great deal of their time and energy was being spent
defending themselves, their property, and their liberty. For man to prosper, he cannot afford
to spend his time constantly guarding his family, his fields, and his property against attack
and theft. When he joins together with his neighbors and hires a sheriff, government is born.
The individual citizens delegate to the sheriff their unquestionable right to protect themselves.
The sheriff now does for them only that which they had a right to do for themselves&mdash;nothing more.
</p><p>
But suppose pioneer "A" wants another horse for his wagon. He doesn't have the money to
buy one, but since pioneer "B" has an extra horse, he decides that he is entitled to share in his
neighbor's good fortune. Is he entitled to take his neighbor's horse? Obviously not! If his
neighbor wishes to give it or lend it, that is another question. But so long as pioneer "B"
wishes to keep his property, pioneer "A" has no just claim to it.
</p><p>
If "A" has no proper power to take "B's" property, can he delegate any such power to the
sheriff? No. Even if everyone in the community desires that "B" give his extra horse to "A,"
they have no right individually or collectively to force him to do it. They cannot delegate a
power they themselves do not have.
</p><p>
<b>Function of government</b>
</p><p>
The proper function of government is limited only to those spheres of activity within which
the individual citizen has the right to act. By deriving its just powers from the governed,
government becomes primarily a mechanism for defense against bodily harm, theft, and
involuntary servitude. It cannot claim the power to redistribute the wealth or force reluctant
citizens to perform acts of charity against their will. Government is created by man. No man
can delegate a power that he does not possess. The creature cannot exceed the creator.
</p><p>
In general terms, therefore, the proper role of government includes such defensive activities as
maintaining national military and local police forces for protection against loss of life, loss of
property, and loss of liberty at the hands of either foreign despots or domestic criminals.
</p><p>
It also includes those powers necessarily incidental to the protective function.
</p><p>
We should recognize that government is no plaything. It is an instrument of force; and unless
our conscience is clear that we would not hesitate to put a man to death, put him in jail, or
forcibly deprive him of his property for failing to obey a given law, we should oppose that
law.
</p><p>
<b>Constitution an inspired document</b>
</p><p>
The Constitution of the United States, an inspired document, is a solemn agreement between
the citizens of this nation that every officer of government is under a sacred duty to obey.
</p><p>
The Constitution provides that the great bulk of the legitimate activities of government are to
be carried out at the state or local level. This is the only way in which the principle of
self-government can be made effective.
</p><p>
The smallest or lowest level that can possibly undertake the task is the one that should do so.
The smaller the governmental unit and the closer it is to the people, the easier it is to guide it,
to correct it, to keep it solvent, and to keep our freedom.
</p><p>
Remember that the people of the states of this republic created the federal government. The
federal government did not create the states.
</p><p>
<b>Self-proclaimed powers</b>
</p><p>
A category of government activity that not only requires the closest scrutiny but that also
poses a grave danger to our continued freedom is the activity <i>not</i> within the proper sphere of
government. No one has the authority to grant such powers as welfare programs, schemes for
redistributing the wealth, and activities that coerce people into acting in accordance with a
prescribed code of social planning. There is one simple test. Do I as an individual have a right
to use force upon my neighbor to accomplish this goal? If I do, then I may delegate that
power to my government to exercise it in my behalf. If I do not have that right, I cannot
delegate it.
</p><p>
If we permit government to manufacture its own authority and to create self-proclaimed
powers not delegated to it by the people, then the creature exceeds the creator and becomes
master. Who is to say "this far, but no farther"? What clear principle will stay the hand of
government from reaching farther and farther into our daily lives? Grover Cleveland said that
"though the people support the Government, the Government should not support the people.
</p><p>
<b>Legalized plunder</b>
</p><p>
Once government steps over this clear line between the protective or negative role into the
aggressive role of redistributing the wealth through taxation and providing so-called "benefits"
for some of its citizens, it becomes a means for legalized plunder. It becomes a lever of
unlimited power that is the sought-after prize of unscrupulous individuals and pressure groups,
each seeking to control the machine to fatten his own pockets or to benefit his favorite
charity, all with the other fellow's money, of course. Each class or special interest group
competes with the others to throw the lever of governmental power in its favor, or at least to
immunize itself against the effects of a previous thrust. Labor gets a minimum wage.
Agriculture gets a price support. Some consumers demand price controls. In the end, no one is
much further ahead, and everyone suffers the burdens of a gigantic bureaucracy and a loss of
personal freedom. With each group out to get its share of the spoils, such governments
historically have mushroomed into total welfare states. Once the process begins, once the
principle of the protective function of government gives way to the aggressive or
redistributive function, then forces are set in motion that drive the nation toward
totalitarianism.
</p><p>
<b>Workers create wealth</b>
</p><p>
No government in the history of mankind has ever created any wealth. People who work
create wealth.
</p><p>
The free creative energy of this choice nation "created more than 50 percent of all the world's
products and possessions in the short span of 160 years. The only imperfection in the system
is the imperfection in man himself." (James R. Evans, <i>The Glorious Quest</i> [Chicago: Charles
Hallberg and Company].)
</p><p>
<b>Marxist doctrine</b>
</p><p>
According to Marxist doctrine, a human being is primarily an economic creature. His material
well-being is all important; his privacy and his freedom are secondary. The Soviet constitution
reflects this philosophy in its emphasis on security: food, clothing, housing, medical
care&mdash;the same things that might be considered in a jail. The basic concept is that the government
has full responsibility for the welfare of the people and, in order to discharge that
responsibility, must assume control of all their activities. It is significant that in actuality the
Russian people have few of the rights supposedly "guaranteed" to them in their constitution,
while the American people have them in abundance even though they are not guaranteed. The
reason is that material gain and economic prosperity and security simply cannot be guaranteed
by any government. They are the result and reward of hard work and industrious production.
Unless the people bake one loaf of bread for each citizen, the government cannot guarantee
that each will have one loaf to eat. Constitutions can be written, laws can be passed, and
imperial decrees can be issued, but unless the bread is produced, it can never be distributed.
</p><p>
<b>Destruction of productive base</b>
</p><p>
Why, then, do Americans bake more bread, manufacture more shoes, and assemble more TV
sets than Russians do? They do so precisely because our government does not guarantee these
things. If it did, there would be so many accompanying taxes, controls, regulations, and
political manipulations that the productive genius that is America's would soon be reduced to
the floundering level of waste and inefficiency now found behind the Iron Curtain.
</p><p>
Any attempt through governmental intervention to redistribute the material rewards of labor
can only result in the eventual destruction of the productive base of society, without which
real abundance and security for more than the ruling elite is quite impossible.
</p><p>
What happens to a nation that ignores these basic principles? Former FBI agent Dan Smoot
succinctly points this out: 
</p><p>
"England was killed by an idea; the idea that the weak, indolent, and profligate must be
supported by the strong, industrious, and frugal&mdash;to the degree that tax consumers will have
a living standard comparable to that of taxpayers; the idea that government exists for the
purpose of plundering those who work to give the product of their labor to those who do not
work.
</p><p>
"The economic and social cannibalism produced by this communist-socialist idea will destroy
any society which adopts it and clings to it as a basic principle&mdash;any society."
</p><p>
<b>Individual freedom ignored</b>
</p><p>
This may sound heartless and insensitive to the needs of those less fortunate individuals who
are found in any society, no matter how affluent. "What about the lame, the sick and the
destitute?" is an often-voiced question. Most other countries have attempted to use the power
of government to meet this need. Yet, in every case, the improvement has been marginal at
best and has, in the long run, created more misery, more poverty, and certainly less freedom
than when government first stepped in.
</p><p>
As Henry Grady Weaver wrote: 
</p><p>
"Most of the major ills of the world have been caused by well-meaning people who ignored
the principle of individual freedom, except as applied to themselves, and who were obsessed
with fanatical zeal to improve the lot of mankind-in-the-mass through some pet formula of
their own . . . The harm done by ordinary criminals, murderers, gangsters, and thieves is
negligible in comparison with the agony inflicted upon human beings by the professional
'do-gooders,' who attempt to set themselves up as gods on earth and who would ruthlessly
force their views on all others&mdash;with the abiding assurance that the end justifies the means."
(<i>The Mainspring of Human Progress</i>.)
</p><p>
<b>Reliance on individual action</b>
</p><p>
America has traditionally followed Jefferson's advice of relying on the profit motive,
individual action, and charity. The United States has fewer cases of genuine hardship per
capita than any other country in the world now or throughout all history. Even during the
depression of the 1930's, Americans ate and lived better than most people in other countries
do today.
</p><p>
History proves that the growth of the welfare state is difficult to check before it comes to its
full flower of dictatorship. But let us hope that this time around, the trend can be reversed. If
not, then we will see the inevitability of complete socialism&mdash;probably within our lifetime.
</p><p>
Three factors may make a difference: (1) sufficient historical knowledge of the failures of
socialism in contrast to the proven success of free enterprise; (2) modern means of rapid
communications to transmit this information to a large literate population; (3) a growing
number of dedicated men and women actively working to promote a wider appreciation of
these basic concepts. The timely joining together of these three factors may make it entirely
possible for us to reverse the trend.
</p><p>
<b>Cut welfare-state features</b>
</p><p>
How is it possible to cut out the various welfare-state features of our government that have
already fastened themselves like cancer cells onto the body politic? Can drastic surgery be
performed without endangering the patient? Drastic measures are called for. No compromise
actions will suffice. Like all surgery, it will not be without discomfort and perhaps even some
scar tissue for a long time to come. But it must be done if the patient is to be saved&mdash;and it
can be done without undue risk.
</p><p>
Not all welfare-state programs currently in force can be dropped simultaneously without
causing tremendous economic and social upheaval. The first step toward restoring the limited
concept of government should be to freeze all welfare-state programs at their present levels,
making sure that no new ones are added. The next step would be to allow all present
programs to run out their term with absolutely no renewal. The third step would involve the
gradual phasing-out of those programs which are indefinite in their term. The bulk of the
transition could be accomplished, I believe, within a ten-year period and virtually completed
within 20 years.
</p><p>
<b>Return to basic concepts</b>
</p><p>
We must return to basic concepts and principles, to eternal verities in this choice land. There
is no other way. The storm signals are up. They are clear and ominous.
</p><p>
We are building up a generation of lazy, government-dole-consuming weaklings. If this
Communist-planned program of deception is not stopped, it will destroy our nation.
</p><p>
As Americans&mdash;citizens of the greatest nation under heaven&mdash;we face difficult days. Never
since the days of the Civil War&mdash;100 years ago&mdash;has this choice nation faced such a crisis.
</p><p>
I have faith in the American people. I pray that we will refrain from doing anything further
that will jeopardize in any manner, our priceless heritage. This is a choice land. If we live and
work so as to enjoy the approbation of a Divine Providence, we cannot fail. Without that
help, we cannot long endure.
</p><p>
As Americans, let us put our courage to the test&mdash;to be firm in the conviction that our cause
is just, to reaffirm our faith in all things for which true Americans have always stood in years
past.
</p><p>
Let all Americans arouse themselves and stay aroused. We must stop and then reverse the
concessions we have made to socialistic Communism at home and abroad. We should oppose
these evil forces from our position of strength, for we are not weak.
</p><p>
There is much work to be done. The time is short. Let us begin in earnest&mdash;now&mdash;and may
God bless our efforts, I humbly pray in the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
