<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">The Test of Christianity</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder Levi Edgar Young</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Of the First Council of the Seventy</p>
<p class="gcbib">Levi Edgar Young, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1944, pp. 83-85</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
Sitting in this large audience are a number of men in the service of their country. They wear
the uniform of United States soldiers. It is always a fine thing to have them in our midst. On
the banks of the Potomac River in Washington at Arlington Cemetery, is the tomb of the
Unknown Soldier whose body was brought from France at the close of the First World War.
Carved on the tomb is a message of beauty. It reads: "Here lies in honored glory an American
soldier known but to God"&mdash;a message that all Americans may do well to keep in mind.
</p><p>
I wish to have the help of my Father in heaven while I speak to you this afternoon.
</p><p>
PRESENT-DAY CONDITIONS
</p><p>
The Puritan preacher, John Eliot, known as the apostle to the Indians, wrote as a preface to
his Bible after having translated it into the Narragansett language: "Work, with faith in Jesus
Christ, can accomplish all things." It was a motto peculiarly fitting to his times; it is
peculiarly fitting in our own day. It meant as Frederick Harrison has aptly written that to toil
in producing things needful for human life is to offer up ourselves to the law of creation
which ordained that life on this earth could only be sustained by the sweat of man's brow.
The terrible times through which we are passing are destined to leave war within every nation
as well as our own. It may prove harder to win peace than to win war. There will be a dearth
of food, of clothing, and saddest of all, a lack of Christian fellowship. Are the religious forces
influential enough to set an example of self-denial, of self-restraint, of discipline and a
renewed faith in the teachings of the Savior of the world, who taught that peace can only
come as people love the Lord their God, and their neighbors as themselves?
</p><p>
We have too often failed to give ourselves to the word of the Lord. We have run after wealth,
praise, and honor, and thought that Christ may be found by seeking eminence and power. This
is not so. Many of us will have to learn that it is not the outward and physical, but by the
inward and physical that men become true men. Did not the Master say: "Whosoever will
save his life shall lose it" (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/25#25">Matt. 16:25</a>).
He taught that the majesty and sanctity of living is for the
invisible: that is to say for honor, truth, fidelity, and the kingdom of righteousness.
</p><p>
There were honored names that took part in the great religious changes that came into the
world in the sixteenth century. The daring and forceful methods of John Calvin, Martin
Luther, Melanchthon, Zwingli, and John Knox, and many others left their results upon the
world. We do not doubt their integrity to what they considered the fundamental doctrines of
Jesus Christ, but sin and disaster have been growing to the present day. There are in this
country two hundred and fifty different religious creeds with a total membership of some
eighty million souls. The burning question of the hour is: Where is the simple and pure
religion of Jesus Christ as taught by the Master two thousand years ago? The Bible has
suffered at the hands of those whom it sought to help. Men have failed to read its teachings
through to the end with an intelligent thoroughness. They have made selections according to
their human knowledge "and have missed its spirit and the trend of its instruction, and the
glorious uplift of its truths."
</p><p>
CHRISTIAN BELIEF OF THE FUTURE
</p><p>
What will be the characteristics of a religion of Jesus Christ as humanity returns to the old
way&mdash;the way of Christ our Savior? The followers will hold to the power of the priesthood of
God, to authority, and liberty, to the doctrine of individual salvation, the spirit of truth that
binds people into a Christian society. The unity of the Church of the living God will be
envisaged by a society, for which Christendom waits. It will be the religion of Jesus Christ,
and not a religion about Jesus Christ. Thus we come to the supreme test of
religion&mdash;<i>revelation</i>. This was the fundamental teaching of the prophets of the Old Testament.
Isaiah in richness of spiritual expression wrote ages ago:
</p><p>
The Spirit of the Lord God is upon me; because the Lord hath anointed me to preach good
tidings unto the meek; he hath sent me to bind up the broken hearted, to proclaim liberty to
the captives, and the opening up of the prison to them that are bound. To appoint unto them
that mourn in Zion, to give unto them beauty for ashes, the oil of joy for mourning, the
garment of praise for the spirit of heaviness; that they might be called trees of righteousness,
the planting of the Lord, that he might be glorified
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/61/1-3#1">Isa. 61:1-3</a>).
</p><p>
Our Savior came to save. He sought out the lost souls who had wandered far away. Sin was
in the world then as it is today. He came to redeem the lost by the principle of repentance and
holy baptism by one who has the power of God. If the Christian world has forgotten this, then
it has lost its divine power. "All great truths," it has been said, "are simple truths." If the
followers of Jesus will begin to teach the ways of the gospel of Christ in that humility which
comes of the genuinely pure heart and the high regard for the intellect, then the divinity of
the gospel will take new root in the souls of men. It will be Christianity again.
</p><p>
A MESSAGE GIVEN THROUGH THE RESTORATION OF THE GOSPEL
</p><p>
A new message of the Redeemer is in the world today. It says in part:
</p><p>
We believe in God, the Eternal Father, and in his Son, Jesus Christ, and in the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
We believe that men will be punished for their own sins, and not for Adam's transgression.
</p><p>
We believe that through the atonement of Christ, all mankind may be saved, by obedience to
the laws and ordinances of the Gospel.
</p><p>
We believe that the first principles and ordinances of the Gospel are: first, Faith in the Lord
Jesus Christ; second, Repentance; third, Baptism by immersion for the remission of sins;
fourth, Laying on of hands for the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
We believe that a man must be called of God, by prophecy, and by the laying on of hands, by
those who are in authority to preach the Gospel and administer in the ordinances thereof.
</p><p>
We believe in the same organization that existed in the primitive Church, viz., apostles,
prophets, pastors, teachers, evangelists, etc.
</p><p>
* * *
</p><p>
We believe in being honest, true, chaste, benevolent, virtuous, and in doing good to all men;
indeed, we may say that we follow the admonition of Paul&mdash;We believe all things, we hope all
things, we have endured many things, and hope to be able to endure all things. If there is
anything virtuous, lovely, or of good report or praiseworthy, we seek after these things
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/1-6,13#1">A of F 1:1-6,13</a>).
</p><p>
This message is purifying and refining. It will correct the abuses of human society; the abuses
that obstruct the pathway of God's work. It is revelatory, "fulfilling the largest meaning and
possibility of <i>revelation</i>." And furthermore, we have a truth: "Whatsoever principles of
knowledge we attain unto in this life will rise with us in the resurrection"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/18#18">D&amp;C 130:18</a>). This provides a
scope of unlimited progress, and makes due place for all the human instincts that constitute
the spiritual nature of man. It limits man to his highest possibilities. This new message meets
the supreme test of religion&mdash;<i>revelation</i>. For in him is the supreme Sonship: "The glory of the
Only Begotten of the Father, full of grace and truth"
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/1/14#14">John 1:14</a>).
What we have this day has redeemed
you and me far more than we have realized. Our world must go forth with the teaching that
God does live, and we freely give that which we have freely received. We will become a
power through our idealism and faith. All of this, the Prophet Joseph Smith meant when he
declared in words as revealed from God:
</p><p>
Ye must grow in grace and in the knowledge of the truth
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/40#40">D&amp;C 50:40</a>).
</p><p>
May we all abide more and more each day by the laws and commandments of God. I ask in
the name of Jesus Christ. Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
