<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="gcera">
<div class="gchead">
<p class="gctitle">Jesus the Christ</p>
<p class="gcspeaker">Elder John Longden</p>
<p class="gcspkpos">Assistant to the Council of the Twelve Apostles</p>
<p class="gcbib">John Longden, <i>Conference Report</i>, October 1954, pp. 30-32</p>
</div>
<div class="gcbody">
<p>
My dear brothers and sisters: This is my third anniversary and seventh time that I have been
honored with the privilege of standing in this position.  I assure you that the timidity is just as
great today as it was seven conferences ago.  When I realize that the Prophet of God, who
opened this glorious conference this morning, in his wisdom, humbly sought divine aid as he
occupied this position, as the others have done who have succeeded him, I more than ever
realize the need for that assistance, and I am brought to a consciousness that there is not
anything that we do in this Church if we have desire to aid and assist, to benefit and bless
people but what we should act under the inspiration of our heavenly Father.
</p><p>
Another anniversary&mdash;it was forty-five years ago on the seventh of this month, since I was
privileged to land in Salt Lake City with my father, he having accepted the gospel just shortly
before I was born in the little town of Oldham, England.  I am grateful that he still lives at
eighty-one and has a testimony of the divinity of the gospel of Jesus Christ and in this thing
called "Mormonism."
</p><p>
We have heard servants of God bear their testimonies that this is his work in which we are
engaged, and I believe therein lies the strength of this Church. When I make that statement, I
am mindful of the fact that there is great strength in the missionary program of the Church,
which is a great voluntary service.  I am conscious of this because I have had the privilege of
touring the New England Mission going as far as St. Johns, Newfoundland.  In the past two
months I have been all the way from the West Coast to St. Johns, Newfoundland.  I have
heard testimonies of those newly converted to the Church, and I have heard testimonies of
those who have been stalwarts through the years.  It is recorded by the Psalmist David: 
</p><p>
Blessed are they that keep his testimonies, and that seek him with the whole heart
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/119/2#2">Ps. 119:2</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, I am also mindful that there is great strength in the evidence we have from people
paying their tithes and offerings that this work of the Lord may grow and progress.  I believe
that the strength of this Church lies in the individual testimony which people may posses if
they will but conform their teachings of the restored gospel of Jesus Christ.
</p><p>
I am mindful of this vast congregation here this afternoon and also the vast
congregation&mdash;the capacity of which we know not&mdash;who will be listening in over the radio and those who may
be viewing over television I trust that in the few moments I occupy this position I may bring
you a message that will be of value and of worth in assisting you to seek for a testimony.
</p><p>
I have heard so many people say, and you have had the same experience I am sure: "You
seem so positive in your testimony or in your statement that God lives and that Jesus is the
Christ." I am positive in my testimony, but I want to assure you that it is not in the spirit of
egotism or self-exaltation whatsoever&mdash;only in the spirit of humility.  I would call to your
attention the experience which the Savior had on one occasion when he approached Peter and
the other disciples when he had been mistaken for many other personages,
</p><p>
When Jesus came into the coasts of Caesarea Philippi, he asked his disciples, saying, Whom
do men say that I the Son of man am?
</p><p>
And they said, Some say that thou art John the Baptist: some, Elias; and others, Jeremias, or
one of the prophets.
</p><p>
He saith unto them, But whom say ye that I am?
</p><p>
And Simon Peter answered and said, Thou art the Christ, the Son of the living God.
</p><p>
And Jesus answered and said unto him, Blessed art thou, Simon Bar-jona: for flesh and blood
hath not revealed it unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.
</p><p>
And I say also unto thee, That thou art Peter, and upon this rock I will build my church; and
the gates of hell shall not prevail against it.
</p><p>
And I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt bind
on earth shall be bound in heaven: and whatsoever thou shalt loose on earth shall be loosed in
heaven (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/13-19#13">Matt. 16:13-19</a>).
</p><p>
Would you say that was a positive testimony that Peter had?  He knew that Jesus was the
Christ, the Son of the living God.  That came unto him by divine revelation It can come unto
every individual who has a desire to serve God, to know his commandments and be
submissive to his will and be obedient to the same.  Anyone may possess a positive
testimony.
</p><p>
Again on another occasion, on the day of Pentecost the Savior had commissioned his disciples
to go forward and proclaim his doctrines.  They had the power and authority necessary to
teach the gospel of Jesus Christ and to administer in the ordinances thereof which pertain to
the salvation and exaltation of our heavenly Father's children.
</p><p>
Therefore let all the house of Israel know assuredly, that God hath made that same Jesus,
whom ye have crucified, both Lord and Christ.
</p><p>
Now when they heard this, they were pricked in their heart, and said unto Peter and to the
rest of the apostles, Men and brethren, what shall we do?
</p><p>
Then Peter said unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus
Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost.
</p><p>
For the promise is unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many
as the Lord our God shall call.
</p><p>
And with many other words did he testify and exhort, saving, Save yourselves from this
untoward generation (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/36-40#36">Acts 2:36-40</a>).
</p><p>
I believe that applies in this dispensation in this year 1954, as it did almost two thousand
years ago when that positive declaration was given by Peter.
</p><p>
After the resurrection of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, he appeared in the upper chamber
on one occasion and, oh, they were glad to see him&mdash;to receive their Lord.  He gave them
these consoling words in which we, today, might find comfort: "Peace be unto you."
</p><p>
Then the same day at evening, before the first day of the week, when the doors were shut
where the disciples were assembled for fear of the Jews, came Jesus and stood in the midst,
and saith unto them, Peace be unto you.
</p><p>
And when he had so said, he shewed unto them his hands and his side.  Then were the
disciples glad, when they saw the Lord.
</p><p>
Then said Jesus to them again, Peace be unto you: as my Father hath sent me, even so send I
you.
</p><p>
And when he had said this, he breathed on them, and saith unto them, Receive ye the Holy
Ghost: 
</p><p>
Whose soever sins ye remit, they are remitted unto them; and whose soever sins ye retain,
they are retained.
</p><p>
But Thomas, one of the twelve, called Didymus, was not with them when Jesus came.
</p><p>
The other disciples therefore said unto him, We have seen the Lord.  But he said unto them,
Except I shall see in his hands the print of the nails, and put my finger into the print of the
nails, and thrust my hand into his side, I will not believe.
</p><p>
And after eight days again his disciples were within, and Thomas with them: then came Jesus,
the doors being shut, and stood in the midst, and said, Peace be unto you.
</p><p>
Then saith he to Thomas, Reach hither thy finger, and behold my hands; and reach hither thy
hand, and thrust it into my side: and be not faithless, but believing.
</p><p>
And Thomas answered and said unto him, My Lord and my God.
</p><p>
Jesus saith unto him, Thomas, because thou hast seen me, thou hast believed: blessed are they
that have not seen, and yet have believed
(<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/20/19-29#19">John 20:19-29</a>).
</p><p>
I have not seen the Master Jesus Christ, but I have a firm conviction and testimony that he
lives.  I know that I have been blessed as I go about in my humble, weak way endeavoring to
fulfil assignments which come to me by those in authority.  I cannot deny that God and his
Son Jesus Christ have been with me to bless me that the people might be fed the bread of
life.
</p><p>
I am grateful for a positive testimony.
</p><p>
In conclusion I should like to give you a positive testimony from the Old Testament.  The
Prophet Job had suffered much, and yet his testimony was sufficiently strong that he had the
power to subdue and rise above and overcome the weaknesses of the flesh
because the Spirit of the Lord had taken precedence in his life.  So indelibly did he desire his
testimony to be inscribed upon the hearts and minds of men that he said: 
</p><p>
Oh that my words were now written! oh that they were printed in a book!
</p><p>
That they were graven with an iron pen and lead in the rock for ever!
</p><p>
For I know that my redeemer liveth, and that he shall stand at the latter day upon the earth: 
</p><p>
And though after my skin worms destroy this body, yet in my flesh shall I see God.
</p><p>
Whom I shall see for myself, and mine eyes shall behold, and not another; though my reins
be consumed within me (<a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/19/23-27#23">Job 19:23-27</a>).
</p><p>
Yes, my brothers and sisters and friends of the radio and television audience, you may also
have a positive testimony that God lives and that Jesus is the Christ, the divine Son of God
our heavenly Father, and I trust that those who are hungering and thirsting after righteousness
may have a desire within their hearts to accept truth, for all truth emanates from God our
eternal Father.
</p><p>
This is my testimony to you today, and I bear it in humility and in the name of the Lord
Jesus Christ.  Amen.
</p>
</div>
</div>
