<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="97"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs96.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs98.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 97</div>
  <p class="cont">word, by and by, he is offended. He also that receiveth seed among the thorns, is he that heareth the
  word; and the care of this world, and the deceitfulness of riches choke the word, and he becometh
  unfruitful. But he that received seed into the good ground, is he that heareth the word, and
  understandeth it, which also beareth fruit, and bringeth forth, some an hundred fold, some sixty,
  some thirty.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> Thus the Savior Himself explains unto His disciples the parable which He put forth,
  and left no mystery or darkness upon the minds of those who firmly believe on His words.</p>
  <p class="std">We draw the conclusion, then, that the very reason why the multitude, or the world, as they
  were designated by the Savior, did not receive an explanation upon His parables, was because of
  unbelief.<span class="footRef">2</span> To you, He says (speaking to His disciples) it is given to know the mysteries of the
  Kingdom of God.<span class="footRef">3</span> And why? Because of the faith and confidence they had in Him. This parable was
  spoken to demonstrate the effects that are produced by the preaching of the word; and we believe
  that it has an allusion directly, to the commencement, or the setting up of the Kingdom in that age;
  therefore we shall continue to trace His sayings concerning this Kingdom from that time forth, even
  unto the end of the world.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Parable of the Tares</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Another parable put He forth unto them, saying, [which parable has an allusion to the setting
  up of the Kingdom, in that age of the world also], The Kingdom of Heaven is likened unto a man
  which sowed good seed in his field, but while men slept, his enemy came and sowed tares among
  the wheat, and went his way. But when the blade was sprung up, and brought forth fruit, then
  appeared the tares also; so the servants of the householder came and said unto him, Sir, didst not
  thou sow good seed in thy field? From whence, then, hath it tares? He said unto them, An enemy
  hath done this. The servants said unto him, Wilt thou then that we go and gather them up? But he
  said, Nay; lest while ye gather up the tares, ye root up also the wheat with them. Let both grow
  together until the harvest: and in the time of harvest I will say to the reapers, Gather ye together first
  the tares, and bind them in bundles to burn them, but gather the wheat into my barn.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <p class="std">Now we learn by this parable, not only the setting up of</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/20-23" target="_blank">Matt. 13:20-23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/11-15,58" target="_blank">Matt. 13:11-15,58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/11" target="_blank">Matt. 13:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/39,49" target="_blank">Matt. 13:39,49</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/4/7" target="_blank">Mosiah 4:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 19:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:49</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/67" target="_blank">Moses 7:67</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_m/1/4" target="_blank">JS&mdash;M 1:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/24-30" target="_blank">Matt. 13:24-30</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
