<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="86"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs85.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs87.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 86</div>
  <p class="cont">the very identical continent and spot of land upon which the New Jerusalem is to stand, and it must
  be caught up<span class="footRef">1</span> according to the vision of John upon the isle of Patmos.</p>
  <p class="std">Now many will feel disposed to say, that this New Jerusalem spoken of, is the Jerusalem that
  was built by the Jews on the eastern continent. But you will see, from Revelation 21:2,<span class="footRef">2</span> there was
  a New Jerusalem coming down from God out of heaven, adorned as a bride for her husband; that
  after this, the Revelator was caught away in the Spirit, to a great and high mountain, and saw the
  great and holy city descending out of heaven from God.<span class="footRef">3</span> Now there are two cites spoken of here.
  As everything cannot be had in so narrow a compass as a letter, I shall say with brevity, that there
  is a New Jerusalem to be established on this continent, and also Jerusalem shall be rebuilt on the
  eastern continent (see Book of Mormon, Ether 13:1–12). &ldquo;Behold, Ether saw the days of Christ, and
  he spake also concerning the house of Israel, and the Jerusalem from whence Lehi should come;
  after it should be destroyed, it should be built up again, a holy city unto the Lord, wherefore it could
  not be a New Jerusalem, for it had been in a time of old.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> This may suffice, upon the subject of
  gathering, until my next.</p>
  <div class="topic">Duties of Elders</div>
  <p class="std">I now proceed, at the close of my letter, to make a few remarks on the duty of Elders with
  regard to their teaching parents and children, husbands and wives, masters and slaves,<span class="footRef">5</span> or servants,
  as I said I would in my former letter.</p>
  <p class="std">And first, it becomes an Elder when he is traveling through the world, warning the inhabitants
  of the earth<span class="footRef">6</span> to gather together, that they may be built up an holy city unto the Lord,<span class="footRef">7</span> instead of
  commencing with children, or those who look up to parents or guardians to influence their minds,
  thereby drawing them from their duties, which they rightfully owe these legal guardians, they should
  commence their labors with parents, or guardians; and their teachings should be such as are
  calculated to turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the hearts of children to the fathers;<span class="footRef">8</span>
  and no influence should be used with children, contrary to the consent of their parents or guardians;
  but all such as can be persuaded in a lawful and righteous manner, and with common consent,<span class="footRef">9</span> we
  should feel</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/100" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:100</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/63-64" target="_blank">Moses 7:63-64</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/2" target="_blank">Rev. 21:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/10" target="_blank">Rev. 21:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/13/1-12" target="_blank">Ether 13:1-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/37" target="_blank">D&amp;C 63:37</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/106" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:106</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/48/2" target="_blank">Isa. 48:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/52/1" target="_blank">Isa. 52:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 63:49</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/58" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:58</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/56" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:56</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/6" target="_blank">Mal. 4:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/26/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 26:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/28/13" target="_blank">D&amp;C 28:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/71-72,85" target="_blank">D&amp;C 104:71-72,85</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
