<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="182"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs181.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs183.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 182</div>
  <div class="topic">EXCERPTS FROM A PROCLAMATION OF THE FIRST PRESIDENCY</div>
  <div class="topic">TO THE SAINTS SCATTERED ABROAD</div>
  <p class="wideEllipse"> * * *</p>
  <div class="topic">Nauvoo</div>
  <p class="std">The name of our City (Nauvoo) is of Hebrew origin, and signifies a beautiful situation, or place,
  carrying with it, also, the idea of rest; and is truly descriptive of the most delightful location. It is
  situated on the east bank of the Mississippi River, at the head of the Des Moines Rapids, in Hancock
  County, bounded on the east by an extensive prairie of surpassing beauty, and on the north, west and
  south, by the Mississippi. This place has been objected to by some on account of the sickness which
  as prevailed in summer months, but * * * all the eastern and southern portions of the City of
  Nauvoo, are as healthful as any other portions of the western country, to acclimatized citizens.
  * * *</p>
  <p class="std">The population of the city is increasing with unparalleled rapidity, numbering more than 3,000
  inhabitants. Every facility is afforded, in the city and adjacent country, in Hancock County, for the
  successful prosecution of the mechanical arts and the pleasing pursuits of agriculture. The waters
  of the Mississippi can be successfully used for manufacturing purposes to almost an unlimited
  extent.&mdash;DHC 4:268.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">The Temple</div>
  <p class="std">The Temple of the Lord is in process of erection here, where the Saints will come to worship
  the God of their fathers,<span class="footRef">1</span> according to the order of His house<span class="footRef">2</span> and the powers of the Holy Priesthood,
  and will be so constructed as to enable all the functions of the Priesthood to be duly exercised, and
  where instructions from the Most High will be received, and from this place go forth to distant
  lands.<span class="footRef">3</span> Let us then concentrate all our powers, under the provisions of our <i>magna charta</i> granted by
  the Illinois legislature, at the &ldquo;City of Nauvoo&rdquo; and surrounding country, and strive to emulate the
  action of the ancient covenant fathers and patriarchs,<span class="footRef">4</span> in those things which are of such vast
  importance to this and every succeeding generation.&mdash;DHC 4:269.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/4/5" target="_blank">Ex. 4:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/15/12" target="_blank">2 Chr. 15:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/119" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:119</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/8,18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:8,18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/64" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:64</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/32" target="_blank">D&amp;C 98:32</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/31" target="_blank">Abr. 1:31</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
