<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="382"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs381.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs383.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 382</div>
  <p class="cont">consequently the proceedings are illegal, and we desire the time may be hastened when all things
  shall be made right, and we relieved from this imprisonment.</p>
  <p class="std">Your servant,</p>
  <p class="std">JOSEPH SMITH.</p>
  <p class="std">P.S.&mdash;Please send an answer per bearer.</p>
  <p class="std">(June 26, 1844.) DHC 6:575.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Prophet&rsquo;s Premonition</div>
  <p class="summary">At noon, June 26, 1844, Willard Richards, the recorder, made copies of orders from the Prophet to brethren in
  Nauvoo; while doing so&mdash;</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="cont">&mdash;Joseph remarked, &ldquo;I have had a good deal of anxiety about my safety<span class="footRef">1</span> since I left Nauvoo, which
  I never had before when I was under arrest. I could not help those feelings, and they have depressed
  me. Most of the forenoon was spent by Dan Jones and Col. Stephen Markham in hewing with a
  pen-knife a warped door to get it on the latch, thus preparing to fortify the place against any attack.</p>
  <p class="std">The Prophet, Patriarch, and their friends took turns preaching to the guards,<span class="footRef">2</span> several of whom
  were relieved before their time was out, because they admitted they were convinced of the innocence
  of the prisoners. They frequently admitted they had been imposed upon, and more than once it was
  heard, &ldquo;Let us go home, boys, for I will not fight any longer against these men.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">During the day Hyrum encouraged Joseph to think that the Lord, for His Church&rsquo;s sake, would
  release him from prison. Joseph replied, &ldquo;Could my brother, Hyrum, but be liberated, it would not
  matter so much about me. Poor Rigdon, I am glad he is gone to Pittsburg out of the way; were he
  to preside he would lead the Church to destruction in less than five years.&rdquo;  (June 26, 1844.) DHC
  6:592–593.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Ill-Treatment of John Smith&mdash;5:30 p.m.</div>
  <p class="std">Patriarch John Smith<span class="footRef">3</span> came from Macedonia to jail to see his nephews, Joseph and Hyrum. The
  road was thronged with mobbers. Three of them snapped their guns at him, and he was threatened
  by many others who recognized him. The guard at the jail refused him admittance.</p>
  <p class="std">Joseph saw him through the prison window, and said to</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/3/25-26" target="_blank">Job 3:25-26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/16/23-34" target="_blank">Acts 16:23-34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/102/3,34" target="_blank">D&amp;C 102:3,34</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
