<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="278"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs277.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs279.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 278</div>
  <p class="cont">persons that are so righteous;<span class="footRef">1</span> they will be damned anyhow; you cannot save them. (Jan. 29, 1843.)
  DHC 5:260–262.</p>
  <div class="topic">Scriptural Correction</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;The Spirit maketh intercession for us with groanings which cannot be uttered.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span> It would be
  better thus: &ldquo;The Spirit maketh intercession for us with striving which cannot be expressed.&rdquo; (Feb.
  2, 1843.) DHC 5:264.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Calling of a Prophet</div>
  <p class="std">Wednesday, Feb. 8.&mdash;This morning I read German and visited with a brother and sister from
  Michigan, who thought that &ldquo;a prophet is always a prophet;&rdquo; but I told them that a prophet was a
  prophet only when he was acting as such.&mdash;DHC 5:265.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Sign Seeker</div>
  <p class="std">When I was preaching in Philadelphia, a Quaker called out for a sign. I told him to be still. After
  the sermon, he again asked for a sign. I told the congregation the man was an adulterer; that a
  wicked and adulterous generation seeketh after a sign;<span class="footRef">3</span> and that the Lord had said to me in a
  revelation, that any man who wanted a sign was an adulterous person.<span class="footRef">4</span> &ldquo;It is true,&rdquo; cried one, &ldquo;for
  I caught him in the very act,&rdquo; which the man afterwards confessed when he was baptized.<span class="footRef">5</span> (Feb. 9,
  1843.) DHC 5:268.</p>
  <div class="topic">Views of the Prophet on Constitutional Powers</div>
  <p class="std">Situated as we are, with a flood of immigration constantly pouring in upon us, I consider that
  it is not only prudential, but absolutely necessary to protect the inhabitants of this city from being
  imposed upon by a spurious currency. Many of our eastern and old country friends are altogether
  unacquainted with the situation of the banks in this region of country; and as they generally bring
  specie with them, they are perpetually in danger of being gulled by speculators. Besides there is so
  much uncertainty in the solvency of the best of banks, that I think it much safer to go upon the hard
  money system altogether. I have examined the Constitution upon this subject and find my doubts
  removed. The Constitution<span class="footRef">6</span> is not a law, but it empowers the people to make laws. For instance, the
  Con-</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/7" target="_blank">Luke 15:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/8/26" target="_blank">Rom. 8:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/39" target="_blank">Matt. 12:39</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/16/4" target="_blank">Matt. 16:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/9" target="_blank">D&amp;C 46:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/7-14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 63:7-14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/3/6" target="_blank">Matt. 3:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/16/1,5" target="_blank">Hel. 16:1,5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/78-80" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:78-80</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
