<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="394"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs393.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs395.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 394</div>
  <p class="cont">the opportunity to walk out of the barn about up to my ankles in mud.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;When I was a little distance from the barn, I heard them screeching and screaming in a very
  distressed manner, as it appeared they had engaged in a general fight with their knives. While they
  were thus engaged, the dream of vision ended.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">Both Joseph and Hyrum bore a faithful testimony to the Latter-day work, and the coming forth
  of the Book of Mormon, and prophesied of the triumph of the Gospel over all the earth, exhorting
  the brethren present to faithfulness<span class="footRef">1</span> and persevering diligence in proclaiming the Gospel,<span class="footRef">2</span> building
  up the Temple,<span class="footRef">3</span> and performing all the duties<span class="footRef">4</span> connected with our holy religion.</p>
  <p class="std">Joseph dictated the following postscript to Emma:</p>
  <p class="std">Letter: Postscript.</p>
  <p class="std">P.S.&mdash;20 minutes to 10.&mdash;I just learn that the Governor is about to disband his troops, all but
  a guard to protect us and the peace, and come himself to Nauvoo and deliver a speech to the people.
  This is right as I suppose.</p>
  <p class="std">He afterwards wrote a few lines with his own hand, which were not copied. (June 27, 1844.)
  DHC 6:608–611.</p>
  <div class="topic">Letter: Joseph Smith to O. H. Browning&mdash;</div>
  <div class="topic">Engaging Browning as Legal Counsel</div>
  <p class="right">Carthage Jail, June 27th, 1844.</p>
  <p class="cont">Lawyer Browning:&mdash;</p>
  <p class="std">Sir.&mdash;Myself and brother Hyrum are in jail on charge of treason, to come up for examination
  on Saturday morning, 29th inst., and we request you professional services at that time, on our
  defense, without fail.</p>
  <p class="std">Most respectfully your servant,</p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH.</p>
  <p class="std">P.S.&mdash;There is no cause of action, for we have not been guilty of any crime, neither is there any
  just cause of suspicion against us; but certain circumstances make your attendance very necessary.</p>
  <p class="right">J. S.&mdash;DHC 6:613.</p>
  <p class="std">This account brings us up to the afternoon of the day of the martyrdom. At 1:30 p.m. on that day
  some of the visitors at the prison were forced to leave, and Joseph Smith, Hyrum</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/15" target="_blank">1 Ne. 17:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/99/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 99:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/88" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:88</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/24" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:99</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
