<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="222"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs221.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs223.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 222</div>
  <p class="cont">the Gospel, when they never heard it? Certainly not. But they will possess the same privilege that
  we here enjoy, through the medium of the everlasting Priesthood, which not only administers on
  earth, but also in heaven,<span class="footRef">1</span> and the wise dispensations of the great Jehovah; hence those characters
  referred to by Isaiah will be visited by the Priesthood,<span class="footRef">2</span> and come out of their prison<span class="footRef">3</span> upon the same
  principle as those who were disobedient in the days of Noah<span class="footRef">4</span> were visited by our Savior<span class="footRef">5</span> [who
  possessed the everlasting Melchizedek Priesthood] and had the Gospel preached to them by Him in
  prison; and in order that they might fulfill all the requisitions of God, living friends were baptized
  for their dead friends, and thus fulfilled the requirement of God, which says, &ldquo;Except a man be born
  of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">6</span> they were baptized of course,
  not for themselves, but for their dead.</p>
  <p class="std">Chrysostum says that the Marcionites practiced baptism for their dead. &ldquo;After a catechumen was
  dead, they had a living man under the bed of the deceased; then coming to the dead man, they asked
  him whether he would receive baptism, and he making no answer, the other answered for him, and
  said that he would be baptized in his stead; and so they baptized the living for the dead.&rdquo; The church
  of course at that time was degenerate, and the particular form might be incorrect, but the thing is
  sufficiently plain in the Scriptures, hence Paul, in speaking of the doctrine, says, &ldquo;Else what shall
  they do which are baptized for the dead, if the dead rise not at all? Why are they then baptized for
  the dead?&rdquo; (1 Cor. 15:29.)<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Responsibility of the Jews</div>
  <p class="std">Hence it was that so great a responsibility rested upon the generation<span class="footRef">8</span> in which our Savior lived,
  for, says he, &ldquo;That upon you may come all the righteous blood shed upon the earth, from the blood
  of righteous Abel unto the blood of Zacharias, son of Barachias, whom ye slew between the temple
  and the altar. Verily I say unto you, all these things shall come upon this generation.&rdquo;  (Matthew
  23:35, 36.)<span class="footRef">9</span> Hence as they possessed greater privileges than any other generation, not only
  pertaining to themselves, but to their dead, their sin was greater, as they not only neglected their own
  salvation<span class="footRef">10</span> but</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/8-9" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:8-9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/42/7" target="_blank">Isa. 42:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/20" target="_blank">1 Pet. 3:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/3/19" target="_blank">1 Pet. 3:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/5" target="_blank">John 3:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/29" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/12/41-42" target="_blank">Matt. 12:41-42</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/35-36" target="_blank">Matt. 23:35-36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/7/30" target="_blank">Luke 7:30</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
