<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="180"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs179.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs181.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 180</div>
  <p class="std">Without enlarging on the subject, you will undoubtedly see its consistency and reasonableness;
  and it presents the Gospel of Christ<span class="footRef">1</span> in probably a more enlarged scale than some have imagined it.
  But as the performance of this rite is more particularly confined to this place, it will not be necessary
  to enter into particulars; at the same time I always feel glad to give all the information in my power,
  buy my space will not allow me to do it.</p>
  <p class="std">We had a letter from Elder Hyde, a few days ago, who is in New Jersey, and is expecting to
  leave for England as soon as Elder Page reaches him. He requested to know if converted Jews are
  to go to Jerusalem or to come to Zion. I therefore wish you to inform him that converted Jews must
  come here.</p>
  <p class="std">Give my kind love to all the brethren and sisters, and tell them I should have been pleased to
  come over to England to see them, but I am afraid that I shall be under the necessity of remaining
  here for some time; therefore I give them a pressing invitation to come and see me.</p>
  <p class="std">I remain, dear brethren, yours affectionately,</p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH, (Oct. 19, 1840.) DHC 4:226–232.</p>
  <div class="topic">Description of Paul</div>
  <p class="std">Given by the Prophet Joseph, January 5, 1841, at the organization of a school of instruction:
  &ldquo;He is about five feet high; very dark hair; dark complexion; dark skin; large Roman nose; sharp
  face; small black eyes, penetrating as eternity; round shoulders; a whining voice, except when
  elevated, and then it almost resembled the roaring of a lion.<span class="footRef">2</span> He was a good orator, active and
  diligent, always employing himself in doing good<span class="footRef">3</span> to his fellow man.&rdquo;</p>
  <div class="topic">Different Degrees of the Priesthood of Melchizedek</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Answer to the question, Was the Priesthood of Melchizedek taken away when Moses died?
  All Priesthood is Melchizedek,<span class="footRef">4</span> but there are different portions or degrees of it. That portion which
  brought Moses to speak with God face to face was taken away;<span class="footRef">5</span> but that which brought the ministry</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/1/16" target="_blank">Rom. 1:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/28/23" target="_blank">3 Ne. 28:23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/74/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 74:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/50,82" target="_blank">D&amp;C 76:50,82</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1000" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1 Endnote</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/19/12" target="_blank">Prov. 19:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/27-28" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:27-28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/1-5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:1-5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/33/11" target="_blank">Ex. 33:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/22-23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:22-23</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
