<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="53"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs52.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs54.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 53</div>
  <p class="cont">ileges with his son, and those who had been obedient to his commandments? Certainly not. Because
  they disregarded the voice of their lawful king; they had no regard for his virtuous laws, for his
  dignity, nor for the honor of his name; neither for the honor of their country, nor their private virtue.
  They regarded not his authority enough to obey him, neither did they regard the immediate
  advantages and blessings arising from these laws if kept, so destitute were they of virtue and
  goodness; and above all, they regarded so little the joy and satisfaction of a legal seat in the presence
  of the king&rsquo;s only son, and to be made equal with him all the blessings, honors, comforts, and
  felicities of his kingdom, that they turned away from a participation in them, and considered that
  they were beneath their present notice, though they had no doubt as to the real authenticity of the
  royal edict.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <p class="std">How could a government be conducted with harmony if its administrators were possessed with
  such different dispositions and different principles? Could it prosper? Could it flourish? Would
  harmony prevail? Would order be established,<span class="footRef">1</span> and could justice be executed in righteousness<span class="footRef">2</span> in
  all branches of its departments? No!  In it were two classes of men as dissimilar as light and
  darkness, virtue and vice, justice and injustice, truth and falsehood, holiness and sin. One class were
  perfectly harmless and virtuous: they knew what virtue was for they had lived in the fullest
  enjoyment of it, and their fidelity to truth had been fairly tested by a series of years of faithful
  obedience to all its heavenly precepts. They knew what good order was, for they had been orderly
  and obedient to the laws imposed on them by their wise sovereign, and had experienced the benefits
  arising from a life spent in his government till he has now seen proper to make them equal with his
  son. Such individuals would indeed adorn any court where perfection was one of its main springs
  of action, and shine far more fair<span class="footRef">3</span> than the richest gem in the diadem<span class="footRef">4</span> of the prince.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">God Speaks from Heaven</div>
  <p class="std">We take the sacred writings<span class="footRef">5</span> into our hands, and admit that they were given by direct inspiration
  for the good of man.<span class="footRef">6</span> We believe that God condescended to speak from the heavens<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/6/4" target="_blank">Alma 6:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 78:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 104:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/26" target="_blank">Abr. 1:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/10/30" target="_blank">2 Kgs. 10:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/99/4" target="_blank">Ps. 99:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/103/6" target="_blank">Ps. 103:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/33/15" target="_blank">Jer. 33:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/22/21" target="_blank">1 Ne. 22:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/7/1,11,27" target="_blank">Ether 7:1,11,27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/73" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:73</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/28/5" target="_blank">Isa. 28:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/62/3" target="_blank">Isa. 62:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/68" target="_blank">D&amp;C 104:68</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/16-17" target="_blank">2 Tim. 3:16-17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/4/15" target="_blank">2 Ne. 4:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/2/1" target="_blank">Moses 2:1</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
