<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="147"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs146.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs148.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 147</div>
  <p class="cont">to human nature, against our friends, neighbors, and brethren of the world, who choose to differ from
  us in opinion and in matters of faith. Our religion is between us and our God. Their religion is
  between them and their God.</p>
  <p class="std">There is a love from God that should be exercised toward those of our faith, who walk uprightly,
  which is peculiar to itself, but it is without prejudice;<span class="footRef">1</span> it also gives scope to the mind, which enables
  us to conduct ourselves with greater liberality towards all that are not of our faith,<span class="footRef">2</span> than what they
  exercise towards one another. These principles approximate nearer to the mind of God, because it
  is like God, or Godlike.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Principle of Religious Freedom</div>
  <p class="std">Here is a principle also, which we are bound to be exercised with, that is, in common with all
  men, such as governments, and laws, and regulations in the civil concerns of life. This principle
  guarantees to all parties, sects, and denominations, and classes of religion, equal, coherent, and
  indefeasible rights; they are things that pertain to this life; therefore all are alike interested; they
  make our responsibilities one towards another in matters of corruptible things, while the former
  principles do not destroy the latter, but bind us stronger, and make our responsibilities not only one
  to another, but unto God also. Hence we say, that the Constitution of the United States<span class="footRef">3</span> is a glorious
  standard; it is founded in the wisdom of God.<span class="footRef">4</span> It is a heavenly banner; it is to all those who are
  privileged with the sweets of liberty, like the cooling shades and refreshing waters of a great rock
  in a thirsty and weary land.<span class="footRef">5</span> It is like a great tree under whose branches men from every clime can
  be shielded from the burning rays of the sun.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">We, brethren, are deprived of the protection of its glorious principles, by the cruelty of the cruel,
  by those who only look for the time being, for pasturage like the beasts of the field, only to fill
  themselves; and forget that the &ldquo;Mormons,&rdquo; as well as the Presbyterians, and those of every other
  class and description, have equal rights to partake of the fruits of the great tree of our national
  liberty. But notwithstanding we see what we see, and feel what we feel, and know what we know,
  yet that fruit is no less precious and delicious to our taste; we cannot be weaned from the milk,
  neither can we be driven from the breast;</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/43-48" target="_blank">Matt. 5:43-48</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/78-80" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:78-80</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/3/28" target="_blank">1 Kgs. 3:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/1/21" target="_blank">1 Cor. 1:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/3/10" target="_blank">Eph. 3:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/8" target="_blank">2 Ne. 9:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/60" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1:60</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/32/2" target="_blank">Isa. 32:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 121:11</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
