<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="277"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs276.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs278.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 277</div>
  <p class="cont">or caused Jesus to utter the parable? It is not national; it does not refer to Abraham, Israel or the
  Gentiles, in a national capacity, as some suppose. To ascertain its meaning, we must dig up the root
  and ascertain what it was that drew the saying out of Jesus.</p>
  <p class="std">While Jesus was teaching the people, all the publicans and sinners drew near to hear Him; &ldquo;and
  the Pharisees and scribes murmured, saying: This man receiveth sinners, and eateth with them.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span>
  This is the keyword which unlocks the parable of the prodigal son. It was given to answer the
  murmurings and questions of the Sadducees and Pharisees, who were querying, finding fault,<span class="footRef">2</span> and
  saying, &ldquo;How is it that this man as great as He pretends to be, eats with publicans and sinners?&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span>
  Jesus was not put to it so, but He could have found something to illustrate His subject, if He had
  designed it for nation or nations; but He did not. It was for men in an individual capacity; and all
  straining on this point is a bubble. &ldquo;This man receiveth sinners and eateth with them.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">And he spake this parable unto them&mdash;&ldquo;What man of you, having an hundred sheep, if he lose
  one of them doth not leave the ninety-and-nine in the wilderness, and go after that which is lost, until
  he find it? And when he hath found it, he layeth it on his shoulders, rejoicing. And when he cometh
  home, he calleth together his friends and neighbors, saying unto them, Rejoice with me; for I have
  found my sheep which was lost. I say unto you, that likewise joy shall be in heaven over one sinner
  that repenteth, more than over ninety-and-nine just persons which need no repentance.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span> The
  hundred sheep represent one hundred Sadducees and Pharisees, as though Jesus had said, &ldquo;If you
  Sadducees and Pharisees are in the sheepfold, I have no mission for you; I am sent to look up sheep
  that are lost; and when I have found them, I will back them up and make joy in heaven.&rdquo;  This
  represents hunting after a few individuals,<span class="footRef">6</span> or one poor publican, which the Pharisees and Sadducees
  despised.</p>
  <p class="std">He also gave them the parable of the woman and her ten pieces of silver, and how she lost one,
  and searching diligently, found it again, which gave more joy among the friends and neighbors than
  the nine which were not lost; like I say unto you, there is joy in the presence of the angels of God
  over one sinner that repenteth,<span class="footRef">7</span> more than over ninety-and-nine just</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/1-2" target="_blank">Luke 15:1-2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/7/2" target="_blank">Mark 7:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/9/11" target="_blank">Matt. 9:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/2/16" target="_blank">Mark 2:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/5/30" target="_blank">Luke 5:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/2" target="_blank">Luke 15:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/3-7" target="_blank">Luke 15:3-7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/16/16" target="_blank">Jer. 16:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/15/8-10" target="_blank">Luke 15:8-10</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
