<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="7"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs6.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs8.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 7</div>
  <div class="topic dominant">TEACHINGS</div>
  <div class="topic subordinate">OF THE</div>
  <div class="topic dominant">PROPHET JOSEPH SMITH</div>
  <div class="topic">Title Page of The Book of Mormon</div>
  <p class="std">Meantime our translation drawing to a close, we went to Palmyra, Wayne County, New York,
  secured the copyright, and agreed with Mr. Egbert B. Grandin to print five thousand copies for the
  sum of three thousand dollars.</p>
  <p class="std">I wish to mention here, that the title-page of the Book of Mormon<span class="footRef">1</span> is a literal translation, taken
  from the very last leaf, on the left hand side of the collection or book of plates, which contained the
  record which has been translated, the language of the whole running the same as all Hebrew<span class="footRef">2</span> writing
  in general; and that said title-page is not by any means a modern composition, either of mine or of
  any other man who has lived or does live in this generation. Therefore, in order to correct an error
  which generally exists concerning it, I give below that part of the title-page of the English version
  of the Book of Mormon, which is a genuine and literal translation of the title-page of the original
  Book of Mormon, as recorded on the plates.&mdash;DHC 1:71. (1830.)</p>
  <div class="topic">Value of the Revelations and Commandments</div>
  <p class="std">My time was occupied closely in reviewing the commandments and sitting in conference, for
  nearly two weeks, for from the first to the twelfth of November [1831] we held four special
  conferences. In the last which was held at Brother Johnson&rsquo;s, in Hiram, after deliberate
  consideration, in consequence of the Book of revelations,<span class="footRef">3</span> now to be printed,<span class="textFootRef">a</span> being</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/bm/ttlpg" target="_blank">BM Title Page</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/33" target="_blank">Morm. 9:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:17</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>At a conference of the Church held in November, 1831, the Prophet received the revelation known as Section
        One, or the Preface to the <i>Book of Commandments.</i> At this conference the Elders considered the question of
        publishing the revelations which had been given up to that time as the <i>Book of Commandments.</i> This action the Lord
        approved by revelation. It was decided that 10,000 copies should be published, but later this was</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
