<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="246"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs245.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs247.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 246</div>
  <div class="topic">The Things of God Known Only by the Spirit of God<span class="footRef">1</span></div>
  <p class="std">There are several gifts mentioned here, yet which of them all could be known by an observer
  at the imposition of hands? The word of wisdom, and the word of knowledge, are as much gifts as
  any other, yet if a person possessed both of these gifts, or received them by the imposition of hands,
  who would know it? Another might receive the gift of faith, and they would be as ignorant of it. Or
  suppose a man had the gift of healing or power to work miracles, that would not then be known; it
  would require time and circumstances to call these gifts into operation. Suppose a man had the
  discerning of spirits, who would be the wiser of it? Or if he had the interpretation of tongues,<span class="footRef">2</span> unless
  someone spoke in an unknown tongue, he of course would have to be silent; there are only two gifts
  that could be made visible&mdash;the gift of tongues and the gift of prophecy. These are things that are the
  most talked about, and yet if a person spoke in an unknown tongue, according to Paul&rsquo;s testimony,
  he would be a barbarian to those present.<span class="footRef">3</span> They would say that it was gibberish; and if he prophesied
  they would call it nonsense. The gift of tongues is the smallest gift perhaps of the whole, and yet it
  is one that is the most sought after.</p>
  <p class="std">So that according to the testimony of Scripture and the manifestations of the Spirit in ancient
  days, very little could be known about it by the surrounding multitude, except on some extraordinary
  occasion, as on the day of Pentecost.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">The greatest, the best, and the most useful gifts would be known nothing about by an observer.
  It is true that a man might prophesy,<span class="footRef">5</span> which is a great gift, and one that Paul told the people&mdash;the
  Church&mdash;to seek after and to covet,<span class="footRef">6</span> rather than to speak in tongues; but what does the world know
  about prophesying? Paul says that it &ldquo;serveth only to those that believe.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">7</span> But does not the Scriptures
  say that they spake in tongues and prophesied?<span class="footRef">8</span> Yes; but who is it that writes these Scriptures? Not
  the men of the world or mere casual observers, but the Apostles&mdash;men who knew one gift from
  another, and of course were capable of writing about it; if we had the testimony of the Scribes and
  Pharisees concerning the outpouring of the Spirit on the day of Pentecost, they would have told us
  that it was no gift, but that the people were &ldquo;drunken with new</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/8-10" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:8-10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/11,23" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:11,23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/1-12" target="_blank">Acts 2:1-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/1" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/31" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:31</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/22" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/6" target="_blank">Acts 19:6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
