<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="242"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs241.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs243.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 242</div>
  <p class="cont">The Ladies&rsquo; Relief Society is not only to relieve the poor,<span class="footRef">1</span> but to save souls.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std">President Smith then said that he would give a lot of land to the society by deeding to the
  treasurer, that the society may build houses for the poor. He also said he would give a house, frame
  not finished, and that Brother Cahoon will move it on to the aforesaid lot, and the society can pay
  him by giving orders on the store; that it was a good plan to set those to work who are owing
  widows, and thus make an offset, &amp;c.&mdash;DHC 5:23–25.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Gift of the Holy Ghost</div>
  <div class="topic centerEmphasis">An Editorial in the &ldquo;Times and Seasons,&rdquo; by the Prophet</div>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std">Various and conflicting are the opinions of men in regard to the gift of the Holy Ghost. Some
  people have been in the habit of calling every supernatural manifestation the effects of the Spirit of
  God, whilst there are others that think there is no manifestation connected with it at all; and that it
  is nothing but a mere impulse of the mind, or an inward feeling, impression, or secret testimony or
  evidence, which men possess, and that there is no such a thing as an outward manifestation.</p>
  <p class="std">It is not to be wondered at that men should be ignorant, in a great measure, of the principles of
  salvation, and more especially of the nature, office, power, influence, gifts, and blessings of the gift
  of the Holy Ghost, when we consider that the human family have been enveloped in gross darkness<span class="footRef">3</span>
  and ignorance for many centuries past, without revelation, or any just criterion [by which] to arrive
  at a knowledge of the things of God, which can only be known by the Spirit of God.<span class="footRef">4</span> Hence it not
  infrequently occurs, that when the Elders of this Church preach to the inhabitants of the world, that
  if they obey the Gospel they shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost,<span class="footRef">5</span> that the people expect to see
  some wonderful manifestation,<span class="footRef">6</span> some great display of power, or some extraordinary miracle
  performed; and it is often the case that young members of this Church for want of better information,
  carry along with them their old notions of things, and sometimes fall into egregious errors. We have
  lately had some information concerning a few members that are in this dilemma, and for their
  information make a few remarks upon the subject.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/lev/25/35" target="_blank">Lev. 25:35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 38:35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/44/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 44:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/72/13" target="_blank">Ps. 72:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/5/32" target="_blank">Acts 5:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/6" target="_blank">Acts 19:6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
