<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="57"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs56.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs58.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 57</div>
  <p class="cont">to us a law? Was it that it might be obeyed, or disobeyed? And think further, too, not only of the
  propriety, but of the importance of attending to His laws in every particular.<span class="footRef">1</span> If, then, there is an
  importance in this respect, is there not a responsibility of great weight resting upon those who are
  called to declare these truths to men?<span class="footRef">2</span> Were we capable of laying any thing before you as a just
  comparison, we would cheerfully do it; but in this our ability fails, and we are inclined to think that
  man is unable, without assistance beyond what has been given to those before, of expressing in
  words the greatness of this important subject. We can only say, that if an anticipation of the joys of
  the celestial glory, as witnessed to the hearts of the humble<span class="footRef">3</span> is not sufficient, we will leave to
  yourselves the result of your own diligence; for God ere long, will call all His servants before Him,
  and there from His own hand they will receive a just recompense and a righteous reward<span class="footRef">4</span> for all their
  labors.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">Man Departed from the Lord&rsquo;s Government</div>
  <p class="std">It is reasonable to suppose that man departed from the first teachings, or instructions which he
  received from heaven in the first age, and refused by his disobedience to be governed by them.
  Consequently, he formed such laws as best suited his own mind, or as he supposed, were best
  adapted to his situation. But that God has influenced man more or less since that time in the
  formation of law for His benefit we have no hesitancy in believing; for, as before remarked, being
  the source of all good, every just and equitable law was in a greater or less degree influenced by
  Him. And though man in his own supposed wisdom would not admit the influence of a power
  superior to his own, yet for wise and great purposes, for the good and happiness of His creatures,
  God has instructed man to form wise and wholesome laws,<span class="footRef">5</span> since he had departed from Him and
  refused to be governed by those laws which God had given by His own voice<span class="footRef">6</span> from on high<span class="footRef">7</span> in the
  beginning. But notwithstanding the transgression, by which man had cut himself off from an
  immediate intercourse with his Maker without a Mediator, it appears that the great and glorious plan
  of His redemption was previously provided; the sacrifice prepared;</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/25/17" target="_blank">Alma 25:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/9/6" target="_blank">Alma 9:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/30/34" target="_blank">Alma 30:34</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/37" target="_blank">D&amp;C 19:37</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 61:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/2/2" target="_blank">Heb. 2:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/77" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:77</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/25" target="_blank">D&amp;C 43:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/37" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:37</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/58" target="_blank">Moses 5:58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 78:2</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
