<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="213"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs212.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs214.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 213</div>
  <p class="cont">they of course speak Hebrew, Latin, Greek, Italian, Dutch, or any other language that the devil
  knew.</p>
  <p class="std">Some will say, &ldquo;try the spirits&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> by the word. &ldquo;Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is
  come in the flesh is of God, and every spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh
  is not of God.&rdquo;  1 John 4:2–3.<span class="footRef">2</span> One of the Irvingites once quoted this passage whilst under the
  influence of a spirit, and then said, &ldquo;I confess that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh.&rdquo;  And yet these
  prophecies failed, their Messiah did not come; and the great things spoken of by them have fallen
  to the ground. What is the matter here? Did not the Apostle speak the truth? Certainly he did&mdash;but
  he spoke to a people who were under the penalty of death, the moment they embraced Christianity;
  and no one without a knowledge of the fact would confess it, and expose themselves to death, and
  this was consequently given as a criterion to the church or churches to which John wrote. But the
  devil on a certain occasion cried out, &ldquo;I know thee, who thou art, the Holy One of God!&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> Here was
  a frank acknowledgment under other circumstances that &ldquo;Jesus had come in the flesh.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> On another
  occasion the devil said, &ldquo;Paul we know, and Jesus we know&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span>&mdash;of course, &ldquo;come in the flesh.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">6</span> No
  man nor sect of men without the regular constituted authorities, the Priesthood and discerning of
  spirits, can tell true from false spirits.<span class="footRef">7</span> This power they possessed in the Apostles&rsquo; day, but it has
  departed from the world for ages.</p>
  <div class="topic">False Spirits in the Church</div>
  <p class="std">The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints has also had its false spirits;<span class="footRef">8</span> and as it is made
  up of all those different sects professing every variety of opinion, and having been under the
  influence of so many kinds of spirits, it is not to be wondered at if there should be found among us
  false spirits.</p>
  <p class="std">Soon after the Gospel was established in Kirtland, and during the absence of the authorities of
  the Church, many false spirits were introduced, many strange visions were seen, and wild,
  enthusiastic notions were entertained; men ran out of doors under the influence of this spirit, and
  some of them got upon the stumps of trees and shouted, and all kinds of extravagances were entered
  into by them; one man pursued a ball that he said he saw flying in the air, until he came to a
  precipice, when he jumped into the top of a tree, which saved his life;</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/1-3" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:1-3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/31-35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:31-35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/2-3" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:2-3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/1/24" target="_blank">Mark 1:24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/2" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/15" target="_blank">Acts 19:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/2" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/2-3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:2-3</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
