<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="393"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs392.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs394.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 393</div>
  <p class="cont">writing them all down, fearing Wheelock might forget, but Brother Hyrum fastened his eyes upon
  him,<span class="footRef">1</span> and with a look of penetration said, &ldquo;Brother Wheelock will remember all that we tell him, and
  he will never forget<span class="footRef">2</span> the occurrences of this day.&rdquo;</p>
  <div class="topic">The Prophet&rsquo;s Dream</div>
  <p class="std">Joseph related the following dream which he had last night:</p>
  <p class="std">I was back in Kirtland, Ohio, and thought I would take a walk out by myself, and view my old
  farm, which I found grown up with weeds and brambles,<span class="footRef">3</span> and altogether bearing evidence of neglect
  and want of culture. I went into the barn, which I found without floor or doors, with the
  weather-boarding off, and was altogether in keeping with the farm.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;While I viewed the desolation around me, and was contemplating how it might be recovered
  from the curse upon it, there came rushing into the barn a company of furious men, who commenced
  to pick a quarrel with me.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;The leader of the party ordered me to leave the barn and farm, stating it was none of mine, and
  that I must give up all hope of ever possessing it.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;I told him the farm was given me by the Church, and although I had not had any use of it for
  some time back, still I had not sold it,<span class="footRef">4</span> and according to righteous principles it belonged to me or
  the Church.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;He then grew furious and began to rail<span class="footRef">5</span> upon me, and threaten me, and said it never did belong
  to me nor to the Church.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;I then told him that I did not think it worth contending about, that I had no desire to live upon
  it in its present state, and if he thought he had a better right I would not quarrel with him about it but
  leave; but my assurance that I would not trouble him at present did not seem to satisfy him, as he
  seemed determined to quarrel with me, and threatened me with the destruction of my body.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;While he was thus engaged, pouring out his bitter words<span class="footRef">6</span> upon me, a rabble rushed in and
  nearly filled the barn, drew out their knives, and began to quarrel among themselves for the
  premises, and for a moment forgot me, at which time I took</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/4/20" target="_blank">Luke 4:20</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/11/6" target="_blank">Acts 11:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/119/93" target="_blank">Ps. 119:93</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/amos/8/7" target="_blank">Amos 8:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/34/13" target="_blank">Isa. 34:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/57" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:57</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/32/17" target="_blank">2 Chr. 32:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/64/3" target="_blank">Ps. 64:3</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
