<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="8"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs7.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs9.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 8</div>
  <p class="cont">the foundation of the Church<span class="footRef">1</span> in these last days, and a benefit to the world, showing that the keys
  of the mysteries<span class="footRef">2</span> of the kingdom of our Savior<span class="footRef">3</span> are again entrusted to man;<span class="footRef">4</span> and the riches of
  eternity<span class="footRef">5</span> within the compass<span class="footRef">6</span> of those who are willing to live by every word that proceedeth out of
  the mouth of God<span class="footRef">7</span>&mdash;therefore the conference voted that they prize<span class="footRef">8</span> the revelations to be worth to
  the Church the riches of the whole earth,<span class="footRef">9</span> speaking temporally. The great benefits to the world which
  result from the Book of Mormon and the revelations, which the Lord has seen fit<span class="footRef">10</span> in His infinite
  wisdom<span class="footRef">11</span> to grant unto us for our salvation,<span class="footRef">12</span> and for the salvation of all that will believe,<span class="footRef">13</span> were
  duly appreciated; and in answer to an inquiry, I received the following.<span class="footRef">14</span> (Nov., 1831) DHC
  1:235–236.</p>
  <div class="topic">Parting the Veil Through Perfect Faith</div>
  <p class="std">Brother Joseph Smith, Jr. said: We have assembled together to do the business of the Lord<span class="footRef">15</span> and
  it is through the great</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/28/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 28:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 64:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/11" target="_blank">2 Pet. 1:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/14" target="_blank">Alma 37:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/3/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 3:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 78:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/44/13" target="_blank">Isa. 44:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/18/12,21" target="_blank">1 Ne. 18:12,21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/43-44" target="_blank">Alma 37:43-44</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/4" target="_blank">Matt. 4:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/55" target="_blank">Moses 6:55</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/39" target="_blank">D&amp;C 38:39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/27/28" target="_blank">Mosiah 27:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/147/5" target="_blank">Ps. 147:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/85/7" target="_blank">Ps. 85:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/15" target="_blank">Alma 34:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">14. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/70/1-18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 70:1-18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">15. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 64:29</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="cont">changed to 3,000 copies. A number of the brethren, at this conference, arose and stated
        that they were willing to testify to the world that they knew that the revelations received by the Prophet
        were of the Lord. In due time the revelations were compiled by the Prophet, and at a conference held
        November 12, 1831, the revelations were received with thanksgiving. Oliver Cowdery, John Whitmer and
        William W. Phelps, were appointed to review the revelations for printing, and Oliver Cowdery and John Whitmer
        were appointed to carry them to Missouri where the printing was to be done. These brethren were
        &ldquo;dedicated and consecrated with the sacred writings and all they have entrusted to their care to the
        Lord.&rdquo; The publication was commenced by William W. Phelps and Co. in Jackson County, Missouri, but
        before the work was completed the press and type were destroyed by a mob, July 20, 1833, and only a few of
        the printed forms were preserved; these were bound and used by those fortunate enough to secure them in the
        uncompleted condition as the <i>Book of Commandments.</i> Later, in the year 1835, the
        revelations, now greatly increased in number, were again compiled and ordered printed as
        <i>The Doctrine and Covenants.</i> This first edition, prepared under the care of the
        Prophet Joseph Smith, contained 254 pages and was printed by Frederick G. Williams and Co. in Kirtland, Ohio.
        The revelations ranged over a period from 1828 to 1834. Seven Lectures on Faith, which had been given before
        the School of the Elders in Kirtland were also added to the volume, not as revelations, but as stated by the
        brethren at that time &ldquo;as profitable for doctrine.&rdquo; In this book there also appeared two articles
        written by Oliver Cowdery, one on <i>Marriage,</i> and the other on <i>Governments and
        Laws in General.</i> These were ordered printed in the volume with the revelations, but it should be
        remembered this was done in the absence and without the approval of the Prophet Joseph Smith, who with
        President Frederick G. Williams was in Michigan at the time this action was taken. Hence these articles are
        not, as some have supposed, revelations and were not so considered by the Church. It was on the occasion of
        the acceptance of the revelations for publication, November 12, 1831, when the Prophet wrote in his journal
        the comment on the value of the revelations.</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
