<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="395"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs394.html">Prev</a></div>
			    STPJS 395</div>
  <p class="cont">Smith, John Taylor and Willard Richards<span class="footRef">1</span> were left to themselves. At 3:15 after the change of
  guards, they, the guards, became more severe and threatening. About this time Elder Taylor sang&mdash;<i>A</i>
  <i>Poor Wayfaring Man of Grief.</i> When he finished the song the Prophet requested him to sing it again,
  which he did, reluctantly, as he did not feel like singing. At 4 p.m. Hyrum did some reading<span class="footRef">2</span> to his
  fellow prisoners. The guard was again changed, only eight men being stationed at the jail, the main
  body of the Carthage Greys were in camp a quarter of a mile distant, on the public square. At 5 p.m.
  the jailor, Mr. Stigall, suggested that the brethren return to the cell where they would be safer. The
  Prophet turned to Dr. Richards and said, &ldquo;If we go into the cell, will you go in with us?&rdquo;  The Doctor
  replied, &ldquo;Brother Joseph, you did not ask me to cross the river with you&mdash;you did not ask me to
  come to jail with you&mdash;and do you think I would forsake you now? But I will tell you what I will
  do; if you are condemned to be hung for treason, I will be hung in your stead,<span class="footRef">3</span> and you shall go
  free.&rdquo; Joseph said, &ldquo;You cannot.&rdquo; The Doctor said, &ldquo;I will.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">It was but a short time following this that there was a rustling at the door of the prison, the mob
  had arrived and was bent on taking the lives of the prisoners, which, as we all know, they wickedly
  did. The account of this tragedy is not to be related here. The reader is referred to the full account
  of the awful and bloody deed as it is recorded in the <i>Documentary History of the Church.</i></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/36-38" target="_blank">Ether 12:36-38</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4-5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:4-5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/35" target="_blank">Matt. 26:35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/22/33" target="_blank">Luke 22:33</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/13/37" target="_blank">John 13:37</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/13" target="_blank">John 15:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/3/16" target="_blank">1 Jn. 3:16</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
