<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="49"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs48.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs50.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 49</div>
  <p class="cont">appease the wrath of some imaginary god,<span class="footRef">1</span> are now raising their voices in the worship of the Most
  High,<span class="footRef">2</span> and are lifting their thoughts up to Him with the full expectation that one day they will meet
  with a joyful reception in His everlasting kingdom!<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Law of Free Agency</div>
  <p class="std">But a moment&rsquo;s candid reflection upon the principles of these systems, the manner in which
  they are conducted, the individuals employed, the apparent object held out as an inducement to cause
  them to act, we think, is sufficient for every candid man to draw a conclusion in his own mind
  whether this is the order of heaven<span class="footRef">4</span> or not. We deem it a just principle,<span class="footRef">5</span> and it is one the force of
  which we believe ought to be duly considered by every individual, that all men are created equal,
  and that all have the privilege of thinking for themselves upon all matters relative to conscience.
  Consequently, then, we are not disposed, had we the power, to deprive any one of exercising that
  free independence of mind<span class="footRef">6</span> which heaven has so graciously bestowed upon the human family<span class="footRef">7</span> as
  one of its choicest gifts; but we take the liberty (and this we have a right to do) of looking at this
  order of things a few moments, and contrasting it with the order of God<span class="footRef">8</span> as we find it in the sacred
  Scriptures. In this review, however, we shall present the points as we consider they were really
  designed by the great Giver to be understood, and the happy results arising from a performance of
  the requirements of heaven as revealed to every one who obeys them; and the consequence attending
  a false construction, a misrepresentation, or a forced meaning that was never designed in the mind
  of the Lord<span class="footRef">9</span> when He condescended to speak from the heavens to men<span class="footRef">10</span> for their salvation.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">Obedience to Governments Necessary</div>
  <p class="std">All regularly organized and well established governments have certain laws by which, more or
  less, the innocent are protected and the guilty punished. The fact admitted that certain laws are good,
  equitable and just, ought to be binding upon the individual who admits this, and lead him to observe
  in the strictest manner an obedience to those laws. These laws when</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/22-23" target="_blank">Acts 17:22-23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/10,15" target="_blank">Morm. 9:10,15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/17" target="_blank">3 Ne. 11:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/145/13" target="_blank">Ps. 145:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/4/3" target="_blank">Dan. 4:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/27" target="_blank">Dan. 7:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/11" target="_blank">2 Pet. 1:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/13/37" target="_blank">1 Ne. 13:37</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/129/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 129:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/77" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:77</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/2/4" target="_blank">Alma 2:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/6/5" target="_blank">Alma 6:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/3/20" target="_blank">Morm. 3:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/6/1" target="_blank">Alma 6:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/8/18" target="_blank">Hel. 8:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/lev/24/12" target="_blank">Lev. 24:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/16" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 68:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/102/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 102:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/4/26" target="_blank">2 Ne. 4:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1000" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1 Endnote</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
