<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="83"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs82.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs84.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 83</div>
  <p class="cont">good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, if they shall fall away, to renew them again
  unto repentance, seeing they crucify to themselves the Son of God afresh, and put Him to an open
  shame.&rdquo;  (Heb. 6:1–6).<span class="footRef">1</span> * * *</p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH, JUN., M&amp;A, Sept. 1, 1835, also DHC 2:253–259.</p>
  <div class="topic">To the Elders of the Church of the Latter-day Saints</div>
  <p class="std">At the close of my letter in the September number of the <i>Messenger and Advocate</i> I promised
  to continue the subject there commenced. I do so with a hope that it may be a benefit and a means
  of assistance in the labors of the Elders, while they are combating the prejudices of a crooked and
  perverse generation,<span class="footRef">2</span> by having in their possession the facts of my religious principles, which are
  misrepresented by almost all those whose crafts are in danger<span class="footRef">3</span> by the same; and also, to aid those
  who are anxiously inquiring, and have been excited to do so from rumor, to ascertain correctly what
  my principles are. I have been drawn into this course of proceeding by persecution, that is brought
  upon us from false rumors and misrepresentations concerning my sentiments.</p>
  <div class="topic">Righteousness to Sweep the Earth</div>
  <p class="std">But to proceed. In the letter alluded to, the principles of repentance and baptism for the
  remission of sins were not only set forth, but many passages of scripture were quoted, clearly
  elucidating the subject; let me add, I do positively rely upon the truth of those principles inculcated
  in the New Testament, and then pass on from the above-named items, to the item or subject of the
  gathering, and show my views upon this point. It is a principle I esteem to be of the greatest
  importance to those who are looking for salvation in this generation, or in these, that may be called,
  &ldquo;the latter times.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> All that the prophets that have written, from the days of righteous Abel,<span class="footRef">5</span> down
  to the last man that has left any testimony on record for our consideration, in speaking of the
  salvation of Israel in the last days,<span class="footRef">6</span> goes directly to show that it consists in the work of the gathering.</p>
  <p class="std">First, I shall begin by quoting from the prophecy of Enoch, speaking of the last days:
  &ldquo;Righteousness will I send down out</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/6/1-6" target="_blank">Heb. 6:1-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/32/5" target="_blank">Deut. 32:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 33:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/34/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 34:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/16/16-24" target="_blank">Acts 16:16-24</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/24-28" target="_blank">Acts 19:24-28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1000" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1 Endnote</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/4/1" target="_blank">1 Tim. 4:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/15/12" target="_blank">Hel. 15:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/23/35" target="_blank">Matt. 23:35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/38/8,16" target="_blank">Ezek. 38:8,16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hosea/3/5" target="_blank">Hosea 3:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/18" target="_blank">1 Ne. 15:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/5" target="_blank">2 Ne. 3:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 39:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/113/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 113:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/22" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:22</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
