<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="346"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs345.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs347.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 346</div>
  <p class="cont"><i>he was once a man like us; yea, that God himself, the Father of us all,</i><span class="footRef">1</span> <i>dwelt on an earth, the same
  as Jesus Christ himself did; and I will show it from the Bible.</i></p>
  <div class="topic">Power of the Father and the Son</div>
  <p class="std">I wish I was in a suitable place to tell it, and that I had the trump of an archangel,<span class="footRef">2</span> so that I could
  tell the story in such a manner that persecution would cease for ever. What did Jesus say? (Mark it,
  Elder Rigdon!) The Scriptures inform us that Jesus said, As the Father hath power in Himself, even
  so hath the Son power<span class="footRef">3</span>&mdash;to do what? Why, what the Father did.<span class="footRef">4</span> The answer is obvious&mdash;in a
  manner to lay down His body and take it up again.<span class="footRef">5</span> Jesus, what are you going to do?<span class="footRef">6</span> To lay down
  my life as my Father did, and take it up again.<span class="footRef">7</span> Do we believe it? If you do not believe it, you do not
  believe the Bible.<span class="textFootRef">a</span> The Scriptures say it, and I defy all the learning and wisdom and all the combined
  powers of earth and hell<span class="footRef">8</span> together to refute it.</p>
  <p class="std">Here, then, is eternal life&mdash;to know the only wise and true God;<span class="footRef">9</span> and you have got to learn how
  to be Gods yourselves, and to be kings and priests to God,<span class="footRef">10</span> the same as all Gods have done before
  you,<span class="textFootRef">b</span> namely, by going from one</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/6" target="_blank">Eph. 4:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/7/27" target="_blank">Mosiah 7:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 27:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/38" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:38</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/1" target="_blank">Alma 29:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/26" target="_blank">John 5:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/19" target="_blank">John 5:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/17-18" target="_blank">John 10:17-18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/19" target="_blank">John 5:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/17-18" target="_blank">John 10:17-18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/16" target="_blank">Alma 37:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/34" target="_blank">D&amp;C 6:34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/3" target="_blank">John 17:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/24" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/6" target="_blank">Rev. 1:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/10" target="_blank">Rev. 5:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/20/6" target="_blank">Rev. 20:6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>The argument here made by the Prophet is very much strengthened by the following passage: &ldquo;The Son can do nothing of himself, but what he seeth the Father do;
        for what things soever he [the Father] doeth, these also doeth the Son likewise.&rdquo; (St. John 5:19).</p>
    
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">b</span>Perhaps no passage in the Prophet&rsquo;s discourse has given more offense than the one here noted, and yet men are coming to think and feel the truth of what he said. Henry Drummond, for instance (following the Prophet by half a century), in his really great work, <i>Natural Law In the Spiritual World,</i> in the chapter on Growth, wherein he points out the difference between the merely moral man and one whose life has been touched by the spiritual power of God, and so received something that the merely moral man has not received, says &ldquo;The end of salvation is perfection, the Christ-like mind, character and life. * * * Therefore the man who has within himself this great formative agent, Life [spiritual life] is nearer the end than the man who has morality alone. The latter can never reach perfection, the former <i>must.</i> For the life must develop out according to its type
        and being a germ of the Christ-life, <i>it must unfold into a Christ</i>.&rdquo; Joseph Smith&rsquo;s doctrine means no more than this.</p>
      <p class="std">Sir Oliver Lodge says much to the same effect in the following passage on &ldquo;Christianity and Science&rdquo; (<i>The Hibbert Journal</i>, April 1906):</p>
      <p class="std">It is orthodox therefore to maintain that Christ&rsquo;s birth was miraculous and his death portentous, that he continued in existence otherwise than as we men continue, that his very body rose and ascended into heaven,&mdash;whatever that collocation of words may mean. But I suggest that such an attempt</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
