<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="55"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs54.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs56.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 55</div>
  <p class="cont">reward to all who obey, predicated upon the fact that they are really the promises of a Being who
  cannot lie,<span class="footRef">1</span> One who is abundantly able to fulfill every tittle of His word:<span class="footRef">2</span> and if man were as well
  prepared, or could be as well prepared, to meet God<span class="footRef">3</span> without their ever having been given in the first
  instance, why were they ever given? for certainly, in that case they can now do him no good.</p>
  <div class="topic">All Governments Have Laws</div>
  <p class="std">As we previously remarked, all well established and properly organized governments have
  certain fixed and prominent laws for the regulation and management of the same. If man has grown
  to wisdom and is capable of discerning the propriety of laws to govern nations, what less can be
  expected from the Ruler and Upholder of the universe? Can we suppose that He has a kingdom
  without laws?<span class="footRef">4</span> Or do we believe that it is composed of an innumerable company of beings who are
  entirely beyond all law? Consequently have need of nothing to govern or regulate them? Would not
  such ideas be a reproach to our Great Parent, and at variance with His glorious intelligence? Would
  it not be asserting that man had found out a secret beyond Deity? That he had learned that it was
  good to have laws, while God after existing from eternity and having power to create man, had not
  found out that it was proper to have laws for His government? We admit that God is the great source
  and fountain from whence proceeds all good;<span class="footRef">5</span> that He is perfect intelligence, and that His wisdom
  is alone sufficient to govern and regulate the mighty creations and worlds which shine and blaze
  with such magnificence and splendor over our heads, as though touched with His finger and moved
  by His Almighty word.<span class="footRef">6</span> And if so, it is done and regulated by law; for without law all must certainly
  fall into chaos. If, then, we admit that God is the source of all wisdom and understanding,<span class="footRef">7</span> we must
  admit that by His direct inspiration He has taught man that law is necessary in order to govern and
  regulate His own immediate interest and welfare; for this reason, that law is beneficial to promote
  peace and happiness among men. And as before remarked, God is the source from whence proceeds
  all good; and if man is benefited by law, then certainly, law is good; and if law is good, then law,
  or the principle of it emanated from God; for God is the source of all good;<span class="footRef">8</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/titus/1/2" target="_blank">Titus 1:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/62/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 62:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/18" target="_blank">Matt. 5:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/28" target="_blank">Alma 5:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/24" target="_blank">Alma 12:24</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/32" target="_blank">Alma 34:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/36" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/8/26" target="_blank">Ether 8:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/12/28" target="_blank">Ether 12:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/46" target="_blank">1 Ne. 17:46</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/31/3" target="_blank">Ex. 31:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/4/29" target="_blank">1 Kgs. 4:29</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/1/17" target="_blank">Dan. 1:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/26/35" target="_blank">Alma 26:35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/12,24" target="_blank">Moro. 7:12,24</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
