<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="248"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs247.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs249.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 248</div>
  <p class="cont">their own tongues. The gifts of God are all useful in their place,<span class="footRef">1</span> but when they are applied to that
  which God does not intend,<span class="footRef">2</span> they prove an injury, a snare and a curse instead of a blessing.<span class="footRef">3</span> We may
  some future time enter more fully into this subject, but shall let this suffice<span class="footRef">4</span> for the present. (June
  15, 1842.) DHC 5:26–32.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Government of God</div>
  <div class="topic centerEmphasis">An Editorial by the Prophet on the Failure of Man-made</div>
  <div class="topic centerEmphasis">Governments and the Right of God to Rule</div>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std">The government of the Almighty has always been very dissimilar to the governments of men,
  whether we refer to His religious government, or to the government of nations. The government of
  God has always tended to promote peace, unity, harmony, strength, and happiness; while that of man
  has been productive of confusion, disorder, weakness, and misery.</p>
  <div class="topic">Man&rsquo;s Government Brings Misery and Destruction</div>
  <p class="std">The greatest acts of the mighty men have been to depopulate nations and to overthrow
  kingdoms; and whilst they have exalted themselves and become glorious, it has been at the expense
  of the lives of the innocent,<span class="footRef">5</span> the blood of the oppressed, the moans of the widow, and the tears of
  the orphan.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">Egypt, Babylon, Greece, Persia, Carthage, Rome&mdash;each was raised to dignity amidst the clash
  of arms and the din of war; and whilst their triumphant leaders led forth their victorious armies to
  glory and victory, their ears were saluted with the groans of the dying and the misery and distress
  of the human family; before them the earth was a paradise, and the behind them a desolate
  wilderness; their kingdoms were founded in carnage and bloodshed, and sustained by oppression,
  tyranny, and despotism. The designs of God, on the other hand, have been to promote the universal
  good of the universal world; to establish peace<span class="footRef">7</span> and good will among men;<span class="footRef">8</span> to promote the principles
  of eternal truth; to bring about a state of things that shall unite man to his fellow man; cause the
  world to &ldquo;beat their swords into plowshares, and their spears into pruning hooks,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">9</span> make the nations
  of the earth dwell in peace, and to bring about the millennial glory, when &ldquo;the earth shall yield</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/26" target="_blank">D&amp;C 46:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/num/22/2-7" target="_blank">Num. 22:2-7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/23/14" target="_blank">Jer. 23:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/8/18-20" target="_blank">Acts 8:18-20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/3/26" target="_blank">Deut. 3:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/15" target="_blank">D&amp;C 130:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/66" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:66</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/29/2" target="_blank">Prov. 29:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/7/5" target="_blank">Hel. 7:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/8/40" target="_blank">Morm. 8:40</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/9/7" target="_blank">Isa. 9:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/w_of_m/1/18" target="_blank">W of M 1:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/14" target="_blank">Luke 2:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/2/4" target="_blank">Isa. 2:4</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
