<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="82"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs81.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs83.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 82</div>
  <p class="std">Therefore we believe in preaching the doctrine of repentance<span class="footRef">1</span> in all the world,<span class="footRef">2</span> both to old and
  young,<span class="footRef">3</span> rich and poor,<span class="footRef">4</span> bond and free,<span class="footRef">5</span> as we shall endeavor to show hereafter how, and in what
  manner, and how far, it is binding on the consciences of mankind, making proper distinctions
  between old and young, men, women, children and servants. But we discover, in order to be
  benefited by the doctrine of repentance, we must believe in obtaining the remission of sins. And in
  order to obtain the remission of sins, we must believe in the doctrine of baptism in the name of the
  Lord Jesus Christ. And if we believe in baptism for the remission of sins, we may expect a
  fulfillment of the promise of the Holy Ghost, for the promise extends to all whom the Lord our God
  shall call;<span class="footRef">6</span> and hath He not surely said, as you will find in the last chapter of Revelation&mdash;&ldquo;And the
  Spirit and the bride say, Come. And let him that heareth say, Come. And let him that is athirst come.
  And whosoever will let him take the water of life freely&rdquo; (Rev. 22:17).<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <p class="std">Again, the Savior says, &ldquo;Come unto me, all ye that labor, and are heavy laden, and I will give
  you rest. Take my yoke upon you, and learn of me; for I am meek and lowly in heart: and ye shall
  find rest unto your souls. For my yoke is easy, and my burden is light&rdquo; (Matt. 11:28, 29, 30).<span class="footRef">8</span></p>
  <p class="std">Again, Isaiah says, &ldquo;Look unto me, and be ye saved, all the ends of the earth: for I am God, and
  there is none else. I have sworn by myself, the word is gone out of my mouth in righteousness, and
  shall not return. That unto me every knee shall bow, every tongue shall swear. Surely shall one say,
  in the Lord have I righteousness and strength: even to Him shall men come; and all that are incensed
  against Him shall be ashamed&rdquo; (Isaiah 45:22–24).<span class="footRef">9</span></p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">Not Leaving the First Principles</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Therefore, leaving the principles of the doctrine of Christ, let us go on unto perfection; not
  laying again the foundation of repentance from dead works, and of faith toward God, of the doctrine
  of baptisms, and of laying on of hands, and of resurrection of the dead, and of eternal judgment. And
  this will we do, if God permit. For it is impossible for those who were once enlightened, and have
  tasted of the heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghost, and have tasted the</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/16/15" target="_blank">Mark 16:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/49" target="_blank">Alma 5:49</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/49/2" target="_blank">Ps. 49:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/20" target="_blank">D&amp;C 43:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/39" target="_blank">Acts 2:39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/22/17" target="_blank">Rev. 22:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/28-30" target="_blank">Matt. 11:28-30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/45/22-24" target="_blank">Isa. 45:22-24</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
