<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="125"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs124.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs126.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 125</div>
  <p class="std">After we were bartered away by Hinkle, and were taken into the militia camp, we had all the
  evidence we could have asked for that the world hated us.<span class="footRef">1</span> If there were priests among them of all
  the different sects, they hated us, and that most cordially too. If there were generals, they hated us;
  if there were colonels, they hated us; and the soldiers, and officers of every kind, hated us; and the
  most profane, blasphemous, and drunkards; and whoremongers,<span class="footRef">2</span> hated us&mdash;they all hated us, most
  cordially. And now what did they hate us for? Purely because of the testimony of Jesus Christ. Was
  it because we were liars? We know that it has been so reported by some, but it has been reported
  falsely. Was it because we have committed treason against the government in Daviess county, or
  burglary, or larceny, or arson, or any other unlawful act in Daviess county? We know that we have
  been so reported by priests, and certain lawyers, and certain judges, who are the instigators, aiders,
  and abettors of a certain gang of murderers and robbers, who have been carrying on a scheme of
  mobocracy to uphold their priestcraft,<span class="footRef">3</span> against the Saints of the last days;<span class="footRef">4</span> and for a number of yours
  have tried, by a well contemplated and premeditated scheme, to put down by physical power a
  system of religion that all the world, by their mutual attainments, and by any fair means whatever,
  were not able to resist.</p>
  <div class="topic">Accused by False Witnesses</div>
  <p class="std">Hence mobbers were encouraged by priests and Levites, by the Pharisees, by the Sadducees,
  and Essenes, and Herodians,<span class="footRef">5</span> and the most worthless, abandoned, and debauched, lawless, and
  inhuman, and the most beastly set of men that the earth can boast of&mdash;and indeed a parallel cannot
  be found anywhere else&mdash;to gather together to steal, to plunder, to starve, and to exterminate, and
  burn the houses of the &ldquo;Mormons.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">These are characters that, by their treasonable and overt acts, have desolated and laid waste
  Daviess county. These are the characters that would fain make all the world believe that we are
  guilty of the above named acts. But they represent us falsely; we stood in our own defense, and we
  believe that no man of us acted only in a just, a lawful, and a righteous retaliation against such
  marauders.</p>
  <p class="std">We say unto you, that we have not committed treason, nor any other unlawful act in Daviess
  county. Was it for</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/18" target="_blank">John 15:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/3/13" target="_blank">1 Jn. 3:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/22/15" target="_blank">Rev. 22:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/103" target="_blank">D&amp;C 76:103</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/1/16" target="_blank">Alma 1:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 64:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/89/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 89:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/3/6" target="_blank">Mark 3:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/12/13" target="_blank">Mark 12:13</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
