<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="196"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs195.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs197.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 196</div>
  <p class="cont">harvest, they will do well to be at the place of labor in good season in the morning, bringing all
  necessary tools, according to their occupation, and those who have teams bring them also, unless
  otherwise advised by the Temple Committee. Should any one be detained from his labor by
  unavoidable circumstances on the day appointed, let him labor the next day, or the first day possible.</p>
  <p class="std">N. B.&mdash;The captains of the respective wards are particularly requested to be at the place of labor
  on their respective days, and keep an accurate account of each man&rsquo;s work, and be ready to exhibit
  a list of the same when called for.</p>
  <p class="std">The heart of the Trustee is daily made to rejoice in the good feelings of the brethren, made
  manifest in their exertion to carry forward the work of the Lord,<span class="footRef">1</span> and rear His Temple; and it is
  hoped that neither planting, sowing, or reaping will hereafter be made to interfere with the
  regulations hinted at above.</p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH, Trustee in Trust.</p>
  <p class="right">(February 21, 1842.) DHC 4:517.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Prophet&rsquo;s Sermon on Life and Death; the Resurrection</div>
  <div class="topic">and the Salvation of Children</div>
  <p class="std">President Smith read the 14th chapter of Revelation,<span class="footRef">2</span> and said&mdash;We have again the warning
  voice<span class="footRef">3</span> sounded in our midst, which shows the uncertainty of human life; and in my leisure moments
  I have meditated upon the subject, and asked the question, why it is that infants, innocent children,
  are taken away from us, especially those that seem to be the most intelligent and interesting. The
  strongest reasons that present themselves to my mind are these: This world is a very wicked world;<span class="footRef">4</span>
  and it is a proverb that the &ldquo;world grows weaker and wiser&rdquo;; if that is the case, the world grows more
  wicked and corrupt. In the earlier ages of the world<span class="footRef">5</span> a righteous man, and a man of God and of
  intelligence, had a better chance to do good, to be believed and received than at the present day; but
  in these days such a man is much opposed and persecuted by most of the inhabitants of the earth,<span class="footRef">6</span>
  and he has much sorrow to pass through here. The Lord takes many away even in infancy, that they
  may escape the envy of man, and the sorrows and evils of this present world; they were too pure,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/51/10" target="_blank">Jer. 51:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/58" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/1-20" target="_blank">Rev. 14:1-20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/41" target="_blank">D&amp;C 38:41</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/37" target="_blank">D&amp;C 63:37</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/36" target="_blank">Moses 7:36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/7/7-8" target="_blank">Hel. 7:7-8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/33/14" target="_blank">Ps. 33:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/17/2" target="_blank">Rev. 17:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/1/14" target="_blank">1 Ne. 1:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/6,8,13,17,34" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:6,8,13,17,34</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/21,25" target="_blank">Moses 7:21,25</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
