<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="144"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs143.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs145.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 144</div>
  <p class="cont">days are known, and thy years shall not be numbered less; therefore, fear not what man can do, for
  God shall be with you<span class="footRef">1</span> forever and ever.]<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std">Now, brethren, I would suggest for the consideration of the conference, its being carefully and
  wisely understood by the council or conferences that our brethren scattered abroad,<span class="footRef">3</span> who understood
  the spirit of the gathering,<span class="footRef">4</span> that they fall into the places and refuge of safety<span class="footRef">5</span> that God shall open
  unto them, between Kirtland and Far West. Those from the east and from the west, and from far
  countries,<span class="footRef">6</span> let them fall in somewhere between those two boundaries, in the most safe and quiet
  places they can find; and let this be the present understanding, until God shall open a more effectual
  door<span class="footRef">7</span> for us for further considerations.</p>
  <p class="std">And again, we further suggest for the considerations of the Council, that there be no
  organization of large bodies upon common stock principles, in property, or of large companies of
  firms, until the Lord shall signify it in a proper manner, as it opens such a dreadful field for the
  avaricious, the indolent, and the corrupt hearted to prey upon the innocent and virtuous, and honest.</p>
  <p class="std">We have reason to believe that many things were introduced among the Saints before God had
  signified the times; and notwithstanding the principles and plans may have been good, yet aspiring
  men, or in other words, men who had not the substance of godliness<span class="footRef">8</span> about them, perhaps undertook
  to handle edged tools. Children, you know, are fond of tools, while they are not yet able to use them.</p>
  <p class="std">Time and experience, however, are the only safe remedies against such evils. There are many
  teachers, but, perhaps, not many fathers.<span class="footRef">9</span> There are times coming when God will signify<span class="footRef">10</span> many
  things which are expedient for the well-being of the Saints; but the times have not yet come, but will
  come, as fast as there can be found place and reception for them.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Gathering of False Reports</div>
  <p class="std">[And again, we would suggest for your consideration the propriety of all the Saints gathering
  up a knowledge of all the facts and sufferings and abuses put upon them by the people of this state;
  and also of all the property and amount of damages which they have sustained, both of character and
  personal</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/118/6" target="_blank">Ps. 118:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/122/1-9" target="_blank">D&amp;C 122:1-9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/11/52" target="_blank">John 11:52</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/1/1" target="_blank">James 1:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/21/1" target="_blank">1 Ne. 21:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/22" target="_blank">Alma 13:22</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/115/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 115:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/34/16" target="_blank">Isa. 34:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/66" target="_blank">D&amp;C 45:66</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/8/9" target="_blank">Isa. 8:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/10/9" target="_blank">Zech. 10:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 38:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/16/9" target="_blank">1 Cor. 16:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/100/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 100:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/3/5" target="_blank">2 Tim. 3:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/4/15" target="_blank">1 Cor. 4:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/1/11" target="_blank">1 Pet. 1:11</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
