<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="294"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs293.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs295.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 294</div>
  <p class="cont">precisely according to the plain reading of the revelations. I give this as a key to the elders of Israel.
  The independent beast is a beast that dwells in heaven, abstract [apart] from the human family. The
  beast that rose up out of the sea<span class="footRef">1</span> should be translated the image of a beast, as I have referred to it in
  Daniel&rsquo;s vision.</p>
  <p class="std">I have said more than I ever did before, except once at Ramus, and then up starts the little fellow
  (Charles Thompson) and stuffed me like a cock-turkey with the prophecies of Daniel, and crammed
  it down my throat with his finger. (April 8, 1843.) DHC 5:339–345.</p>
  <div class="topic">REMARKS OF THE PROPHET ON THE DEATH OF LORENZO D. BARNES</div>
  <div class="topic">The Resurrection</div>
  <p class="std">Almost all who have fallen in these last days in the Church have fallen in a strange land.<span class="footRef">2</span> This
  is a strange land to those who have come from a distance. We should cultivate sympathy for the
  afflicted among us.<span class="footRef">3</span> If there is a place on earth where men should cultivate the spirit and pour in the
  oil and wine<span class="footRef">4</span> in the bosoms of the afflicted, it is in this place; and this spirit is manifest here; and
  although a stranger and afflicted<span class="footRef">5</span> when he arrives, he finds a brother and a friend ready to administer
  to his necessities.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">I would esteem it one of the greatest blessings, if I am to be afflicted in this world, to have my
  lot cast where I can find brothers and friends all around me. But this is not the thing I referred to:
  it is to have the privilege of having our dead buried on the land where God has appointed to gather
  His Saints together, and where there will be none but Saints, where they may have the privilege of
  laying their bodies where the Son of Man will make His appearance,<span class="footRef">7</span> and where they may hear the
  sound of the trump<span class="footRef">8</span> that shall call them forth to behold Him, that in the morn of the resurrection they
  may come forth in a body, and come up out of their graves and strike hands immediately in eternal
  glory and felicity,<span class="footRef">9</span> rather than be scattered thousands of miles apart. There is something good and
  sacred to me in this thing. The place where a man is buried is sacred to me. This subject is made
  mention of in the Book of Mormon<span class="footRef">10</span> and other scriptures. Even to the aborigines of this land, the
  burying places of their fathers are more sacred than anything else.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/1" target="_blank">Rev. 13:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/7/6" target="_blank">Acts 7:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/26/36" target="_blank">Alma 26:36</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/16" target="_blank">Abr. 1:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/13" target="_blank">James 5:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/17/7" target="_blank">3 Ne. 17:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 105:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/34" target="_blank">Luke 10:34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/15/13" target="_blank">Gen. 15:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/20/34" target="_blank">Acts 20:34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/93-98" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:93-98</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/52" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:52</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/13" target="_blank">Morm. 9:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/13,26" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:13,26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/18" target="_blank">D&amp;C 43:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/45/45" target="_blank">D&amp;C 45:45</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 77:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/14/22" target="_blank">Ether 14:22</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
