<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="215"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs214.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs216.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 215</div>
  <p class="cont">be known by, and by his contradicting a former revelation.<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <p class="std">We have also had brethren and sisters who have written revelations, and who have started
  forward to lead this Church. Such was a young boy in Kirtland, Isaac Russell, of Missouri, and
  Gladden Bishop, and Oliver Olney of Nauvoo. The boy is now living with his parents who have
  submitted to the laws of the Church.<span class="footRef">2</span> Mr. Russell stayed in Far West, from whence he was to go to
  the Rocky Mountains, led by three Nephites;<span class="footRef">3</span> but the Nephites never came, and his friends forsook
  him, all but some of the blood relations, who have since been nearly destroyed by the mob. Mr.
  Bishop was tried by the High Council, his papers examined, condemned and burned, and he cut off
  the Church. He acknowledged the justice of the decision, and said &ldquo;that he now saw his error, for
  if he had been governed by the revelations given before, he might have known that no man was to
  write revelations for the Church, but Joseph Smith,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> and begged to be prayed for,<span class="footRef">5</span> and forgiven by
  the brethren. Mr. Olney has also been tried by the High Council and disfellowshiped, because he
  would not have his writings tested by the word of God;<span class="footRef">6</span> evidently proving that he loves darkness
  rather than light, because his deeds are evil.<span class="footRef">7</span>  (April 1, 1842) DHC 4:571–581.</p>
  <div class="topic">Remarks of the Prophet at the Funeral of Ephraim Marks</div>
  <p class="std">The Saints in Nauvoo assembled at the house of President Marks, at an early hour in the
  morning, to pay their last respects to the body of Ephraim Marks, son of President William Marks,
  who died on the evening of the 7th. A large procession formed and walked to the Grove, where a
  numerous congregation had assembled. President Joseph Smith spoke upon the occasion with much
  feeling and interest. Among his remarks he said, &ldquo;It is a very solemn and awful time. I never felt
  more solemn; it calls to mind the death of my oldest brother, Alvin,<span class="footRef">8</span> who died in New York, and my
  youngest brother, Don Carlos Smith,<span class="footRef">9</span> who died in Nauvoo. It has been hard for me to live on earth
  and see these young men upon whom we have leaned for support and comfort taken from us in the
  midst of their youth. Yes, it has been hard to be reconciled to these things. I have sometimes thought
  that I should have felt more reconciled to have been called away myself if it had been the will of
  God; yet I know we ought to be still and know it is of God,<span class="footRef">10</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/28/11-12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 28:11-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/83/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 83:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/79" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:79</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/37" target="_blank">4 Ne. 1:37</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/5/10" target="_blank">D&amp;C 5:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/18/30" target="_blank">3 Ne. 18:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/8/20" target="_blank">Isa. 8:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/3/19" target="_blank">John 3:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/21" target="_blank">D&amp;C 10:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/45" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:45</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/137/5-6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 137:5-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/4" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/46/10" target="_blank">Ps. 46:10</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
