<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="131"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs130.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs132.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 131</div>
  <p class="cont">our homes and smitten without cause.<span class="footRef">1</span> We mutually understand that if the inhabitants of the state
  of Missouri had let the Saints alone, and had been as desirable of peace as they were, there would
  have been nothing but peace and quietude in the state unto this day; we should not have been in this
  hell, surrounded with demons (if not those who are damned, they are those who shall be damned)
  and where we are compelled to hear nothing but blasphemous oaths, and witness a scene of
  blasphemy, and drunkenness and hypocrisy, and debaucheries of every description.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Persecution of the Saints</div>
  <p class="std">And again the cries of orphans and widows<span class="footRef">2</span> would not have ascended up to God against them.
  Nor would innocent blood have stained the soil of Missouri.<span class="footRef">3</span> But oh!  the unrelenting hand!  The
  inhumanity and murderous disposition of this people!  It shocks all nature; it beggars and defies all
  description; it is a tale of woe; a lamentable tale; yea a sorrowful tale; too much to tell; too much for
  contemplation; too much for human beings; it cannot be found among the heathens; it cannot be
  found among the nations where kings and tyrants are enthroned; it cannot be found among the
  savages of the wilderness; yea, and I think it cannot be found among the wild and ferocious beasts
  of the forest&mdash;that a man should be mangled for sport!  women be robbed of all that they have&mdash;their
  last morsel for subsistence, and then be violated to gratify the hellish desires<span class="footRef">4</span> of the mob, and finally
  left to perish with their helpless offspring clinging around their necks.</p>
  <p class="std">But this is not all. After a man is dead, he must be dug up from his grave and mangled to pieces,
  for no other purpose than to gratify their spleen against the religion of God.</p>
  <p class="std">They practice these things upon the Saints, who have done them no wrong, who are innocent
  and virtuous; who loved the Lord their God,<span class="footRef">5</span> and were willing to forsake all things for Christ&rsquo;s
  sake.<span class="footRef">6</span> These things are awful to relate, but they are verily true. It must needs be that offenses come,
  but woe unto them by whom they come.<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <div class="topic">A Righteous Appeal to Heaven</div>
  <p class="std">[Oh God! where art Thou?<span class="footRef">8</span> And where is the pavilion that covereth Thy hiding place? How
  long shall<span class="footRef">9</span> Thy hand</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/35/7" target="_blank">Ps. 35:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/1/11" target="_blank">Prov. 1:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/lam/3/52" target="_blank">Lam. 3:52</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/15/25" target="_blank">John 15:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/64/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 64:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:49</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:49</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/36" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/9/8-10" target="_blank">Moro. 9:8-10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/29/46" target="_blank">Ex. 29:46</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/4/13" target="_blank">Alma 4:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/18/7" target="_blank">Matt. 18:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 105:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/1-6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 121:1-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/14/26" target="_blank">Alma 14:26</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
