<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="85"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs84.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs86.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 85</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;And it shall come to pass, when all these things are come upon thee, the blessing and the curse
  which I have set before thee, and thou shalt call them to mind, among all the nations whither the
  Lord thy God hath driven thee, and shalt return unto the Lord thy God, and shalt obey His voice,
  according to all that I command thee, this day, thou and thy children, with all thine heart, and with
  all thy soul, that then the Lord thy God will turn thy captivity, and have compassion upon thee, and
  will return and gather thee from all the nations whither the Lord thy God hath scattered thee. If any
  of thine be driven out unto the outmost parts of heaven, from thence will the Lord thy God gather
  thee, and from thence will He fetch thee (Deut. 30:1–4).<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The New Jerusalem</div>
  <p class="std">It has been said by many of the learned and wise men, or historians, that the Indians or
  aborigines of this continent, are of the scattered tribes of Israel. It has been conjectured by many
  others, that the aborigines of this continent are not of the tribes of Israel, but the ten tribes have been
  led away into some unknown regions of the north.<span class="footRef">2</span> Let this be as it may, the prophecy I have just
  quoted &ldquo;will fetch them,&rdquo; in the last days, and place them in the land which their fathers possessed.
  And you will find in the 7th verse of the 30th chapter, quoted, &ldquo;And the Lord thy God will put all
  these curses upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which persecuted thee.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <p class="std">Many may say that this scripture is fulfilled, but let them mark carefully what the prophet says:
  &ldquo;If any are driven out unto the outmost parts of heaven,&rdquo; (Which must mean the breadth of the
  earth). Now this promise is good to any, if there should be such, that are driven out, even in the last
  days, therefore, the children of the fathers have claim unto this day. And if these curses are to be laid
  over on the heads of their enemies, wo be unto the Gentiles. (See Book of Mormon, 3 Nephi, Chap.
  16, current edition). &ldquo;Wo unto the unbelieving of the Gentiles, saith the Father.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> And again (see
  Book of Mormon, 3 Nephi 20:22, current edition, which says), &ldquo;Behold this people will I establish
  in this land, unto the fulfilling of the covenant which I made with your father Jacob, and it shall be
  a New Jerusalem.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span> Now we learn from the Book of Mormon</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/30/1-4" target="_blank">Deut. 30:1-4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/110/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 110:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/30/7" target="_blank">Deut. 30:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/16/8" target="_blank">3 Ne. 16:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/20/22" target="_blank">3 Ne. 20:22</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
