<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="249"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs248.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs250.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 249</div>
  <p class="cont">its increase,<span class="footRef">1</span> resume its paradisean glory,<span class="footRef">2</span> and become as the garden of the Lord.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Failure of the Governments of Men</div>
  <p class="std">The great and wise of ancient days have failed in all their attempts to promote eternal power,
  peace and happiness. Their nations have crumbled to pieces; their thrones have been cast down in
  their turn, and their cities, and their mightiest works of art have been annihilated; or their dilapidated
  towers, or time-worn monuments have left us but feeble traces of their former magnificence and
  ancient grandeur. They proclaim as with a voice of thunder,<span class="footRef">4</span> those imperishable truths&mdash;that man&rsquo;s
  strength is weakness,<span class="footRef">5</span> his wisdom is folly,<span class="footRef">6</span> his glory is his shame.<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <p class="std">Monarchial, aristocratical, and republican governments of their various kinds and grades, have,
  in their turn, been raised to dignity, and prostrated in the dust. The plans of the greatest politicians,
  the wisest senators, and most profound statesmen have been exploded; and the proceedings of the
  greatest chieftains, the bravest generals, and the wisest kings have fallen to the ground. Nation has
  succeeded nation, and we have inherited nothing but their folly.<span class="footRef">8</span> History records their puerile plans,
  their short-lived glory, their feeble intellect and their ignoble deeds.</p>
  <div class="topic">Has Man Increased in Intelligence?</div>
  <p class="std">Have we increased in knowledge or intelligence? Where is there a man that can step forth and
  alter the destiny of nations and promote the happiness of the world? Or where is there a kingdom
  or nation that can promote the universal happiness of its own subjects, or even their general
  well-being? Our nation, which possesses greater resources than any other, is rent, from center to
  circumference, with party strife, political intrigues, and sectional interest; our counselors are panic
  stricken, our legislators are astonished, and our senators are confounded, our merchants are
  paralyzed, our tradesmen are disheartened, our mechanics out of employ, our farmers distressed, and
  our poor crying for bread,<span class="footRef">9</span> our banks are broken, our credit ruined, and our states overwhelmed in
  debt, yet we are, and have been in peace.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/67/6" target="_blank">Ps. 67:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/10" target="_blank">A of F 1:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/13/10" target="_blank">Gen. 13:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/51/3" target="_blank">Isa. 51:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/45" target="_blank">1 Ne. 17:45</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/1/20" target="_blank">1 Cor. 1:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/3/19" target="_blank">Philip. 3:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/14/18" target="_blank">Prov. 14:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/132/15" target="_blank">Ps. 132:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/22/9" target="_blank">Prov. 22:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/58/7" target="_blank">Isa. 58:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
