<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="120"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs119.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs121.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 120</div>
  <p class="cont">disapprove of the custom, which has gained in the world, and has been practiced among us, to our
  great mortification, in marrying in five or six weeks, or even in two or three months, after the death
  of their companion. We believe that due respect ought to be had to the memory of the dead, and the
  feelings of both friends and children.<span class="textFootRef">a</span></p>
  <p class="std">Eighth&mdash;&ldquo;Can they [the Mormons] raise the dead?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">No, nor can any other people that now lives, or ever did live. But God can raise the dead,<span class="footRef">1</span>
  through man as an instrument.</p>
  <p class="std">Ninth&mdash;&ldquo;What signs does Joseph Smith give of his divine mission?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">The signs which God is pleased to let him give, according as His wisdom thinks best, in order
  that He may judge the world<span class="footRef">2</span> agreeably to His own plan.</p>
  <p class="std">Tenth&mdash;&ldquo;Was not Joseph Smith a money digger?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">Yes, but it was never a very profitable job for him, as he only got fourteen dollars a month for
  it.</p>
  <p class="std">Eleventh&mdash;&ldquo;Did not Joseph Smith steal his wife?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">Ask her, she was of age, she can answer for herself.<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <p class="std">Twelfth&mdash;&ldquo;Do the people have to give up their money when they join his Church?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">No other requirement than to bear their proportion of the expenses of the Church, and support
  the poor.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">Thirteenth&mdash;&ldquo;Are the Mormons abolitionists?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">No, unless delivering the people from priestcraft, and the priests from the power of Satan,<span class="footRef">5</span>
  should be considered abolition. But we do not believe in setting the negroes free.</p>
  <p class="std">Fourteenth&mdash;&ldquo;Do they not stir up the Indians to war, and to commit depredations?&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">No, and they who reported the story knew it was false when they put it in circulation. These and
  similar reports are</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/10/8" target="_blank">Matt. 10:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/8" target="_blank">Acts 26:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/7/19" target="_blank">3 Ne. 7:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/5" target="_blank">4 Ne. 1:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/100" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:100</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/96/13" target="_blank">Ps. 96:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/98/9" target="_blank">Ps. 98:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/21,23" target="_blank">John 9:21,23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/89" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:89</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/26/18" target="_blank">Acts 26:18</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>Notwithstanding this remark about due respect for both the living and the dead, the Prophet varied from this view in counseling his brother Hyrum. Hyrum Smith&rsquo;s wife Jerusha, died in October, 1837, leaving an infant daughter and a large family of small children. The Prophet told his brother Hyrum that it was the will of the Lord that he should marry without delay and take as a wife a young English girl, named Mary  Fielding, who had joined the Church through the preaching of Elder Parley P. Pratt in Toronto, Canada. Hyrum accepted this counsel from the Prophet and Mary Fielding became his wife and the mother of President Joseph F. Smith, who was born November 13, 1838.</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
