<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="212"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs211.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs213.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 212</div>
  <p class="cont">ance with many of their proceedings, and the thing never has been attempted to be denied.</p>
  <div class="topic">All This Is Wrong</div>
  <p class="std">It may be asked, where is there anything in all this that is wrong?</p>
  <p class="std">First. The church was organized by women, and God placed in the Church (first apostles,
  secondarily prophets,)<span class="footRef">1</span> and not first women; but Mr. Irving placed in his church first women
  (secondarily apostles,) and the church was founded and organized by them. A woman has no right
  to found or organize a church&mdash;God never sent them to do it.</p>
  <p class="std">Second. Those women would speak in the midst of a meeting, and rebuke Mr. Irving or any of
  the church. Now the Scripture positively says, &ldquo;Thou shalt not rebuke an Elder, but entreat him as
  a father;&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span> not only this, but they frequently accused the brethren, thus placing themselves in the seat
  of Satan, who is emphatically called &ldquo;the accuser of the brethren.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <p class="std">Third. Mr. Baxter received the spirit on asking for it, without attending to the ordinances,<span class="footRef">4</span> and
  began to prophesy, whereas the scriptural way of attaining the gift of the Holy Ghost is by baptism,
  and by laying on of hands.<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <p class="std">Fourth. As we have stated in regard to others, the spirit of the prophets is subject to the
  prophets;<span class="footRef">6</span> but those prophets were subject to the spirits, the spirits controlling their bodies at
  pleasure.</p>
  <p class="std">But it may be asked how Mr. Baxter could get a sign from a second person? To this we would
  answer, that Mr. Baxter&rsquo;s brother was under the influence of the same spirit<span class="footRef">7</span> as himself, and being
  subject to that spirit<span class="footRef">8</span> he could be easily made to speak to Mr. Baxter whatever the spirit should
  dictate; but there was not power in the spirit to heal the child.</p>
  <div class="topic">Satan May Give Manifestations in Tongues</div>
  <p class="std">Again it may be asked, how it was that they could speak in tongues if they were of the devil.
  We would answer that they could be made to speak in another tongue,<span class="footRef">9</span> as well as their own, as they
  were under the control of that spirit, and the devil can tempt the Hottentot, the Turk, the Jew, or any
  other nation; and if these men were under the influence of his spirit,<span class="footRef">10</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/28" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/5/1" target="_blank">1 Tim. 5:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/12/10" target="_blank">Rev. 12:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/2-6" target="_blank">Acts 19:2-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/32" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/34" target="_blank">Alma 34:34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/20" target="_blank">Luke 10:20</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/28/11" target="_blank">Isa. 28:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/123/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 123:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
