<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="81"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs80.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs82.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 81</div>
  <p class="cont">standing of our principles, they would have embraced them with all their hearts,<span class="footRef">1</span> and been rejoicing
  in the love of the truth.<span class="footRef">2</span> And now to show our doctrine on this subject, we shall commence with the
  first principles of the Gospel, which are faith, repentance, and baptism for the remission of sins, and
  the gift of the Holy Ghost by the laying on of the hands.<span class="footRef">3</span> This we believe to be our duty&mdash;to teach
  to all mankind the doctrine of repentance,<span class="footRef">4</span> which we shall endeavor to show from the following
  quotations:</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Then opened He their understanding, that they might understand the scriptures, and said unto
  them, Thus it is written, and thus it behooved Christ to suffer, and to rise from the dead the third day:
  and that repentance and remission of sins should be preached in His name among all nations,
  beginning at Jerusalem&rdquo; (Luke 24:45, 46, 47).<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <p class="std">By this we learn that it behooved Christ to suffer, and to be crucified, and rise again on the third
  day for the express purpose that repentance and remission of sins should be preached to all nations.</p>
  <div class="topic">Repentance</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Then Peter said unto them, Repent, and be baptized every one of you in the name of Jesus
  Christ for the remission of sins, and ye shall receive the gift of the Holy Ghost. For the promise is
  unto you, and to your children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God shall
  call&rdquo; (Acts 2:38, 39).<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">By this we learn that the promise of the Holy Ghost<span class="footRef">7</span> is made unto as many as those to whom
  the doctrine of repentance was to be preached, which was unto all nations.<span class="footRef">8</span> And we discover also,
  that the promise was to extend by lineage; for Peter says, not only unto you, but &ldquo;to your children,
  and to all that are afar off.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">9</span> From this we infer, that the promise was to continue unto their
  children&rsquo;s children, and even unto as many as the Lord their God should call.<span class="footRef">10</span> We discover here that
  we are blending two principles together in these quotations. The first is the principle of repentance,
  and the second is the principle of the remission of sins; and we learn from Peter that remission of
  sins is to be obtained by baptism in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ; and the gift of the Holy Ghost
  follows inevitably, for, says Peter, &ldquo;you shall receive the Holy Ghost.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">11</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/36/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 36:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/2/10" target="_blank">2 Thes. 2:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/4" target="_blank">A of F 1:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/25" target="_blank">D&amp;C 68:25</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/24/45-47" target="_blank">Luke 24:45-47</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38-39" target="_blank">Acts 2:38-39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/33" target="_blank">Acts 2:33</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/31/18" target="_blank">2 Ne. 31:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/14" target="_blank">Matt. 24:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/39" target="_blank">Acts 2:39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/39" target="_blank">Acts 2:39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/38" target="_blank">Acts 2:38</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
