<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="289"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs288.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs290.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 289</div>
  <p class="cont">and majesty of His kingdom?<span class="footRef">1</span> By taking a lesser figure to represent a greater, you missed it that
  time, old gentleman; but the sectarians did not know enough to detect you.</p>
  <p class="std">When God made use of the figure of a beast in visions to the prophets He did it to represent
  those kingdoms which had degenerated and become corrupt, savage and beast-like in their
  dispositions, even the degenerate kingdoms of the wicked world; but He never made use of the
  figure of a beast nor any of the brute kind to represent His kingdom.</p>
  <div class="topic">Daniel&rsquo;s Vision of Beasts</div>
  <p class="std">Daniel says (chap. 7, v. 16) when he saw the vision of the four beasts,<span class="footRef">2</span> &ldquo;I came near unto one
  of them that stood by, and asked him the truth of all this,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> the angel interpreted the vision to
  Daniel;<span class="footRef">4</span> but we find, by the interpretation that the figures of beasts had no allusion to the kingdom
  of God. You there see that the beasts are spoken of to represent the kingdoms of the world,<span class="footRef">5</span> the
  inhabitants whereof were beastly and abominable characters; they were murderers, corrupt,
  carnivorous, and brutal in their dispositions. The lion, the bear, the leopard, and the ten-horned beast
  represented the kingdoms of the world, says Daniel;<span class="footRef">6</span> for I refer to the prophets to qualify my
  observations which I make, so that the young elders who know so much, may not rise up like a flock
  of hornets and sting me. I want to keep out of such a wasp-nest.</p>
  <div class="topic">John&rsquo;s Vision of Futurity</div>
  <p class="std">There is a grand difference and distinction between the visions and figures spoken of by the
  ancient prophets, and those spoken of in the revelations of John. The things which John saw had no
  allusion to the scenes of the days of Adam, Enoch, Abraham or Jesus, only so far as is plainly
  represented by John, and clearly set forth by him. John saw that only which was lying in futurity and
  which was shortly to come to pass. See Rev. 1:1–3,<span class="footRef">7</span> which is a key to the whole subject: &ldquo;The
  revelation of Jesus Christ, which God gave unto Him, to show unto his servants things which must
  shortly come to pass; and He sent and signified it by His angel unto His servant John: who bare
  record of the word of God, and of the testimony of Jesus Christ, and of all things that he saw.
  Blessed is he that readeth, and they that hear the words of his prophecy and keep those</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/50" target="_blank">Alma 5:50</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/77" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:77</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/3" target="_blank">Dan. 7:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/16" target="_blank">Dan. 7:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/17" target="_blank">Dan. 7:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/23/17" target="_blank">Isa. 23:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/8" target="_blank">Matt. 4:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/82" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:82</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/103/7-8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 103:7-8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/32" target="_blank">D&amp;C 105:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/3-7" target="_blank">Dan. 7:3-7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/1-3" target="_blank">Rev. 1:1-3</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
