<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="230"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs229.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs231.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 230</div>
  <div class="topic">THE TEMPLE</div>
  <div class="topic">Diligence of the Saints in Building the Temple</div>
  <p class="std">This noble edifice is progressing with great rapidity; strenuous exertions are being made on
  every hand to facilitate its erection, and materials of all kinds are in a great state of forwardness, and
  by next fall we expect to see the building enclosed; if not the top stone raised with &ldquo;shouting of
  grace&mdash;grace unto it.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> There have been frequently, during the winter, as many as one hundred hands
  quarrying rock, while at the same time multitudes of others have been engaged in hauling, and in
  other kinds of labor.</p>
  <p class="std">A company was formed last fall to go up to the pine country to purchase mills, and prepare and
  saw lumber for the Temple and the Nauvoo House, and the reports from them are very favorable:
  another company has started, this last week, to take their place and to relieve those that are already
  there: on their return they are to bring a very large raft of lumber, for the use of the above-named
  houses.</p>
  <p class="std">While the busy multitudes have thus been engaged in their several vocations performing their
  daily labor, and working one-tenth of their time, others have not been less forward in bringing in
  their tithings and consecrations for the same great object. Never since the foundation of this Church
  was laid, have we seen manifested a greater willingness to comply with the requisitions of Jehovah,
  a more ardent desire to do the will of God,<span class="footRef">2</span> more strenuous exertions used, or greater sacrifices
  made than there have been since the Lord said, &ldquo;Let the Temple be built by the tithing of my
  people.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> It seemed as though the spirit of enterprise, philanthropy and obedience rested
  simultaneously upon old and young, and brethren and sisters, boys and girls, and even strangers,
  who were not in the Church, united with an unprecedented liberality in the accomplishment of this
  great work; nor could the widow, in many instances, be prevented, out of her scanty pittance from
  throwing in her two mites.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">We feel at this time to tender to all, old and young, both in the Church and out of it, our
  unfeigned thanks for their unprecedented liberality, kindness, diligence, and obedience which they
  have so opportunely manifested on the present occasion. Not that we are personally or individually
  benefitted</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/zech/4/7" target="_blank">Zech. 4:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/21" target="_blank">3 Ne. 27:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/97/11-12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 97:11-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/12/42" target="_blank">Mark 12:42</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
