<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="380"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs379.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs381.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 380</div>
  <div class="topic">Joseph Smith to Governor Ford&mdash;Explaining His Return to Nauvoo</div>
  <p class="right">Four Miles West of Carthage Mound,</p>
  <p class="right">Hancock County, Illinois,</p>
  <p class="right">Monday, 10 o&rsquo;clock.</p>
  <p class="cont">His Excellency Governor Ford:</p>
  <p class="std">Dear Sir:&mdash;On my way to Carthage to answer your request this morning, I here met Captain
  Dunn, who has here made known to me your orders to surrender the state arms in possession of the
  Nauvoo Legion, which command I shall comply with; and that the same may be done properly and
  without trouble to the state, I shall return with Captain Dunn to Nauvoo, see that the arms are put
  into his possession, and shall then return to headquarters in his company, when I shall most
  cheerfully submit to any requisition of the Governor or our state.</p>
  <p class="std">With all due respect to your Excellency, I remain your obedient servant.</p>
  <p class="std">JOSEPH SMITH.</p>
  <p class="std">(June 24, 1844.) DHC 6:556.</p>
  <div class="topic">On the Way to Carthage</div>
  <p class="std">The company (about fifteen) then started again for Carthage, and when opposite to the Masonic
  Hall, Joseph said, &ldquo;Boys, if I don&rsquo;t come back, take care of yourselves; I am going like a lamb to the
  slaughter.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> When they passed his farm he took a good look at it, and after they had passed it, he
  turned round several times to look again, at which some of the company made remarks, when Joseph
  said: &ldquo;If some of you had got such a farm and knew you would not see it any more, you would want
  to take a good look at it for the last time.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span> When they got to the edge of the woods near Nauvoo,
  they met A. C. Hodge returning from Carthage. He reported to Hyrum what he had heard in
  Carthage, told him what his feelings were and said, &ldquo;Brother Hyrum, you are now clear, and if it was
  my duty to counsel you, I would say, do not go another foot, for they say they will kill you, if you
  go to Carthage,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> but as other persons gathered around, nothing further was said. (June 24, 1844.)
  DHC 6:558.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/53/7" target="_blank">Isa. 53:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/5/62-63" target="_blank">Jacob 5:62-63</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/6/2" target="_blank">Jacob 6:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/24/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 24:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 33:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/21/10-11" target="_blank">Acts 21:10-11</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
