<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="302"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs301.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs303.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 302</div>
  <p class="cont">matter, but is more fine or pure, and can only be discerned by purer eyes. We cannot see it, but when
  our bodies are purified, we shall see that it is all matter.<span class="footRef">1</span> (May 17, 1843.) DHC 5:392–393.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Prophecy on the Head of Stephen A. Douglas</div>
  <p class="summary">The following brief account of the Prophet&rsquo;s visit with Judge Douglas while at Carthage is from the journal of
  William Clayton, who was present. For the fulfilment of this prophecy the reader is referred to the comments in the
  <i>Documentary History of the Church,</i> 5:395–398.</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std">Dined with Judge Stephen A. Douglas, who is presiding at court. After dinner Judge Douglas
  requested President Joseph to give him a history of the Missouri persecutions,<span class="footRef">2</span> which he did in a
  very minute manner, for about three hours. He also gave a relation of his journey to Washington
  City, and his application in behalf of the Saints to Mr. Van Buren, the President of the United
  States,<span class="footRef">3</span> for redress<span class="footRef">4</span> and Mr. Van Buren&rsquo;s pusillanimous reply, &ldquo;Gentlemen, your cause is just, but
  I can do nothing for you;&rdquo; and the cold, unfeeling manner in which he was treated by most of the
  senators and representatives in relation to the subject, Clay saying, &ldquo;You had better go to Oregon,&rdquo;
  and Calhoun shaking his head solemnly, saying, &ldquo;It&rsquo;s a nice question&mdash;a critical question, but it will
  not do to agitate it.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">The judge listened with the greatest attention and spoke warmly in deprecation of the conduct
  of Governor Boggs and the authorities of Missouri, who had taken part in the extermination, and
  said that any people that would do as the mobs of Missouri had done ought to be brought to
  judgment: they ought to be punished.<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <p class="std">President Smith, in concluding his remarks, said that if the government, which received into its
  coffers the money of citizens for its public lands, while its officials are rolling in luxury at the
  expense of its public treasury, cannot protect such citizens in their lives and property, it is an old
  granny anyhow; and I prophesy in the name of the Lord God of Israel,<span class="footRef">6</span> unless the United States
  redress the wrongs committed upon the Saints in the state of Missouri and punish the crimes
  committed by her officers that in a few years the government will be utterly overthrown and wasted,<span class="footRef">7</span>
  and there will not be so much as a potsherd left, for their wickedness in permitting the murder of
  men, women and children, and the wholesale plunder and</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/7-8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 131:7-8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/123/1-6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 123:1-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/89" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:89</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/76" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:76</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/25" target="_blank">D&amp;C 105:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 130:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/87/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 87:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
