<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="205"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs204.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs206.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 205</div>
  <p class="cont">by which spirits are governed; for as no man knows the things of God, but by the Spirit of God,<span class="footRef">1</span> so
  no man knows the spirit of the devil, and his power and influence, but by possessing intelligence
  which is more than human, and having unfolded through the medium of the Priesthood the
  mysterious operations of his devices; without knowing the angelic form, the sanctified look and
  gesture, and the zeal that is frequently manifested by him for the glory of God,<span class="footRef">2</span> together with the
  prophetic spirit, the gracious influence, the godly appearance, and the holy garb, which are so
  characteristic of his proceedings and his mysterious windings.</p>
  <p class="std">A man must have the discerning of spirits<span class="footRef">3</span> before he can drag into daylight this hellish influence
  and unfold it unto the world in all its soul-destroying, diabolical, and horrid colors; for nothing is
  a greater injury to the children of men than to be under the influence of a false spirit when they think
  they have the Spirit of God. Thousands have felt the influence of its terrible power and baneful
  effects. Long pilgrimages have been undertaken, penances endured, and pain, misery and ruin have
  followed in their train; nations have been convulsed, kingdoms overthrown, provinces laid waste,
  and blood, carnage and desolation are habiliments in which it has been clothed.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">The Spirit of God the Spirit of Knowledge</div>
  <p class="std">As we have noticed before, the great difficulty lies in the ignorance of the nature of spirits, of
  the laws by which they are governed, and the signs by which they may be known; if it requires the
  Spirit of God to know the things of God;<span class="footRef">4</span> and the spirit of the devil can only be unmasked through
  that medium, then it follows as a natural consequence that unless some person or persons have a
  communication, or revelation from God, unfolding to them the operation of the spirit, they must
  eternally remain ignorant of these principles; for I contend that if one man cannot understand these
  things but by the Spirit of God,<span class="footRef">5</span> ten thousand men cannot; it is alike out of the reach of the wisdom
  of the learned,<span class="footRef">6</span> the tongue of the eloquent, the power of the mighty. And we shall at last have to
  come to this conclusion, whatever we may think of revelation, that without it we can neither know
  nor understand anything of God, or the devil; and however unwilling the world may be</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/2/3-4" target="_blank">2 Thes. 2:3-4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/2/17" target="_blank">2 Ne. 2:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/28" target="_blank">D&amp;C 76:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/1,3" target="_blank">Moses 4:1,3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/10" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 46:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/2/11" target="_blank">1 Cor. 2:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/27/26" target="_blank">2 Ne. 27:26</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
