<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="95"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs94.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs96.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 95</div>
  <p class="cont">and refers to the multitude.] He answered and said unto them, [that is unto the disciples] because it
  is given unto you, to know the mysteries<span class="footRef">1</span> of the Kingdom of Heaven, but to them, [that is,
  unbelievers] it is not given;<span class="footRef">2</span> for whosoever hath, to him shall be given, and he shall have more
  abundance; but whosoever hath not, from him shall be taken away even that he hath.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span></p>
  <p class="std">We understand from this saying, that those who had been previously looking for a Messiah to
  come, according to the testimony of the prophets, and were then, at that time looking for a Messiah,
  but had not sufficient light, on account of their unbelief,<span class="footRef">4</span> to discern Him to be their Savior; and He
  being the true Messiah, consequently they must be disappointed, and lose even all the knowledge,
  or have taken away from them all the light, understanding, and faith which they had upon this
  subject; therefore he that will not receive the greater light, must have taken away from him all the
  light which he hath;<span class="footRef">5</span> and if the light which is in you become darkness, behold, how great is that
  darkness!<span class="footRef">6</span> &ldquo;Therefore,&rdquo; says the Savior, &ldquo;speak I unto them in parables because they, seeing, see not,
  and hearing, they hear not, neither do they understand; and in them is fulfilled the prophecy of
  Esaias, which saith, By hearing ye shall hear, and shall not understand; and seeing ye shall see, and
  not perceive.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <p class="std">Now we discover that the very reason assigned by this prophet,<span class="footRef">8</span> why they would not receive
  the Messiah, was, because they did not or would not understand; and seeing, they did not perceive;
  &ldquo;for this people&rsquo;s heart is waxed gross, and their ears are dull of hearing, and their eyes they have
  closed, lest at any time they should see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with
  their heart, and should be converted, and I should heal them.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">9</span> But what saith He to His disciples?
  &ldquo;Blessed are your eyes for they see, and your ears for they hear; for verily I say unto you, that many
  prophets and righteous men have desired to see those things which ye see, and have not seen them;
  and to hear those things which ye hear, and have not heard them.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">10</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Darkness the Condemnation of the World</div>
  <p class="std">We again make remark here&mdash;for we find that the very principle upon which the disciples were
  accounted blessed, was</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/9" target="_blank">Alma 12:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 6:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/21-22" target="_blank">D&amp;C 19:21-22</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/42" target="_blank">Moses 1:42</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/32" target="_blank">Moses 4:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/11-12" target="_blank">Matt. 13:11-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/19/6" target="_blank">Alma 19:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/45/12" target="_blank">Alma 45:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/30" target="_blank">2 Ne. 28:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/10-11" target="_blank">Alma 12:10-11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/24/30" target="_blank">Alma 24:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/23" target="_blank">Matt. 6:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/13-14" target="_blank">Matt. 13:13-14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/6/9-10" target="_blank">Isa. 6:9-10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/15" target="_blank">Matt. 13:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/16-17" target="_blank">Matt. 13:16-17</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
