<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="389"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs388.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs390.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 389</div>
  <p class="cont">how far we could trust anyone; besides, a question necessarily arose, how shall we come? Your
  request was that we should come unarmed. It became a matter of serious importance to decide how
  far promises could be trusted, and how far we were safe from mob violence.</p>
  <p class="std"><i>Geddes.</i>&mdash;It certainly did look from all I have heard, from the general spirit of violence and
  mobocracy that here prevails, that it was not safe for you to come unprotected.</p>
  <p class="std"><i>Gov.</i>&mdash;I think that sufficient time was not allowed by the posse for you to consult and get ready.
  They were too hasty; but I suppose they found themselves bound by their orders. I think, too, there
  is great deal of truth in what you say, and your reasoning is plausible; yet, I must beg leave to differ
  from you in relation to the acts of the City Council. That council, in my opinion, had no right to act
  in a legislative capacity, and in that of the judiciary.</p>
  <p class="std">They should have passed a law in relation to the matter, and then the Municipal Court, upon
  complaint, could have removed it; but for the City Council to take upon themselves the law-making
  and the execution of the laws, in my opinion, was wrong; besides, these men ought to have had a
  hearing before their property was destroyed; to destroy it without was an infringement of their
  rights; besides, it is so contrary to the feelings of the American people to interfere with the press.</p>
  <p class="std">And furthermore, I cannot but think that it would have been more judicious for you to have gone
  with Mr. Bettisworth to Carthage, notwithstanding the law did not require it. Concerning your being
  in jail, I am sorry for that, I wish it had been otherwise. I hope you will soon be released, but I
  cannot interfere.</p>
  <p class="std"><i>Joseph Smith.</i>&mdash;Governor Ford, allow me, sir, to bring one thing to your mind, that you seem
  to have overlooked. You state that you think it would have been better for us to have submitted to
  the requisition of Constable Bettisworth, and to have gone to Carthage.</p>
  <p class="std">Do you not know, sir, that that writ was served at the instance of an anti-Mormon mob, who had
  passed resolutions and published them to the effect that they would exterminate the Mormon leaders;
  and are you not informed that Captain Anderson was not only threatened when coming to Nauvoo,
  but had a gun fired at his boat by this said mob at Warsaw, when</p>
</div>
