<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="351"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs350.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs352.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 351</div>
  <p class="cont">infer that God had materials to organize the world<span class="footRef">1</span> out of chaos&mdash;chaotic matter, which is element,
  and in which dwells all the glory. Element had an existence from the time he had.<span class="footRef">2</span> The pure
  principles of element are principles which can never be</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/131/7-8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 131:7-8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/29,33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:29,33</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="cont">lutely &lsquo;making out of nothing,&rsquo; or calling into existence that which did not exist before, in the strictest sense of the term, is not a doctrine of scripture;
        but it has been held by many on the grounds of natural theology, as enhancing the ideas we form of the divine power, and more especially since the contrary must imply the belief in the eternity and self-existence of matter.&rdquo;</p>
      <p class="std">Dr. William Smith&rsquo;s great dictionary of the Bible (Hackett edition, 1894) has no article on the term &ldquo;create&rdquo; or &ldquo;creation,&rdquo; but in the article &ldquo;earth&rdquo; we have reference to the subject, and really an implied explanation as to why this work contains no treatise on &ldquo;create&rdquo; or &ldquo;creation.&rdquo; &ldquo;The act of creation itself, as recorded in the first chapter of Genesis, is a subject beyond and above the experience of man;
        human language, derived, as it originally was, from the sensible and material world, fails to find an adequate term to describe the act;
        for our word &lsquo;create&rsquo; and the Hebrew <i>bara,</i> though most appropriate to express the idea of an original creation, are yet applicable and must necessarily be applicable to other modes of creation;
        nor does the addition of such expressions as &lsquo;out of things that were not,&rsquo; or &lsquo;not from things which appear,&rsquo; contribute much to the force of the declaration. The absence of a term which shall describe exclusively an original creation is a necessary infirmity of language;
        as the events occurred but once, the corresponding term must, in order to be adequate, have been coined for the occasion and reserved for it alone, which would have been impossible.&rdquo;</p>
      <p class="std">The philosophers with equal emphasis sustain the contention of the Prophet. Herbert Spencer, in his <i>First Principles,</i> (1860), said:</p>
      <p class="std">&ldquo;There was once universally current, a notion that things could vanish into absolute nothing, or arise out of absolute nothing. * * * The current theology, in its teachings respecting the beginning and end of the world, is clearly pervaded by it. * * * The gradual accumulation of experiences, has tended slowly to reverse this conviction;
        until now, the doctrine that matter is indestructible has become a commonplace. All the apparent proofs that something can come of nothing, a wider knowledge has one by one cancelled. The comet that is suddenly discovered in the heavens and nightly waxes larger, is proved not to be a newly-created body, but a body that was until lately beyond the range of vision. The cloud which in the course of a few minutes forms in the sky, consists not of substance that has begun to be, but of substance that previously existed in a more diffused and transparent form. And similarly with a crystal or precipitate in relation to the fluid depositing it. Conversely, the seeming annihilations of matter turn out, on closer observation, to be only changes of state. It is found that the evaporated water, though it has become invisible, may be brought by condensation to its original shape. The discharged fowling-piece gives evidence that though the gunpowder has disappeared, there have appeared in place of it certain gases which, in assuming a larger volume, have caused the explosion.&rdquo;</p>
      <p class="std">Fiske follows Spencer, of course, and in his <i>Cosmic Philosophy</i> sums up the matter in these words. &ldquo;It is now unconceivable that a particle of matter should either come into existence, or lapse into non-existence.&rdquo;</p>
      <p class="std">Robert Kennedy Duncan (1905), in his <i>New Knowledge</i> says: &ldquo;Governing matter in all its varied forms, there is one great fundamental law which up to this time has been ironclad in its character. This law, known as the law of the conservation of mass, states that no particle of matter, however</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
