<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="386"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs385.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs387.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 386</div>
  <p class="cont">much endurance on our part, is to maintain and uphold the Constitution and institutions of our
  country, and to protect an injured, innocent, and persecuted people against misrule and mob
  violence.</p>
  <p class="std">Concerning the destruction of the press to which you refer, men may differ somewhat in their
  opinions about it; but can it be supposed that after all the indignities to which we have been
  subjected outside, that this people could suffer a set of worthless vagabonds to come into our city,
  and right under our own eyes and protection, vilify and calumniate not only ourselves, but the
  character of our wives and daughters, as was impudently and unblushingly done in that infamous
  and filthy sheet? There is not a city in the United States that would have suffered such an indignity
  for twenty-four hours.</p>
  <p class="std">Our whole people were indignant, and loudly called upon our city authorities for redress<span class="footRef">1</span> of
  their grievances, which, if not attended to they themselves would have taken the matter into their
  own hands, and have summarily punished the audacious wretches, as they deserved.</p>
  <p class="std">The principles of equal rights that have been instilled into our bosoms from our cradles, as
  American citizens, forbid us submitting to every foul indignity, and succumbing and pandering to
  wretches so infamous as these. But, independent of this, the course that we pursued we considered
  to be strictly legal; for notwithstanding the insult we were anxious to be governed strictly by law,<span class="footRef">2</span>
  and therefore convened the City Council; and being desirous in our deliberations to abide law,<span class="footRef">3</span>
  summoned legal counsel to be present on the occasion.</p>
  <p class="std">Upon investigating the matter, we found that our City Charter gave us power to remove all
  nuisances; and, furthermore, upon consulting Blackstone upon what might be considered a nuisance,
  that distinguished lawyer, who is considered authority, I believe, in all our courts, states, among
  other things, that a libelous and filthy press may be considered a nuisance, and abated as such.</p>
  <p class="std">Here, then, one of the most eminent English barristers, whose works are considered standard
  with us, declares that a libelous press may be considered a nuisance; and our own charter, given us
  by the legislature of this State, gives us the power to remove nuisances; and by ordering that press
  abated as a nuisance, we conceived that we were acting strictly in</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/76" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:76</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jarom/1/5" target="_blank">Jarom 1:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/13/30" target="_blank">Mosiah 13:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/1/21" target="_blank">Alma 1:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/30/7" target="_blank">Alma 30:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/62/10" target="_blank">Alma 62:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/22,35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:22,35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:5</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
