<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="279"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs278.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs280.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 279</div>
  <p class="cont">stitution governs the land of Iowa, but it is not a law for the people. The Constitution tells us what
  shall not be a lawful tender. Article I, Section 10 declares that nothing else except gold and silver
  shall be lawful tender, this not saying that gold and silver shall be lawful tender. It only provides that
  the state may make a law to make gold and silver lawful tender. I know of no state in the Union that
  has passed such a law; and I am sure that Illinois has not. The legislature has ceded up to us the
  privilege of enacting such laws as are not inconsistent with the Constitution of the United States and
  the state of Illinois; and we stand in the same relation to the state as the state does to the Union. The
  clause referred to in the Constitution is for the legislature&mdash;it is not a law for the people. The
  different states, and even Congress itself, have passed many laws diametrically contrary to the
  Constitution of the United States.</p>
  <p class="std">The state of Illinois has passed a stay law making property a lawful tender for the payment of
  debts; and if we have no law on the subject we must be governed by it. Shall we be such fools as to
  be governed by its laws, which are unconstitutional? No!  We will make a law for gold and silver;
  and then the state law ceases and we can collect our debts. Powers not delegated to the states or
  reserved from the states are constitutional. The Constitution acknowledges that the people have all
  power not reserved to itself. I am a lawyer; I am a big lawyer and comprehend heaven, earth and
  hell, to bring forth knowledge that shall cover up all lawyers, doctors and other big bodies. This is
  the doctrine of the Constitution, so help me God. The Constitution is not law to us, but it makes
  provision for us whereby we can make laws. Where it provides that no one shall be hindered from
  worshiping God according to his own conscience,<span class="footRef">1</span> is a law.<span class="footRef">2</span> No legislature can enact a law to
  prohibit it. The Constitution provides to regulate bodies of men and not individuals. (Feb. 25, 1843.)
  DHC 5:289–290.</p>
  <div class="topic">The &ldquo;Sign&rdquo; of the Son of Man</div>
  <p class="std">Sir:&mdash;Among the many signs of the times and other strange things which are continually
  agitating the minds of men, I notice a small speculation in the <i>Chicago Express</i>, upon the certificate
  of one Hyrum Redding, of Ogle county, Illinois, stating</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/30/7-12" target="_blank">Alma 30:7-12</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
