<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="334"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs333.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs335.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 334</div>
  <p class="cont">rights. We will whip the mob by getting up a candidate for President.</p>
  <p class="std">When I get hold of the Eastern papers, and see how popular I am, I am afraid myself that I shall
  be elected; but if I should be, I would not say, <i>&ldquo;Your cause is just, but I can do nothing for you.&rdquo;</i></p>
  <p class="std">What I have said in my views in relation to the annexation of Texas is with some unpopular;
  the people are opposed to it. Some of the Anti-Mormons are good fellows. I say it, however, in
  anticipation that they will repent.<span class="footRef">1</span> They object to Texas on account of slavery. Why, it is the very
  reason she ought to be received, so that we may watch over them;<span class="footRef">2</span> for, of the two evils,<span class="footRef">3</span> we should
  reject the greatest.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">Governor Houston of Texas, says&mdash;&ldquo;If you refuse to receive us into the United States, we must
  go to the British Government for protection.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">This would certainly be bad policy for this nation; the British are now throughout the whole
  country, trying to bribe all they can; and the first thing they would do, if they got possession, would
  be to set the negroes and the Indians to fight, and they would use us up. British officers are now
  running all over Texas to establish British influence in that country.</p>
  <p class="std">It will be more honorable for us to receive Texas and set the negroes free, and use the negroes
  and Indians against our foes. Don&rsquo;t let Texas go, lest our mothers and the daughters of the land
  should laugh<span class="footRef">5</span> us in the teeth; and if these things are not so, God never spoke by any Prophet since
  the world began.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">How much better it is for the nation to bear a little expense than to have the Indians and British
  upon us and destroy us all. We should grasp all the territory we can. I know much that I do not tell.
  I have had bribes offered me,<span class="footRef">7</span> but I have rejected them.</p>
  <p class="std">The government will not receive any advice or counsel from me: they are self-sufficient. But
  they must go to hell and work out their own salvation with fear and trembling.<span class="footRef">8</span></p>
  <p class="std">The South holds the balance of power. By annexing Texas, I can do away with this evil. As soon
  as Texas was annexed, I would liberate the slaves in two or three States, indemnifying their owners,
  and send the negroes to Texas, and from Texas to Mexico, where all colors are alike.<span class="footRef">9</span> And</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/27,39-40" target="_blank">D&amp;C 98:27,39-40</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/31/28" target="_blank">Jer. 31:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/23/18" target="_blank">Mosiah 23:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/42" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:42</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/38/21" target="_blank">D&amp;C 38:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/2/13" target="_blank">Jer. 2:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/25" target="_blank">Moses 5:25</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/18/12-13,15" target="_blank">Gen. 18:12-13,15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/21/6" target="_blank">Gen. 21:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/70" target="_blank">Luke 1:70</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21" target="_blank">Acts 3:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/33/15" target="_blank">Isa. 33:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/12" target="_blank">Philip. 2:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/9/27" target="_blank">Morm. 9:27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/26/33" target="_blank">2 Ne. 26:33</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
