<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="186"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs185.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs187.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 186</div>
  <p class="cont">in the enjoyment of the privileges of freemen<span class="footRef">1</span> themselves, but also that they willingly and cheerfully
  extend that invaluable blessing to others, and that they freely award to faithfulness and virtue their
  due.</p>
  <p class="std">The proceedings of the legislature, in regard to the citizens of this place, have been marked with
  philanthropy and benevolence; and they have laid us under great and lasting obligations, in granting
  us the several liberal charters<span class="footRef">2</span> we now enjoy, and by which we hope to prosper until our city
  becomes the most splendid, our University the most learned, and our Legion the most effective of
  any in the Union.</p>
  <div class="topic">Impoverished Saints</div>
  <p class="std">In consequence of the impoverished condition of the Saints, the buildings which are in course
  of erection do not progress as fast as could be desired; but from the interest which is generally
  manifested by the Saints at large, we hope to accomplish much by a combination of effort, and a
  concentration of action, and erect the Temple and other public buildings, which we so much need
  for our mutual instruction and the education of our children.</p>
  <p class="std">From the reports which have been received, we may expect a large emigration this season. The
  proclamation which was sent, some time ago, to the churches abroad, has been responded to, and
  great numbers are making preparations to come and locate themselves in this city and vicinity.</p>
  <p class="std">From what we now witness, we are led to look forward with pleasing anticipation to the future,
  and soon expect to see the thousands of Israel<span class="footRef">3</span> flocking to this region in obedience to the heavenly
  command; numerous inhabitants&mdash;Saints&mdash;thickly studding the flowery and wide-spread prairies
  of Illinois; temples for the worship of our God erecting in various parts, and great peace resting<span class="footRef">4</span>
  upon Israel.</p>
  <p class="std">We would call the attention of the Saints more particularly to the building of the Temple, for
  on its speedy erection great blessings depend. The zeal which is manifested by the Saints in this city
  is, indeed, praiseworthy, and, we hope will be imitated by the Saints in the various stakes and
  branches of the Church, and that those who cannot contribute labor will bring their gold and their
  silver,<span class="footRef">5</span> their brass and their iron, with the pine tree, and box tree,<span class="footRef">6</span> to beautify the same.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/51/6" target="_blank">Alma 51:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/46" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:46</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/num/10/4,36" target="_blank">Num. 10:4,36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/5-6" target="_blank">Luke 10:5-6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/7/27" target="_blank">Alma 7:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/105/25" target="_blank">D&amp;C 105:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/2" target="_blank">Abr. 1:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/26-27" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:26-27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/60/13,17" target="_blank">Isa. 60:13,17</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
