<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="59"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs58.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs60.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 59</div>
  <p class="cont">subject of atonement, it is evident in our minds, that he was instructed more fully in the plan than
  what the Bible speaks of, for how could he offer a sacrifice in faith,<span class="footRef">1</span> looking to God for a remission
  of his sins<span class="footRef">2</span> in the power of the great atonement, without having been previously instructed in that
  plan? And further, if he was accepted of God,<span class="footRef">3</span> what were the ordinances performed further than the
  offering of the firstlings of the flock?<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Lord Spake to Abel</div>
  <p class="std">It is said by Paul in his letter to the Hebrew brethren, that Abel obtained witness that he was
  righteous, God testifying of his gifts.<span class="footRef">5</span> To whom did God testify of the gifts of Abel, was it to Paul?
  We have very little on this important subject in the forepart of the Bible. But it is said that Abel
  himself obtained witness that he was righteous. Then certainly God spoke to him: indeed, it is said
  that God talked with him;<span class="footRef">6</span> and if He did, would He not, seeing that Abel was righteous deliver to
  him the whole plan of the Gospel? And is not the Gospel the news of the redemption?<span class="footRef">7</span> How could
  Abel offer a sacrifice and look forward with faith on the Son of God for a remission of his sins, and
  not understand the Gospel? The mere shedding of the blood of beasts or offering anything else in
  sacrifice, could not procure a remission of sins, except it were performed in faith of something to
  come; if it could, Cain&rsquo;s offering must have been as good as Abel&rsquo;s. And if Abel was taught of the
  coming of the Son of God, was he not taught also of His ordinances? We all admit that the Gospel
  has ordinances, and if so, had it not always ordinances, and were not its ordinances always the same? </p>
  <div class="topic">Gospel Ordinances from the Beginning</div>
  <p class="std">Perhaps our friends will say that the Gospel and its ordinances were not known till the days of
  John,<span class="footRef">8</span> the son of Zacharias, in the days of Herod, the king of Judea.<span class="footRef">9</span> But we will here look at this
  point: For our own part we cannot believe that the ancients in all ages were so ignorant of the system
  of heaven as many suppose, since all that were ever saved, were saved through the power of this
  great plan of redemption,<span class="footRef">10</span> as much before the coming of Christ as since; if not, God has had</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/4" target="_blank">Heb. 11:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/16" target="_blank">Alma 13:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/12/1" target="_blank">Rom. 12:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/14/18" target="_blank">Rom. 14:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/5" target="_blank">1 Pet. 2:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/4/4" target="_blank">Gen. 4:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/4" target="_blank">Heb. 11:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/17,26" target="_blank">Moses 5:17,26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/19,57" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:19,57</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/11/12" target="_blank">Matt. 11:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/5" target="_blank">Luke 1:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/31" target="_blank">Alma 34:31</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
