<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="385"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs384.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs386.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 385</div>
  <p class="cont">since our settlement here, with sufficient evidence of my pacific intentions, and those of the
  people with whom I am associated, by the endurance of every conceivable indignity and lawless
  outrage perpetrated upon me and upon this people since our settlement here, and you yourself
  know that I have kept you well posted in relation to all matters associated with the late
  difficulties. If you have not got some of my communications, it has not been my fault.</p>
  <p class="std">Agreeably to your orders, I assembled the Nauvoo Legion for the protection of Nauvoo and
  the surrounding country against an armed band of marauders, and ever since they have been
  mustered I have almost daily communicated with you in regard to all the leading events that have
  transpired; and whether in the capacity of mayor of the city, or lieutenant-general of the Nauvoo
  Legion, I have striven to preserve the peace and administer even-handed justice to all; but my
  motives are impugned, my acts are misconstrued, and I am grossly and wickedly misrepresented.
  I suppose I am indebted for my incarceration here to the oath of a worthless man that was
  arraigned before me and fined for abusing and maltreating his lame, helpless brother.</p>
  <p class="std">That I should be charged by you, sir, who know better, of acting contrary to law, is to me a
  matter of surprise. Was it the Mormons or our enemies who first commenced these difficulties?
  You know well it was not us; and when this turbulent, outrageous people commenced their
  insurrectionary movements, I made you acquainted with them, officially, asked your advice, and
  have followed strictly your counsel in every particular.</p>
  <p class="std">Who ordered out the Nauvoo Legion? I did, under your direction. For what purpose? To
  suppress these insurrectionary movements. It was at your instance, sir, that I issued a
  proclamation calling upon the Nauvoo Legion to be in readiness, at a moment&rsquo;s warning, to
  guard against the incursions of mobs, and gave an order to Jonathan Dunham, acting
  major-general, to that effect. Am I then to be charged for the acts of others; and because
  lawlessness and mobocracy abound, am I when carrying out your instructions, to be charged
  with not abiding the law? Why is it that I must be held accountable for other men&rsquo;s acts?<span class="footRef">1</span> If there
  is trouble in the country, neither I nor my people made it, and all that we have ever done, after</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/108" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:108</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/a_of_f/1/2" target="_blank">A of F 1:2</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
