<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="28"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs27.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs29.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 28</div>
  <p class="cont">with usual health. We parted with Father and Mother Nickerson at Buffalo, in good health, and they
  expressed a degree of satisfaction for the prosperity and blessings of their journey.</p>
  <p class="std">Since our arrival here, Brother Sidney has been afflicted with sore eyes, which is probably the
  reason why you have not previously heard from us, as he was calculating to write you immediately.
  But though I expect he will undoubtedly write you soon, as his eyes are evidently better, yet, lest
  you should be impatient to learn something concerning us, I have thought that perhaps a few lines
  from me, though there may be a lack of fluency according to the <i>literati</i> of the age, might be
  received with a degree of satisfaction on your part, at least, when you call to mind the near relation
  with which we are united by the everlasting ties of the Gospel of our Lord Jesus Christ.<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <p class="std">We found our families and the Church in this place well, generally. Nothing of consequence
  happened while we were absent, except the death of one of our brethren&mdash;David Johnson&mdash;a young
  man of great worth as a private citizen among us, the loss of whom we justly mourn.</p>
  <p class="std">We are favored with frequent intelligence from different sections of our country, respecting the
  progress of the Gospel, and our prayers are daily<span class="footRef">2</span> to our Father, that it may greatly spread, even till
  all nations shall hear<span class="footRef">3</span> the glorious news and come to a knowledge of the truth.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">We have received letters from our brethren in Missouri of late, but we cannot tell, from their
  contents, the probable extent to which those persons who are desirous to expel them from that
  country will carry their unlawful and unrighteous purposes. Our brethren have applied to the
  executive of the state, who has promised them all the assistance that the civil law can give; and in
  all probability a suit has been commenced ere this.</p>
  <p class="std">We are informed, however, that those persons are very violent, and threaten immediate
  extermination upon all those who profess our doctrine.<span class="footRef">5</span> How far they will be suffered to execute
  their threats, we know not, but we trust in the Lord,<span class="footRef">6</span> and leave the event with Him to govern in His
  own wise providence.<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <p class="std">I shall expect a communication from you on receipt of</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/1/8" target="_blank">2 Thes. 1:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/31/10" target="_blank">Alma 31:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/34/1" target="_blank">Isa. 34:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/6/18" target="_blank">Jer. 6:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/23" target="_blank">D&amp;C 43:23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/94" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:94</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/2/4" target="_blank">1 Tim. 2:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 56:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/3/5" target="_blank">Prov. 3:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/36/7" target="_blank">Isa. 36:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 78:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/75" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1:75</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
