<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="177"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs176.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs178.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 177</div>
  <div class="topic">The Saints Prospering</div>
  <p class="std">I am happy to inform you that we are prospering in this place, and that the Saints are more
  healthy than formerly; and from the decrease of sickness this season, when compared with the last,
  I am led to the conclusion that this must eventually become a healthy place. There are at present
  about 3,000 inhabitants in Nauvoo, and numbers are flocking in daily. Several stakes have been set
  off in different parts of the country, which are in prosperous circumstances.</p>
  <p class="std">Provisions are much lower than when you left. Flour is about $4 per barrel. Corn and potatoes
  about 25 cents per bushel; and other things in proportion. There has been a very plentiful harvest
  throughout the Union.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Temple</div>
  <p class="std">You will observe, by the Times and Seasons, that we are about building a temple for the
  worship of our God<span class="footRef">1</span> in this place. Preparations are now making; every tenth day is devoted by the
  brethren for quarrying rock, etc. We have secured one of the most lovely situations for it in this
  region of country. It is expected to be considerably larger than the one in Kirtland, and on a more
  magnificent scale, and which will undoubtedly attract the attention of the great men of the earth.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std">We have a bill before the legislature for the incorporation of the city of Nauvoo, and for the
  establishment of a seminary of learning, and other purposes, which I expect will pass in a short time.</p>
  <div class="topic">Death of Patriarch Joseph Smith</div>
  <p class="std">You will also receive intelligence of the death of my father; which event, although painful to
  the family and to the Church generally, yet the sealing testimony<span class="footRef">3</span> of the truth of the work of the
  Lord<span class="footRef">4</span> was indeed satisfactory. Brother Hyrum succeeds him as Patriarch of the Church,<span class="footRef">5</span> according
  to his last directions and benedictions.</p>
  <p class="std">Several persons of eminence and distinction in society have joined the Church and become
  obedient to the faith;<span class="footRef">6</span> and I am happy to inform you that the work is spreading very fast upon this
  continent. Some of the brethren are now in New Orleans,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/5/7" target="_blank">Ps. 5:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/138/2" target="_blank">Ps. 138:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/11/1" target="_blank">Rev. 11:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/18/23" target="_blank">Rev. 18:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/8/16" target="_blank">Isa. 8:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/72" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:72</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/34/10" target="_blank">Ex. 34:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/58" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:58</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/19/36" target="_blank">Alma 19:36</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/3/9" target="_blank">D&amp;C 3:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/91" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:91</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/6/7" target="_blank">Acts 6:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
