<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="343"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs342.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs344.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 343</div>
  <div class="topic">The Character of God</div>
  <p class="std">In the first place, I wish to go back to the beginning&mdash;to the morn of creation. There is the
  starting point for us to look to, in order to understand and be fully acquainted with the mind,
  purposes and decrees of the Great Elohim,<span class="footRef">1</span> who sits in yonder heavens as he did at the creation of
  this world. It is necessary for us to have an understanding of God himself<span class="footRef">2</span> in the beginning. If we
  start right, it is easy to go right all the time; but if we start wrong, we may go wrong, and it be a hard
  matter to get right.</p>
  <p class="std">There are but a very few beings in the world who understand rightly the character of God. The
  great majority of mankind do not comprehend anything, either that which is past, or that which is
  to come, as it respects their relationship to God. They do not know, neither do they understand the
  nature of that relationship; and consequently they know but little above the brute beast,<span class="footRef">3</span> or more
  than to eat, drink and sleep. This is all man knows about God or his existence, unless it is given by
  the inspiration of the Almighty.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">If a man learns nothing more than to eat, drink and sleep, and does not comprehend any of the
  designs of God,<span class="footRef">5</span> the beast comprehends the same things. It eats, drinks, sleeps, and knows nothing
  more about God; yet it knows as much as we, unless we are able to comprehend by the inspiration
  of Almighty God.<span class="footRef">6</span> If men do not comprehend the character of God, they do not comprehend
  themselves. I want to go back to the beginning, and so lift your minds into a more lofty sphere and
  a more exalted understanding than what the human mind generally aspires to.</p>
  <div class="topic">What Kind of Being Is God?</div>
  <p class="std">I want to ask this congregation, every man, woman and child, to answer the question in their
  own heart, what kind of a being God is? Ask yourselves; turn your thoughts into your hearts, and
  say if any of you have seen, heard, or communed with him.<span class="footRef">7</span> This is a question that may occupy your
  attention for a long time. I again repeat the question&mdash;What kind of a being is God? Does any man
  or woman know? Have any of you seen him, heard him, or communed with him? Here is the
  question that will, peradventure, from this</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/4/6" target="_blank">Moses 4:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/45/18" target="_blank">Isa. 45:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_thes/3/11" target="_blank">1 Thes. 3:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/40/3" target="_blank">Alma 40:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/22" target="_blank">Moses 6:22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/2/12" target="_blank">2 Pet. 2:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jude/1/10" target="_blank">Jude 1:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/32/8" target="_blank">Job 32:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/3/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 3:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/32/8" target="_blank">Job 32:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/31/18" target="_blank">Ex. 31:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:19</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
