<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="267"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs266.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs268.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 267</div>
  <p class="cont">to such important developments of the remains and ruins of those mighty people.</p>
  <p class="std">When we read in the Book of Mormon that Jared and his brother came on to this continent from
  the confusion and scattering at the Tower,<span class="footRef">1</span> and lived here more than a thousand years, and covered
  the whole continent from sea to sea,<span class="footRef">2</span> with towns and cities; and that Lehi went down by the Red Sea<span class="footRef">3</span>
  to the great Southern Ocean,<span class="footRef">4</span> and crossed over to this land,<span class="footRef">5</span> and landed a little south of the Isthmus
  of Darien,<span class="footRef">6</span> and improved the country according to the word of the Lord,<span class="footRef">7</span> as a branch of the house
  of Israel,<span class="footRef">8</span> and then read such a goodly traditionary account as the one below, we can not but think
  the Lord has a hand in bringing to pass his strange act,<span class="footRef">9</span> and proving the Book of Mormon true in the
  eyes of all the people. The extract below, comes as near the real fact, as the four Evangelists do to
  the crucifixion of Jesus.&mdash;Surely &ldquo;facts are stubborn things.&rdquo;  It will be as it ever has been, the world
  will prove Joseph Smith a true prophet by circumstantial evidence, in experiments, as they did
  Moses<span class="footRef">10</span> and Elijah.<span class="footRef">11</span> Now read Stephen&rsquo;s story:</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;According to Fuentes, the chronicler of the kingdom of Guatemala, the kings of Quiche and
  Cachiquel were descended from the Toltecan Indians, who, when they came into this country, found
  it already inhabited by people of different nations. According to the manuscripts of Don Juan Torres,
  the grandson of the last king of the Quiches, which was in the possession of the lieutenant general
  appointed by Pedro de Alvarado, and which Fuentes says he obtained by means of Father Francis
  Vasques, the historian of the order of San Francis, the Toltecas themselves descended from the
  house of Israel, who were released by Moses from the tyranny of Pharaoh, and after crossing the
  Read Sea,<span class="footRef">12</span> fell into idolatry.<span class="footRef">13</span> To avoid the reproofs of Moses, or from fear of his inflicting upon
  them some chastisement, they separated from him and his brethren, and under the guidance of
  Tanub, their chief, passed from one continent to the other, to a place which they called the seven
  caverns, a part of the kingdom of Mexico, where they founded the celebrated city of Tula.&rdquo;  (Sept.
  15, 1842.) T&amp;S 3:921–922.</p>
  <div class="topic">Effects of Disobeying Counsel</div>
  <p class="std">About ten in the forenoon I rode up and viewed the Temple. I expressed my satisfaction at the
  arrangements,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/1/33" target="_blank">Ether 1:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/8" target="_blank">Hel. 3:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/5" target="_blank">1 Ne. 2:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/5-6" target="_blank">1 Ne. 17:5-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/18/8" target="_blank">1 Ne. 18:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/18/23-24" target="_blank">1 Ne. 18:23-24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/18/4" target="_blank">1 Ne. 18:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/26/34" target="_blank">Mosiah 26:34</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/1/33" target="_blank">Ether 1:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/15/12" target="_blank">1 Ne. 15:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/28/21" target="_blank">Isa. 28:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/95" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:95</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/7/12" target="_blank">Ex. 7:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/18/36-39" target="_blank">1 Kgs. 18:36-39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/14/21-22" target="_blank">Ex. 14:21-22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/32/1-6" target="_blank">Ex. 32:1-6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
