<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="118"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs117.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs119.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 118</div>
  <div class="topic">Revelation Given to Brigham Young at Far West</div>
  <p class="std">Verily, thus saith the Lord, let my servant Brigham Young go unto the place which he has
  bought, on Mill Creek, and there provide for his family until an effectual door is opened<span class="footRef">1</span> for the
  support of his family, until I shall command him to go hence, and not to leave his family until they
  are amply provided for.<span class="footRef">2</span> Amen. (April 17, 1838.) DHC 3:23.</p>
  <div class="topic">Evils of Hasty Judgment</div>
  <p class="std">Sunday, May 6, 1838&mdash;I preached to the Saints, setting forth the evils that existed, and that
  would exist, by reason of hasty judgment,<span class="footRef">3</span> or decisions upon any subject given by any people, or
  in judging before they had heard both sides of a question.<span class="footRef">4</span> I also cautioned the Saints against men
  who came amongst them whining and growling about their money, because they had kept the Saints,
  and borne some of the burden with others,<span class="footRef">5</span> and thus thinking that others, who are still poorer, and
  have borne greater burdens than they themselves, ought to make up their losses. I cautioned the
  Saints to beware of such, for they were throwing out insinuations here and there, to level a dart at
  the best interests of the Church, and if possible destroy the character of its Presidency. I also gave
  some instructions in the mysteries of the kingdom<span class="footRef">6</span> of God; such as the history of the planets,
  Abraham&rsquo;s writings upon the planetary systems,<span class="footRef">7</span> etc.<span class="textFootRef">a</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/118/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 118:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/5/8" target="_blank">1 Tim. 5:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/21/5" target="_blank">Prov. 21:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/24" target="_blank">John 7:24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/20/12" target="_blank">Matt. 20:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 76:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/31" target="_blank">Abr. 1:31</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/9" target="_blank">Abr. 3:9</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>There is a prevalent notion in the world today that before the time of Columbus, Galileo, and Copernicus, all ancient people believed that the earth was flat and the center of the universe. From the writings of the Scriptures, and more especially those which have come to us in this dispensation, we know that the ancient peoples, when they were guided by the Spirit of the Lord, had the true conception of the universe. The Lord revealed to Abraham great truths about the heavenly bodies, their revolutions, times and seasons, and these were published by the Prophet Joseph Smith before modern astronomers were familiar with these facts. From the writings of Abraham we learn that the Egyptians understood the nature of the planets. Moses also recorded much about this and other worlds, but because of the unbelief and apostasy from truth, these writings were eliminated from his writings. In the Book of Abraham we find the following:</p>
      <p class="std">&ldquo;But the records of the fathers, even the patriarchs concerning, the right of Priesthood the Lord my God preserved in mine own hands
        therefore a knowledge of the beginning of the creation, and also of the planets, and of the stars, as they were made known unto the fathers, have I kept even unto this day, and I shall endeavor to write some of these things upon this record, for the benefit of my posterity that shall come after me.&rdquo;</p>
      <p class="std">We learn from the Book of Mormon (Helaman 12:13–15) that the Ne-</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
