<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="176"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs175.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs177.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 176</div>
  <div class="topic">Printing of Books</div>
  <p class="std">In my former epistle I told you my mind respecting the printing of the Book of Mormon, hymn
  book, etc. I have been favored by receiving a hymn book<span class="footRef">1</span> from you, and as far as I have examined
  it, I highly approve of it, and think it to be a very valuable collection. I am informed that the Book
  of Mormon is likewise printed, which I am glad to hear, and should be pleased to hear that it was
  printed in all the different languages of the earth. You can use your own pleasure respecting the
  printing of the Doctrine and Covenants.<span class="footRef">2</span> If there is a great demand for it, I have no objections, but
  would rather encourage it.</p>
  <p class="std">I can say, that as far as I have been made acquainted with your movements, I am perfectly
  satisfied that they have been in wisdom; and I have no doubt but that the Spirit of the Lord has
  directed you,<span class="footRef">3</span> and this proves to my mind that you have been humble,<span class="footRef">4</span> and your desires have been
  for the salvation of your fellow men, and not for your own aggrandizement, and selfish interests. As
  long as the Saints manifest such a disposition, their counsels will be approved of, and their exertions
  crowned with success.</p>
  <p class="std">There are many things of much importance, on which you ask counsel, but which I think you
  will be perfectly able to decide upon, as you are move conversant with the peculiar circumstances
  than I am; and I feel great confidence in your united wisdom; therefore you will excuse me for not
  entering into detail. If I should see anything that is wrong, I would take the privilege of making
  known my mind to you, and pointing out the evil.</p>
  <p class="std">If Elder Parley P. Pratt should wish to remain in England some time longer than the rest of the
  Twelve, he will feel himself at liberty to do so, as his family are with him, consequently his
  circumstances are somewhat different from the rest; and likewise it is necessary that someone should
  remain who is conversant with the rules and regulations of the Church,<span class="footRef">5</span> and continue the paper
  which is published. Consequently, taking all these things into consideration, I would not press it
  upon Brother Pratt to return in the spring.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/25/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 25:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/141" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:141</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3,6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:3,6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/13" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 46:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/38" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:38</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/62/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 62:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/54" target="_blank">Alma 5:54</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/28" target="_blank">Alma 13:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/21-22" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:21-22</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/97" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:97</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/6/7" target="_blank">Alma 6:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/45/21" target="_blank">Alma 45:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/62/44" target="_blank">Alma 62:44</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/10" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:10</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
