<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="197"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs196.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs198.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 197</div>
  <p class="cont">too lovely, to live on earth; therefore, if rightly considered, instead of mourning we have reason to
  rejoice as they as delivered from evil,<span class="footRef">1</span> and we shall soon have them again.</p>
  <div class="topic">Do Not Procrastinate Repentance</div>
  <p class="std">What chance is there for infidelity when we are parting with our friends almost daily? None at
  all. The infidel will grasp at every straw for help until death stares him in the face,<span class="footRef">2</span> and then his
  infidelity takes its flight, for the realities of the eternal world are resting upon him in mighty power;
  and when every earthly support and prop fails him, he then sensibly feels the eternal truths of the
  immortality of the soul. We should take warning and not wait for the death-bed to repent, as we see
  the infant taken away by death, so may the youth and middle-aged, as well as the infant be suddenly
  called into eternity. Let this, then, prove as a warning to all not to procrastinate repentance,<span class="footRef">3</span> or wait
  till a death-bed, for it is the will of God that man should repent and serve Him<span class="footRef">4</span> in health, and in the
  strength and power of his mind,<span class="footRef">5</span> in order to secure his blessing, and not wait until he is called to die.</p>
  <div class="topic">Redemption of Little Children<span class="footRef">6</span></div>
  <p class="std">The doctrine of baptizing children,<span class="footRef">7</span> or sprinkling them, or they must welter in hell, is a doctrine
  not true, not supported in Holy Writ,<span class="footRef">8</span> and is not consistent with the character of God. All children
  are redeemed by the blood of Jesus Christ,<span class="footRef">9</span> and the moment that children leave this world, they are
  taken to the bosom of Abraham.<span class="footRef">10</span> The only difference between the old and young dying is, one lives
  longer in heaven and eternal light and glory than the other, and is freed a little sooner from this
  miserable wicked world. Notwithstanding all this glory, we for a moment lose sight of it, and mourn
  the loss, but we do not mourn as those without hope.<span class="footRef">11</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Decrees Fixed and Immovable</div>
  <p class="std">My intention was to have spoken on the subject of baptism, but having a case of death before
  us, I thought proper to refer to that subject. I will now, however, say a few words upon baptism, as
  I intended.</p>
  <p class="std">God has made certain decrees which are fixed and immovable;<span class="footRef">12</span> for instance, God set the sun,
  the moon, and the stars</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/6/13" target="_blank">Matt. 6:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/4/23" target="_blank">Hel. 4:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/32-35" target="_blank">Alma 34:32-35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/42/4" target="_blank">Alma 42:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/11" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/32" target="_blank">Moro. 10:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/46-48" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:46-48</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/8/8-15" target="_blank">Moro. 8:8-15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/37/5" target="_blank">Alma 37:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/27" target="_blank">Alma 5:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/5/9" target="_blank">Hel. 5:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/16/22-23" target="_blank">Luke 16:22-23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/46-47" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:46-47</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/133" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:133</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
