<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="193"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs192.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs194.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 193</div>
  <div class="topic">Salvation for the Dead</div>
  <p class="std">This doctrine presents in a clear light the wisdom and mercy of God in preparing an ordinance
  for the salvation of the dead,<span class="footRef">1</span> being baptized by proxy, their names recorded<span class="footRef">2</span> in heaven and they
  judged according to the deeds done in the body.<span class="footRef">3</span> This doctrine was the burden of the scriptures.
  Those Saints who neglect it in behalf of their deceased relatives, do it at the peril of their own
  salvation. The dispensation of the fullness of times<span class="footRef">4</span> will bring to light the things that have been
  revealed in all former dispensations; also other things that have not been before revealed. He shall
  send Elijah,<span class="footRef">5</span> the Prophet, &amp;c., and restore all things in Christ.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">President Joseph Smith then announced: &ldquo;There shall be no more baptisms for the dead, until
  the ordinance can be attended to in the Lord&rsquo;s House;<span class="footRef">7</span> and the Church shall not hold another General
  Conference, until they can meet in said house. For thus saith the Lord!&rdquo;<span class="footRef">8</span><span class="textFootRef">,a</span>(Oct. 3, 1841.) DHC
  4:424–426.</p>
  <div class="topic">Do Not Accuse the Brethren</div>
  <p class="std">I charged the Saints not to follow the example of the adversary in accusing the brethren,<span class="footRef">9</span> and
  said, &ldquo;If you do not accuse each other, God will not accuse you. If you have no accuser you will
  enter heaven, and if you will follow the revelations and instructions which God gives you through
  me, I will take you into heaven as my back load. If you will not accuse me, I will not accuse you.
  If you will throw a cloak of charity over my sins, I will over yours&mdash;for charity covereth a multitude
  of sins.<span class="footRef">10</span> What many people call sin is not sin; I do many things to break down superstition, and I
  will break it down&rdquo;; I referred to the curse of Ham for laughing at Noah,<span class="footRef">11</span> while in his wine, but
  doing no harm. Noah was a righteous man, and yet he drank wine<span class="footRef">12</span> and became intoxicated; the
  Lord did not forsake him<span class="footRef">13</span> in consequence thereof, for he retained all the power of his Priesthood,
  and when he was accused by Canaan,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/5,8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:5,8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/1-2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:1-2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/4/6" target="_blank">1 Pet. 4:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/15" target="_blank">Alma 5:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10" target="_blank">Eph. 1:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/4/5-6" target="_blank">Mal. 4:5-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/1/10" target="_blank">Eph. 1:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/28-29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:28-29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/9/13" target="_blank">Ex. 9:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/28/16" target="_blank">Isa. 28:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/21/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 21:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/12/10" target="_blank">Rev. 12:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/4/8" target="_blank">1 Pet. 4:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/9/22" target="_blank">Gen. 9:22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/9/21" target="_blank">Gen. 9:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/9/20-27" target="_blank">Gen. 9:20-27</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>The reason for the commandment from the Lord discontinuing baptism for the dead in the Mississippi River is found in the fact that the font in the Nauvoo Temple had been prepared for these ordinances. It was only in the days of poverty and when there was no font in a Temple, that the Lord granted baptism for the dead outside of his holy house. November 8, 1841, the font in the Nauvoo Temple was dedicated and from that time forth until the exodus baptism for the dead in the Temple in Nauvoo was performed.</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
