<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="304"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs303.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs305.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 304</div>
  <div class="topic">The Prophet&rsquo;s Characterization of Himself</div>
  <p class="std">I am like a huge, rough stone rolling down from a high mountain; and the only polishing I get
  is when some corner gets rubbed off by coming in contact with something else, striking with
  accelerated force against religious bigotry, priestcraft, lawyer-craft, doctor-craft, lying editors,
  suborned judges and jurors, and the authority of perjured executives, backed by mobs, blasphemers,
  licentious and corrupt men and women&mdash;all hell knocking off a corner here and a corner there. Thus
  I will become a smooth and polished shaft in the quiver<span class="footRef">1</span> of the Almighty, who will give me
  dominion over all<span class="footRef">2</span> and every one of them, when their refuge of lies shall fail, and their hiding place
  shall be destroyed,<span class="footRef">3</span> while these smooth-polished stones with which I come in contact become
  marred.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Secrets of Peter&rsquo;s Writings</div>
  <p class="std">There are three grand secrets lying in this chapter, [2 Peter 1.]<span class="footRef">5</span> which no man can dig out, unless
  by the light of revelation, and which unlock the whole chapter as the things that are written are only
  hints of things which existed in the prophet&rsquo;s mind, which are not written concerning eternal glory.<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">I am going to take up this subject by virtue of the knowledge of God in me, which I have
  received from heaven.<span class="footRef">7</span> The opinions of men,<span class="footRef">8</span> so far as I am concerned, are to me as the crackling
  of thorns under the pot,<span class="footRef">9</span> or the whistling of the wind. I break the ground;<span class="footRef">10</span> I lead the way like
  Columbus when he was invited to a banquet where he was assigned the most honorable place at the
  table, and served with the ceremonials which were observed towards sovereigns. A shallow courtier
  present, who was meanly jealous of him, abruptly asked him whether he thought that in case he had
  not discovered the Indies, there were not other men in Spain who would have been capable of the
  enterprise? Columbus made no reply, but took an egg and invited the company to make it stand on
  end. They all attempted it, but in vain; whereupon he struck it upon the table so as to break one end,
  and left it standing on the broken part, illustrating that when he had once shown the way to the new
  world nothing was easier than to follow it.</p>
  <div class="topic">Things Unlawful to Utter</div>
  <p class="std">Paul ascended into the third heavens,<span class="footRef">11</span> and he could un-</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/49/2" target="_blank">Isa. 49:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/21/2" target="_blank">1 Ne. 21:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/judg/5/13" target="_blank">Judg. 5:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/49/14" target="_blank">Ps. 49:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/28/15-17" target="_blank">Isa. 28:15-17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/2/22" target="_blank">Mark 2:22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/1-21" target="_blank">2 Pet. 1:1-21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_tim/2/10" target="_blank">2 Tim. 2:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/5/10" target="_blank">1 Pet. 5:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 130:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 121:33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/6,10" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1:6,10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eccl/7/6" target="_blank">Eccl. 7:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hosea/10/12" target="_blank">Hosea 10:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/12/2" target="_blank">2 Cor. 12:2</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
