<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="184"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs183.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs185.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 184</div>
  <div class="topic">Report of the First Presidency at the April Conference, 1841</div>
  <p class="std">The Presidency of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, feel great pleasure in
  assembling with the Saints at another general conference,<span class="footRef">1</span> under circumstances so auspicious and
  cheering; and with grateful hearts to Almighty God for His providential regard, they cordially unite
  with the Saints, on this occasion, in ascribing honor, glory, and blessing to His Holy name.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std">It is with unfeigned pleasure that they have to make known the steady and rapid increase of the
  Church in this state, the United States, and Europe. The anxiety to become acquainted with the
  principles of the Gospel, on every hand is intense, and the cry of &ldquo;come over and help us,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> is
  reaching the Elders on the wings of every wind; while thousands who have heard the Gospel have
  become obedient thereto, and are rejoicing in its gifts and blessings. Prejudice, with its attendant
  train of evil, is giving way before the force of truth, whose benign rays are penetrating the nations
  afar off.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Missionary Reports Satisfactory</div>
  <p class="std">The reports from the Twelve Apostles in Europe are very satisfactory, and state that the work
  continues to progress with unparalleled rapidity, and that the harvest is truly great.<span class="footRef">5</span> In the Eastern
  States the faithful laborers<span class="footRef">6</span> are successful, and many are flocking to the standard of truth. Nor is the
  South keeping back.<span class="footRef">7</span> Churches have been raised up in the Southern and Western States, and a very
  pressing invitation has been received from New Orleans, for some of the Elders to visit that city;
  which has been complied with. In our own state and immediate neighborhood, many are avowing
  their attachment to the principles of our holy religion, and have become obedient to the faith.<span class="footRef">8</span></p>
  <p class="std">Peace and prosperity<span class="footRef">9</span> attend us; and we have favor in the sight of God and virtuous men.<span class="footRef">10</span> The
  time was, when we were looked upon as deceivers, and that &ldquo;Mormonism&rdquo; would soon pass away,
  come to nought,<span class="footRef">11</span> and be forgotten. But the time has gone by when it is looked upon as a transient
  matter, or a bubble on the wave, and it is now taking a deep hold in the hearts and affections of all
  those, who are noble-minded<span class="footRef">12</span> enough to lay aside the prejudice of education, and investigate the
  subject with candor and honesty. The truth, like the sturdy</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/88" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:88</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/36" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/16/9" target="_blank">Acts 16:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/micah/4/3" target="_blank">Micah 4:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/39" target="_blank">Acts 2:39</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/10/2" target="_blank">Luke 10:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 39:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/72/14,17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 72:14,17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/43/6" target="_blank">Isa. 43:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/6/7" target="_blank">Acts 6:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/122/7" target="_blank">Ps. 122:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/49/30" target="_blank">Alma 49:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/3/4" target="_blank">Prov. 3:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/5/34-39" target="_blank">Acts 5:34-39</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/11" target="_blank">Acts 17:11</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
