<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="352"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs351.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs353.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 352</div>
  <p class="cont">destroyed; they may be organized and re-organized,<span class="footRef">1</span> but not destroyed. They had no beginning, and
  can have no end.<span class="footRef">2</span><span class="textFootRef">,a</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Immortal Spirit</div>
  <p class="std">I have another subject to dwell upon, which is calculated to exalt man; but it is impossible for
  me to say much on this subject. I shall therefore just touch upon it, for time will not permit me to
  say all. It is associated with the subject of the resurrection of the dead,<span class="footRef">3</span>&mdash;namely, the soul<span class="footRef">4</span>&mdash;the
  mind of man<span class="footRef">5</span>&mdash;the immortal spirit.<span class="footRef">6</span><span class="textFootRef">,b</span> Where did it come from? All learned men and doctors of
  divinity say that God created it in the beginning; but it is not so:<span class="footRef">7</span> the very idea lessens man in my
  estimation.<span class="footRef">8</span> I do not believe the doctrine; I know better. Hear it, all ye ends of the world; for God
  has told me so; and if you don&rsquo;t believe me, it will not make the truth without effect.<span class="footRef">9</span> I will make
  a man appear a fool before I get through; if he does not believe it. I am going to tell of things more
  noble.</p>
  <p class="std">We say that God himself is a self-existent being.<span class="footRef">10</span> Who told you so? It is correct enough; but
  how did it get into your heads? Who told you that man did not exist in like manner upon the same
  principles? Man does exist upon the same principles.<span class="footRef">11</span> God made a tabernacle and put a spirit into
  it,<span class="footRef">12</span> and</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/18/1-6" target="_blank">Jer. 18:1-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:33</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/18" target="_blank">Abr. 3:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/31-33" target="_blank">Matt. 22:31-33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/7" target="_blank">Gen. 2:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/15" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/67/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 67:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/28" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/33-35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:33-35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/3/3" target="_blank">Rom. 3:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/33/27" target="_blank">Deut. 33:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/1/17" target="_blank">1 Tim. 1:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/5" target="_blank">Mosiah 3:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/15/4" target="_blank">Mosiah 15:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/28" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 39:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/67" target="_blank">Moses 6:67</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/35" target="_blank">Moses 7:35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/29-30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:29-30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/5/7" target="_blank">Abr. 5:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="cont">small, may be created or destroyed. All the king&rsquo;s horses and all the king&rsquo;s men cannot destroy a pins head. We may smash that pin&rsquo;s head, dissolve it in acid, burn it in the electric furnace, employ, in a word, every annihilating agency, and yet that pin&rsquo;s head persists in being. Again, it is as uncreatable as it is indestructible. In other words, we cannot create something out of nothing. The material must be furnished for every existent article. The sum of matter in the universe is x pounds,&mdash;and, while it may be carried through a myriad of forms, when all is said and done, it is just&mdash;x pounds.&mdash; Note by Elder B. H. Roberts.</p>
    
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>&ldquo;The elements are eternal, and spirit and element inseparably connected receive a fullness of joy. * * * The elements are the tabernacle of God;
        yea, man is the tabernacle of God, even temples.&rdquo; (D. and C. Sec. 93:33-35.)</p>
    
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">b</span>It appears to be very clear that the Prophet had in mind the <i>intelligence,</i> when he said &ldquo;the soul&mdash;the mind of man&mdash;the immortal spirit,&rdquo; was not created or made, and he did not have reference to the spirit as a begotten child of God. It was the doctrine of the Prophet, and is of the Church, that the spirits of men are begotten sons and daughters of God. See the official statement of the First Presidency and the Council of the Twelve as published in the <i>Improvement Era,</i> August, 1916, under the caption, <i>The Father and The Son.</i> The passage in the Doctrine and Covenants on which this doctrine is based is found in Sec. 93:29-30, and is as follows: &ldquo;Man was in the beginning with God. Intelligence, or the light of truth, was not created or made, neither indeed can be.&rdquo; See also the statements in following paragraphs.</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
