<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="377"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs376.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs378.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 377</div>
  <p class="cont">taken again we should be massacred,<span class="footRef">1</span> or I was not a prophet of God. I want Hyrum to live to avenge
  my blood,<span class="footRef">2</span> but he is determined not to leave me.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>
  <p class="std">Saturday, June 22, 1844, about 9 p.m. Hyrum came out of the Mansion and gave his hands to
  Reynolds Cahoon, at the same time saying, &ldquo;A company of men are seeking to kill<span class="footRef">3</span> my brother
  Joseph, and the Lord has warned him to flee<span class="footRef">4</span> to the Rocky Mountains to save his life. Good-by,
  Brother Cahoon, we shall see you again.&rdquo;  In a few minutes afterwards Joseph came from his family.
  His tears were flowing fast. He held a handkerchief to his face, and followed after Brother Hyrum
  without uttering a word.</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="summary">Late that night the Prophet and Patriarch were taken across the river by Orrin P. Rockwell preparatory to their start
  towards the Rocky Mountains. Early the next morning other brethren joined them. That same morning a posse arrived
  in Nauvoo to arrest Joseph Smith, but they did not find him, but they did succeed in creating fear in the hearts of some
  of the timid. At one p.m. that day Orrin P. Rockwell, who had returned to Nauvoo, arrived with a letter from Emma
  Smith, requesting the Prophet to return to Nauvoo. The Prophet and Patriarch with Willard Richards were in a room
  where they had assembled provisions preparatory for their journey. Reynolds Cahoon informed the Prophet what the
  troops intended to do and urged upon him to give himself up, inasmuch as the Governor had pledged his faith and the
  faith of the state to protect him while he underwent a legal trial. The Prophet, however, knew that the word of the
  Governor was not to be received in good faith. At this point our narrative continues.</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <div class="topic">False Accusations</div>
  <p class="std">Reynolds Cahoon, Lorenzo D. Wasson and Hiram Kimball accused Joseph of cowardice for
  wishing to leave the people, adding that their property would be destroyed, and they left without
  house or home. Like the fable, when the wolves came the shepherd ran from the flock, and left the
  sheep to be devoured.<span class="footRef">5</span> To which Joseph replied: &ldquo;If my life is of no value to my friends it is of none
  to myself.&rdquo;</p>
  <p class="std">Joseph said to Rockwell, &ldquo;What shall I do?&rdquo; Rockwell replied, &ldquo;You are the oldest and ought
  to know best; and as you make your bed, I will lie with you.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">6</span> Joseph then turned to Hyrum, who
  was talking with Cahoon, and said, &ldquo;Brother Hyrum, you are the oldest, what shall we do?&rdquo; Hyrum
  said, &ldquo;Let us go back and give ourselves up, and see the thing out.&rdquo; After studying a few moments,
  Joseph said, &ldquo;If you go back I</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/1,6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:1,6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_kgs/9/7" target="_blank">2 Kgs. 9:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/7/25" target="_blank">John 7:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/37,40" target="_blank">John 8:37,40</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/1" target="_blank">1 Ne. 2:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/4_ne/1/31" target="_blank">4 Ne. 1:31</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/2/2" target="_blank">1 Ne. 2:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/1/3" target="_blank">2 Ne. 1:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/5/5" target="_blank">2 Ne. 5:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/omni/1/12" target="_blank">Omni 1:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ether/9/3" target="_blank">Ether 9:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ezek/34/5,8" target="_blank">Ezek. 34:5,8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/10/12" target="_blank">John 10:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/139/8" target="_blank">Ps. 139:8</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
