<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="250"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs249.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs251.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 250</div>
  <div class="topic">Man Not Able to Govern Himself</div>
  <p class="std">What is the matter? Are we alone in this thing? Verily no. With all our evils we are better
  situated than any other nation. Let Egypt, Turkey, Spain, France, Italy, Portugal, Germany, England,
  China, or any other nation, speak, and tell the tale of their trouble, their perplexity,<span class="footRef">1</span> and distress, and
  we should find that their cup was full, and that they were preparing to drink the dregs of sorrow.<span class="footRef">2</span>
  England, that boasts of her literature, her science, commerce, etc., has her hands reeking with the
  blood of the innocent<span class="footRef">3</span> abroad, and she is saluted with the cries of the oppressed<span class="footRef">4</span> at home. Chartism,
  O&rsquo;Connelism, and radicalism are gnawing her vitals at home; and Ireland, Scotland, Canada, and
  the east are threatening her destruction abroad. France is rent to the core, intrigue, treachery, and
  treason lurk in the dark, and murder, and assassination stalk forth at noonday.<span class="footRef">5</span> Turkey, once the
  dread of European nations, has been shorn of her strength, has dwindled into her dotage, and has
  been obliged to ask her allies to propose to her tributary terms of peace; and Russia and Egypt are
  each of them opening their jaws to devour her. Spain has been the theater of bloodshed, of misery
  and woe for years past. Syria is now convulsed with war and bloodshed. The great and powerful
  empire of China, which has for centuries resisted the attacks of barbarians, has become tributary to
  a foreign foe, her batteries thrown down, many of her cities destroyed, and her villages deserted. We
  might mention the Eastern Rajahs, the miseries and oppressions of the Irish; the convulsed state of
  Central America; the situation of Texas and Mexico; the state of Greece, Switzerland and Poland;
  nay, the world itself presents one great theater of misery, woe, and &ldquo;distress of nations with
  perplexity.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">6</span> All, all, speak with a voice of thunder,<span class="footRef">7</span> that man is not able to govern himself, to
  legislate for himself, to protect himself, to promote his own good, nor the good of the world.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Design of Jehovah</div>
  <p class="std">It has been the design of Jehovah, from the commencement of the world, and is His purpose
  now, to regulate the affairs of the world in His own time, to stand as a head of the universe, and take
  the reins of government in His own hand. When</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/22/5" target="_blank">Isa. 22:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/75/8" target="_blank">Ps. 75:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/prov/6/17" target="_blank">Prov. 6:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/35/9" target="_blank">Job 35:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/91/6" target="_blank">Ps. 91:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jer/15/8" target="_blank">Jer. 15:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/21/25" target="_blank">Luke 21:25</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/17/45" target="_blank">1 Ne. 17:45</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/2" target="_blank">Alma 29:2</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
