<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="244"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs243.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs245.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 244</div>
  <p class="cont">to the surrounding multitude;<span class="footRef">1</span> this will appear plain when we consult the writings of the Apostles,
  and notice their proceedings in relation to this matter. Paul, in 1st Cor. 12, says, &ldquo;Now concerning
  spiritual gifts, brethren, I would not have you ignorant;&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span> it is evident from this, that some of them
  were ignorant in relation to these matters, or they would not need instruction.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Gift of Prophecy</div>
  <p class="std">Again in chapter 14, he says, &ldquo;Follow after charity and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye
  may prophesy.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> It is very evident from these Scriptures that many of them had not spiritual gifts,
  for if they had spiritual gifts where was the necessity of Paul telling them to follow after them, and
  it is evident that they did not all receive those gifts by the imposition of the hands; for they as a
  Church had been baptized and confirmed by the laying on of hands<span class="footRef">4</span>&mdash;and yet to a Church of this
  kind, under the immediate inspection and superintendency of the Apostles, it was necessary for Paul
  to say, &ldquo;Follow after charity, and desire spiritual gifts, but rather that ye may prophesy,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span> evidently
  showing that those gifts were in the Church, but not enjoyed by all in their outward manifestations.</p>
  <p class="std">But suppose the gifts of the Spirit were immediately, upon the imposition of hands, enjoyed by
  all, in all their fulness and power, the skeptic would still be as far from receiving any testimony
  except upon a mere casualty as before, for all the gifts of the Spirit are not visible to the natural
  vision, or understanding of man; indeed very few of them are. We read that &ldquo;Christ ascended into
  heaven and gave gifts unto men;<span class="footRef">6</span> and He gave some Apostles, and some Prophets, and some
  Evangelists, and some Pastors and Teachers.&rdquo; (Eph. 4.)<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Church a Compact Body</div>
  <p class="std">The Church is a compact body composed of different members, and is strictly analogous to the
  human system, and Paul, after speaking of the different gifts, says, &ldquo;Now ye are the body of Christ
  and members in particular; and God hath set some in the Church, first Apostles, secondarily
  Prophets, thirdly Teachers, after that miracles, then gifts of healing, helps, governments, diversities
  of tongues. Are all Teachers? Are all workers of miracles? Do all speak with tongues? Do all
  interpret?&rdquo;<span class="footRef">8</span> It is evident that they do not; yet are they all</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/6" target="_blank">Acts 2:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/1" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/1" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/41,43,68" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:41,43,68</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/15" target="_blank">D&amp;C 33:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/1" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/8" target="_blank">Eph. 4:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11" target="_blank">Eph. 4:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/27-30" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:27-30</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
