<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="133"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs132.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs134.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 133</div>
  <p class="cont">to what it reads, against us; which prevented us from introducing our evidence before the mock
  court.</p>
  <p class="std">They have done us much harm from the beginning. They have of late acknowledged that the law
  was misconstrued, and tantalized our feelings with it, and have entirely forsaken us, and have
  forfeited their oaths and their bonds; and we have a come-back on them, for they are co-workers
  with the mob.</p>
  <div class="topic">Change of Public Opinion</div>
  <p class="std">As nigh as we can learn, the public mind has been for a long time turning in our favor, and the
  majority in now friendly; and the lawyers can no longer browbeat us by saying that this or that is
  a matter of public opinion, for public opinion is not willing to brook it; for it is beginning to look
  with feelings of indignation against our oppressors, and to say that the &ldquo;Mormons&rdquo; were not in the
  fault in the least. We think that truth, honor, virtue and innocence will eventually come out
  triumphant. We should have taken a habeas corpus before the high judge and escaped the mob in
  a summary way; but unfortunately for us, the timber of the wall being very hard, our auger handles
  gave out, and hindered us longer than we expected; we applied to a friend, and a very slight
  incautious act gave rise to some suspicions, and before we could fully succeed, our plan was
  discovered; we had everything in readiness, but the last stone, and we could have made our escape
  in one minute, and should have succeeded admirably, had it not been for a little imprudence or
  over-anxiety on the part of our friend.</p>
  <p class="std">The sheriff and jailer did not blame us for our attempt; it was a fine breach, and cost the county
  a round sum; but public opinion says that we ought to have been permitted to have made our escape;
  that then the disgrace would have been on us, but now it must come on the state; that there cannot
  be any charge sustained against us; and that the conduct of the mob, the murders committed at
  Haun&rsquo;s Mills, and the exterminating order of the governor, and the one-sided, rascally proceedings
  of the legislature, have damned the state of Missouri to all eternity.<span class="footRef">1</span> I would just name also that
  General Atchison has proved himself as contemptible as any of them.</p>
  <p class="std">We have tried for a long time to get our lawyers to draw us some petitions to the supreme judges
  of this state, but they</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/3/5" target="_blank">Mosiah 3:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/7" target="_blank">Alma 13:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/39/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 39:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/31" target="_blank">Moses 7:31</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
