<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="56"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs55.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs57.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 56</div>
  <p class="cont">consequently, then, he was the first Author of law, or the principle of it, to mankind.</p>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">What Is the Purpose of Existence?</div>
  <p class="std">Think for a moment, of the greatness of the Being who created the Universe; and ask, could He
  be so inconsistent with His own character, as to leave man without a law<span class="footRef">1</span> or rule by which to
  regulate his conduct, after placing him here, where, according to the formation of his nature he must
  in a short period sink into the dust?<span class="footRef">2</span> Is there nothing further; is there no existence beyond this veil
  of death which is so suddenly to be cast over all of us? If there is, why not that Being who had power
  to place us here, inform us something of the hereafter? If we had power to place ourselves in this
  present existence, why not have power to know what shall follow when that dark veil<span class="footRef">3</span> is cast over
  our bodies? If in this life we receive our all; if when we crumble back to dust<span class="footRef">4</span> we are no more, from
  what source did we emanate, and what was the purpose of our existence? If this life were all, we
  should be led to query, whether or not there was really any substance in existence, and we might
  with propriety say, &ldquo;Let us eat, drink, and be merry, for to-morrow we die!&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span> But if this life is all,
  then why this constant toiling, why this continual warfare, and why this unceasing trouble? But this
  life is not all; the voice of <i>reason</i>, the language of <i>inspiration</i>, and the Spirit of the living God,<span class="footRef">6</span> our
  Creator, teaches us, as we hold the record of truth in our hands, that this is not the case, that this is
  not so; for, the heavens declare the glory of a God, and the firmament showeth His handiwork;<span class="footRef">7</span> and
  a moment&rsquo;s reflection is sufficient to teach every man of common intelligence, that all these are not
  the mere productions of <i>chance</i>, nor could they be supported by any power less than an Almighty
  hand; and He that can mark the power of Omnipotence, inscribed upon the heavens, can also see
  God&rsquo;s own handwriting in the sacred volume: and he who reads it oftenest will like it best, and he
  who is acquainted with it, will know the hand wherever he can see it; and when once discovered,
  it will not only receive an acknowledgment, but an obedience to all its heavenly precepts. For a
  moment reflect: what could have been the purpose of our Father in giving</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/15/3" target="_blank">2 Chr. 15:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/2/12" target="_blank">Rom. 2:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/9/21" target="_blank">1 Cor. 9:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/76/72" target="_blank">D&amp;C 76:72</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/3/19" target="_blank">Gen. 3:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/19/6" target="_blank">Alma 19:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/9/7" target="_blank">2 Ne. 9:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/6/15" target="_blank">Morm. 6:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/22/13" target="_blank">Isa. 22:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/28/7" target="_blank">2 Ne. 28:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/3/3" target="_blank">2 Cor. 3:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/28" target="_blank">D&amp;C 61:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 68:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/19/1" target="_blank">Ps. 19:1</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
