<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="201"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs200.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs202.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 201</div>
  <p class="std">After baptism, the congregation again repaired to the grove, near the Temple, to attend to the
  ordinance of confirmation,<span class="footRef">1</span> and, notwithstanding President Smith had spoken in the open air to the
  people, and stood in the water and baptized about eighty persons, about fifty of those baptized
  received their confirmation under his hands<span class="footRef">2</span> in the after part of the day. While this was progressing,
  great numbers were being baptized in the font for the dead.<span class="footRef">3</span> (March 20, 1842.) DHC 4:553–557.</p>
  <div class="topic">Synopsis of the Prophet&rsquo;s Sermon on Baptism for the Dead</div>
  <p class="std">This was an interesting day. A large assembly met in the grove near the Temple. Brother Amasa
  Lyman addressed the people in a very interesting manner. He was followed by Joseph, the Seer,<span class="footRef">4</span>
  who made some highly edifying and instructive remarks concerning baptism for the dead. He said
  the Bible supported the doctrine, quoting 1 Cor. 15:29: &ldquo;Else what shall they do which are baptized
  for the dead, if the dead rise not at all, why are they then baptized for the dead?&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span> If there is one
  word of the Lord that supports the doctrine of baptism for the dead, it is enough to establish it as a
  true doctrine. Again; if we can, by the authority of the Priesthood of the Son of God,<span class="footRef">6</span> baptize a man
  in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost,<span class="footRef">7</span> for the remission of sins, it is just as
  much our privilege to act as an agent, and be baptized for the remission of sins for and in behalf of
  our dead kindred, who have not heard the Gospel,<span class="footRef">8</span> or the fullness of it. (March 27, 1842.) DHC
  4:568–569.</p>
  <div class="topic">Synopsis of the Prophet&rsquo;s Remarks to the Female Relief Society</div>
  <p class="std">President Joseph Smith arose. Spoke of the organization of the Female Relief Society; said he
  was deeply interested, that it might be built up to the Most High in an acceptable manner; that its
  rules must be observed; that none should be received into it but those who were worthy; proposed
  a close examination of every candidate; that the society was growing too fast. It should grow up by
  degrees, should commence with a few individuals, thus have a select society of the virtuous, and
  those who would walk circumspectly;<span class="footRef">9</span> commended them for their zeal, but said sometimes their zeal
  was not according to knowledge.<span class="footRef">10</span> One principle object of the institution was to purge</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/46/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 46:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/43,68" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:43,68</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:29</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/12-13" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:12-13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/3/6-7,14" target="_blank">2 Ne. 3:6-7,14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/94,125" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:94,125</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/29" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/28/19" target="_blank">Matt. 28:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/25" target="_blank">3 Ne. 11:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/73" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:73</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/11" target="_blank">Moses 7:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/137/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 137:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/32" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/5/15" target="_blank">Eph. 5:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/26/37" target="_blank">Mosiah 26:37</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/10/2" target="_blank">Rom. 10:2</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
