<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="293"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs292.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs294.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 293</div>
  <p class="std">He then read Rev. 13:1–8.<span class="footRef">1</span> John says, &ldquo;And I saw one of his heads as it were wounded to death;
  and his deadly wound was healed; and all the world wondered after the beast.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span> Some spiritualizers
  say the beast that received the wound was Nebuchadnezzar, some Constantine, some Mohammed,
  and others the Roman Catholic Church; but we will look at what John saw in relation to this beast.
  Now for the wasp&rsquo;s nest. The translators have used the term &ldquo;dragon&rdquo; for devil.<span class="footRef">3</span> Now it was a beast
  that John saw in heaven, and he was then speaking of &ldquo;things which must shortly come to pass;&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span>
  and consequently the beast John saw could not be Nebuchadnezzar. The beast John saw was an
  actual beast,<span class="footRef">5</span> and an actual intelligent being gives him his power, and his seat, and great authority.<span class="footRef">6</span>
  It was not to represent a beast in heaven: it was an angel in heaven who has power in the last days
  to do a work.</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;All the world wondered after the beast,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">7</span> Nebuchadnezzar and Constantine the Great not
  excepted. And if the beast was all the world, how could the world wonder after the beast? It must
  have been a wonderful beast to cause all human beings to wonder after it; and I will venture to say
  that when God allows the old devil to give power to the beast to destroy the inhabitants of the earth,<span class="footRef">8</span>
  all will wonder. Verse 4 reads, &ldquo;And they worshiped the dragon which gave power unto the beast;
  and they worshiped the beast, saying. Who is like unto the beast? Who is able to make war with
  him?&rdquo;<span class="footRef">9</span></p>
  <p class="std">Some say it means the kingdom of the world. One thing is sure, it does not mean the kingdom
  of the Saints. Suppose we admit that it means the kingdoms of the world, what propriety would there
  be in saying, Who is able to make war with my great big self? If these spiritualized interpretations
  are true, the book contradicts itself in almost every verse. But they are not true.</p>
  <p class="std">There is a mistranslation of the word dragon in the second verse.<span class="footRef">10</span> The original word signifies
  the devil, and not dragon, as translated. In chapter 12, verse 9, it reads, &ldquo;That old serpent, called the
  devil,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">11</span> and it ought to be translated devil in this case, and not dragon. It is sometimes translated
  Apollyon. Everything that we have not a key-word<span class="footRef">12</span> to, we will take it as it reads. The beasts which
  John saw and speaks of being in heaven, were actually living in heaven, and were actually to have
  power given to them over the inhabitants of the earth,<span class="footRef">13</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/1-8" target="_blank">Rev. 13:1-8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/3" target="_blank">Rev. 13:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/2,4" target="_blank">Rev. 13:2,4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/1" target="_blank">Rev. 1:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/1" target="_blank">Rev. 13:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/2" target="_blank">Rev. 13:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/3" target="_blank">Rev. 13:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/7-8" target="_blank">Rev. 13:7-8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/4" target="_blank">Rev. 13:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/2" target="_blank">Rev. 13:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/12/9" target="_blank">Rev. 12:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/130/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 130:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/6/8" target="_blank">Rev. 6:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/9/13" target="_blank">Rev. 9:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/5,7" target="_blank">Rev. 13:5,7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/16/8" target="_blank">Rev. 16:8</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
