<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="103"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs102.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs104.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 103</div>
  <div class="topic">False Doctrines of Joshua the Jewish Minister</div>
  <p class="std">While sitting in my house, between ten and eleven this morning, a man came in and introduced
  himself to me by the name of &ldquo;Joshua, the Jewish Minister.&rdquo;  His appearance was something
  singular, having a beard about three inches in length, quite grey; also his hair was long and
  considerably silvered with age; I thought him about fifty or fifty-five years old; tall, straight, slender
  built, of thin visage, blue eyes, and fair complexion; wore a sea-green frock coat and pantaloons,
  black fur hat with narrow brim; and, while speaking, frequently shut his eyes, with a scowl on his
  countenance. I made some inquiry after his name, but received no definite answer. We soon
  commenced talking on the subject of religion, and, after I had made some remarks concerning the
  Bible, I commenced giving him a relation of the circumstances connected with the coming forth of
  the Book of Mormon, as recorded in the former part of this history.</p>
  <p class="std">While I was relating a brief history of the establishment of the Church of Christ<span class="footRef">1</span> in the last days,
  Joshua seemed to be highly entertained. When I had closed my narration, I observed that the hour
  of worship and dinner had arrived, and invited him to tarry, to which he consented. After dinner, the
  conversation was resumed, and Joshua proceeded to make some remarks on the prophecies, as
  follows&mdash;he observed that he was aware that I could bear stronger meat<span class="footRef">2</span> than many others, therefore
  he should open his mind the more freely:</p>
  <p class="std">Daniel has told us that he is to stand in his proper lot,<span class="footRef">3</span> in the latter days; according to his vision
  he had a right to shut it up, and also to open it again after many days,<span class="footRef">4</span> or in latter times. Daniel&rsquo;s
  image, whose head was gold, and body, arms, legs and feet, were composed of the different
  materials described in his vision,<span class="footRef">5</span> represents different governments. The golden head was to
  represent Nebuchadnezzar, King of Babylon;<span class="footRef">6</span> the other parts, other kings and forms of governments
  which I shall not now mention in detail, but confine my remarks more particularly to the feet of the
  image.<span class="footRef">7</span> The policy of the wicked spirit<span class="footRef">8</span> is to separate what God has joined together,<span class="footRef">9</span> and unite what
  He has separated, which the devil has succeeded in doing to admiration in the present society, which
  is like unto iron and clay.<span class="footRef">10</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/26/21" target="_blank">3 Ne. 26:21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/20/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 20:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/12,14" target="_blank">Heb. 5:12,14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/12/13" target="_blank">Dan. 12:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/8/26" target="_blank">Dan. 8:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/31-33" target="_blank">Dan. 2:31-33</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/38" target="_blank">Dan. 2:38</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/41-43" target="_blank">Dan. 2:41-43</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/22/15" target="_blank">Alma 22:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/19/6" target="_blank">Matt. 19:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/43" target="_blank">Dan. 2:43</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
