<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="52"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs51.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs53.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 52</div>
  <p class="cont">bring forward another item, to further urge the propriety of yielding obedience to the law of heaven,
  after the fact is admitted, that the laws of man are binding upon man. Were a king to extend his
  dominion over the habitable earth, and send forth his laws which were the most perfect kind, and
  command his subjects one and all to yield obedience to the same, and add as a reward to those who
  obeyed them, that at a certain period they should be called to attend the marriage of his son,<span class="footRef">1</span> who
  in due time was to receive the kingdom, and they should be made equal with him<span class="footRef">2</span> in the same; and
  fix as a penalty for disobedience that every individual guilty of it should be cast out at the marriage
  feast, and have no part nor portion with his government, what rational mind could for a moment
  accuse the king with injustice for punishing such rebellious subjects? In the first place his laws were
  just, easy to be complied with, and perfect: nothing of a tyrannical nature was required of them; but
  the very construction of the laws was equity and beauty; and when obeyed would produce the
  happiest condition possible to all who adhered to them, beside the last great benefit of sitting down
  with a royal robe in the presence of the king at the great, grand marriage supper of his son, and be
  made equal with him in all affairs of the kingdom.</p>
  <div class="topic">&ldquo;Thus Saith the King&rdquo;</div>
  <p class="std">When these royal laws were issued, and promulgated throughout the vast dominion, every
  subject, when interrogated whether he believed them to be from his sovereign or not, answered, Yes;
  I know they are, I am acquainted with the signature, for it is as usual. <i>Thus saith the King!</i><span class="footRef">3</span> This
  admitted, the subject is bound by every consideration of honor to his country, his king, and his own
  personal character, to observe in the strictest sense every requisition in the royal edict. Should any
  escape the search of the ambassadors of the king, and never hear these last laws, giving his subjects
  such exalted privileges, an excuse might be urged in their behalf,<span class="footRef">4</span> and they escape the censure of
  the king. But for those who had heard, who had admitted, and who had promised obedience to these
  just laws<span class="footRef">5</span> no excuse could be urged, and when brought into the presence of the king certainly, justice
  would require that they should suffer a penalty. Could that king be just in admitting these rebellious
  individuals into the full enjoyment and priv-</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/22/1-14" target="_blank">Matt. 22:1-14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/5/18" target="_blank">John 5:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/2/6" target="_blank">Philip. 2:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_kgs/2/30" target="_blank">1 Kgs. 2:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/5" target="_blank">Alma 29:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/7/12" target="_blank">Rom. 7:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/10/24" target="_blank">Alma 10:24</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/42/18" target="_blank">Alma 42:18</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
