<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="268"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs267.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs269.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 268</div>
  <p class="cont">and was pleased with the progress made in the sacred edifice. After conversing with several of the
  brethren, and shaking hands with numbers who were very much rejoiced to see their Prophet again,
  I returned home; but soon afterwards went over to the store, where a number of brethren and sisters
  were assembled, who had arrived this morning from the neighborhood of New York, Long Island,
  &amp;c. After Elders Taylor, Woodruff and Samuel Bennett had addressed the brethren and sisters, I
  spoke to them at considerable length, showing them the proper course to pursue, and how to act in
  regard to making purchases of land, &amp;c.</p>
  <p class="std">I showed them that it was generally in consequence of the brethren disregarding or disobeying
  counsel<span class="footRef">1</span> that they became dissatisfied and murmured; and many when they arrived here, were
  dissatisfied with the conduct of some of the Saints, because everything was not done perfectly right,
  and they get angry, and thus the devil gets advantage over them to destroy them. I told them I was
  but a man,<span class="footRef">2</span> and they must not expect me to be perfect;<span class="footRef">3</span> if they expected perfection from me, I should
  expect it from them;<span class="footRef">4</span> but if they would bear with my infirmities<span class="footRef">5</span> and the infirmities of the brethren,
  I would likewise bear with their infirmities.</p>
  <p class="std">I told them it was likely I would have again to hide up in the woods, but they must not be
  discouraged, but build up the city, the Temple, &amp;c. When my enemies take away my rights, I will
  bear it and keep out of the way; but if they take away your rights, I will fight for you. I blessed them
  and departed. (Oct. 29, 1842.) DHC 5:181.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Rule of Christ in the Millennium</div>
  <p class="std">While in conversation at Judge Adams&rsquo; during the evening, I said, Christ and the resurrected
  Saints<span class="footRef">6</span> will reign over the earth during the thousand years.<span class="footRef">7</span> They will not probably dwell upon the
  earth, but will visit it when they please, or when it is necessary to govern it. There will be wicked<span class="textFootRef">a</span>
  men on the</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/56/14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 56:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/63/55" target="_blank">D&amp;C 63:55</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/101/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 101:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/84" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:84</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/136/19" target="_blank">D&amp;C 136:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/25" target="_blank">Moses 5:25</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/36" target="_blank">Acts 10:36</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/14/15" target="_blank">Acts 14:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/17" target="_blank">James 5:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/10-11" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:10-11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/60" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:60</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/48" target="_blank">Matt. 5:48</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/12/48" target="_blank">3 Ne. 12:48</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/27/27" target="_blank">3 Ne. 27:27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/15/1" target="_blank">Rom. 15:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/11/1" target="_blank">2 Cor. 11:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jude/1/14-15" target="_blank">Jude 1:14-15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/20/6" target="_blank">Rev. 20:6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>The Prophet&rsquo;s statement that there will be wicked men on the earth during the Millennium has caused considerable confusion in the minds of many who have read in the Scripture in many places that when Christ comes the earth shall be cleansed from its wickedness, and that the wicked shall not stand, but shall be consumed. See D. and C. 5:18-19, 29:8-10, 101:23-25;
        Isaiah 24:1-3; Malachi 4:1. The evil-minded inhabitants, those &ldquo;who love and make a lie&rdquo; and are guilty of all manner of corruption, will be consumed</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
