<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="104"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs103.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs105.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 104</div>
  <p class="std">There is confusion in all things, both political and religious; and notwithstanding all the efforts
  that are made to bring about a union, society remains disunited, and all attempts to unite it are as
  fruitless as to attempt to unite iron and clay. The feet of the image<span class="footRef">1</span> are the government of these
  United States. Other nations and kingdoms are looking up to her for an example of union, freedom,
  and equal rights, and therefore worship her as Daniel saw in the vision;<span class="footRef">2</span> although they are beginning
  to lose confidence in her, seeing the broils and discord that rise on her political and religious
  horizon. The image is characteristic of all governments.</p>
  <p class="std">We should leave Babylon. Twenty-four hours of improvement now, are worth as much as a year
  a hundred years ago. The spirits of the fathers that were cut down, or those that were under the altar,<span class="footRef">3</span>
  are now rising; this is the first resurrection. The Elder that falls first will rise last.<span class="footRef">4</span> We should not
  form any opinion only for the present, and leave the result of futurity with God. I have risen up out
  of obscurity,<span class="footRef">5</span> but was looked up to in temporal things when but a youth. It is not necessary that God
  should give us all things in His first commission to us, but in His second. John saw the angel deliver
  the Gospel in the last days.<span class="footRef">6</span> The small lights that God has given are sufficient to lead us out of
  Babylon;<span class="footRef">7</span> when we get out, we shall have the greater light.<span class="footRef">8</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Transmigration a Doctrine of the Devil</div>
  <p class="std">I told Joshua I did not understand his remarks on the resurrection, and wished him to explain.
  He replied that he did not feel impressed by the Spirit to unfold it further at present,<span class="footRef">9</span> but perhaps he
  might at some future time.</p>
  <p class="std">I then withdrew to transact some business with a gentleman who had called to see me, when
  Joshua informed my scribe that he was born in Cambridge, Washington County, New York. He says
  that all the railroads, canals, and other improvements are projected by the spirits of the resurrection.
  The silence spoken of by John the Revelator, which is to be in heaven for the space of half an hour,<span class="footRef">10</span>
  is between 1830 and 1851, during which time the judgments of God will be poured out,<span class="footRef">11</span> after that
  time there will be peace. * * *</p>
  <p class="std">Suspicions were entertained that the said Joshua was the noted Matthias of New York, spoken
  so much of in the public</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/41-43" target="_blank">Dan. 2:41-43</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/2/38" target="_blank">Dan. 2:38</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/6/9" target="_blank">Rev. 6:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/20/16" target="_blank">Matt. 20:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/29/18" target="_blank">Isa. 29:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/6-7" target="_blank">Rev. 14:6-7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/82/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 82:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/4/18" target="_blank">Jacob 4:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/40/3" target="_blank">Alma 40:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 90:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/8/1" target="_blank">Rev. 8:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/58" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:58</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/45" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:45</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
