<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="140"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs139.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs141.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 140</div>
  <p class="cont">respects to fathers, mothers, wives and children, brothers and sisters; we hold them in the most
  sacred remembrance.<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <p class="std">We feel to inquire after Elder Rigdon; if he has not forgotten us, it has not been signified to us
  by his writing. Brother George W. Robinson also; and Elder Cahoon, we remember him, but would
  like to jog his memory a little on the fable of the bear and the two friends who mutually agreed to
  stand by each other. And perhaps it would not be amiss to mention uncle John [Smith], and various
  others. A word of consolation and a blessing would not come amiss from anybody, while we are
  being so closely whispered by the bear. But we feel to excuse everybody and everything, yea the
  more readily when we contemplate that we are in the hands of persons worse than a bear, for the
  bear would not prey upon a dead carcass.</p>
  <p class="std">Our respects and love and fellowship to all the virtuous Saints. We are your brethren and
  fellow-sufferers, and prisoners of Jesus Christ<span class="footRef">2</span> for the Gospel&rsquo;s sake,<span class="footRef">3</span> and for the hope of glory<span class="footRef">4</span>
  which is in us. Amen.</p>
  <div class="topic">Continued Reflections</div>
  <p class="std">We continue to offer further reflections to Bishop Partridge, and to the Church of Jesus Christ
  of Latter-day Saints, whom we love with a fervent love, and do always bear them in mind in all our
  prayers to the throne of God.<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <p class="std">It still seems to bear heavily on our minds that the Church would do well to secure to
  themselves the contract of the land which is proposed to them by Mr. Isaac Galland,<span class="footRef">6</span> and to cultivate
  the friendly feelings of that gentleman, inasmuch as he shall prove himself to be a man of honor and
  a friend to humanity; also Isaac Van Allen, Esq., the attorney-general of Iowa Territory, and
  Governor Lucas, that peradventure such men may be wrought upon by the providence of God,<span class="footRef">7</span> to
  do good unto His people. We really think that Mr. Galland&rsquo;s letter breathes that kind of a spirit, if
  we may judge correctly. Governor Lucas&rsquo; also. We suggest the idea of praying fervently<span class="footRef">8</span> for all men
  who manifest any degree of sympathy for the suffering children of God.<span class="footRef">9</span></p>
  <p class="std">We think that the United States Surveyor of the Iowa Territory may be of great benefit to the
  Church, if it be the will of God to this end; and righteousness should be manifested as the girdle of
  our loins.<span class="footRef">10</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/117/12" target="_blank">D&amp;C 117:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philem/1/9" target="_blank">Philem. 1:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/9/23" target="_blank">1 Cor. 9:23</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/col/1/27" target="_blank">Col. 1:27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/8/3-4" target="_blank">Rev. 8:3-4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/124/78-79" target="_blank">D&amp;C 124:78-79</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/col/4/12" target="_blank">Col. 4:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/16" target="_blank">James 5:16</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_h/1/1000" target="_blank">JS&mdash;H 1 Endnote</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/5/9" target="_blank">Matt. 5:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/51" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:51</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/11/5" target="_blank">Isa. 11:5</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
