<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="255"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs254.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs256.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 255</div>
  <p class="cont">may be assured that they are duly appreciated by me, and shall be reciprocated.</p>
  <p class="std">I am perfectly satisfied with regard to the subject under consideration, and with your remarks.
  I shall consider myself and our citizens secure from harm under the broad canopy of the law under
  your administration. We look to you for protection in the event of any violence being used towards
  us, knowing that our innocence with regard to all the accusations in circulation will be duly
  evidenced before an enlightened public.</p>
  <p class="std">Any service we can do the state at any time will be cheerfully done,<span class="footRef">1</span> for our ambition is to be
  serviceable to our country.</p>
  <p class="std">With sentiments of respect and esteem, I remain your humble servant.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH. DHC 5:83.</p>
  <div class="topic">Prophecy That the Saints Would Be Driven to Rocky Mountains</div>
  <p class="std">Saturday, Aug. 6, 1842.&mdash;Passed over the river to Montrose, Iowa, in company with General
  Adams, Colonel Brewer, and others, and witnessed the installation of the officers of the Rising Sun
  Lodge Ancient York Masons, at Montrose, by General James Adams, Deputy Grand-Master of
  Illinois. While the Deputy Grand-Master was engaged in giving the requisite instructions to the
  Master-elect, I had a conversation with a number of brethren in the shade of the building on the
  subject of our persecutions in Missouri and the constant annoyance which has followed us since we
  were driven from that state. I prophesied that the Saints would continue to suffer much affliction<span class="footRef">3</span>
  and would be driven to the Rocky Mountains, many would apostatize, others would be put to death
  by our persecutors or lose their lives in consequence of exposure of disease, and some of you will
  live to go and assist in making settlements and build cities and see the Saints become a mighty
  people in the midst of the Rocky Mountains.<span class="footRef">4</span> (Aug. 6, 1842.) DHC 5:85.</p>
  <div class="topic">Happiness the Design of Existence</div>
  <p class="std">Happiness is the object<span class="footRef">5</span> and design of our existence; and will be the end thereof, if we pursue
  the path that leads to it; and this path is virtue, uprightness, faithfulness, holiness,<span class="footRef">6</span> and</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/9/7" target="_blank">2 Cor. 9:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/24/15" target="_blank">Mosiah 24:15</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/123/17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 123:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/8/19" target="_blank">Alma 8:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/128/25" target="_blank">D&amp;C 128:25</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/11/25" target="_blank">Heb. 11:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/34" target="_blank">Hel. 3:34</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:49</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/33/16" target="_blank">Isa. 33:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/5/27" target="_blank">2 Ne. 5:27</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/41" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:41</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/1/2" target="_blank">Abr. 1:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/4-8" target="_blank">2 Pet. 1:4-8</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
