<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="173"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs172.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs174.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 173</div>
  <p class="cont">that the offerings and sacrifices are not all consumed upon the altar&mdash;but the blood is sprinkled,<span class="footRef">1</span> and
  the fat and certain other portions are consumed.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <div class="topic">All Ordinances Restored</div>
  <p class="std">These sacrifices, as well as every ordinance belonging to the Priesthood, will, when the Temple
  of the Lord shall be built, and the sons of Levi be purified,<span class="footRef">3</span> be fully restored and attended to in all
  their powers, ramifications, and blessings. This ever did and ever will exist when the powers of the
  Melchizedek Priesthood are sufficiently manifest; else how can the restitution of all things spoken
  of by the Holy Prophets<span class="footRef">4</span> be brought to pass. It is not to be understood that the law of Moses will be
  established again with all its rites and variety of ceremonies; this has never been spoken of by the
  prophets; but those things which existed prior to Moses&rsquo; day, namely, sacrifice, will be continued.</p>
  <p class="std">It may be asked by some, what necessity for sacrifice, since the Great Sacrifice<span class="footRef">5</span> was offered?
  In answer to which, if repentance, baptism, and faith existed prior to the days of Christ, what
  necessity for them since that time? The Priesthood has descended in a regular line from father to
  son,<span class="footRef">6</span> through their succeeding generations. (See Book of Doctrine and Covenants.) (October 5,
  1840.) DHC 4:207–212.</p>
  <div class="topic">An Epistle of the Prophet to the Twelve</div>
  <p class="std">To the Traveling High Council and Elders of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints
  in Great Britain:</p>
  <p class="std">Beloved Brethren.&mdash;May grace, mercy, and peace rest upon you from God the Father and the
  Lord Jesus Christ.<span class="footRef">7</span> Having several communications lying before me from my brethren the Twelve,
  some of which ere this have merited a reply, but from the multiplicity of business which necessarily
  engages my attention, I have delayed communicating with you to the present time.</p>
  <p class="std">Be assured, beloved brethren, that I am no disinterested observer of the things which are
  transpiring on the face of the whole earth;<span class="footRef">8</span> and amidst the general movements which are in progress,
  none is of more importance than the glorious work in which you are now engaged; consequently I
  feel some anxiety on your account, that you may by your virtue, faith,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/24/6" target="_blank">Ex. 24:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/29/13" target="_blank">Ex. 29:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mal/3/3" target="_blank">Mal. 3:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/3/21" target="_blank">Acts 3:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/14" target="_blank">Alma 34:14</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/13" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/40-52" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:40-52</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/1/2" target="_blank">1 Tim. 1:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/8/9" target="_blank">Gen. 8:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/21/35" target="_blank">Luke 21:35</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/3/8" target="_blank">Hel. 3:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:30</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/26" target="_blank">Moses 7:26</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
