<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="26"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs25.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs27.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 26</div>
  <p class="cont">eternal. As ever, we salute you in the name of the Lord Jesus.<span class="footRef">1</span> Amen.</p>
  <div class="signatureBlock">
    <p class="signatureLine">JOSEPH SMITH, JUN.,</p>
    <p class="signatureLine">SIDNEY RIGDON,</p>
    <p class="signatureLine">F. G. WILLIAMS.</p>
    <p class="std">&mdash;DHC 1:368–370.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="topic">Minor Events in Zion and Kirtland&mdash;</div>
  <div class="topic">an Appeal to the Governor of Missouri</div>
  <p class="wideEllipse">* * *</p>

  <div class="topic">Letter to Vienna Jaques</div>
  <p class="std">September 4.&mdash;I wrote as follows to Sister Vienna Jaques,<span class="footRef">2</span> at Independence, Missouri:</p>
  <p class="std">Dear Sister:&mdash;Having a few leisure moments, I sit down to communicate to you a few words,
  which I know I am under obligation to improve for your satisfaction, if it should be a satisfaction
  for you to receive a few words from your unworthy brother in Christ. I received your letter some
  time since, containing a history of your journey and your safe arrival, for which I bless the Lord; I
  have often felt a whispering since I received your letter, like this: &ldquo;Joseph, thou art indebted to thy
  God for the offering of thy Sister Vienna, which proved a savor of life as pertaining to thy pecuniary
  concerns. Therefore she should not be forgotten of thee, for the Lord hath done this,<span class="footRef">3</span> and thou
  shouldst remember her in all thy prayers and also by letter, for she oftentimes calleth on the Lord,
  saying, O Lord, inspire thy servant Joseph to communicate by letter some word to thine unworthy
  handmaiden, and say all my sins are forgiven,<span class="footRef">4</span> and art thou not content with the chastisement
  where-with thou hast chastised thy handmaiden?&rdquo;  Yea, sister, this seems to be the whispering of
  a spirit, and judge ye what spirit it is. I was aware when you left Kirtland that the Lord would
  chasten<span class="footRef">5</span> you, but I prayed fervently<span class="footRef">6</span> in the name of Jesus that you might live to receive your
  inheritance, agreeable to the commandment which was given concerning you.<span class="footRef">7</span> I am not at all
  astonished at what has happened to you, neither to what has happened to Zion, and I could tell all
  they whys and wherefores of all these calamities. But alas, it is in vain to warn and give precepts,
  for all men are naturally disposed to walk in their own paths<span class="footRef">8</span> as they are pointed out by their own
  fingers, and are not</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/133" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:133</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/28" target="_blank">D&amp;C 90:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/126/3" target="_blank">Ps. 126:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/41/20" target="_blank">Isa. 41:20</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/44/23" target="_blank">Isa. 44:23</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/5/19" target="_blank">Mark 5:19</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/112/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 112:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/36" target="_blank">D&amp;C 90:36</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/95/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 95:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/21" target="_blank">D&amp;C 98:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/16" target="_blank">James 5:16</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/28,30" target="_blank">D&amp;C 90:28,30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/joel/2/8" target="_blank">Joel 2:8</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
