<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="214"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs213.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs215.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 214</div>
  <p class="cont">and many ridiculous things were entered into, calculated to bring disgrace upon the Church of God,
  to cause the Spirit of God to be withdrawn,<span class="footRef">1</span> and to uproot and destroy those glorious principles
  which had been developed for the salvation of the human family. But when the authorities returned,
  the spirit was made manifest,<span class="footRef">2</span> those members that were exercised with it were tried for their
  fellowship, and those that would not repent and forsake it were cut off.</p>
  <p class="std">At a subsequent period a Shaker spirit was on the point of being introduced, and at another time
  the Methodist and Presbyterian falling down power, but the spirit was rebuked<span class="footRef">3</span> and put down, and
  those who would not submit to rule and good order were disfellowshiped. We have also had brethren
  and sisters who have had the gift of tongues falsely; they would speak in a muttering, unnatural
  voice, and their bodies be distorted like the Irvingites before alluded to; whereas, there is nothing
  unnatural in the Spirit of God. A circumstance of this kind took place in Upper Canada, but was
  rebuked by the presiding Elder; another, a woman near the same place, professed to have the
  discerning of spirits, and began to accuse another sister of things that she was not guilty of, which
  she said she knew was so by the spirit, but was afterwards proven to be false; she placed herself in
  the capacity of the &ldquo;accuser of the brethren,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> and no person through the discerning of spirits can
  bring a charge against another, they must be proven guilty by positive evidence, or they stand clear.</p>
  <p class="std">There have also been ministering angels in the Church which were of Satan appearing as an
  angel of light.<span class="footRef">5</span> A sister in the state of New York had a vision, who said it was told her that if she
  would go to a certain place in the woods, an angel would appear to her. She went at the appointed
  time, and saw a glorious personage descending, arrayed in white,<span class="footRef">6</span> with sandy colored hair; he
  commenced and told her to fear God,<span class="footRef">7</span> and said that her husband was called to do great things, but
  that he must not go more than one hundred miles from home, or he would not return; whereas God
  had called him to go to the ends of the earth,<span class="footRef">8</span> and he has since been more than one thousand miles
  from home, and is yet alive. Many true things were spoken by this personage, and many things that
  were false. How, it may be asked, was this known to be a bad angel? By the color of his hair; that
  is one of the signs that he can</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/34/35" target="_blank">Alma 34:35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/31" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:31</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mark/9/25" target="_blank">Mark 9:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/9/42" target="_blank">Luke 9:42</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/12/10" target="_blank">Rev. 12:10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_cor/11/14" target="_blank">2 Cor. 11:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/5/12" target="_blank">2 Chr. 5:12</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/7/13" target="_blank">Rev. 7:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/19/8" target="_blank">Rev. 19:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eccl/12/13" target="_blank">Eccl. 12:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/2/17" target="_blank">1 Pet. 2:17</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/14/7" target="_blank">Rev. 14:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/104" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:104</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/38" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:38</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/45/22" target="_blank">Isa. 45:22</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/13/47" target="_blank">Acts 13:47</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/11/41" target="_blank">3 Ne. 11:41</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/1/11" target="_blank">D&amp;C 1:11</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/90/9" target="_blank">D&amp;C 90:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/23,57" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:23,57</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
