<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="84"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs83.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs85.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 84</div>
  <p class="cont">of heaven, and truth will I send forth out of the earth, to bear testimony of mine Only Begotten, His
  resurrection from the dead (this resurrection I understand to be the corporeal body); yea, and also
  the resurrection of all men; righteousness and truth will I cause to sweep the earth as with a flood,
  to gather out mine own elect from the four quarters of the earth, unto a place which I shall prepare,
  a holy city, that my people may gird up their loins, and be looking forth for the time of my coming,
  for there shall be my tabernacle, and it shall be called Zion a new Jerusalem.&rdquo;  (Moses 7:62, 1902
  edition.)<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <div class="topic">The Glorious Resurrection</div>
  <p class="std">Now I understand by this quotation, that God clearly manifested to Enoch the redemption which
  He prepared, by offering the Messiah as a Lamb slain from before the foundation of the world;<span class="footRef">2</span> and
  by virtue of the same, the glorious resurrection<span class="footRef">3</span> of the Savior, and the resurrection of all the human
  family, even a resurrection of their corporeal bodies, is brought to pass; and also righteousness and
  truth are to sweep the earth as with a flood. And now, I ask, how righteousness and truth are going
  to sweep the earth as with a flood? I will answer. Men and angels are to be co-workers in bringing
  to pass this great work, and Zion is to be prepared, even a new Jerusalem, for the elect that are to
  be gathered from the four quarters<span class="footRef">4</span> of the earth, and to be established an holy city, for the tabernacle
  of the Lord<span class="footRef">5</span> shall be with them.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Elect Must Be Gathered</div>
  <p class="std">Now Enoch was in good company in his views upon this subject: &ldquo;And I heard a great voice out
  of heaven, saying, Behold, the tabernacle of God is with men, and He will dwell with them, and they
  shall be His people and God Himself shall be with them, and be their God&rdquo; (Revelation 21:3).<span class="footRef">6</span></p>
  <p class="std">I discover by this quotation, that John upon the isle of Patmos,<span class="footRef">7</span> saw the same things concerning
  the last days, which Enoch saw. But before the tabernacle can be with men, the elect must be
  gathered from the four quarters of the earth.<span class="footRef">8</span> And to show further upon this subject of the gathering,
  Moses, after having pronounced the blessing and cursing<span class="footRef">9</span> upon the children of Israel, for their
  obedience or disobedience, says thus:</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/62" target="_blank">Moses 7:62</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/7/47" target="_blank">Moses 7:47</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/45" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:45</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/14" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 33:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_m/1/27" target="_blank">JS&mdash;M 1:27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/num/16/9" target="_blank">Num. 16:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_chr/16/39" target="_blank">1 Chr. 16:39</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_chr/21/29" target="_blank">1 Chr. 21:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/3" target="_blank">Rev. 21:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/1/9" target="_blank">Rev. 1:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/33/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 33:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/js_m/1/27" target="_blank">JS&mdash;M 1:27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/deut/28/1-68" target="_blank">Deut. 28:1-68</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
