<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="50"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs49.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs51.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 50</div>
  <p class="cont">violated, or broken by the individual, must, in justice, convict his mind with a double force, if
  possible, of the extent and magnitude of his crime; because he could have no plea of ignorance to
  produce; and his act of transgression was openly committed against light and knowledge.<span class="footRef">1</span> But the
  individual who may be ignorant and imperceptibly transgresses or violates laws, though the voice
  of the country requires that he should suffer, yet he will never feel that remorse of conscience<span class="footRef">2</span> that
  the other will, and that keen, cutting reflection will never rise in his breast that otherwise would, had
  he done the deed, or committed the offense in full conviction that he was breaking the law of his
  country, and having previously acknowledged the same to be just. It is not our intention by these
  remarks, to attempt to place the law of man<span class="footRef">3</span> on a parallel with the law of heaven;<span class="footRef">4</span> because we do
  not consider that it is formed in the same wisdom and propriety; neither do we consider that it is
  sufficient in itself to bestow anything on man in comparison with the law of heaven, even should
  it promise it. The laws of men<span class="footRef">5</span> may guarantee to a people protection in the honorable pursuits of this
  life, and the temporal happiness arising from a protection against unjust insults and injuries; and
  when this is said, all is said, that can be in truth, of the power, extent, and influence of the laws of
  men, exclusive of the law of God.<span class="footRef">6</span> The law of heaven is presented to man, and as such guarantees
  to all who obey it a reward far beyond any earthy consideration; though it does not promise that the
  believer in every age should be exempt from the afflictions and troubles arising from different
  sources in consequence of the acts of wicked men<span class="footRef">7</span> on earth. Still in the midst of all this there is a
  promise predicated upon the fact that it is the law of heaven, which transcends the law of man, as
  far as eternal life the temporal; and as the blessings which God is able to give, are greater than those
  which can be given by man. Then, certainly, if the law of man is binding upon man when
  acknowledged, how much more must the law of heaven be!  And as much as the law of heaven is
  more perfect than the law of man, so much greater must be the reward if obeyed.<span class="footRef">8</span> The law of man
  promises safety in temporal life; but the law of God promises that life which is eternal,<span class="footRef">9</span> even an
  inheritance at God&rsquo;s own right hand,<span class="footRef">10</span> secure from all the powers of the wicked one.<span class="footRef">11</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/39/6" target="_blank">Alma 39:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/45/12" target="_blank">Alma 45:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/18" target="_blank">Alma 5:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/29/5" target="_blank">Alma 29:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/42/18" target="_blank">Alma 42:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/98/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 98:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/102/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 102:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/7/22,25" target="_blank">Rom. 7:22,25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/33" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:33</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/81,91" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:81,91</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/num/16/26" target="_blank">Num. 16:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/3/2" target="_blank">2 Thes. 3:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/19/10" target="_blank">1 Ne. 19:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/8" target="_blank">D&amp;C 10:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/48" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:48</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/34-35" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:34-35</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/132/24" target="_blank">D&amp;C 132:24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/5/58" target="_blank">Alma 5:58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/42,49" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:42,49</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
