<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="3"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs2.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs4.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 3</div>
  <div class="topic">Author&rsquo;s Foreword</div>
  <p class="std">I have had a fondness for the sermons and writings of the Prophet Joseph Smith for many
  years. My interest was initially sparked in the classes of Hyrum L. Andrus when I was an
  undergraduate student at Brigham Young University. I always appreciated the Prophet&rsquo;s usage of
  the scriptures, and would occasionally note a few scriptural references in the margins of my copy
  of the <i>Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith.</i></p>
  <p class="std">In November, 1989, I decided it was time to formally catalog these marginal notes and hunt
  up what scriptural references remained. I contacted a friend in the Ancient Scripture Department,
  Monte S. Nyman, and asked if he had any scriptural references in his copy of the Teachings which
  might save me a little time. Mont gave me a list containing 700 entries. I was sure the task was
  nearly done.</p>
  <p class="std">As with so many things, the little project began to take on a life of its own. My first careful
  reading of the <i>Teachings</i> resulted in 2,000 scriptural references. In addition, I discovered that many
  of the phrases and passages of the <i>Teachings,</i> although not quoting verbatim, were extremely useful
  in the interpretation of many other scriptures, and vice versa. Several readings have transpired since,
  and the final count now stands at over 11,000 references, both direct and contextual. Doubtless there
  are others.</p>
  <p class="std">I also found that the line between scripture cited and scriptural concept noted became
  increasingly blurred as my appreciation of the Prophet&rsquo;s scriptural prowess grew. When asked if he
  stole his wife, the Prophet once replied &ldquo;Ask her, she was of age, she can answer for herself&rdquo; (<i>Teachings</i>,
  p. 120). In a strict sense, this is not a scriptural citation. But after experiencing the Prophet&rsquo;s
  scriptural genius time and again, I am persuaded that a clever use was made of John 9:21. In this
  passage, the parents of the man born blind, seeking to avoid excommunication (John 9:22), replied
  to the Pharisees, &ldquo;he is of age; ask him: he shall speak for himself."</p>
  <p class="std">A brief sampling of the Prophet&rsquo;s scriptural usage, including a basis for this ability from his
  life experiences, is included in the Appendix. It is hoped that the present work highlights one of the
  great contributions of the Prophet Joseph Smith, that of &ldquo;expounding all scriptures unto the church"
  (D&amp;C 24:5).</p>
  <p class="std">The <i>Scriptural Teachings of the Prophet Joseph Smith</i> has benefitted from the contributions
  of friends and family. My wife Sandy, and children James, Jennifer, Daniel, Stefanie, and Michelle
  have patiently allowed me to see an idea through to fruition. The Department of Family Sciences
  at Brigham Young University (Terrance D. Olson, Chairman) has tolerated my wide range of
  research interests and generously provided computer equipment. Specialty Reference Retrieval (Paul
  M. Urie, Mark L. Donaldson, Richard C. Galbraith) provided Retriever, a computer text retrieval program, which
  greatly aided in the identification of scriptural references. Don E. Norton of the English Department,
  Brigham Young University, has been most helpful in editing my nonscriptural material.
  Finally, two women have greatly influenced my love of the scriptures and the restored gospel
  of Jesus Christ. My angel grandmother, Harriet Amanda Davis, raised me as a child to appreciate
  the abundant life contained in the scriptures (John 10:10). Her life was &ldquo;seasoned with grace&rdquo; (<i>Teachings,</i>
  p. 156, Col. 4:6). Truly, &ldquo;She openeth her mouth with wisdom; and in her tongue is the law of
  kindness&rdquo; (Prov. 31:26; Eph. 4:32). Louise O. Belnap, a dear friend, was a saint &ldquo;instructed unto the
  kingdom of heaven who freely brought forth of her treasure goodly pearls, new and old&rdquo; (Matt.
  13:45, 52; Matt. 10:8).</p>
</div>
