<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="183"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs182.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs184.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 183</div>
  <div class="topic">The Gathering of Saints</div>
  <p class="std">The greatest temporal and spiritual blessings which always come from faithfulness and
  concerted effort, never attended individual exertion or enterprise. The history of all past ages
  abundantly attests this fact. In addition to all temporal blessings, there is no other way for the Saints
  to be saved in these last days, [than by the gathering] as the concurrent testimony of all the holy
  prophets clearly proves, for it is written&mdash;&ldquo;They shall come from the east, and be gathered from the
  west; the north shall give up, and the south shall keep not back.&rdquo;  &ldquo;The sons of God shall be gathered
  from afar, and his daughters from the ends of the earth.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <p class="std">It is also the concurrent testimony of all the prophets, that this gathering together of all the
  Saints, must take place before the Lord comes to &ldquo;take vengeance<span class="footRef">2</span> upon the ungodly,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">3</span> and &ldquo;to be
  glorified and admired by all those who obey the Gospel.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">4</span> The fiftieth Psalm, from the first to the
  fifth verse inclusive,<span class="footRef">5</span> describes the glory and majesty of that event. (Jan. 8, 1841.) DHC 4:272.</p>
  <div class="topic">Order of the Priesthood in Temple Building</div>
  <p class="summary">The following instruction was given at the time of the laying of the corner stones of the Nauvoo Temple, April 6,
  1841.</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std">If the strict order of the Priesthood<span class="footRef">6</span> were carried out in the building of Temples, the first stone
  would be laid at the south-east corner, by the First Presidency of the Church. The south-west corner
  should be laid next. The third, or north-west corner next; and the fourth, or north-east corner last.
  The First Presidency should lay the south-east corner stone and dictate who are the proper persons
  to lay the other corner stones.</p>
  <p class="std">If a Temple is built at a distance, and the First Presidency are not present, then the Quorum of
  the Twelve Apostles are the persons to dictate the order for that Temple; and in the absence of the
  Twelve Apostles, then the Presidency of the Stake will lay the south-east corner stone; the
  Melchizedek Priesthood laying the corner stones on the east side of the Temple, and the Lesser
  Priesthood those on the west side.&mdash;DHC 4:331.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/43/5-6" target="_blank">Isa. 43:5-6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/47/3" target="_blank">Isa. 47:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/nahum/1/2" target="_blank">Nahum 1:2</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/17" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/97/22" target="_blank">D&amp;C 97:22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_thes/1/8,10" target="_blank">2 Thes. 1:8,10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/50/1-5" target="_blank">Ps. 50:1-5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/94/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 94:6</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
