<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="291"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs290.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs292.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 291</div>
  <p class="cont">grand distinction between the actual meaning of the prophets and the present translation. The
  prophets do not declare that they saw a beast or beasts, but that they saw the <i>image</i> or <i>figure</i> of a
  beast.<span class="footRef">1</span> Daniel did not see an actual bear or a lion, but the images or figures of those beasts. The
  translation should have been rendered &ldquo;image&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;beast,&rdquo; in every instance where beasts
  are mentioned by the prophets. But John saw the actual beast in heaven,<span class="footRef">2</span> showing to John that beasts
  did actually exist there, and not to represent figures of things on the earth. When the prophets speak
  of seeing beasts in their visions, they mean that they saw the images, they being types to represent
  certain things. At the same time they received the interpretation as to what those images or types
  were designed to represent.</p>
  <p class="std">I make this broad declaration, that whenever God gives a vision of an image, or beast, or figure
  of any kind, He always holds Himself responsible to give a revelation or interpretation of the
  meaning thereof, otherwise we are not responsible or accountable for our belief in it. Don&rsquo;t be afraid
  of being damned for not knowing the meaning of a vision or figure, if God has not given a revelation
  or interpretation of the subject.</p>
  <p class="std">John saw curious looking beasts in heaven; he saw every creature that was in heaven,&mdash;all the
  beasts, fowls and fish in heaven,<span class="footRef">3</span>&mdash;actually there, giving glory to God.<span class="footRef">4</span> How do you prove it? (See
  Rev. 5:13.) &ldquo;And every creature which is in heaven, and on the earth, and under the earth, and such
  as are in the sea, and all that are in them, heard I saying, Blessing, and honor, and glory, and power,
  be unto Him that sitteth upon the throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">5</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Varied Creatures in Heaven</div>
  <p class="std">I suppose John saw beings there of a thousand forms, that had been saved from ten thousand
  times ten thousand<span class="footRef">6</span> earths like this,&mdash;strange beasts of which we have no conception: all might be
  seen in heaven. The grand secret was to show John what there was in heaven. John learned that God
  glorified Himself by saving all<span class="footRef">7</span> that His hands had made,<span class="footRef">8</span> whether beasts, fowls, fishes or men; and
  He will glorify Himself with them.<span class="footRef">9</span></p>
  <p class="std">Says one, &ldquo;I cannot believe in the salvation of beasts.&rdquo;  Any man who would tell you that this
  could not be, would tell you that the revelations are not true. John heard the words of</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/2-3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 77:2-3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/13/1" target="_blank">Rev. 13:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/24" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:24</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/117/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 117:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/4/9" target="_blank">Rev. 4:9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/7/11-12" target="_blank">Rev. 7:11-12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/13" target="_blank">Rev. 5:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dan/7/10" target="_blank">Dan. 7:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/11" target="_blank">Rev. 5:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/5/13" target="_blank">Rev. 5:13</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/12,21" target="_blank">Abr. 3:12,21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/17/1,4,6,12,21-22" target="_blank">John 17:1,4,6,12,21-22</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
