<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="178"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs177.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs179.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 178</div>
  <p class="cont">and we expect a large gathering from the south. I have had the pleasure of welcoming about one
  hundred brethren who came with Brother Turley; the remainder I am informed stayed in Kirtland,
  not having means to get any further. I think that those who came here this fall, did not take the best
  possible route, or the least expensive. Most of the brethren have obtained employment of one kind
  or another, and appear tolerably well contented, and seem disposed to hearken to counsel.<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <div class="topic">Spread of the Gospel</div>
  <p class="std">Brothers Robinson and Smith lately had a letter from Elders Kimball, Smith and Woodruff,
  which gave us information of the commencement of the work of the Lord in the city of London,
  which I was glad to hear. I am likewise informed that elders have gone to Australia and to the East
  Indies. I feel desirous that every providential opening of the kind should be filled, and that you
  should, prior to your leaving England, send the Gospel into as many parts<span class="footRef">2</span> as you possibly can.</p>
  <p class="std">Beloved brethren, you must be aware in some measure of my feelings, when I contemplate the
  great work which is now rolling on,<span class="footRef">3</span> and the relationship which I sustain to it, while it is extending
  to distant lands, and thousands are embracing it. I realize in some measure my responsibility, and
  the need I have of support from above, and wisdom from on high,<span class="footRef">4</span> that I may be able to teach this
  people,<span class="footRef">5</span> which have now become a great people, the principles of righteousness,<span class="footRef">6</span> and lead them
  agreeably to the will of Heaven; so that they may be perfected, and prepared to meet the Lord Jesus
  Christ when He shall appear in great glory.<span class="footRef">7</span> Can I rely on your prayers to our heavenly Father on
  my behalf, and on all the prayers of all my brethren<span class="footRef">8</span> and sisters in England, (whom having not seen,
  yet I love),<span class="footRef">9</span> that I may be enabled to escape every stratagem of Satan,<span class="footRef">10</span> surmount every difficulty,
  and bring this people to the enjoyment of those blessings which are reserved<span class="footRef">11</span> for the righteous? I
  ask this at your hands in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ.</p>
  <p class="std">Let the Saints remember that great things depend on their individual exertion,<span class="footRef">12</span> and that they
  are called to be co-workers with us and the Holy Spirit<span class="footRef">13</span> in accomplishing the great work of the last
  days; and in consideration of the extent, the blessings and glories of the same, let every selfish
  feeling be not only buried, but annihilated; and let love to God and man<span class="footRef">14</span> predom-</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ex/18/19" target="_blank">Ex. 18:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/103/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 103:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/108/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 108:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/109/59" target="_blank">D&amp;C 109:59</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/78/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 78:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/42/58" target="_blank">D&amp;C 42:58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/36" target="_blank">D&amp;C 121:36</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/24/30" target="_blank">Matt. 24:30</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/43/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 43:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/1/8" target="_blank">1 Pet. 1:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/10/5" target="_blank">D&amp;C 10:5</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/27/36" target="_blank">Gen. 27:36</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_pet/1/4" target="_blank">1 Pet. 1:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/morm/5/19" target="_blank">Morm. 5:19</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/104/45" target="_blank">D&amp;C 104:45</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/58/26-29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 58:26-29</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/107/99-100" target="_blank">D&amp;C 107:99-100</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/121/46" target="_blank">D&amp;C 121:46</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">14. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/4" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:4</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
