<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="61"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs60.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs62.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 61</div>
  <p class="cont">time of His coming, and rely upon the power of that atonement<span class="footRef">1</span> for a remission of their sins.<span class="footRef">2</span> And
  this they have done, thousands who have gone before us, whose garments are spotless,<span class="footRef">3</span> and who are,
  like Job, waiting with an assurance like his, that they will see Him in the <i>latter day</i> upon the earth,
  even in their flesh.<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">We may conclude, that though there were different dispensations, yet all things which God
  communicated to His people were calculated to draw their minds to the great object, and to teach
  them to rely upon God<span class="footRef">5</span> alone as the author of their salvation,<span class="footRef">6</span> as contained in His law.</p>
  <div class="topic">Not All Revelation Is in the Bible</div>
  <p class="std">From what we can draw from the Scriptures relative to the teaching of heaven, we are induced
  to think that much instruction has been given to man since the beginning which we do not possess
  now. This may not agree with the opinions of some of our friends who are bold to say that we have
  everything written in the Bible which God ever spoke to man since the world began,<span class="footRef">7</span> and that if He
  had ever said anything more we should certainly have received it. But we ask, does it remain for a
  people who never had faith enough to call down one scrap of revelation from heaven, and for all
  they have now are indebted to the faith of another people who lived hundreds and thousands of years
  before them, does it remain for them to say how much God has spoken and how much He has not
  spoken? We have what we have, and the Bible contains what it does contain: but to say that God
  never said anything more to man than is there recorded, would be saying at once that we have at last
  received a revelation: for it must require one to advance thus far, because it is nowhere said in that
  volume by the mouth of God,<span class="footRef">8</span> that He would not, after giving what is there contained, speak again;
  and if any man has found out for a fact that the Bible contains all that God ever revealed to man he
  has ascertained it by an immediate revelation, other than has been previously written by the prophets
  and apostles. But through the kind providence of our Father a portion of His word<span class="footRef">9</span> which he
  delivered to His ancient saints, has fallen into our hands, is presented to us with a promise of a
  reward if obeyed, and with a penalty if disobeyed. That all are deeply</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/10/25" target="_blank">2 Ne. 10:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/8/20" target="_blank">Moro. 8:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/26/28" target="_blank">Matt. 26:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rom/3/25" target="_blank">Rom. 3:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_ne/25/26" target="_blank">2 Ne. 25:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/34" target="_blank">Alma 12:34</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/2" target="_blank">D&amp;C 27:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/7/25" target="_blank">Alma 7:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/34" target="_blank">D&amp;C 61:34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/job/19/25-27" target="_blank">Job 19:25-27</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/13/18" target="_blank">2 Chr. 13:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_chr/16/7" target="_blank">2 Chr. 16:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/5/9" target="_blank">Heb. 5:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/1/70" target="_blank">Luke 1:70</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/9/32" target="_blank">John 9:32</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_ne/3/20" target="_blank">1 Ne. 3:20</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/27/6" target="_blank">D&amp;C 27:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/4/4" target="_blank">Matt. 4:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/25" target="_blank">Moro. 7:25</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/84/44" target="_blank">D&amp;C 84:44</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/5/15" target="_blank">Moses 5:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/12/9-11" target="_blank">Alma 12:9-11</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
