<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="210"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs209.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs211.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 210</div>
  <p class="cont">coming, then cometh the end.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> But Jemimah, according to her testimony, died, and rose again
  before the time mentioned in the Scriptures. The idea of her soul being in heaven while her body was
  [living] on earth, is also preposterous. When God breathed into man&rsquo;s nostrils, he became a living
  soul,<span class="footRef">2</span> before that he did not live, and when that was taken away his body died;<span class="footRef">3</span> and so did our
  Savior when the spirit left the body,<span class="footRef">4</span> nor did His body live until His spirit returned in the power of
  His resurrection.<span class="footRef">5</span> But Mrs. Wilkinson&rsquo;s soul [life] was in heaven, and her body without the soul [or
  life] on earth, living [without the soul, or] without life!</p>
  <div class="topic">Irvingites</div>
  <p class="std">The Irvingites are a people that have counterfeited the truth, perhaps the nearest of any of our
  modern sectarians. They commenced about ten years ago in the city of London, in England; they
  have churches formed in various parts of England and Scotland, and some few in Upper Canada. Mr.
  Irving, their founder, was a learned and talented minister of the Church of Scotland, he was a great
  logician, and a powerful orator, but withal wild and enthusiastic in his views. Moving in the higher
  circles, and possessing talent and zeal, placed him in a situation to become a conspicuous character,
  and to raise up a society similar to that which is called after his name.</p>
  <p class="std">The Irvingites have apostles, prophets, pastors, teachers, evangelists,<span class="footRef">6</span> and angels. They profess
  to have the gift of tongues, and the interpretation of tongues, and, in some few instances, to have the
  gift of healing.<span class="footRef">7</span></p>
  <p class="std">The first prophetic spirit that was manifested was in some Misses Campbell that Mr. Irving met
  with, while on a journey in Scotland; they had [what is termed among their sect] &ldquo;utterances,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">8</span>
  which were evidently of a supernatural agency. Mr. Irving, falling into the common error of
  considering all supernatural manifestations to be of God, took them to London with him, and
  introduced them into his church.</p>
  <p class="std">They were there honored as the prophetesses<span class="footRef">9</span> of God, and when they spoke, Mr. Irving or any
  of his ministers had to keep silence. They were peculiarly wrought upon before the congregation,
  and had strange utterances, uttered with an unnatural, shrill voice, and with thrilling intonations they
  frequently made use of a few broken, unconnected sentences,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/23-24" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:23-24</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/7" target="_blank">Gen. 2:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/2/26" target="_blank">James 2:26</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/46" target="_blank">Luke 23:46</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/philip/3/10" target="_blank">Philip. 3:10</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/41" target="_blank">Moro. 7:41</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/eph/4/11" target="_blank">Eph. 4:11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/12/9-10" target="_blank">1 Cor. 12:9-10</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/2/4" target="_blank">Acts 2:4</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/2/36" target="_blank">Luke 2:36</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
