<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="391"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs390.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs392.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 391</div>
  <p class="std"><i>Joseph Smith</i>.&mdash;Governor Ford, I ask nothing but what is legal. I have a right to expect
  protection at least from you; for, independent of law, you have pledged your faith,<span class="footRef">1</span> and that of the
  State, for my protection, and I wish to go to Nauvoo.</p>
  <p class="std"><i>Gov</i>.&mdash;And you shall have protection, General Smith. I did not make this promise without
  consulting my officers, who all pledged their honor to its fulfillment. I do not know that I shall go
  tomorrow to Nauvoo, but if I do, I will take you along. (June 26, 1844.) DHC 6:579–585.</p>
  <div class="topic">Letter: Joseph Smith to Emma Smith&mdash;</div>
  <div class="topic">Prophet&rsquo;s Instruction as to Reception of the Governor</div>
  <p class="right">Carthage Jail, June 27th, 1844.</p>
  <p class="right">20 minutes past eight a.m.</p>
  <p class="std">Dear Emma.&mdash;The Governor continues his courtesies, and permits us to see our friends. We
  hear this morning that the Governor will not go down with his troops today to Nauvoo, as we
  anticipated last evening; but if he does come down with his troops you will be protected; and I want
  you to tell Brother Dunham to instruct the people to stay at home and attend to their own business,
  and let there be no groups or gathering together, unless by permission of the Governor, they are
  called together to receive communications from the Governor, which would please our people, but
  let the Governor direct.</p>
  <p class="std">Brother Dunham of course will obey the orders of the government officers, and render them the
  assistance they require. There is no danger of any extermination order. Should there be a mutiny
  among the troops (which we do not anticipate, excitement is abating) a part will remain loyal and
  stand for the defense of the state and our rights.</p>
  <p class="std">There is one principle which is eternal; it is the duty of all men to protect their lives and the
  lives of the household,<span class="footRef">2</span> whenever necessity requires, and no power has a right to forbid it, should
  the last extreme arrive, but I anticipate no such extreme, but caution is the parent of safety.</p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH.</p>
  <p class="std">P.S.&mdash;Dear Emma, I am very much resigned to my lot, knowing I am justified, and have done
  the best that could be done. Give my love to the children<span class="footRef">3</span> and all my friends, Mr. Brewer, and all
  who inquire after me: and as for treason, I know that I have not committed any, and they cannot
  prove</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/135/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 135:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_tim/5/8" target="_blank">1 Tim. 5:8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/46/12" target="_blank">Alma 46:12</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/luke/23/28" target="_blank">Luke 23:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/titus/2/4" target="_blank">Titus 2:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_jn/1/1" target="_blank">2 Jn. 1:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/jacob/3/7" target="_blank">Jacob 3:7</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
