<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="387"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs386.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs388.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 387</div>
  <p class="cont">accordance with law. We made that order in our corporate capacity, and the City Marshal carried
  it out. It is possible there may have been some better way, but I must confess that I could not see it.</p>
  <p class="std">In relation to the writ served upon us, we were willing to abide the consequences of our own
  acts,<span class="footRef">1</span> but were unwilling, in answering a writ of that kind, to submit to illegal exactions sought to
  be imposed upon us under the pretense of law, when we knew they were in open violation of it.</p>
  <p class="std">When that document was presented to me by Mr. Bettisworth, I offered, in the presence of more
  than 20 persons, to go to any other magistrate, either in our city or Appanoose, or any other place
  where we should be safe, but we all refused to put ourselves into the power of a mob.</p>
  <p class="std">What right had that constable to refuse our request? He had none according to law; for you
  know, Governor Ford, that the statute law in Illinois is, that the parties served with the writ shall go
  before him who issued it, or some other justice of the peace. Why, then, should we be dragged to
  Carthage, where the law does not compel us to go? Does not this look like many others of our
  prosecutions with which you are acquainted? And had we not a right to expect foul play?</p>
  <p class="std">This very act was a breach of law on his part&mdash;an assumption of power that did not belong to
  him, and an attempt, at least, to deprive us of our legal and constitutional rights and privileges. What
  could we do under the circumstances different from what we did do? We sued for, and obtained a
  writ of <i>habeas corpus</i> from the Municipal Court, by which we were delivered from the hands of
  Constable Bettisworth, and brought before and acquitted by the Municipal Court.</p>
  <p class="std">After our acquittal, in a conversation with Judge Thomas, although he considered the acts of
  the party illegal, he advised, that to satisfy the people, we had better go before another magistrate
  who was not in our Church.</p>
  <p class="std">In accordance with his advice we went before Esq. Wells, with whom you are well acquainted;
  both parties were present, witnesses were called on both sides, the case was fully investigated, and
  we were again dismissed.</p>
  <p class="std">And what is this intended desire to enforce the law, and these lying, base rumors put into
  circulation for, but to seek, through mob influence, under pretense of law, to make us</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/134/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 134:1</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
