<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="4"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs3.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs5.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 4</div>
  <div class="topic">INTRODUCTION</div>
  <p class="std">A quarter of a century ago, Elder Edwin F. Parry compiled and published a classified
  arrangement of excerpts from doctrinal sermons and writings of the Prophet Joseph Smith.  These
  sayings were taken from the <i>Documentary History of the Church.</i>  That little work filled an
  important mission, but left in the hearts and minds of all who were interested in the sayings of the
  great latter-day Prophet, a longing for more of his sayings, which longing was not satisfied.  Many
  faithful members of the Church have expressed the desire that a more extensive work of this kind
  be published.  The members of the Church quite generally desire to know what the Prophet Joseph
  Smith may have said on important subjects, for they look upon his utterances as coming through
  divine inspiration.</p>
  <p class="std">Many of these discourses and writings appear in the Documentary History of the Church, but
  others have not been included in these volumes, but are scattered through the early publications of
  the Church.  It has been difficult even for the student to obtain these because the old publications
  are not accessible for general use.</p>
  <p class="std">In accordance with the many calls that have been made that there be a more extensive
  compilation of these discourses and sayings, the matter was taken up in the Historian&rsquo;s Office and
  such a compilation has been prepared, submitted to the First Presidency and passed by them for
  publication.</p>
  <p class="std">It should be remembered that this compilation contains some discourses and statements from
  the minutes of council and priesthood meetings, which are not verbatim reports of the Prophet&rsquo;s
  remarks, but which have been approved in those minutes.  There has been no attempt to compile
  these sayings by subject, because frequently in the same article or discourse, several subjects are
  discussed.  It has been thought best to give each article, or portion of article, chronologically, with
  an exhaustive index through which the various subjects may be found.  Historical matters and
  incidental or unimportant matters have been eliminated.  By the use of asterisks these portions left
  out are indicated in the body of the work.</p>
  <p class="std">Articles which are accessible, such as <i>Joseph Smith Tells His Own Story,</i> which has been
  published in tract form and also in the Pearl of Great Price, are not added to this work.  References
  have been made to the revelations in the Doctrine and Covenants where necessary, but these
  revelations are not included in this work.</p>
  <p class="std">It is felt that this volume will meet a need and promote faith among the members of the
  Church.  With this intent it is sent out on its mission as another testimony of the divine calling of
  the Prophet Joseph Smith.</p>
  <p class="std">JOSEPH FIELDING SMITH,</p>
  <p class="std">Church Historian.</p>
  <p class="std">First published in 1938.</p>
</div>
