<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="94"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs93.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs95.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 94</div>
  <p class="cont">speak in his turn<span class="footRef">1</span> and in his place, and in his time and season,<span class="footRef">2</span> that there may be perfect order in all
  things; and that every man, before he makes an objection to any item that is brought before a council
  for consideration, should be sure that he can throw light upon the subject rather than spread
  darkness,<span class="footRef">3</span> and that his objection be founded in righteousness, which may be done by men applying
  themselves closely to study the mind and will of the Lord,<span class="footRef">4</span> whose spirit always makes manifest and
  demonstrates the truth to the understanding of all who are in possession of the Spirit.<span class="footRef">5</span> (Jan. 15,
  1836). DHC, Vol. 2:370.</p>
  <div class="topic">To the Elders of the Church of Latter-day Saints</div>
  <div class="topic">Parable of the Sower<span class="footRef">6</span></div>
  <p class="std">I have shown unto you, in my last, that there are two Jerusalems spoken of in holy writ, in a
  manner I think satisfactory to your minds; at any rate I have given my views upon the subject, I shall
  now proceed to make some remarks from the sayings of the Savior, recorded in the 13th chapter of
  His Gospel according to St. Matthew,<span class="footRef">7</span> which, in my mind, afforded us as clear an understanding
  upon the important subject of the gathering, as anything recorded in the Bible. At the time the Savior
  spoke these beautiful sayings and parables contained in the chapter above quoted, we find Him
  seated in a ship<span class="footRef">8</span> on account of the multitude that pressed upon Him to hear His words; and He
  commenced teaching them, saying:</p>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Behold, a sower went forth to sow, and when he sowed, some seeds feel by the way side, and
  the fowls came and devoured them up: some fell upon stony places, where they had not much earth;
  and forthwith they sprang up because they had no deepness of earth: and when the sun was up they
  were scorched: and because they had no root they withered away. And some fell among thorns; and
  the thorns sprung up and choked them: but other fell in good ground, and brought forth good fruit,
  some an hundred fold, some sixty fold, some thirty fold. Who hath ears to
  hear, let him hear.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">9</span></p>
  <div class="topic">He Who Will Not Receive Light Shall Lose Light</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;And the disciples came and said unto Him, Why speakest thou unto them in parables?<span class="footRef">10</span> [I
  would here remark, that the &lsquo;them&rsquo; made use of in this interrogation, is a personal pronoun,</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/102/12,34" target="_blank">D&amp;C 102:12,34</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/58" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:58</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/hel/6/28" target="_blank">Hel. 6:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/68/4" target="_blank">D&amp;C 68:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/133/61" target="_blank">D&amp;C 133:61</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/16/13" target="_blank">John 16:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/10/5" target="_blank">Moro. 10:5</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/6/15" target="_blank">D&amp;C 6:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/3-9" target="_blank">Matt. 13:3-9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/3-9" target="_blank">Matt. 13:3-9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/2" target="_blank">Matt. 13:2</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/3-9" target="_blank">Matt. 13:3-9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/matt/13/10" target="_blank">Matt. 13:10</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
