<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="353"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs352.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs354.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 353</div>
  <p class="cont">it became a living soul.<span class="footRef">1</span> (Refers to the old Bible.) How does it read in the Hebrew? It does not say
  in the Hebrew that God created the spirit of man. It says &ldquo;God made man out of the earth and put
  into him Adam&rsquo;s spirit, and so became a living body.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std">The mind or the intelligence which man possesses is co-equal<span class="footRef">3</span><span class="textFootRef">,a</span> with God himself. I know that
  my testimony is true;<span class="footRef">4</span> hence, when I talk to these mourners, what have they lost? Their relatives and
  friends are only separated from their bodies for a short season:<span class="footRef">5</span> their spirits which existed with God
  have left the tabernacle of clay<span class="footRef">6</span> only for a little moment,<span class="footRef">7</span> as it were; and they now exist in a place
  where they converse together the same as we do<span class="footRef">8</span> on the earth.</p>
  <p class="std">I am dwelling on the immortality of the spirit<span class="footRef">9</span> of man. Is it logical to say that the intelligence
  of spirits is immortal,<span class="footRef">10</span> and yet that it had a beginning? The intelligence of spirits had no beginning,
  neither will it have an end.<span class="footRef">11</span> That is good logic. That which has a beginning<span class="footRef">12</span> may have an end.<span class="footRef">13</span>
  There never was a time when there were not spirits; for they are co-equal [co-eternal] with our
  Father in heaven.<span class="footRef">14</span></p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/7" target="_blank">Gen. 2:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/gen/2/7" target="_blank">Gen. 2:7</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/15/45" target="_blank">1 Cor. 15:45</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/5/7" target="_blank">Abr. 5:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/john/8/14" target="_blank">John 8:14</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/127/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 127:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/9/6" target="_blank">Moro. 9:6</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/isa/26/20" target="_blank">Isa. 26:20</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/138/12-15" target="_blank">D&amp;C 138:12-15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/28" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:28</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/6/59" target="_blank">Moses 6:59</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/93/29" target="_blank">D&amp;C 93:29</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/18" target="_blank">Abr. 3:18</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/heb/7/3" target="_blank">Heb. 7:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">13. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/21/6" target="_blank">Rev. 21:6</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/rev/22/13" target="_blank">Rev. 22:13</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/11/39" target="_blank">Alma 11:39</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/13/7-9" target="_blank">Alma 13:7-9</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/3_ne/9/18" target="_blank">3 Ne. 9:18</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/19/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 19:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/29/33" target="_blank">D&amp;C 29:33</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/61/1" target="_blank">D&amp;C 61:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/1/3" target="_blank">Moses 1:3</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moses/2/1" target="_blank">Moses 2:1</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/2/8" target="_blank">Abr. 2:8</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">14. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/abr/3/18" target="_blank">Abr. 3:18</a>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div class="textFootnotes">
    
      <p class="std"><span class="textMark">a</span>Undoubtedly the proper word here would be &ldquo;co-eternal,&rdquo; not &ldquo;coequal.&rdquo; This illustrates the imperfection of the report made of the sermon. For surely the mind of man is not co-equal with God except in the matter of its eternity. It is the direct statement in the Book of Abraham&mdash;accepted by the Church as scripture&mdash;that there are differences in the intelligences that exist, that some are more intelligent than others;
        and that God is &ldquo;more intelligent than them all&rdquo; (Book of Abraham, Chapt. 3). I believe that this means more than that God is more intelligent than any other one of the intelligences. It means that he is more intelligent than all of the other intelligences combined. His intelligence is greater than that of the mass, and that has led me to say In the second Year Book of the Seventies:&mdash;&ldquo;It is this fact doubtless which makes this One, &lsquo;more intelligent than them all&rsquo;,&rdquo; God. He is the All-Wise One! The All-Powerful One! What he tells other Intelligences to do must be precisely the wisest, fittest thing that they could anywhere or anyhow learn&mdash;the thing which it will always behoove them, with right loyal thankfulness, and nothing doubting, to do. There goes with this, too, the thought that this All-Wise One will be the Unselfish One, the All-Loving One, the One who desires that which is highest, and best;
        not for himself alone, but for all: and that will be best for him too. His glory, his power, his joy will be enhanced by the uplifting of all, by enlarging them;
        by increasing their joy, power, and glory. And because this All Intelligent One is all this, and does all this, the other Intelligences worship him, submit their judgments and their will to his judgment and his will. He knows, and can do that which is best;
        and this submission of the mind to the Most Intelligent, Wisest&mdash;wiser than all&mdash;is worship. This is the whole meaning of the doctrine and the life of the Christ expressed in&mdash;&ldquo;Father, not my will but Thy will, be done.&rdquo;&mdash;Note by Elder B. H. Roberts.</p>
    
  </div>
</div>
