<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="89"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs88.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs90.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 89</div>
  <p class="cont">this is well pleasing unto the Lord. Fathers, provoke not your children to anger, lest they be
  discouraged. Servants, obey in all things your masters, according to the flesh, not with eye-service,
  as men-pleasers, but in singleness of heart, fearing God&rdquo; (Colossians 3:18–22).<span class="footRef">1</span></p>
  <p class="std">But I must close this letter, and resume the subject in another number.</p>
  <p class="std">In the bonds of the New and Everlasting Covenant,<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="right">JOSEPH SMITH, JUN., M&amp;A, November, 1835; also DHC 2:259–264.</p>
  <div class="topic">Reflections</div>
  <p class="std">Friday, November 6.&mdash;At home. Attended school during school hours, returned and spent the
  evening at home. I was this morning introduced to a man from the east. After hearing his name, he
  remarked that I was nothing but a man, indicating by this expression, that he had supposed that a
  person to whom the Lord should see fit to reveal His will, must be something more than a man.<span class="footRef">3</span> He
  seemed to have forgotten the saying that fell from the lips of St. James, that Elias was a man subject
  to like passions as we are, yet he had such power with God, that He, in answer to his prayers, shut
  the heavens that they gave no rain for the space of three years and six months; and again, in answer
  to his prayer, the heavens gave forth rain, and the earth gave forth fruit.<span class="footRef">4</span> Indeed, such is the darkness
  and ignorance of this generation, that they look upon it as incredible that a man should have any
  intercourse with his Maker. (Nov. 6, 1835). DHC, Vol. 2:302.</p>
  <div class="topic">The Prophet&rsquo;s Remarks to the Twelve</div>
  <p class="summary">At six o&rsquo;clock, Nov. 12, 1835, the Apostles met with the First Presidency in council and on this occasion the
  Prophet made the following remarks:</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std">I am happy in the enjoyment of this opportunity of meeting with this Council on this occasion.
  I am satisfied that the Spirit of the Lord is here, and I am satisfied with all the brethren present; and
  I need not say that you have my utmost confidence, and that I intend to uphold you to the uttermost,
  for I am well aware that you have to sustain my character against the vile calumnies and reproaches
  of this ungodly generation, and that you delight in so doing.</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/col/3/18-22" target="_blank">Col. 3:18-22</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/88/133" target="_blank">D&amp;C 88:133</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/10/26" target="_blank">Acts 10:26</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/mosiah/2/10-11" target="_blank">Mosiah 2:10-11</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/james/5/17-18" target="_blank">James 5:17-18</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
