<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="203"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs202.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs204.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 203</div>
  <p class="cont">spirit the Apostles prophesied,<span class="footRef">1</span> or by what power the Apostles spoke<span class="footRef">2</span> and worked miracles. Who
  could have told whether the power of Simon, the sorcerer,<span class="footRef">3</span> was of God or of the devil?<span class="footRef">4</span></p>
  <p class="std">There always did, in every age, seem to be a lack of intelligence pertaining to this subject.
  Spirits of all kinds have been manifested,<span class="footRef">5</span> in every age, and almost among all people. If we go
  among the pagans, they have their spirits; the Mohammedans, the Jews, the Christians, the
  Indians&mdash;all have their spirits, all have a supernatural agency, and all contend that their spirits are
  of God. Who shall solve the mystery? &ldquo;Try the spirits,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">6</span> says John, but who is to do it? The learned,
  the eloquent, the philosopher, the sage, the divine&mdash;all are ignorant. The heathens will boast of their
  gods, and of the great things that have been unfolded by their oracles. The Mussulman will boast
  of his Koran, and of the divine communications that his progenitors have received. The Jews have
  had numerous instances, both ancient and modern, among them of men who have professed to be
  inspired,<span class="footRef">7</span> and sent to bring about great events, and the Christian world has not been slow in making
  up the number.</p>
  <div class="topic">Ignorance of the Nature of Spirits</div>
  <p class="std">&ldquo;Try the spirits,&rdquo;<span class="footRef">8</span> but what by? Are we to try them by the creeds of men?<span class="footRef">9</span> What preposterous
  folly&mdash;what sheer ignorance&mdash;what madness!  Try the motions and actions of an eternal being<span class="footRef">10</span> (for
  I contend that all spirits are such) by a thing that was conceived in ignorance, and brought forth in
  folly&mdash;a cobweb of yesterday!  Angels would hide their faces, and devils would be ashamed and
  insulted, and would say, &ldquo;Paul we know, and Jesus we know, but who are ye?&rdquo;<span class="footRef">11</span> Let each man of
  society make a creed and try evil spirits by it, and the devil would shake his sides; it is all that he
  would ask&mdash;all that he would desire. Yet many of them do this, and hence &ldquo;many spirits are abroad
  in the world.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">12</span></p>
  <p class="std">One great evil is, that men are ignorant of the nature of spirits; their power, laws, government,
  intelligence, etc., and imagine that when there is anything like power, revelation, or vision
  manifested, that it must be of God. Hence the Methodists, Presbyterians, and others frequently
  possess a spirit that will cause them to lie down, and during its operation, animation is frequently
  entirely suspended; they consider it to be the power</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_cor/14/32" target="_blank">1 Cor. 14:32</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/2_pet/1/21" target="_blank">2 Pet. 1:21</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">3. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/8/9" target="_blank">Acts 8:9</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">4. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/moro/7/14,17" target="_blank">Moro. 7:14,17</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">5. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/50/31" target="_blank">D&amp;C 50:31</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">6. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/1" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">7. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/5/36-37" target="_blank">Acts 5:36-37</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">8. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/1" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:1</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">9. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/123/7" target="_blank">D&amp;C 123:7</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">10. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/dc/77/3" target="_blank">D&amp;C 77:3</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">11. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/19/15" target="_blank">Acts 19:15</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">12. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/1_jn/4/1" target="_blank">1 Jn. 4:1</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
