<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="page"><div class="pageNum"><a name="384"></a><div class="prev"><a href="stpjs383.html">Prev</a></div><div class="next"><a href="stpjs385.html">Next</a></div>
			    STPJS 384</div>
  <p class="cont">to God that I could preach to the Saints in Nauvoo once more.&rdquo; Fullmer tried to rally his spirits,
  saying he thought he would often have that privilege, when Joseph thanked him for the remark and
  good feelings expressed to him.</p>
  <p class="std">Soon after Dr. Richards retired to the bed which Joseph had left, and when all were apparently
  fast asleep, Joseph whispered to Dan Jones, &ldquo;Are you afraid to die?&rdquo;  Dan said, &ldquo;Has that time come,
  think you? Engaged in such a cause I do not think that death would have many terrors.&rdquo;<span class="footRef">1</span> Joseph
  replied, &ldquo;You will yet see Wales, and fulfill the mission appointed to you before you die.&rdquo; (June 26,
  1844&mdash;midnight.) DHC 6:600–601.</p>
  <div class="topic">Elder John Taylor&rsquo;s Account of Governor Ford&rsquo;s and</div>
  <div class="topic">President Smith&rsquo;s Interview</div>
  <p class="summary">This account was written by John Taylor subsequent to the events here portrayed.</p>
  <hr class="centerQuarter" />
  <p class="std"><i>Governor.</i>&mdash;General Smith, I believe you have given me a general outline of the difficulties that
  have existed in the country, in the documents forwarded to me by Dr. Bernhisel and Mr. Taylor; but,
  unfortunately, there seems to be a discrepancy between your statements and those of your enemies.
  It is true that you are substantiated by evidence and affidavit, but for such an extraordinary
  excitement as that which is now in the country, there must be some cause, and I attribute the last
  outbreak to the destruction of the Expositor, and to your refusal to comply with the writ issued by
  Esq. Morrison. The press in the United States is looked upon as the great bulwark of American
  freedom, and its destruction in Nauvoo was represented and looked upon as a high-handed measure,
  and manifests to the people a disposition on your part to suppress the liberty of speech and of the
  press; this, with your refusal to comply with the requisition of a writ, I conceive to be the principal
  cause of this difficulty, and you are, moreover, represented to me as turbulent and defiant of the laws
  and institutions of your country.<span class="footRef">2</span></p>
  <p class="std"><i>Gen. Smith.</i>&mdash;Governor Ford, you, sir, as Governor of this State, are aware of the prosecutions
  and persecutions that I have endured. You know well that our curse has been peaceable and
  law-abiding, for I have furnished this State, ever</p>
  <div class="footnotes">
    <div class="footnote">1. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/ps/55/4" target="_blank">Ps. 55:4</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/alma/27/28" target="_blank">Alma 27:28</a>
    </div>
    <div class="footnote">2. 
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/16/20-21" target="_blank">Acts 16:20-21</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/17/6-8" target="_blank">Acts 17:6-8</a>;
      <a href="http://scriptures.lds.org/acts/24/5" target="_blank">Acts 24:5</a>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
